<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20130701.EN" lang="en" date="2013-07-01" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die am Donnerstag, dem 13.[nbsp ]Juni 2013, unterbrochene Sitzungsperiode für wieder aufgenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Welcome">
    <intervention id="1-006-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken"/>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Formal sitting - Welcoming of the Croatian Members">
    <intervention id="1-010-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">\*(Beifall)</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Wir, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, heißen nun unsere neuen kroatischen Kolleginnen und Kollegen willkommen. Sie, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, die Vertreterinnen und Vertreter des kroatischen Volkes, nehmen jetzt Ihre Sitze hier ein.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Ich habe die Ehre und das Privileg, Sie hier willkommen heißen zu dürfen, in einer feierlichen Zeremonie, der ich nicht zum ersten Mal beiwohne. Ich habe als jung gewählter Abgeordneter 1995 schon einmal erlebt, wie eine ganze Gruppe neu gewählter Abgeordneter in dieses Parlament kam. Immer mehr sind hinzugekommen, und heute Sie. Deshalb freue ich mich, Sie hier willkommen zu heißen.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Jeder Einzelne von Ihnen wird gleich namentlich aufgerufen. Sie nehmen dann Ihre Plätze ein. Wenn Sie Ihre Plätze eingenommen haben, dann werden wir das Symbol der Mitgliedschaft Kroatiens, die Flagge Ihres Landes, zu den anderen Flaggen der Mitgliedstaaten der Europäischen Union hinzufügen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr</p>
      <a text="(Die neu gewählten kroatischen Abgeordneten nehmen ihre Plätze ein. Anschließend folgt der Präsident einem Saaldiener, der die kroatische Flagge trägt, und stellt sie an ihren Platz zwischen den anderen Flaggen.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Nochmals herzlich willkommen, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Statements by the President">
    <intervention id="1-012-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, wir fahren nun mit unseren Arbeiten fort.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Im Namen des Europäischen Parlaments möchte ich alle Beteiligten in Ägypten zur Gewaltfreiheit aufrufen. Wir werden die andauernden Massendemonstrationen in Ägypten sicher aufmerksam verfolgen und sicher gleich bei der Tagesordnung darüber noch reden.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Italien und Europa haben einen außergewöhnlichen Staatsmann verloren, einen ehrlichen, einen weitsichtigen und – wer ihn gekannt hat, der weiß das ganz sicher – einen leidenschaftlichen Mann.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*Ich habe heute Nachmittag den Botschafter der Vereinigten Staaten bei der Europäischen Union telefonisch darum gebeten, so schnell und so vollständig es geht, Aufklärung zu schaffen und uns über den eventuellen Wahrheitsgehalt dieser Vorwürfe in Kenntnis zu setzen. Ich habe darüber hinaus Herrn Kollegen Lopéz Aguilar gebeten, heute Nachmittag eine Sitzung der Koordinatoren des Ausschusses für bürgerliche Freiheiten, Justiz und Inneres einzuberufen, um über das weitere Vorgehen zu beraten.</p>
      <p sl="en">\*(Beifall)</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Verification of credentials: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Corrigendum (Rule 216): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Signature of acts adopted under the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 74): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-023-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Der endgültige Entwurf der Tagesordnung dieser Tagung, wie er in der Konferenz der Präsidenten in ihrer Sitzung vom Donnerstag, dem 27.[nbsp ]Juni 2013 gemäß Artikel[nbsp ]137 der Geschäftsordnung festgelegt wurde, ist verteilt worden. Zu diesem Entwurf wurden folgende Änderungen beantragt:</p>
      <p sl="en">Dienstag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Für Dienstag muss ich Ihnen eine Änderung mitteilen. Die Abstimmung über das Statut, die für Mittwoch vorgesehen ist, sollte auf Dienstag vorverlegt werden. Das war ein Irrtum der Dienste. Werden dagegen Einwände erhoben? Das ist nicht der Fall. Dann stimmen wir am Dienstag darüber ab.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die EVP-Fraktion hat beantragt, dass am Dienstag eine Aussprache mit Erklärungen des Rates und der Kommission zur Lage in Bulgarien auf die Tagesordnung kommt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-000" speaker_id="28229" name="Manfred Weber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Die EVP-Fraktion beantragt eine Diskussion über die aktuelle Situation in Bulgarien nach den dort durchgeführten Neuwahlen. Ich möchte dies nach unserer Geschäftsordnung auch kurz begründen. Wir haben in Bulgarien jetzt eine Minderheitenregierung der Sozialisten. Und die ist nur zustande gekommen, weil man eine Duldung durch die so genannte Ataka-Partei in Kauf genommen hat. Die Ataka-Partei ist eine ausgewiesene rechts-radikale Partei, stachelt zu Hass gegen Juden, gegen Moslems auf, ist antieuropäisch, und vor wenigen Tagen hat der Vorsitzende der Partei sogar einen Bürgerkrieg für Bulgarien angedroht. Mit dieser Partei wird in Bulgarien jetzt gearbeitet, mit Duldung dieser Partei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aus unserer Sicht haben die Sozialisten dort einen Pakt mit dem Teufel geschlossen. Für uns ist das ein Skandal und dieser Skandal muss auch im Europäischen Parlament diskutiert werden können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zudem möchte ich darauf hinweisen, dass der Vorsitzende der Sozialisten dort und der Europäischen Sozialisten Stanischew versucht hat, einen dubiosen Medienunternehmer zum Chef der Behörde für den Kampf gegen die organisierte Kriminalität durchzusetzen. Damit ist er gescheitert, weil Bürger auf die Straße gegangen sind, Zigtausende auf die Straße gegangen sind und das kritisiert haben. Damit stellt Bulgarien – die dortige Regierung – die Zusammenarbeit im Kampf gegen die organisierte Kriminalität auf den Prüfstand, weil es mittlerweile Mitgliedstaaten gibt, die die Zusammenarbeit einstellen wollen. Diese beiden Vorgänge sind es wert, hier diskutiert zu werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Sie haben immer ausgeführt, dass das Europäische Parlament der Ort ist, wo man die Anliegen der Bürger diskutieren sollte. In Sofia sind tagtäglich Tausende von Menschen auf der Straße und demonstrieren gegen diese Vorgänge. Ich darf mir schon erlauben, darauf hinzuweisen, dass in Budapest niemand auf der Straße ist und diskutiert.</p>
      <a text="(Unruhe)"/>
      <p sl="en">In Sofia sind aber Hunderttausende, Zehntausende auf der Straße, die diskutieren und die demonstrieren. Deswegen ist diese Abstimmung, deswegen ist diese Frage, die Abstimmung, ob wir darüber reden dürfen,</p>
      <a text="(Zwischenrufe von Herrn Cohn-Bendit,)"/>
      <p sl="en">Herr Cohn-Bendit, deswegen ist diese Frage eine Schlüsselfrage. Aber es zeigt schon wieder die Stimmungslage hier im Haus, wenn man die Themen ernsthaft diskutieren will, wie dann Linke auf diese Vorgänge reagieren. Wir glauben, dass es jetzt die Bürger bewegt. Wir glauben, dass es jetzt vor der Sommerpause diskutiert werden muss. Und für uns ist es ein Prüfstein, ob die Sozialisten es ernst meinen mit der Debatte über diese Fragen in diesem Haus oder ob sie das Europäische Parlament verkommen lassen zu einem parteipolitischen Instrument.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Wer möchte für den Antrag sprechen?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026-000" speaker_id="96848" name="Мария Габриел" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-н Председател, бих искала да подкрепя предложението на колегата Манфред Вебер.</p>
      <p sl="en">От 18 дни хиляди граждани в България протестират срещу политиката, която води правителството на БСП, ДПС и Атака. Това, което в момента наблюдаваме в България, е следното:</p>
      <p sl="en">От една страна, нестабилност на парламентарното мнозинство, можещо да функционира единствено и само с подкрепата на Атака.</p>
      <p sl="en">Второ, безпрецедентно внушение от страна на председателя на Народното събрание, ограничаващо свободата на медиите в страната.</p>
      <p sl="en">Трето, липса на прозрачност в цялостния процес на вземане на решения и назначенията в изпълнителната и законодателната власт.</p>
      <p sl="en">Дебат по тези теми е необходим, за да покажем най-напред на българските граждани, че техният глас се чува, а тук, като Европейски парламент, да излъчим посланието, че не прилагаме двойни стандарти спрямо различните страни и различните управляващи партии.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Wer möchte gegen den Antrag sprechen?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-000" speaker_id="2295" name="Hannes Swoboda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich bin absolut dafür, dass die Dinge, die von Herrn Kollegen Weber erwähnt worden sind, behandelt werden – und zwar in diesem Parlament, denn für uns gibt es keine Zweideutigkeit. Ich frage mich nur, Herr Weber und liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen: Wo waren Sie denn, als Herr Siderow von Ataka die Regierung von Borissow unterstützt hat – und zwar aktiv unterstützt hat, beteiligt war daran? Da habe ich nichts davon gehört.</p>
      <a text="(Zwischenrufe)"/>
      <p sl="en">Ich habe mich klar gegen Ataka ausgesprochen. Ich habe mich ganz klar und deutlich geäußert, was Ataka und Herrn Siderow betrifft. Er hat mit unseren europäischen Werten nichts gemeinsam! Nichts gemeinsam! Und ich habe mich auch ganz klar gegen die Ernennung ausgesprochen, die ja zurückgenommen worden ist.</p>
      <a text="(Zwischenrufe)"/>
      <p sl="en">Was sind Sie so nervös, ich habe Ihnen genau zugehört, Kollege Weber. Der Anstand gebietet, dass Sie auch mir zuhören.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich habe klar gesagt, dass das ein Fehler war. Herr Stanischew und viele andere haben diesen Fehler eingestanden. Daher mein Vorschlag, den ich hier nur wiederholen kann und der die Mehrheit in der Konferenz der Präsidenten gefunden hat: Es findet nächste Woche eine Anhörung statt. Ich bin dafür, dass man in die Anhörung, die ursprünglich nur für die behauptete Wahlfälschung durch Herrn Borissow vorgesehen war, auch die neuen Ergebnisse mit einbezieht. Absolut! Und ich habe zugesagt, dass meine Fraktion voll unterstützen wird, dass wir im September Bulgarien auf die Tagesordnung setzen und hier offen diskutieren. Ich habe nichts dagegen. Es ist nichts zu beschönigen. Dort, wo Fehler passiert sind, sind Fehler passiert. Ich bin sehr dafür. Wenn Sie wollen, können wir Bulgarien schon in der ersten Septemberwoche nach der Anhörung im LIBE-Ausschuss auf der Tagesordnung haben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-000" speaker_id="1934" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich glaube, wir sind uns alle einig – Sie haben es hier am Anfang gesagt: Die Situation in Ägypten ist sehr gefährlich. Und wenn man das Ultimatum des Militärs richtig liest, dann kann man sich vorstellen, was passiert, wenn innerhalb von 48 Stunden die Lage nicht geregelt ist. Deshalb finde ich, dass wir hier öffentlich darüber diskutieren und eine Entschließung verabschieden sollten. Ich finde, dass die Situation in Ägypten doch so ist, dass dieses Parlament in der Lage sein muss, eine Entschließung zu verabschieden, um die Sicht des Parlaments angesichts dessen, was in Kairo und anderen Städten passiert, auch klar darzustellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deswegen bitte ich, das parteipolitische Geplänkel zu beenden, das hier schon wieder angefangen hat. Herr Weber, haben Sie gesehen, wie wir abgestimmt haben? Danke sehr, dass Sie danke gesagt haben. Das kommt Ihnen gar nicht in den Kopf! Also ich bin für die Debatte plus eine Entschließung mit der Unterstützung der PPE und der Sozialisten und der Liberalen und der Kommunisten, für die wir eine große Mehrheit kriegen werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich teile Ihnen mit, dass der Bericht des Kollegen Pargneaux auf Dienstagabend vorgezogen wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noch zum Mittwoch:</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-000" speaker_id="97058" name="Guy Verhofstadt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on Wednesday we also have on the agenda the NSA surveillance programme. I understand that it will be of a broader scope than foreseen initially because of everything that has been happening and the new revelations on the spying programme.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think that Mr Barroso himself should be present for such a debate, and that it is not Ms Reding who deals with it. It is of such importance that I think you have to request Mr Barroso himself to be present for this important debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-000" speaker_id="26851" name="Νικόλαος Χουντής" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, αναφέρομαι στην ημερήσια διάταξη της Τετάρτης. Επικαλούμαι το άρθρο 110 του Κανονισμού. Στην ημερήσια διάταξη της Τετάρτης έχει μπει το θέμα του κλεισίματος της δημόσιας ελληνικής ραδιοτηλεόρασης. Η ημερήσια διάταξη περιλαμβάνει δηλώσεις της Επιτροπής και του Συμβουλίου. Βλέπω ότι η συζήτηση δεν θα καταλήξει σε ψήφισμα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Αγαπητοί συνάδελφοι, το πρόβλημα παραμένει: Το σήμα της ραδιοτηλεόρασης και το σήμα του ραδιοφώνου δεν εκπέμπονται, παρά μόνο με τη βοήθεια της EBU. Κύριε Πρόεδρε, δώσατε μια επιστολή στον Έλληνα πρωθυπουργό στην οποία κάνετε λόγο για διαπιστωμένες παραβιάσεις του κοινοτικού δικαίου. Η Επιτροπή μίλησε και κάλυψε αυτή την ενέργεια. Στο ερώτημα που έχουν οι απολυθέντες στην ΕΡΤ, που είναι 2.600, και οι Έλληνες πολίτες «Ποια είναι η γνώμη, ποια είναι η απόφαση, ποια είναι η θέση του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου;», τι θα απαντήσουμε; Κάναμε μία συζήτηση; Σας παρακαλώ λοιπόν εξηγήστε μου γιατί ακολουθήσατε αυτή τη διαδικασία, ξαναλέω, σύμφωνα με το άρθρο 110 του Κανονισμού του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Chountis! Die Konferenz der Präsidenten hat die Tagesordnung so beschlossen, dass es keine Entschließung geben soll. Das liegt nicht in meinem Ermessen, es liegt im Ermessen der Fraktionen, ob sie mit oder ohne Entschließung debattieren wollen. Ich kann Ihnen nur anheimstellen, noch einmal mit den anderen Fraktionen Kontakt aufzunehmen, ob sie eine Entschließung verabschieden wollen. Wie gesagt, ich kann das von mir aus nicht auf die Tageordnung setzen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-000" speaker_id="34728" name="Matthias Groote" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Wir stimmen am Mittwoch über die Zeitplanänderung zu den CO2-Emissionszertifikaten ab. Diesen Hänger hatte heute jeder, der ins Parlament gekommen ist, an seiner Tür. Das ist von der Organisation International Paper. Und ich muss sagen, was dort drin steht, das entspricht zu 100[nbsp ]% nicht den Tatsachen, was wir im Parlament miteinander besprochen haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es war eine kabbelige Angelegenheit, wir haben hin und her diskutiert, und das Parlament hat beschlossen, dass der Bericht wieder zurück in den Ausschuss geht. Im Ausschuss haben dann EVP, ALDE und die Sozialisten einen Alternativtext entwickelt, der hier zur Abstimmung steht. Hier wird suggeriert, dass dieses Haus der Befehlsempfänger der Kommission ist, was nicht stimmt. Insofern sollten wir vielleicht einmal überprüfen, ob jede Organisation alles hier im Haus verteilen darf und Zugang zu den Abgeordnetenbüros hat. Ich muss sagen, ich finde es schon sehr, sehr merkwürdig, solche Dinge hier zu verteilen.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Groote, wir gehen der Angelegenheit nach.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, nous venons d'évoquer la possibilité d'avoir un débat sur la situation en Égypte et tous les groupes, y compris le groupe PPE, sont d'accord sur la nécessité de discuter d'une situation qui est très sensible. Nous venons aussi de trancher, un peu vite, sur l'adoption d'une résolution sur la situation en Égypte. Or, il faut rappeler ici que la Conférence des Présidents a déjà décidé d'avoir une résolution d'urgence sur la société civile en Égypte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je crois donc que nous ne pouvons pas faire, au cours d'une même session, deux résolutions sur l'Égypte. C'est un peu trop. Soit nous avons le débat proposé par M.[nbsp ]Cohn-Bendit, sans résolution, et nous maintenons alors la résolution d'urgence sur l'Égypte, soit nous menons le débat proposé par M.[nbsp ]Cohn-Bendit, avec une résolution, et nous déplaçons la résolution d'urgence qui a déjà été adoptée. On ne peut pas adopter durant la même session deux résolutions sur le même pays.</p>
      <p sl="en">Par conséquent, je vous suggère d'avoir le débat sur l'Égypte, tel qu'il a été proposé, et de maintenir la résolution d'urgence ou de reporter éventuellement cette résolution à plus tard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-000" speaker_id="1934" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, d'abord, j'ai proposé un débat avec résolution. Donc, on a voté pour un débat avec résolution. Il est évident que, dans la résolution, on parlera aussi des cas spécifiques, qui devaient être traités dans la résolution d'urgence. Donc, dans la résolution sur l'Égypte, on parlera de la situation de l'Égypte. Il s'agit d'une seule résolution. Dans une résolution, il y a, par exemple, les paragraphes[nbsp ]1, 2, 3 et 4, et, dans le paragraphe[nbsp ]5, ou 6, on abordera exactement les cas qui devaient être traités dans la résolution d'urgence. Donc, dans cette résolution, on traite tous les problèmes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Leider kann ich im Nachhinein nicht mehr auf die Tagesordnung zurückkommen. Die ist eben so festgestellt und beschlossen worden. Herr Preda, ich kann Ihnen nur empfehlen, mit den Kollegen noch einmal bilateral Kontakt aufzunehmen. Ich kann das jetzt hier im Moment nicht mehr ändern.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, je propose alors de voter sur l'abandon, sur le report de la résolution d'urgence, parce que si on adopte une résolution telle que proposée par M.[nbsp ]Cohn-Bendit, on ne peut pas en adopter une deuxième le lendemain. Je vous propose donc de renoncer à la résolution d'urgence qui avait été décidée auparavant. Ainsi nous pouvons voter maintenant sur l'ordre du jour des urgences de jeudi après-midi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Preda, vielen Dank für den Vorschlag. Ich muss jetzt leider auf die Geschäftsordnung verweisen. Wir haben gerade den Sitzungskalender angenommen. Es ist aber kein Problem, wenn Sie morgen Früh zu Beginn der Sitzung Ihren Antrag hier erneut einbringen. Das ist in der Geschäftsordnung zulässig.</p>
      <a text="(Zwischenrufe von Herrn -Cohn-Bendit.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Ich kann Ihnen nur empfehlen, mit den anderen Fraktionen Kontakt aufzunehmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-000" speaker_id="1934" name="Daniel Cohn-Bendit" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! In der Geschäftsordnung steht: Wenn eine Debatte ist, darf es keine Dringlichkeit geben. Damit ist die Sache erledigt. Das wollte ich Ihnen nur als Rat geben, damit Sie nicht morgen Früh damit ankommen müssen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Cohn-Bendit, ich wusste nicht, dass Sie sich so gut mit der Geschäftsordnung auskennen. Toll! Wir prüfen es, Herr Preda, und Sie treffen Ihre Dispositionen.</p>
      <a text="(Der Arbeitsplan ist somit angenommen.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Port State control (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-046-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Brian Simpson im Namen des Ausschusses für Verkehr und Fremdenverkehr über den Vorschlag für eine Richtlinie des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates zur Änderung der Richtlinie 2009/16/EG über die Hafenstaatkontrolle (COM(2012)0129 – C7-0081/2012 – 2012/0062(COD)) (A7-0394/2012).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-000" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to start by thanking the Irish Presidency for its hard work and determination in getting an agreement on much-needed updates to the EU’s port State control system. The current directive needed updating to reflect the Maritime Labour Convention of 2006, which was adopted by the International Labour Organization (ILO) and which provides comprehensive rights and protection at work for all seafarers, regardless of nationality and flag of ship.</p>
      <p sl="en">The relevance of the port State control system to all of this is that it is seen to be the second line of defence against substandard shipping: a kind of safety net to support – or to catch out – flag States that have failed to ensure compliance with international standards. The Port State Control Directive deals with the enforcement side of international conventions, giving port States a clear role to play in ensuring compliance with international standards for safety, pollution prevention and on-board living and working conditions: hence the need to put in place a robust port State control system for the Maritime Labour Convention of 2006 so that the maritime labour standards are applied on board all ships calling at EU ports.</p>
      <p sl="en">It must be said that, if seafarers are to see real improvements in their conditions of employment, accommodation, social security protection and so on, we need ILO countries to get on with ratifying this convention. Sadly, this applies as much to EU countries as to non-EU countries. The Maritime Labour Convention of 2006 is due to come into force in August of this year, yet the following EU countries have not yet ratified it: Austria, Belgium, the Czech Republic, Estonia, Germany, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Lithuania, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia, the United Kingdom and, our newest member, Croatia. This means that 15 out of 28 EU Member States have yet to ratify the convention.</p>
      <p sl="en">We can never be too quick in improving standards and conditions on board ships. As I think we all know, substandard ships are unacceptable, both in terms of workers’ rights, ships’ safety and security and with regard to environmental protection. The Maritime Labour Convention of 2006 and its enforcement via the Port State Control Directive are important tools in eliminating substandard shipping. I believe we obtained good compromises with the Council on some of the key points that were important to us in the revision of this directive, putting guarantees in place that the application of the revised directive would not result in any backward step in terms of employment and social rights, and ensuring a tighter system of control in EU waters for ships flying the flags of states that have not yet signed up to one or more of the international conventions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I now ask that those Member States that I referred to earlier, who have yet to ratify this Maritime Labour Convention of 2006, should do so urgently before it comes into force in August.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, dobro došla Hrvatska! I am very happy that the first plenary session of the European Parliament after Croatia’s accession is starting with a discussion on transport issues. This year is important for the entire seafaring community, as the International Labour Organization’s Maritime Labour Convention enters into force in August.</p>
      <p sl="en">That Convention provides comprehensive rights and protection at work for the world’s seafarers. It will in turn help to maintain and improve the safety and the environmental performance of the shipping industry. The proposal aims to enforce the Maritime Labour Convention through port State control. It is one of two enforcement instruments related to the 2006 Convention to be adopted by the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">I therefore welcome the agreement between the rapporteur, Mr Simpson – who has done a splendid job on this dossier – and the Presidency. I was pleased to note that the Committee on Transport and Tourism overwhelmingly supported it, and I hope that this House will come to the same conclusion about the benefits of the text as it stands now.</p>
      <p sl="en">With this amending directive, the European Union will have a strong instrument to make sure that the Convention is applied to all ships entering EU waters, and that the working and living conditions of seafarers are protected. It will also guarantee equal conditions for competition for EU-flagged ships.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-000" speaker_id="97011" name="Γεώργιος Κουμουτσάκος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας PPE. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η ασφάλεια στη θάλασσα αποτελεί θεμελιώδη προτεραιότητα και αδιαπραγμάτευτο όρο και ένα από τα σημαντικότερα στοιχεία της ασφάλειας της θάλασσας είναι ο αποτελεσματικός έλεγχος των πλοίων από το κράτος του λιμένα (port state control). Ενισχύεται έτσι η πολύ σημαντική σύμβαση ναυτικής εργασίας του 2006 που θα τεθεί σε ισχύ τον Αύγουστο. Η συμφωνία για την πρόταση οδηγίας για τον έλεγχο των πλοίων από το κράτος λιμένα που καλούμαστε αύριο να εγκρίνουμε στην ολομέλεια διασφαλίζει όλους τους στόχους και τις προτεραιότητες που έχουμε θέσει, χωρίς να επιβαρύνει με αναίτια μεγάλη αύξηση του αριθμού των επιθεωρήσεων από τα κράτη μέλη. Είναι ένας απολύτως ικανοποιητικός συμβιβασμός που πετύχαμε μετά από εντατικές διαπραγματεύσεις με το Συμβούλιο. Ικανοποιεί πλήρως τις βασικές προτεραιότητες του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου, ενώ λαμβάνει υπόψη τις ευαισθησίες όλων των πλευρών, χωρίς να αφίσταται των προνοιών της διεθνούς σύμβασης ναυτικής εργασίας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πιο συγκεκριμένα, το κείμενο που θα ψηφίσουμε αύριο διασφαλίζει την προάσπιση των δικαιωμάτων των ναυτικών και ισότιμους όρους ανταγωνισμού υπέρ των χωρών και των πλοιοκτητών που έχουν αναλάβει τη δέσμευση να προσφέρουν αξιοπρεπείς συνθήκες εργασίας και διαβίωσης στους ναυτικούς, προστατεύοντάς τους έτσι από τον αθέμιτο ανταγωνισμό πλοίων με περιορισμένο επίπεδο ασφαλείας. Και θα ’θελα να κλείσω προτρέποντας τα κράτη μέλη που δεν το έχουν ακόμα κάνει να κυρώσουν το ταχύτερο δυνατόν τη σύμβαση ναυτικής εργασίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-000" speaker_id="96842" name="Ismail Ertug" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Morgen werden wir über eine entscheidende Verbesserung bei der EU-Regelung zur Hafenstaatkontrolle abstimmen, nämlich die Verankerung des Internationalen Seearbeitsübereinkommens in der Richtlinie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mit mehr als 1[nbsp ]000 Häfen entlang der europäischen Küste, die einen Großteil des EU-Außenhandels abwickeln, sind gemeinsame Kriterien für die Schiffsüberprüfungen heute unverzichtbar, denn sie stärken den Umweltschutz und vor allem die Sicherheit. Das 2006 vereinbarte Übereinkommen über Seearbeit sollte in dieser wichtigen Gesetzgebung unbedingt berücksichtigt werden, damit die Arbeit an Bord aller in EU-Häfen einlaufenden Schiffe auch den internationalen Sozialstandards entspricht. Denn das Leben und Arbeiten auf Schiffen ist außergewöhnlich und fordert den Seeleuten eine extrem hohe Einsatzbereitschaft ab. Und wer sich für diesen Berufsweg entscheidet, sollte sich auch sicher sein können, dass für ausreichend Schutz der Lebens- und Arbeitsbedingungen an Bord gesorgt ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb möchte ich ganz besonders dem Berichterstatter, Herrn Simpson, und auch allen Schattenberichterstattern dafür danken, dass sie sich in den Verhandlungen sehr für bessere Arbeitsrichtlinien eingesetzt haben. Dabei haben sie sichergestellt, dass Schiffe aus Flaggenstaaten, die das internationale Abkommen nicht unterzeichnet haben, besonderer Kontrolle unterliegen und innerhalb der EU mitunter strengere Kriterien zum Einsatz kommen können, als internationale Konventionen es vorgeben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich hoffe sehr, dass die nun vorgenommene Verankerung des Abkommens im EU-Recht der Forderung nach seiner schnellen Ratifizierung Nachdruck verleiht!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ALDE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Ich möchte mich zunächst ganz herzlich bei Brian Simpson bedanken, der nicht nur diese Sache für uns im Parlament bearbeitet, sondern auch wirklich sehr gut mit uns Schattenberichterstattern zusammengearbeitet hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Beruf des Seemanns ist weltweit einer der ältesten Berufe in unserer Geschichte. Es hängt da viel Romantik mit dran, aber es ist tatsächlich auch ein sehr schwerer, sehr harter Beruf, durchaus mit vielen Entbehrungen. Umso wichtiger ist es, dass wir hier anständige Regelungen für die Menschen schaffen, die auf Schiffen arbeiten. Seit 1920 gab es schon insgesamt 37[nbsp ]verschiedene Arbeitsübereinkommen, die jetzt alle zum ersten Mal in einem Arbeitsgesetzbuch für die Seeleute zusammengefasst werden. Über 1,2[nbsp ]Millionen Menschen sind es weltweit, die auf Schiffen arbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es geht um Schiffssicherheit, ganz richtig, es geht aber auch um Arbeitsbedingungen, um das Recht, sich zu beschweren, und auch zum Beispiel darum, wie man gesundheitlich versorgt wird. Alle diese Dinge sind unwahrscheinlich wichtig. Wir haben schon eine ganze Reihe verschiedener Gesetze dafür, die werden nur nicht immer von allen Flaggenstaaten richtig umgesetzt. Verantwortlich dafür sind die Reeder, die Schiffseigner und eben in den entsprechenden Flaggenstaaten auch die Kapitäne. Aber nicht immer klappt das so gut, wie wir es uns wünschen. Jetzt ist eben die gute Gelegenheit, dass zumindest die Mitgliedstaaten der EU alle unterzeichnen. Es wurde schon gesagt, wer bereits unterzeichnet hat und wer noch nicht. Kroatien – das möchte ich noch einmal betonen –, unser neuer Mitgliedstaat seit heute, hat auch relativ frühzeitig unterzeichnet, und natürlich wollen wir, dass das noch viele mehr machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alle Schiffe, die in EU-Häfen einlaufen, sollten kontrolliert werden. Die Inspektoren brauchen natürlich eine Qualifikation. Dafür wird unter anderem die EMSA eingesetzt. Vollkommen richtig! Wir haben auch gesagt, es ist wichtig, dass bei Mitgliedstaaten, die strengere Vorschriften haben, als wir sie jetzt international fordern, diese trotzdem eingehalten werden, dass man also nicht unter diese Standards geht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und als Letztes: Der Seeleute-Beruf ist ein in Zukunft wichtiger und sehr viel gebrauchter Beruf. Darum müssen wir die Attraktivität dieses Berufs erhöhen. Darum nochmals an alle Mitgliedstaaten: Bitte unterzeichnen Sie dieses Abkommen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-000" speaker_id="102931" name="Keith Taylor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as the Greens’ shadow on this file I would like to thank the rapporteur, Brian Simpson, for his effective work. This was a standard procedure to adopt the Maritime Labour Convention (MLC) of 2006 into EU law and in so doing to secure seafarers’ rights and protection.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are going to be supporting this first reading agreement in view of the rapporteur’s call for non-regression. That means no existing standards of social legislation should be allowed to be lowered due to the adoption of this piece of legislation. The recommendations on non-ratification did not go as far as we wanted – our proposal wanted to put ships from flag States not signing the MLC into a higher risk category but this was not accepted.</p>
      <p sl="en">We did at least get an agreement that non-flag vessels would get ‘no more favourable treatment’ than ones sailing under the convention; in Article 3 of the amended directive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-000" speaker_id="96664" name="Anna Rosbach" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">for ECR-Gruppen. – Hr. formand! Hr. kommissær! Europa-Parlamentet har længe støttet bestræbelserne for at indføre minimumsstandarder for arbejds- og leveforhold ombord på skibe. Skibsfarten er et globalt erhverv, derfor er det nødvendigt med internationale aftaler. Som led i ratificeringen og konventionen af 2006 stemmer vi i dag om håndhævelsen af denne i alle EU's medlemslande. Når vi vedtager betænkningen, sikrer vi, at EU-lovgivningen lever op til alle vore eksterne forpligtelser. Redere, skibsførere og flagstater er alle ansvarlige for, at skibene opfylder de gældende lovkrav. Det er imidlertid ikke alle flagstater, der sikrer en effektiv håndhævelse, som også andre kollegaer har nævnt her i salen i dag. Men nu sikrer vi altså, at de relevante standarder finder anvendelse ombord på alle skibe, som anløber EU-havne, uanset de søfarendes nationalitet og skibets flagstat. Vi slår også fast, at internationale standarder ikke må underminere højere standarder i EU. Jeg vil derfor opfordre til at stemme for kollega Brian Simpsons betænkning.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-000" speaker_id="28584" name="Γεώργιος Τούσσας" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το Κομμουνιστικό Κόμμα Ελλάδας καταψηφίζει την οδηγία και την έκθεση της Επιτροπής, γιατί διαμορφώνουν έναν ακόμη γραφειοκρατικό μηχανισμό, ο οποίος όχι μόνο δεν αποσκοπεί στο να προστατεύσει τα δικαιώματα των ναυτεργατών, στην ασφάλεια της ανθρώπινης ζωής στη θάλασσα και στην προστασία του περιβάλλοντος, αλλά αντίθετα θα αξιοποιηθεί για τη συμπίεση της τιμής της εργατικής δύναμης στο κατώτατο δυνατό σημείο, για τη μεγιστοποίηση της κερδοφορίας των εφοπλιστών και των μονοπωλίων. Ο δήθεν έλεγχος συμμόρφωσης των πλοίων με τις διατάξεις της Σύμβασης Ναυτικής Εργασίας του 2006 αποτελεί το άλλοθι που δίνεται στο εφοπλιστικό κεφάλαιο για την πιο άγρια εκμετάλλευση των ναυτεργατών. Οι διαδικασίες για καταγγελίες αποτελούν κοροϊδία και πρόκληση για τους ναυτεργάτες, τη στιγμή που η συνδικαλιστική κοινωνική και πολιτική δράση των ναυτεργατών βρίσκονται υπό διωγμό από τους εφοπλιστές και τις αστικές κυβερνήσεις.</p>
      <p sl="en">Στην Ελλάδα οι ναυτεργάτες βρίσκονται ακόμα κάτω από το επαίσχυντο καθεστώς της πολιτικής επιστράτευσης. Σήμερα εξελίσσεται μια από τις πιο οργανωμένες σκληρές επιθέσεις του κεφαλαίου και της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης κατά των εργαζομένων, κατά των ναυτεργατών, με στόχο την ισοπέδωση των δικαιωμάτων τους. Ενάντια σ’ αυτή την επίθεση στην Ελλάδα πρωτοστατεί η δικομματική κυβέρνηση Νέας Δημοκρατίας – ΠΑΣΟΚ όπως και οι προηγούμενες κυβερνήσεις. Η Σύμβαση Ναυτικής Εργασίας του 2006 κωδικοποιεί και οριοθετεί στο κατώτερο δυνατό όριο τα μισθολογικά και εργασιακά δικαιώματα των ναυτεργατών. Με την εφαρμογή της Σύμβασης Ναυτικής Εργασίας του 2006, από τον Αύγουστο του 2013, εκατοντάδες χιλιάδες ναυτεργάτες θα συνεχίσουν να δουλεύουν σε συνθήκες γαλέρας, με κατώτατο μισθό ναύτη 565 δολάρια, χωρίς δημόσια ασφαλιστικά συνταξιοδοτικά δικαιώματα, με εξοντωτικά ωράρια εργασίας και …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-000" speaker_id="28215" name="Jacky Hénin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, même si ce rapport ne s'attaque qu'aux conséquences du mal, il va dans le bon sens. Il est enfin reconnu que le dumping social sur les mers existe et qu'il est facteur de danger considérable pour les hommes, pour la sûreté maritime et pour l'avenir de notre planète. Combien de catastrophes humaines et environnementales, combien de marées noires auraient pu être évitées si nous avions sérieusement combattu ce dumping, qui est l'une des armes de la mondialisation ultralibérale!</p>
      <p sl="en">Les mesures préconisées par ce rapport sont de bon sens. Encore faudrait-il maintenant que l'Union et les États membres affirment et appliquent tous les mêmes normes, recrutent et forment le nombre nécessaire d'inspecteurs pour que ces mesures ne restent pas lettre morte – des mesures préconisées qui vont se heurter aux politiques de réduction massive des dépenses publiques imposées par la Commission et le Conseil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Très vite également, nous devrons aborder la question des pavillons de complaisance, qui sont un des cancers de notre Union, au même titre que les paradis fiscaux.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-000" speaker_id="101954" name="Jan Kozłowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Wniosek Komisji zmieniający dyrektywę w sprawie kontroli przeprowadzanej przez państwo portu proponuje wiele rozwiązań, które pokrywają się z tymi z konwencji o pracy na morzu z 2006 roku. Uważam, że w większości są to dobre rozwiązania, które stanowią kolejny krok w kierunku poprawy warunków pracy marynarzy, i to niezależnie od ich obywatelstwa i bandery statku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niemniej jednak w mojej opinii część rozwiązań proponowanych przez sprawozdawcę jest zbyt daleko idących. Wymóg częstszych inspekcji okresowych, zwiększenia liczby inspektorów o określonych kompetencjach i zapewnienia odpowiednich szkoleń nakłada na państwa dodatkowe obciążenia administracyjne i finansowe. Ponadto nieuzasadnione wydaje mi się skrócenie czasu implementacji dyrektywy z dwunastu do jednego miesiąca od daty jej wejścia w życie. Ze względu na procedury legislacyjne obowiązujące w poszczególnych krajach, ten termin może nie zostać dotrzymany.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-000" speaker_id="99325" name="Σπύρος Δανέλλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Κύριε Επίτροπε, η Σύμβαση Ναυτικής Εργασίας του 2006 αποτελεί ορόσημο στην προσπάθεια χαλιναγώγησης κάποιων από τις πιο επιζήμιες επιπτώσεις της παγκοσμιοποίησης. Τις τελευταίες δεκαετίες η ποντοπόρος ναυτιλία έχει λειτουργήσει ως κινητήρια δύναμη της παγκόσμιας οικονομίας, διακινώντας το 90% του παγκόσμιου εμπορίου, αλλά το μεταφορικό έργο επιτεύχθηκε χωρίς να έχουν εξασφαλιστεί βασικές συνθήκες εργασίας του 1,2 εκατομμυρίου ναυτεργατών και το αποτέλεσμα, πλην των άλλων, είναι ότι η θέση των σοβαρών πλοιοκτητών και κρατών σημαίας από ευρύτατα διαδεδομένα φαινόμενα ανευθυνότητας και κοινοτικού ντάμπινγκ υποσκάπτεται. Η ενσωμάτωση της σύμβασης στο σύστημα ελέγχου του κράτους λιμένα της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης θα εξασφαλίσει καλύτερες συνθήκες για τους ναυτικούς στα πλοία που ελλιμενίζονται στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, ανεξαρτήτως εθνικότητάς τους. Κατ’ αυτόν τον τρόπο με φόντο τα τραγικά γεγονότα του Απρίλη που μας πέρασε στο Σαβάρ του Μπανγκλαντές καθίσταται άλλη μια φορά σαφές πως η παγκοσμιοποιημένη εργασία μπορεί και πρέπει να υποβάλλεται σε δίκαιους κανόνες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-000" speaker_id="24942" name="Ana Miranda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">As catástrofes que se podiam ter evitado na Europa, acaba de dizer um colega, lembram o “Prestige”, lembram aquele acidente nas costas da Galiza, ainda hoje, dez anos depois, a ser julgado na Corunha. No passado dia 25 de junho, celebrou-se, Sr. Simpson, como o senhor sabe, o Dia Internacional do Mar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hoje, discutimos neste Parlamento um importante relatório que ajuda a melhorar a qualidade de vida dos profissionais marítimos, a segurança marítima e o combate contra navios de má qualidade, inaceitáveis em termos de segurança marítima. Reforçar todas as garantias e controlos de segurança marítima na costa da Europa é uma necessidade para evitar o “dumping” social, mas ainda falta estímulo porque nem todos os 28 Estados-Membros ratificaram esta normativa. Uma normativa que ajude a reforçar a segurança marítima é de vital importância e contará com o meu voto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-000" speaker_id="23413" name="Mojca Kleva Kekuš" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Socialni standardi in standardi dela, ki smo jih vzpostavili v Evropski uniji, so ene temeljnih vrednot, ki jih imamo znotraj EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tudi, ko gre za naše pomorščake, moramo brez izjeme vedno zagotoviti, da mednarodne konvencije ne povzročijo nižanja standardov splošne ravni varstva pri delu. Verjamem, da smo s spremembo direktive o pomorski inšpekciji države pristanišča dosegli prav to in zato bi se rada zahvalila poročevalcu Simpsonu, ki je odlično opravil svoje delo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ker prihajam iz Kopra, slovenskega pristaniškega mesta, verjamem, da lahko s transparentnim pristopom k pomorstvu in pomorskemu gospodarstvu izboljšamo privlačnost pomorskega poklica in tako odpiramo tudi nova delovna mesta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na tem mestu bi res rada pozvala tudi svojo državo, ki tega še ni storila, da konvencijo ne samo podpiše, ampak tudi ratificira čim prej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, I would just like to repeat that we are discussing a proposal which aims to enforce the International Labour Organization’s Maritime Labour Convention through port State control. These are international standards and we must implement and follow these standards.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is one of the two enforcement instruments related to the 2006 Convention to be adopted by the European Union. Therefore we are following international practices and I would like to thank the European Parliament’s Committee on Transport and Tourism for its strong support on enforcing the rights of seafarers.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to draw your attention to the fact that this proposal is linked to another proposal which you will soon debate regarding the responsibilities of EU flag states for enforcing an agreement of the EU social partners on the Maritime Labour Convention. The compromise reached by the rapporteur Ms Berès and the Irish Presidency has recently been approved by the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs. Adopting these two legislative proposals will show how seriously the convention is being taken in the European Union, not only vis-à-vis our stakeholders but also internationally with regard to ships flying third-country flags and calling at EU ports.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-000" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to add my thanks to the Commission and also to the shadow rapporteurs for the work they did in getting this agreement under the Irish Presidency. I just want to remind Members that this ratification is a step in the right direction. What we are doing here is putting into EU law what has already been agreed at the International Labour Organization, but we are not doing just that, we are doing it with provisions which mean that EU labour laws would not be compromised. So we have protected our own labour laws whilst, at the same time, ratifying the international agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Do we still face challenges with flags of convenience and sub-standard ships? Yes we do, but I believe this report takes us in the right direction in trying to address that particular problem. I would say to the national governments that we have done our bit in Parliament; it is now up to them to do their part – especially those who have not ratified the Maritime Labour Convention (MLC) or have not signed up. They should do so immediately, or as soon as possible, so that by August all the Member States should be signed up when the MLC comes into force.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-065-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Dienstag, 2.[nbsp ]Juli 2013, um 12.00[nbsp ]Uhr statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Registration documents for vehicles - Inspection of the roadworthiness of commercial vehicles - Roadworthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-067-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die gemeinsame Aussprache über</p>
      <p sl="en">den Bericht von Vilja Savisaar-Toomast im Namen des Ausschusses für Verkehr und Fremdenverkehr über den Vorschlag für eine Richtlinie des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates zur Änderung der Richtlinie 1999/37/EG des Rates über Zulassungsdokumente für Fahrzeuge (COM(2012)0381[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]C7-0187/2012[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]2012/0185(COD)) (A7-0199/2013),</p>
      <p sl="en">den Bericht von Olga Sehnalová im Namen des Ausschusses für Verkehr und Fremdenverkehr über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates über die technische Unterwegskontrolle von Nutzfahrzeugen, die in der Gemeinschaft am Straßenverkehr teilnehmen, und zur Aufhebung der Richtlinie 2000/30/EG (COM(2012)0382[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]C7-0188/2012[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]2012/0186(COD)) (A7-0207/2013) und</p>
      <p sl="en">den Bericht von Werner Kuhn im Namen des Ausschusses für Verkehr und Fremdenverkehr über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates über die regelmäßige technische Überwachung von Kraftfahrzeugen und Kraftfahrzeuganhängern und zur Aufhebung der Richtlinie 2009/40/EG (COM(2012)0380[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]C7-0186/2012[nbsp ]-[nbsp ]2012/0184(COD)) (A7-0210/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-000" speaker_id="96767" name="Werner Kuhn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. - Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar Kallas, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Das Straßensicherheitspaket ist ein sehr umfangreiches Dossier, das fast alle Bürgerinnen und Bürger in der Europäischen Union betrifft. Wir haben es kombiniert mit der Unterwegskontrolle von Fahrzeugen und der Registrierung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist nachweislich so, dass natürlich subjektive Fehler im Kraftverkehr und im Straßenverkehr durch die Fahrzeugführer verursacht werden, aber es gibt auch viele technische Probleme bei den Kraftfahrzeugen, und die spielen in zunehmendem Maße eine ganz entscheidende Rolle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Diskussion bei uns im Verkehrsausschuss mit einzelnen Kollegen war natürlich auch sehr stark aus der Situation in den Mitgliedstaaten heraus determiniert. Viele haben ihre best practice. Das Inspektionsprozedere hat sich, so wie es in den Mitgliedstaaten jeweils durchgeführt wurde, oft gut bewährt. Aber für uns ist es notwendig, dass wir auch unser ambitioniertes Ziel als Verkehrspolitiker, als Politiker im Europäischen Parlament erreichen, nämlich die Zahl der Verkehrstoten bis 2020 möglichst zu halbieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich danke auch der Kommission, dass sie hier einen exzellenten Vorschlag unterbreitet hat, den wir natürlich auch noch etwas modifizieren mussten. Wir stimmen, Herr Kommissar Kallas, mit Ihnen überein, dass wir unbedingt eine starke Verordnung brauchen und weniger eine Richtlinie, die den Mitgliedstaaten nachher zu viele Freiheiten lässt. Aber wir müssen natürlich auch viele Dinge anpassen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Einen großen Erfolg haben wir dadurch erzielt, dass die technischen Standards der Instandsetzung und der Inspektion auf einem sehr hohen Niveau vereinbart worden sind. Es ist ein Anhang von fast 80[nbsp ]Seiten, der hier eine ganz entscheidende Rolle spielt. Bei den Frequenzen, wie oft kontrolliert und inspiziert werden muss, haben wir uns auf einen Mindeststandard von 4-2-2 geeinigt. Aber alle Mitgliedstaaten, und das ist auch dokumentiert, können über diesen vereinbarten Mindeststandard hinaus höhere Standards ansetzen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben auch bei der Frage der Anhänger eine Einigung gefunden: Bis 2[nbsp ]000 Kilogramm sind sie bei den Mindeststandards erst mal von einer Prüfung befreit. Die Caravans sind mit dabei. Bei den Traktoren sind ab einer Geschwindigkeit von 50[nbsp ]km/h Inspektionen notwendig, wenn diese Traktoren im Transport im öffentlichen Straßenverkehr agieren. Wenn sie auf dem Feld arbeiten, und bei einer Überführung ist das nicht notwendig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei den Zweirädern war es ganz kompliziert, weil hier nämlich in 50[nbsp ]% der Mitgliedstaaten eine Inspektion noch gar nicht vorgeschrieben ist, in den anderen 50[nbsp ]% der Mitgliedstaaten ist eine strikte Kontrolle, eine Inspektion vorgeschrieben. Weil wir auch diesbezüglich noch mehr Information benötigen, um klare Verhältnisse zu haben, ist die Kommission von einer Mehrheit des Ausschusses beauftragt worden, hier bis zum Jahr 2016 nochmals einen Vorschlag vorzulegen. Ab 2016 sind alle Neufahrzeuge von Motorrädern und Mopeds sowieso verpflichtet, technische Inspektionen vorzuweisen, weil dort dann Driving Assistance und auch viele andere Dinge dabei sind.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei den historischen Fahrzeugen ist uns eine Einigung gelungen, die auch klare Verhältnisse schafft: älter als 30[nbsp ]Jahre müssen sie sein und produziert im historischen Bereich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Für die Trennung von Wartung und Inspektion – als letzter Punkt – ist das Vier-Augen-Prinzip Grundprinzip und danach sind alle Werkstätten, die zertifiziert sind, auch in der Lage, diese Objektivität einzuhalten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga Sehnalová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">zpravodajka. - Pane předsedající, návrh nařízení o silničních technických kontrolách komerčních vozidel nahradí stávající směrnici z roku 2000. Podle aktuálních statistik Evropské komise existují v současnosti obrovské rozdíly v provádění silničních technických kontrol v jednotlivých členských státech. Podíl vozidel, u nichž se při silniční kontrole zjistilo, že nejsou v souladu s požadavky na technickou způsobilost vozidla, se pohybuje v rozsahu od 0,2 až po 47 % v různých členských státech, přičemž existují velké rozdíly i mezi sousedními zeměmi. Zároveň se výrazně liší průběh a kvalita silničních technických kontrol. Některé členské státy uplatňují propracované kontrolní postupy podobné pravidelným technickým prohlídkám, zatímco jiné provádějí vizuální prohlídky, nebo pouze kontrolují technické doklady, splňují nicméně minimální požadavky současné směrnice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Významné rozdíly v podílu vozidel, která nesplnila požadavky silniční kontroly, vyplývají rovněž z různých přístupů, jež si členské státy zvolily. Z tohoto důvodu podporuji zavedení systému hodnocení rizika na evropské úrovni. Výběr vozidel, která mají být podrobena silniční technické kontrole, by měl vycházet z rizikového profilu provozovatelů, a snížit tak zátěž těch, kteří svá vozidla udržují v řádném technickém stavu. Systém na stejném principu již sedm let účinně funguje ve Velké Británii a zatímco např. v České republice bylo v letech 2009–2010 na silnicích zkontrolováno více než 44 tisíc užitkových vozidel nad 3,5 tuny a jako nezpůsobilé dalšího provozu z toho bylo označeno 790 vozidel, tj. necelé 2 % všech kontrol, ve Velké Británii bylo ve stejném období, ale při výběru vozidel podle rizikového profilu dopravců zkontrolováno 154 600 vozidel, z čehož bylo vyhodnoceno 30,6 % jako nezpůsobilé dalšího provozu. Tato čísla jasně ukazují účinnost takového systému. Systém je však třeba zavádět postupně a zajistit flexibilitu při jeho uvedení do praxe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proto navrhuji, aby se během prvních tří let zaznamenávala data o technickém stavu užitkových vozidel z pravidelných technických kontrol do národních registrů vozidel a až poté začal systém fungovat na evropské úrovni. Systém bude flexibilní také pro dopravce. Ten bude moci svůj rizikový profil vylepšit pravidelnou technickou kontrolou, nebo dobrovolnou bezpečnostní kontrolou. Výsledky této kontroly se poté zaznamenají do rizikového profilu dopravce. Vzhledem k využití evropského registru dopravců pro vozidla, která jsou kontrolována v jiném členském státě, než ve kterém jsou registrována, nebudou dopravci diskriminováni podle státní příslušnosti nebo země původu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Harmonizace důležitých prvků, jako jsou normy pro posouzení nedostatků a úroveň znalostí a dovedností kontrolorů provádějících silniční kontroly dále přispěje k odstranění nerovného zacházení a zvýší celkovou účinnost kontrol. V návrhu zároveň vyzýváme členské státy k uplatňování evropských standardů při kontrole zabezpečení nákladů na vozidle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naším dalším cílem je přispět ke snížení počtu smrtelných nehod na evropských silnicích. Evropská unie se zavázala ke snížení počtu smrtelných nehod o polovinu do roku 2020. Vzhledem k tomu, že stále narůstá počet nehod způsobený lehkými užitkovými vozidly kategorie N1, např. v roce 2011 bylo kolizí s těmito vozidly způsobeno téměř 4 000 úmrtí, považuji za důležité, abychom do rozsahu působnosti tohoto nařízení opětovně zařadili také lehká užitková vozidla. Tato kategorie by však nebyla započítána do povinného minima 5 % kontrol v členských státech za rok. To se bude vztahovat pouze na těžká užitková vozidla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na závěr mi dovolte ještě jeden údaj. Podle předpokladů Evropské komise by tento balíček měl pomoci snížit počet úmrtí na evropských silnicích způsobených špatným technickým stavem vozidla až o 1 100 úmrtí ročně. Byla bych velmi ráda, pokud bychom jeho schválením k dosažení tohoto cíle přispěli.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-000" speaker_id="97308" name="Vilja Savisaar-Toomast" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raportöör. - Austatud asepresident Kallas, head kolleegid. Mina peatun siis pikemalt direktiivi muudatusel, mis käsitleb registreerimisdokumente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Transpordi- ja turismikomisjonis esitati raportile kolleegide poolt 25 muudatusettepanekut, millest enamus leidsid kas otse või kompromisside näol ka toetust. Kõige olulisemaks käesoleva raporti puhul pean bürokraatia ja paberimajanduse vähendamist ning registreerimisreeglite ja -toimingute ühtlustamist. Mitme muudatusettepanekuga me vähendame reaalset paberiraiskamist ja suurendame kontrollimise võimalusi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Siinkohal on heaks näiteks elektrooniliste andmebaaside loomine ja laialdasem kasutamine. Läbi elektrooniliste andmebaaside kasutamise peab lähiaastatel saama võimalikuks kontrollida, kas antud sõiduki registreerimisdokumentides kirjeldatud andmed vastavad elektroonses andmebaasis olevatele. Andmebaaside laiem kasutamine annab võimaluse tagada, et meie teedel liiguvad tehniliselt korras ja keskkonnanõuetele vastavad sõidukid.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kui täna ei ole põhimõtteliselt võimalik teises liikmesriigis registreeritud sõiduki tehnilist ülevaatust kontrollida, siis tänu mitmele muudatusettepanekule nii minu kui ka kolleeg Kuhni raportis muutub kontrollimine palju efektiivsemaks. Esiteks peavad tehnoülevaatuse tulemused olema kättesaadavad elektrooniliselt ning teiseks peab olema vastav märge kas sõiduki registreerimisdokumentides või siis eraldi paberil, mis peab olema sõidukit kasutades kaasas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Siinkohal tegin omalt poolt muudatusettepanekud mõlemasse raportisse, mis näeb ette, et märge sooritatud ülevaatuse kohta peab olema registreerimisdokumentidel, ning sellisel juhul ei tule eraldi tõendit ülevaatuse kehtivuse kohta väljastada ega kaasas kanda. Selline lahendus on juba olemas paljudes liikmesriikides ning see aitab vähendada paberite hulka, mis sõidukite kasutajad peavad kaasas kandma.</p>
      <p sl="en">Üheks olulisemaks muudatuseks on ka ajutise ja alalise registrist kustutamise mõiste sissetoomine. Kahe mõiste peamine vahe on selles, et esimese puhul ei ole uus registreerimiseprotsess vajalik, aga teise puhul on.</p>
      <p sl="en">Samuti tegin ettepaneku, et sõiduki omanikul peab olema õigus ja võimalus sõiduk omal soovil alaliselt registrist kustutada, kuna kõigis liikmesriikides ei ole piisavalt reguleeritud õiguslik seisund ja vastutus kahjude eest sõiduki müümise ja uuesti registreerimise vahelisel ajal. Seepärast peaks sõiduki eelmine omanik saama sõiduki ise registrist kustutada, et vältida vastutust võimalike hilisemate kahjude eest.</p>
      <p sl="en">Samuti leidis komisjonis toetust ettepanek, mis määratleb, et kui sõidukil on olemas kehtiv ülevaatus, siis selle omaniku või liikmesriigi vahetumisel peab kehtiv ülevaatus ka jääma kehtima, kuna omaniku ega liikmesriigi vahetamisega sõiduki tehniline olukord ei muutu, ja kahe teise eelpoolnimetatud regulatsiooniga tehniliste ülevaatuste toimingud ühtlustatakse.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lõpetuseks on üks muudatusettepanek, mis ei leidnud komisjonis piisavat toetust ning mille olen esitanud täiskogule. See on muudatusettepanek, mis käsitleb registreerimisdokumentide suurust. Hetkel kehtiva direktiivi järgi on registreerimisdokumentide maksimaalseks suuruseks A4-formaat ja tegelikkuses on kasutusel väga palju erineva suurusega registreerimisdokumente. Leian, et ka siin on meil võimalik tulla meie kodanikele vastu ja kehtestada kasutaja- ja keskkonnasõbralik suurus ning läbi ühtse formaadi tagada ka nende dokumentide lihtsam kontroll.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ühtse formaadi kehtestamine ei ole midagi uut, kuna sarnaselt oleme juba otsustanud nii juhilubade kui ka erinevate isikutunnistuste formaadi osas. Loodan, et saate minu muudatusettepanekut toetada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lõpetuseks tahan tänada härra Kuhni ja proua Sehnalovat ning kõiki kaasraportööre hea koostöö eest.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, roadworthiness is all about road safety: roadworthiness tests and roadside inspections make sure that fewer accidents are caused by technical defects. The Committee on Transport and Tourism (TRAN), its rapporteurs and shadow rapporteurs have made progress in some very difficult areas. On roadworthiness testing, the committee has reinforced the provisions on preventing conflicts of interest. With roadside inspections the administrative burden will be significantly reduced by targeting the vehicles which present the greatest risk.</p>
      <p sl="en">Closer cooperation and a better exchange of information between Member States will make it easier to re-register vehicles in other Member States and avoid the re-registration of vehicles that are not fit to be on the road or have been scrapped.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, the Commission cannot be satisfied with what the committee has voted for in other areas. It is a matter of much concern to me that those vehicles which present the highest risks, namely motorcycles and other two-wheelers, are not to be subject to regular tests. It is a big surprise to me how successful the motorcycle supporters have been in having them excluded from this legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Motorcyclists are increasingly over-represented in road death statistics. Seventeen Member States that have introduced testing for motorcycles report a significantly lower number of fatalities. Mandatory testing of motorcycles saves lives. I would therefore ask you to reconsider the arguments and vote in favour of testing. I am also disappointed that the proposal to test old vehicles more frequently has been dismissed. Statistics show that the proportion of technical defects in a vehicle increases exponentially with its age.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should also show more ambition in relation to light vans. These are increasingly used to replace trucks because many obligations for heavy-duty vehicles do not apply to them. Since 2000, the numbers of light vans have increased four times more quickly than those of heavy trucks. At the same time, they are involved increasingly often in fatal crashes.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have to target the groups of vehicles that present the highest risks: motorcycles, old vehicles and light vans. Please keep this in mind when voting tomorrow.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-000" speaker_id="1917" name="Markus Ferber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen, liebe Kollegen! Zunächst einmal ein ganz herzliches Dankeschön an den Kollegen Kuhn, der einen sehr ausgewogenen Kompromiss vorgelegt hat im Interesse all derer, die ein Auto besitzen. Ich glaube nicht, dass die Häufigkeit der Untersuchung, sondern die Qualität der Hauptuntersuchung von entscheidender Bedeutung für die Verkehrssicherheit ist. Dafür ein Dankeschön, dass er dies in dieser deutlichen Art und Weise zum Ausdruck gebracht hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich selbst hatte die Ehre, für meine Fraktion die Unterwegskontrollen begleiten zu dürfen, und ich will nur kurz vier Stichworte nennen. Erstens: Ich glaube, es ist wichtig – und darauf haben wir hingewirkt als EVP –, dass sich die Anzahl der Untersuchungen in den Mitgliedstaaten nicht nur an den zugelassenen Lkw orientiert, sondern auch an denen, die durch ein Land fahren. Ich nehme das Beispiel Österreich oder Luxemburg. Da gibt es wenig zugelassene Lkw, aber viele Lkw, die durchfahren. Deswegen ist es auch im Interesse der Österreicher und der Luxemburger, dass mehr Lkw kontrolliert werden, als es eigentlich diesen Ländern entspricht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Beim Risikoeinstufungssystem war es uns als EVP wichtig, dass es auch die Möglichkeit gibt, durch freiwillige Sicherheitskontrollen, die außerhalb und zusätzlich zur Hauptuntersuchung gemacht werden, eine Verbesserung bei der Risikoeinstufung zu erreichen. Und ich bin sehr dankbar, dass dies auch gelungen ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei der Anwendung auf Nutzfahrzeuge, Herr Kommissar, da sind wir ein bisschen im Dissens. Sie reden über die gestiegenen Zulassungszahlen, aber Sie haben noch keine Zahlen für die Unfallhäufigkeit vorlegen können. Deswegen ist unser Ansatz, das auf Fahrzeuge ab 3,5[nbsp ]t zu beschränken. Ich glaube, das ist auch der richtige Ansatz, dass dort strenger kontrolliert wird, wo eher Unfälle passieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Beim Thema Ladungssicherheit besteht wieder Übereinstimmung. Da freuen wir uns, wenn die Kommission die Initiative des Europäischen Parlaments aufgreift und möglichst bald eigene Vorschläge vorlegt, weil das Thema Ladungssicherung auf europäischen Straßen von ganz entscheidender Bedeutung für die Verkehrssicherheit ist. Deswegen unterstützt die EVP-Fraktion diese Berichte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-000" speaker_id="25718" name="Saïd El Khadraoui" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de S&amp;D-Fractie. – Voorzitter, meneer de commissaris, om te beginnen wil ik natuurlijk de drie rapporteurs bedanken en onze schaduwrapporteur, mevrouw Țicău, verontschuldigen. Zij kon er vandaag spijtig genoeg niet bij zijn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Collega's, in grote mate kan mijn fractie de voorstellen van de Commissie ondersteunen om de regels in verband met de rijwaardigheid van voertuigen verder te stroomlijnen met het oog op een verbetering van de verkeersveiligheid alsook met het oog op het duurzamer maken van het voertuigpark.</p>
      <p sl="en">Met betrekking tot de frequentie van de controles is geopteerd voor een middenweg: vier-twee-twee. Wij waren er in principe voorstander van, meneer de commissaris, om voor vier-twee-één te gaan, maar wij kregen daarvoor niet voldoende steun. Maar zoals u weet blijft het voor lidstaten mogelijk om vaker te controleren en dus strenger te zijn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Over de invoering van nieuwe typen voertuigen in het systeem is er, zoals u weet, heel veel discussie over de motorvoertuigen geweest. Mijn fractie is er in principe voor om daar ook testen voor te ontwikkelen op een veralgemeende manier in heel Europa, omdat uit cijfers blijkt dat in landen die testen voor motorvoertuigen hebben ingevoerd, er wel degelijk positieve effecten zijn die het aantal ongevallen doen dalen. Ik weet ook wel dat nogal wat motorrijders dit bestrijden en dit zeer vervelend vinden, maar het is in hun eigen veiligheid en in de veiligheid van de andere weggebruikers dat we in die richting moeten gaan. Het minste wat we zouden moeten doen als we daarvoor geen meerderheid vinden, is wat extra studiewerk verrichten; we zouden dan desnoods in een later stadium met nieuwe voorstellen kunnen komen. Positief is dat de caravans bijvoorbeeld ook geïntegreerd worden, dat inzake controleapparatuur, opleiding van controleurs e.d. de richtlijnen verfijnd worden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Belangrijk is ook – en dat is het laatste wat ik nog wil vermelden – dat inzake de fraude met meterstanden een aantal positieve punten worden toegevoegd in het voorstel van het Parlement dat veralgemeend zou moeten worden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-000" speaker_id="112014" name="Phil Bennion" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, back in the UK, I have even been asked why we even need minimum standards at EU level for periodic technical inspections – or what we call MOT tests. The answer is simple: in an area of freedom of movement, where we can drive our cars from one end of Europe to the other, it is clear that we need to make sure that all vehicles crossing borders are safe, for the safety of everybody.</p>
      <p sl="de">We also need to be consistent in our approach. We are doing a lot to raise the safety and environmental standards of vehicles at manufacture, but we need to make sure that they are maintained through the life of the vehicle. In the UK, and also in many other Member States, standards of MOTs are already very high, so it is absolutely right that we try to maintain and raise standards across the EU as a whole.</p>
      <p sl="de">I still have some concerns about trailers and caravans. I have been asking questions about the justification and the evidence for the testing of trailers and caravans ever since the beginning of the process. I have to say that the questions have not really been answered, and I would be very grateful if the Commission, even at this very late stage, could provide us with some figures. I have always thought that accidents related to trailers were mostly likely to be caused by driver error, inexperience, overloading or excessive speed, and I therefore believe that subjecting trailers to roadside checks is absolutely justified and that a risk rating system should be included for trailers. Having said that, I would like to say that in general we support the proposals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle Durant" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, j'interviendrai sur un seul point, à savoir le contrôle technique des véhicules motorisés à deux et trois roues, tel que le prévoyait la proposition de la Commission. Le nombre de victimes a fortement diminué en Europe, et c'est très bien. Néanmoins, les motards sont encore surreprésentés parmi les victimes et, en particulier, parmi les blessés.</p>
      <p sl="en">De ce fait, je pense qu'il est difficile d'imaginer que les deux et trois roues, parce qu'ils auraient une roue de moins que des véhicules à quatre roues, soient dispensés du contrôle technique. Je pense que les motos et en particulier les grosses motos, sont aujourd'hui aussi sophistiquées que les voitures. Donc, comme personne ne conteste le contrôle technique des voitures, je ne vois pas très bien pourquoi, parce qu'on a une roue ou deux en moins, on échapperait à cette importance du contrôle technique. Même si les défaillances techniques ne sont que dans de rares cas à l'origine des accidents de moto, des études indépendantes montrent que, dans cinq à dix pour cent des cas, elles en aggravent largement les circonstances.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors je ne comprends pas très bien pourquoi on s'écarte de cette proposition de la Commission, et je défends ici l'idée –[nbsp ]un amendement a d'ailleurs été déposé en ce sens[nbsp ]– que la date devrait être fixée à 2016 pour les grosses motos, et à 2018 pour les petites. Et la Commission nous montrera s'il faut faire autrement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-000" speaker_id="4540" name="Philip Bradbourn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as shadow rapporteur for my group, I wish specifically to address the registration documents proposal. I welcome this report and I thank Ms[nbsp ]Savisaar and the other shadow rapporteurs for the constructive dialogue leading to an agreement on compromises that should work for the United Kingdom – which, of course, has a system of vehicle testing, taxation and registration different from that of many other EU countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">I had concerns about the original draft report’s proposal on the mandatory exchange of database information but these have now been addressed, safeguarding national sovereignty over the data that Member States collect and protecting UK citizens’ private details. We can all agree that we want to see an easier and less bureaucratic system of vehicle re-registration across the European Union; however, I am pleased that this directive still allows Member States as much flexibility in implementation as is feasible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-000" speaker_id="28215" name="Jacky Hénin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. – Monsieur le Président, oui, le nombre de victimes des accidents de la route doit être pris au sérieux. Oui, l'ensemble des pays européens doivent agir de concert pour sauver la vie de nombreux innocents. Si la pédagogie doit servir à instruire les peuples sur les conséquences de leurs actes en termes de conduite, la sécurité de tous les véhicules mais, en particulier, des véhicules utilitaires circulant sur les routes de l'Union doit être améliorée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le contrôle technique est un outil important pour contribuer à cette amélioration.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est urgent que les règles soient les mêmes dans tous les États de l'Union. Il est urgent de mettre un terme aux contrôles bidons. En effet, avec la directive sur les services, qui a favorisé tous les dumpings sociaux, nous autorisons de véritables pavillons de complaisance du transport routier, avec ce que cela représente comme danger pour les salariés eux-mêmes, pour les usagers de la route, pour les populations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le renforcement de la sécurité routière passe aussi par l'entretien des infrastructures routières, de plus en plus souvent mal entretenues et accidentogènes du fait des politiques d'austérité imposées par l'Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, l'Europe doit avoir conscience que, en raison de l'appauvrissement de sa population, ce sont les salariés les plus pauvres qui sont relégués le plus loin de leur lieu de travail, là où il n'existe pas de transport public. Ayant peu de moyens, ils possèdent souvent de vieux véhicules.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'augmentation du pouvoir d'achat des salariés peut donc être un des moyens de lutter contre l'insécurité routière et de relancer la production d'automobiles en Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-000" speaker_id="96654" name="Jaroslav Paška" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu EFD – Niet pochýb o tom, že technický stav motorových vozidiel výrazne ovplyvňuje bezpečnosť dopravy na našich cestách. Pravidelné technické kontroly motorových vozidiel sa preto v zmysle európskej legislatívy stali súčasťou podmienok pre ich používanie na cestách.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chcel by som však upozorniť na to, že niekedy aj dobre myslené legislatívne kroky nám môžu narobiť vážne problémy. Pravidelné technické kontroly motorových vozidiel sa napríklad v mojej krajine stali nástrojom na zdieranie a šikanovanie majiteľov áut.</p>
      <p sl="en">Úrady začali bez akéhokoľvek preskúmavania udeľovať vysoké pokuty majiteľom áut, ktorí nemali v príslušnom termíne vykonanú predpísanú technickú kontrolu. Bez akejkoľvek výzvy či upozornenia vyžadujú pokuty aj od tých majiteľov, ktorých vozidlá sú dlhodobo nepojazdné a v autoopravovniach či v garáži čakajú na náhradné súčiastky.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ukazuje sa tak, že nestačí len prijať legislatívu a nastaviť technické parametre, je treba domyslieť aj mechanizmy uplatňovania zavádzaných pravidiel tak, aby sa nestali oprávneným zdrojom nespokojnosti občanov s nekompetentným pôsobením európskych inštitúcií.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-000" speaker_id="115868" name="Patricia van der Kammen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, het Commissievoorstel voor technische controle van motorvoertuigen is het zoveelste voorbeeld van volstrekt doorgeschoten regeldwang en bemoeizucht met zaken waarmee de EU zich helemaal niet mee zou moeten bezighouden.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Nederland hebben we een prima systeem voor de periodieke technische controle. We hebben het gewoon goed geregeld. Desondanks wil de Europese Commissie weer alles regelen. Pure betutteling. En om deze bemoeienis te legitimeren worden zelfs drogredeneringen en niet-onderbouwde argumenten aangevoerd. Want een noodzaak voor EU-wetgeving ontbreekt hier. Kennelijk zijn er veel te veel EU-ambtenaren die allemaal beziggehouden moeten worden. De EU moet de zeggenschap over technische controle volledig aan de lidstaten laten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-000" speaker_id="112611" name="Petri Sarvamaa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, mietintö ajoneuvojen rekisteröintiasiakirjoista pyrkii edistämään rekisteröintiasiakirjojen ja katsastuskäytäntöjen harmonisointia Euroopan unionissa. Toimin itse ryhmäni neuvottelijana tässä Vilja Savisaar-Toomastin mietinnössä, ja eniten keskustelua neuvotteluissa herätti rekisteriotteen koko. Lopulta valiokunta hylkäsi ehdotuksen asiakirjan pienentämisestä A7-kokoiseksi, ja olen itse tämän valiokuntapäätöksen takana.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nyt kun EU on juuri laajentunut 28 valtion unioniksi, on jäsenvaltioiden dokumenttien yhtenäistäminen samanlaisiksi vielä työn alla. Mielestäni pienin mahdollinen asiakirjakoko ei ole hyvä perusta harmonisoinnille, koska sitä noudattaa vain kaksi EU:n jäsenvaltiota.</p>
      <p sl="en">Toiseksi, mielestäni on tärkeää seurata lainsäädäntöuudistuksen vaikutusta sähköisiin rekisteröintitietokantoihin. Niissä pitää olla erityisen tarkkana ja kansalaisten tietosuoja täytyy turvata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tässä vaiheessa myös tietojen jakamisen jäsenmaiden välillä pitää perustua vapaaehtoisuuteen niin, että pyydettäessä tietojen luovuttaminen on toki mahdollista, mutta siten, että tietoja luovuttavan valtion viranomainen tekee päätöksen tietojen luovuttamisesta – ei siten, että pyytävän maan viranomainen saa tiedot automaattisesti nappia painamalla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Joka tapauksessa keskenään yhteensopivien sähköisten järjestelmien luominen on erittäin hyvä ja kannatettava pyrkimys. Sillä saadaan tehokkuutta ja nopeutta tilanteisiin, joissa tiedot ajoneuvosta on syytä saada mahdollisimman nopeasti esimerkiksi, jos on syytä epäillä rikollista toimintaa. Ja hyvä on sekin saavutus, että nimenomaan parlamentti haluaa rekisteriotteisiin enemmän tietoa ajoneuvon katsastuksesta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Haluan mainita vielä erikseen kollega Kuhnin mietinnön ja siinä suuria tunteita herättäneen moottoripyörien katsastusvaatimuksen. Mielestäni on erinomainen asia, ettei valiokunta niellyt komission näkemystä mukisematta. Moottoripyörien pakollinen katsastuttaminen kaikkialla Euroopassa ei voi perustua niin ristiriitaiseen tilastoon, joka meille esitettiin. Se herättää paljon epäilyksiä ympäri Eurooppaa. On hyvä, että tämä asia tutkitaan perusteellisesti. Toivon, että tämä pysyy myös täysistunnossa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-000" speaker_id="28292" name="Inés Ayala Sender" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, creo que hay que reconocer que en la Comisión de Transportes no hemos conseguido mejorar de una manera clara el texto que nos había presentado la Comisión, al menos en dos aspectos muy importantes. Y estando, como estamos, en plena ofensiva para seguir reduciendo al cincuenta por ciento las víctimas mortales de la carretera y conseguir reducir en un cuarenta por ciento los heridos y heridos graves en carretera, la verdad es que el texto votado en la Comisión de Transportes reduce, por un lado, la frecuencia de la revisión periódica de los vehículos de motor a bianual —yo entiendo que la frecuencia sí que es importante, no solamente la calidad, y más en el caso de una situación de crisis actual— y, por otro, establece la no obligatoriedad de la ITV para las motocicletas y motos de gran cilindrada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Entiendo que, en 2009, fallecieron más de dos mil motoristas, lo que representa un diecisiete por ciento de las muertes en carretera, mientras que los motoristas representan solamente una cuota del dos por ciento del total de kilómetros recorridos. Es decir, que es un diferencial importante que nos manifiesta que los motoristas son personas vulnerables en el ámbito de la seguridad vial. Por lo tanto, hemos presentado una enmienda para recuperar la obligatoriedad de la ITV para las motos de gran cilindrada y, posteriormente, para las motocicletas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Consideramos que el hecho de que cada vez haya más motoristas y de que cada vez se utilicen más motocicletas —incluso en sustitución de los coches, porque significan una economía o, a veces, por problemas en las grandes ciudades— no quiere decir que hayamos de dejar a estos usuarios en peor situación. Si pretendemos una mejora para los coches, para las motocicletas también hemos de hacerlo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Es geht hier um Straßenverkehrssicherheit. Schon ganz lange beschäftigt sich die EU – das Europäische Parlament – damit, wie man die Zahl der Verkehrstoten und der Schwerverletzten reduzieren kann. Wir haben durch viele Maßnahmen schon einige Besserungen erreicht, aber die Zahl ist noch immer viel zu hoch. Jetzt geht es darum, wie man die Fahrzeuge so überprüfen kann, dass sie mehr Verkehrssicherheit bieten. Die Berichterstatter, Herr Kuhn, Frau Sehnalová und Frau Savisaar-Toomast, denen ich herzlich danke, haben sich damit ausführlich beschäftigt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte mich auf den Aspekt der Untersuchungen beschränken, genauer der Verkehrsuntersuchungen, und zwar auch aus folgendem Grund: Im Vorfeld dieser Diskussion ist mir ein Test vorgestellt worden, bei dem man Fahrzeuge mit den gleichen Mängeln in verschiedenen Mitgliedstaaten zur Hauptuntersuchung gegeben hat. Und ich war vollkommen erschrocken, dass es sogar Mitgliedstaaten gab, in denen defekte Bremsen nicht erkannt wurden. D.[nbsp ]h., es gab ganz offensichtlich sehr unterschiedliche Maßstäbe, nach denen untersucht wurde. Das darf nicht sein! Wir brauchen deswegen eine Harmonisierung. Es ist ja nicht so, wie eine Kollegin jetzt suggerierte, dass die Kommission alles selbst überprüft. Das machen nach wie vor die Mitgliedstaaten. Aber es muss eben ein einheitliches Vorgehen geben. Das finde ich vollkommen richtig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich stimme übrigens vollkommen mit dem Kommissar überein: Es ist schade, dass die Motorräder nicht drin sind. In Deutschland sind wir ja sehr gründlich. Wir prüfen nicht nur die Autos, sondern auch die Motorräder, auch die Traktoren, auch die Anhänger. Aber nur die Anhänger haben im Verkehrsausschuss eine Mehrheit erhalten. Das wäre also durchaus zu optimieren. Gut finde ich, dass es nicht nach 160[nbsp ]000 Kilometern automatisch jährlich eine Untersuchung geben muss, denn gerade in Flächenstaaten fahren wir alle sehr viel, und das muss noch lange nicht bedeuten, dass unsere Autos schadenanfällig oder eben sehr verkehrsunsicher sind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-000" speaker_id="96664" name="Anna Rosbach" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Hr. formand! Hr. kommissær! Hver dag krydser tusindvis af bilister grænsen mellem to medlemslande i EU, både private bilister og erhvervsbilister. Transportsektorens grænseoverskridende karakter gør, at vi må have visse fælles regler for alle bilister. I dag er der alt for store forskelle mellem de enkelte medlemslande. Køretøjer, der godkendes i et land, lever ikke op til kravene i et andet, som også andre kollegaer har nævnt i dag. I dag eller i morgen skal vi stemme om tre betænkninger, som vil forbedre trafiksikkerheden i Europa. Betænkningen om minimumstandarder for regelmæssig kontrol af motorkøretøjer udvides forhåbentlig snarest til også at omfatte scootere og motorcykler, da disse jo ofte er involverede i meget, meget tunge og alvorlige ulykker, især på grund af meget høj hastighed. Jeg hilser også betænkningen om minimumsstandarder for syn ved vejsiden af erhvervskøretøjer velkommen. Med forslaget sikrer vi, at alle medlemsstater gennemfører et minimumsniveau af vejsideinspektioner hvert år for erhvervskøretøjer. Jeg vil derfor med god samvittighed stemme for disse betænkninger. Det vil øge trafiksikkerheden i hele EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-000" speaker_id="28506" name="Mike Nattrass" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, here we have more legislation from the EU sausage machine to waste UK civil servants’ time and confuse citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have listened to debates on the length of chickens’ beaks, inquiries into how much wine there is in a wine[nbsp ]gum and facts about rotten fruit leading to drunken reindeer which then savage people. The message-tapping CIA must be bored out of their tiny minds. You would serve your countries better by staying at home and chewing cardboard.</p>
      <p sl="en">There was a time when the British thought the Italians were amusing: ignoring the rules after making so many. We now understand that an over-supply of silly rules leads to disrespect for the law, and pedestrian crossings become suitable only for those with a suicidal tendency. We have far too much law. EU rules are openly broken and are not enforced by the Commission. This puts those who obey the rules into an adverse trading position. The failure to enforce EU law on the size of chicken cages, causing problems with egg production, is just one very costly example.</p>
      <p sl="en">Should you have further rules and mad-cap ideas up your sleeves, I suggest you shove them up your armholes or, like the Italians, make love not law. UKIP backs Westminster as the place where UK law must be made. For these reasons, UKIP will vote against this new law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-000" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, les propositions de texte dont nous débattons ont prétendument pour objectif de contribuer à la sécurité routière et à la protection de l'environnement. Elles veulent renforcer le contenu, la fréquence et le champ d'application des contrôles techniques.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le problème, c'est que les arguments de fond de la Commission pour justifier son intervention ne tiennent pas face aux statistiques. Le lien de causalité entre accidents et défaillances techniques des véhicules est marginal. Pire, en ce qui concerne les deux roues, ce lien est établi par des études menées par des entreprises leaders du marché des contrôles techniques. Ces études sont non seulement orientées mais également démenties par d'autres études indépendantes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons subi un lobbying intense des entreprises qui lorgnent sur la manne financière que représenteraient des contrôles fréquents et obligatoires, ainsi qu'une technocratie boulimique de réglementations pointilleuses et inutiles épaulée par des rapporteurs encore plus enragés. Les premières victimes sont les citoyens européens les plus modestes, ceux qui conduisent des véhicules anciens, faute de moyens pour en changer.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Assemblée nationale et le Sénat français ont estimé que ces textes contrevenaient au principe de subsidiarité. Il est très curieux que l'on aie recours au règlement et non pas simplement à la directive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-000" speaker_id="2247" name="Mathieu Grosch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich möchte der Kommission und auch den Berichterstattern für ihre Arbeit danken. Im Gegensatz zu dem, was einige Kollegen sagen, bin ich überzeugt davon, dass wir hier eine europäische Regulierung brauchen. Jetzt beginnt die Ferienzeit. Stellen Sie sich vor, dass heute die technischen Kontrollen in 27[nbsp ]Ländern verschieden wären und dann noch in jedem Land erneut durchgeführt werden müssten. Das sollten Sie auch mal Ihren Bürgern zuhause erklären, dass Europa auch das Leben erleichtern kann und nicht nur erschweren, wie Sie es immer darstellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die technischen Kontrollen, wie sie hier bereits in der Vergangenheit diskutiert wurden, haben, wie eben gesagt, zur Verbesserung der Technik beigetragen. Wir hatten noch nie eine so gute Technik wie heute, was auch der Verbesserung der Sicherheit dient. Gott sei Dank geht die Anzahl von Unfällen mit tödlichen Folgen sehr stark zurück, bis zu 40[nbsp ]% in den letzten zehn Jahren. Und nicht zuletzt gibt es auch einen positiven Einfluss auf die Umwelt. All das haben wir im Parlament in den letzten Jahren korrekt unterstützt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir wollen aber auch nicht, dass die Kontrolle morgen zur Schikane wird. Die Kontrolle soll diesen Mehrwert weiter unterstützen. Daher bin ich der Meinung – das kommt vielleicht daher, dass ich aus dem Grenzgebiet komme –, dass wir den sich aus Kontrollen ergebenden grenzüberschreitenden Mehrwert suchen müssen. Wir haben den Vorschlag gemacht, dass Angaben über Wagenkilometerstand zum Beispiel oder größere Unfälle, in die ein Wagen verwickelt war, zumindest für den Käufer zugänglich sein sollten, weil nachgewiesen ist, dass über 80[nbsp ]% der Zahlen falsch sind, wenn ein Gebrauchtfahrzeug grenzüberschreitend verkauft wird. Das ist auch europäischer Mehrwert, den wir mit einer derartigen Gesetzgebung schaffen können. Das ist sogar eine Vereinfachung für den Bürger, der sich das zu Herzen nimmt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Als Letztes: Das Thema Lkw ist angesprochen worden. Es stimmt, dass es bei den Lkw-Kontrollen natürlich nicht nur den technischen Aspekt gibt, sondern auch einen sozial wichtigen Aspekt. Denn wer tagtäglich mit so einem Lkw unterwegs ist, der muss wissen, dass er technisch in Ordnung ist. Aber hier muss man auch einen weiteren Aspekt unterstreichen: Unsere Gesetzgebung auf EU-Ebene kann noch so gut sein, wenn die Mitgliedstaaten nicht mitmachen und die Kontrolle nicht selbst durchführen, dann bringt das nichts. Hier herrscht geteilte Verantwortung. Wir tragen sie auf EU-Ebene, die Länder sollen sie auch zuhause durch gute Kontrollen tragen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-000" speaker_id="118999" name="Franco Frigo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mi congratulo con i relatori per l'ottimo lavoro svolto sul pacchetto dei controlli tecnici dei veicoli.</p>
      <p sl="en">Spiace che qualche collega per polemica antieuropea strumentalizzi un argomento così importante e significativo. L'obiettivo infatti della proposta è di migliorare la sicurezza stradale, che è un tema drammatico per tutti gli innumerevoli morti e per le persone che restano danneggiate per tutta la vita, per gli aspetti ambientali – non dimentichiamo quante malattie nascono dalle emissioni non sufficientemente controllate, conseguenti alle carenze di manutenzione dei veicoli – e, non ultimo, la lotta alle frodi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ritengo quindi positivo che la proposta miri ad armonizzare gli aspetti chiave dell'ispezione tecnica dei veicoli, che è molto diversa in ogni Stato membro mentre gli stessi si muovono indipendentemente dagli Stati. È importante che l'ispezione tecnica dei veicoli garantisca la qualità dei test e la sicurezza del veicolo stesso. Mi rammarico che non sia stato possibile approvare anche l'inclusione dei motoveicoli, dei motocicli e degli scooter e mi auguro che il Parlamento con la proposta di emendamenti possa recuperare quest'omissione e in questo mi associo al Commissario Kallas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-000" speaker_id="4553" name="Jacqueline Foster" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would just like to briefly comment on two reports: the periodic testing and the roadside checks.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, on the Kuhn report, we all agree that we need good safety standards across Europe and I think that there are some areas that have still not been addressed. On a positive note, I am relieved to see that the testing on classic cars, motorcycles and agricultural tractors has rightly been left to the competence of the Member State. There is no evidence to suggest that the inclusion of caravans – a six billion pound industry in the UK – and light commercial trailers would benefit from a road safety angle. We should be encouraging our leisure and tourism industries, not penalising them.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have also voiced concerns that this report could potentially prevent over 20[nbsp ]000 repair garages in the UK from effectively carrying out inspections and, as a result, would undermine our UK MOT system, which is robust.</p>
      <p sl="en">On roadside checks, inspections need to be targeted on heavy goods vehicles and not vans and Member States’ subsidiarity must be taken into account.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, the British Conservatives will not support the reports as they currently stand as some of the proposals are, unfortunately, still ill-conceived and unacceptable. They are over-prescriptive, too burdensome and too costly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-000" speaker_id="33775" name="Jean-Pierre Audy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Vice-président de la Commission, chers collègues, nous sommes en train de débattre d'une proposition de règlement de la Commission européenne qui vise à actualiser les exigences techniques de la directive de 2009 sur le contrôle technique des véhicules à moteur et qui élargit son champ d'application aux deux roues. J'interviendrai sur ce dernier point, c'est-à-dire l'élargissement au champ d'application aux deux roues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, dans le débat, on a entendu des parlementaires comparer les motos et les voitures, mais ce n'est pas comparable. Un motard s'occupe bien mieux de sa moto qu'un propriétaire de voiture.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors il faut regarder le lien entre les victimes, les accidents et l'état mécanique de la moto. Or, force est de constater que sur –[nbsp ]je crois[nbsp ]– sept rapports, il y en a deux des administrations, qui sont plus ou moins indépendantes, et trois de DEKRA, qui est un important opérateur sur le marché. Or, les motards nous ont dit, dans tout ce débat, que le chiffre de la Commission selon lequel 8[nbsp ]% d'accidents seraient liés à l'état mécanique du véhicule était erroné; nos assureurs nous disent que c'est moins d'1[nbsp ]%.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'est ce point, Monsieur le Commissaire, que nous aimerions voir éclaircir. C'est la raison pour laquelle je soutiens et je salue le travail qui a été accompli par mon collègue Michel[nbsp ]Dantin au sein de la commission. Nous souhaiterions que ce soit éclairci pour que nous ne légiférions pas sur la base de données qui sont fausses. Les statistiques d'accidentologie doivent être précisées, et nous découvrirons probablement qu'il y a un problème sur les vélomoteurs et les cyclomoteurs, mais non pas tant sur les motos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il faut prévoir des formations pour les motards, les obliger à porter des gants, des bottes, des blousons. Il y a aussi le problème de la qualité des réseaux routiers, et si nous avons des morts parmi les motards, c'est parce qu'il y a des accidents, mais ceux-ci ne sont pas liés, dans les proportions que la Commission affirme, à l'état mécanique des véhicules. Donc, il faut un peu de temps.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous savez que tous les gouvernements sont opposés à cette réglementation. Donc la sagesse du compromis de M.[nbsp ]Kuhn est la bonne décision que ce Parlement devrait prendre.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-000" speaker_id="96842" name="Ismail Ertug" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Die jährliche Zahl an Toten im europäischen Straßenverkehr bleibt nach wie vor alarmierend. 85[nbsp ]Menschen sterben tagtäglich auf Europas Straßen. Umso wichtiger ist es, dass wir gemeinsame und strengere Standards sowohl für die technische Fahrzeuginspektion als auch für die Ausbildung der Prüfer haben. Ich denke, dass das vorgelegte Paket zur Straßenverkehrssicherheit dafür ganz entscheidende Weichen stellt. Denn erstmals soll nach Ansicht der Kommission auch für Anhänger und Motorräder eine europaweite Prüfpflicht gelten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das befürworte ich ausdrücklich und appelliere ebenfalls an alle Kolleginnen und Kollegen, bei der morgigen Abstimmung den Antrag über die Aufnahme der Motorräder in den Geltungsbereich der Verordnung zu unterstützen. Derzeit werden Motorräder nur in jedem zweiten Mitgliedstaat regelmäßig inspiziert, obwohl die Motorradfahrer die am meisten gefährdeten Verkehrsteilnehmer sind und 8[nbsp ]% der Unfälle auf technische Mängel zurückzuführen sind. Das geht klar aus den verschiedenen Unfallstatistiken hervor, und sie zeigen auch, dass die Zahl der verunglückten Motorradfahrer über die letzten Jahre hinweg stagniert hat, während in anderen Bereichen die Verkehrstoten glücklicherweise rückläufig sind. Daher bitte ich nochmals ausdrücklich um Unterstützung morgen, die Motorräder mit in den Geltungsbereich der Richtlinie aufzunehmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-000" speaker_id="96733" name="Antonio Cancian" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mi concentro e faccio riferimento al testo proposto dall'on. Khun sull'intero pacchetto sicurezza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il testo su cui abbiamo trovato un accordo ha il merito di tenere in debita considerazione le specificità nazionali. Il rispetto del principio di sussidiarietà impone di passare ad una direttiva; dobbiamo rispettare le specificità nazionali. Il collega sa che su questo aspetto abbiamo molto dibattuto e c'era disponibilità in tal senso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Occorre poi fare attenzione alle PMI ed alle aziende familiari, le dobbiamo difendere anche nei fatti e quindi è bene non scorporare le attività di revisione da quelle di manutenzione, ove l'imparzialità sia garantita a livello di Stato membro. Abbiamo difficoltà – pensiamo all'unbundling per le grandi aziende – e, a maggior ragione, dobbiamo tenere conto di questo aspetto per le piccole.</p>
      <p sl="en">Accolgo quindi con favore la formulazione votata all'articolo 12.4 e rilevo un errore nella traduzione in cui si omette che il riferimento all'ISO 17020 è a titolo di esempio.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-000" speaker_id="96784" name="Janusz Władysław Zemke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Chciałbym nawiązać w swoim wystąpieniu do dyskusji, która dotyczy tego, czy konieczne jest objęcie badaniami technicznymi motocykli i skuterów? Otóż ja jestem zdecydowanie za tym, żeby tak się stało. Prawda jest bowiem taka, że na europejskim rynku przybywa coraz więcej i motocykli, i skuterów. Nie są to już takie pojazdy, jak to bywało kiedyś. Są to pojazdy często coraz cięższe i coraz bardziej skomplikowane technicznie. Stanowią one w związku z tym istniejące i narastające zagrożenie. Uważam, że przyjęcie dokumentów prawnych bez tych typów pojazdów nie spowoduje na terenie Unii istotnej poprawy bezpieczeństwa i ochrony środowiska. Gdyby Parlament tego nie uczynił, to byłby to moim zdaniem bardzo poważny błąd.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-000" speaker_id="1852" name="Dieter-Lebrecht Koch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Mit Begeisterung sehe ich den Verordnungsvorschlag für die technische Unterwegskontrolle. Dieser umfasst erstmals auch Aspekte der Sicht- und Tiefenkontrolle der Ladungssicherung. Dies ist ein beträchtlicher Schritt zur Verkehrs- und Rechtssicherheit, aber auch zu Wettbewerbsgerechtigkeit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wichtig ist mir vor allem, dass sich europaweit einheitliche Ladungssicherungsregeln durchsetzen, die dann auch in der Aus- und Weiterbildung von Berufskraftfahrern, von Verladepersonal, von Spediteuren und von all den Kontrollpersonen ihren Niederschlag finden. Bisher wird die unfallrelevante Ladungssicherung in den Mitgliedstaaten so extrem unterschiedlich überprüft, wie es schlimmer nicht geht. Es gibt Länder, in denen überhaupt nicht überprüft wird, andere haben nicht einmal anerkannte Regeln, wieder andere legen Fahrzeuge still, wenn die Ladung nicht richtig gesichert ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ladungssicherung war ein Hauptanliegen meines Initiativberichts für Straßenverkehrssicherheit bis 2020. Ich freue mich über diesen Vorschlag der Kommission!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-000" speaker_id="23868" name="Monika Flašíková Beňová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mobilita osôb v Európskej únii neustále rastie a právne predpisy, ktoré sa zaoberajú povinnosťou kontroly technického stavu vozidiel, musia byť na úrovni Európskej únie lepšie harmonizované. Prioritou číslo jeden musí byť najmä bezpečnosť cestnej premávky.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nové návrhy predpisov, ktoré Komisia predložila, sú podľa môjho názoru absolútne opodstatnené. Cieľom má byť najmä zníženie počtu úmrtí na cestách do roku 2020 a povedzme si úprimne, že práve v tomto segmente nám na cestách umierajú najmä mladí ľudia vo veku od 15 do 29 rokov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Preto vozidlá aj infraštruktúra musia byť bezpečnejšie a účastníci cestnej premávky sa musia správať zodpovednejšie. Veľmi dôležitým aspektom tohto návrhu je najmä skutočnosť, že ide iba o minimálne pravidlá a členským štátom musí byť ponechaná možnosť, aby si ustanovili aj prísnejšie pravidlá. Návrh je dôležitý aj z hľadiska vyššej úrovne ochrany životného prostredia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Musíme však zabezpečiť, aby sa zvýšila aj samotná úroveň a kvalita kontroly. Riešiť treba aj podvody spojené s počtom najazdených kilometrov, pretože manipulácia s[nbsp ]meračmi často spôsobuje nepravdivé a zavádzajúce informácie a je skutočne nebezpečná.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dnes som mala opäť možnosť vidieť veľkú dopravnú nehodu na jednej z nemeckých diaľnic a vidieť prevrátený a zhorený obrovský kamión vyvoláva určite obavy nielen vo mne, ale najmä v tých množstvách áut, ktoré za týmto autom išli a ktoré tam potom museli dlhý čas čakať, nehovoriac o zmarenom ľudskom živote. Takže venujme sa tejto téme naozaj s dôslednosťou, ktorú si zaslúži.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-000" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Ms Flašíková Beňová, I am very sorry to hear that. Thank you for telling the House.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-000" speaker_id="28331" name="Jaromír Kohlíček" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, děkuji za velmi zajímavý a potřebný návrh Komisi i zpravodajům. Na rozdíl od kolegy na trase z United Kingdom Independent Party a některých dalších strážců svobody se domnívám, že sjednocení v oblasti technické kontroly vozidel je nezbytné. Domnívám se, že zítra bude důležité odsouhlasit i kontroly zvláště u motocyklů a čtyřkolek. Právě řidiči těchto vozidel mají v případě nehody nejmenší šanci na přežití. Pokud je naším cílem snížení smrtelných nehod, potom upozorňuji, že nejčastější příčinou smrtelných nehod je špatná činnost řidiče, tedy špatná trénovanost. Technický stav vozidla je až na druhém místě. Přesto návrh vřele podporuji, i když vím, že v řadě případů vozidlo ve špatném technickém stavu je často jedinou šancí, jak se dostat do práce v době úspor ve veřejné dopravě.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-000" speaker_id="28323" name="Oldřich Vlasák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, i já bych chtěl poděkovat Evropské komisi za snahu o větší koordinaci těchto bezpečnostních předpisů, technických kontrol a silničních kontrol. Rozhodně jsem pro zvýšení bezpečnosti, ale ne pro zavádění dalších byrokratických systémů, evidencí atd. Totiž tento nový systém hodnocení rizika nemá evidovat konkrétní vozidla, u kterých byly v minulosti odhaleny závady, ale dopravce, a tím pádem jejich kompletní vozový park. Domnívám se, že tím pádem jsou znevýhodněny velké firmy, které provozují více vozidel. Z tohoto pohledu si myslím, že je potřeba udělat ještě některé úpravy. I systémy, které byly používány např. v Británii, tak používají sofistikovanější systém, který tam zohledňuje i osobní prvek řidiče.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-000" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Dass allein 2007/2008 circa 300[nbsp ]000 Fahrzeuge in der EU wegen ihres schlechten Zustands aus dem Verkehr gezogen werden mussten, zeigt, wie wichtig technische Unterwegskontrollen sind. Die Ausweitung des Anwendungsbereichs der technischen Unterwegskontrollen auf Nutzfahrzeuge unter 3,5[nbsp ]t mag in Anbetracht der Tatsache, dass diese bei schlechter Wartung ebenfalls andere Verkehrsteilnehmer und die Umwelt schädigen, ja durchaus sachgerecht sein. Und wenn im Zuge dieser Kontrollen Aufklärungsarbeit hinsichtlich der Ladungssicherung erfolgt, mag dies auch durchaus sinnvoll sein. Immerhin ist das Gros der Autofahrer sich der Gefahr ungesicherter Ladung im Falle einer Vollbremsung bekanntlich nicht bewusst.</p>
      <p sl="en">Einen Übergang von einer Richtlinie aber zu einer Verordnung halte ich indessen nicht für sinnvoll und nicht für nachvollziehbar. Die genaue Durchführung sollte doch den Mitgliedstaaten selbst überlassen bleiben, immerhin sind ja auch die verkehrssicherheitstechnischen Gegebenheiten von Land zu Land verschieden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-000" speaker_id="97296" name="Michel Dantin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, je voudrais tout d'abord remercier notre rapporteur du travail qui a été accompli sur le dossier du contrôle technique. Nous sommes au début de la saison touristique. Un flux important de véhicules va ainsi traverser toute l'Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je viens de l'une de ces régions qui est une destination touristique, et je veux ici apporter le témoignage tant des forces de sécurité que des professionnels de l'automobile pour dire que nous avons besoin, Monsieur le Commissaire, d'un renforcement et d'une harmonisation du contrôle technique. Trop de véhicules roulent dans un état déplorable, et il est trop difficile aujourd'hui pour les forces de sécurité de lire les documents de contrôle d'un pays tiers. C'est aussi une question de formation du personnel, qu'il s'agisse de celle du personnel qui exerce les contrôles ou de celle des personnes qui assurent le contrôle technique dans des sociétés qui doivent être indépendantes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur la question des motos, je veux m'associer à ce qu'a dit notre collègue Audy. La plupart des accidents de moto ont lieu en avril et en mai, principalement à cause du sous-gonflage des pneus. Ce n'est pas un problème technique, et le contrôle à cet égard ne peut être effectué qu'avant la mise en circulation. Nous n'avons pas la capacité de contrôler toutes les motos en mars. C'est donc irréaliste.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-000" speaker_id="28493" name="Derek Roland Clark" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have recently been in contact with the President of the Caravan Club of Great Britain. He is most concerned about this possible new legislation. I personally am horrified. I don’t know how many other people here I speak for, but I was a caravanner for many years and belonged to the Caravan Club – not to attend their gatherings and rallys and so on, but to obtain advice and information, including tips on how to tow.</p>
      <p sl="en">I hardly use my caravan in the UK. I brought it across the Channel and had my holidays here. I’ve towed it all the way from Calais to the south of France. I’ve taken it over the Alps into Italy. I’ve gone around the Alps in Switzerland and other places, all without an accident of any description. Nor did I see one with any other caravan, and nor did I see a caravan on a caravan site which had obviously been damaged in an accident. Why? Because I took my caravan for servicing myself every year.</p>
      <p sl="en">I did not want to part company with my caravan down a German autobahn. Neither does anybody else! Do people not understand that if a caravan is not in good order and has an accident on its own, like snaking or suddenly departing from its pre-designed course, then it takes the car with it and everybody in the car will suffer injury if not death?</p>
      <p sl="en">Caravanners, in spite of what they might look like, are not mad. They will look after their caravans for the sake of their own necks. This proposed regulation is completely superfluous and I will oppose it with all my strength.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the Members for the very constructive discussion that has taken place, both during the preparatory process and here in plenary.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding one fundamental question which was raised by many of you, I am convinced that we should not do anything at European level that it is possible to do at national level. I am in full support of subsidiarity. But many of the questions about road safety and how it could be improved come from the countries most affected by transit traffic – from France, the Netherlands, Germany and the UK – and from Members of the European Parliament, from members of national parliaments and especially from law enforcement agencies and traffic police organisations. The call is to do something! We need action at European level.</p>
      <p sl="en">During our discussions we considered all the details which could be left for Member States and what should be tackled at European level. It is, of course, a delicate balance and we may well have different views about this, but traffic crosses borders, especially in Europe, and ever-increasing cross-border traffic is part of our lives. A very interesting statistic is that almost 40% of accidents in Europe are caused by foreign drivers: it would seem that people are crossing borders and somehow losing vigilance and ability.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am ready to discuss in further detail what should be done at European level and what can be left for Member States. Most of these proposals have come from relevant players in the field. I am open to all discussions. We should definitely not do anything at European level which is not necessary, but all these issues, including technical roadworthiness, are relevant if vehicles – including two-wheelers and caravans – are crossing borders. We must have some kind of harmonised approach and rules concerning the technical quality of our vehicles.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am very happy to say that this is also part of a bigger picture. All our road safety achievements can be considered as a kind of European quality label. In the United States, for instance, the number of deaths on the roads per million inhabitants is twice as high as in the European Union. So we have seriously improved road safety, and we must continue to do so. We must also continue to tackle all the details, including the technical details of our road safety action plans.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-000" speaker_id="96767" name="Werner Kuhn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. - Herr Präsident! Ich möchte mich an dieser Stelle ganz herzlich bei den Schattenberichterstattern für die konstruktive Zusammenarbeit und das gute Miteinander bedanken und dafür, dass wir im Prinzip auch die Punkte angesprochen haben, die uns in unseren jeweiligen Mitgliedstaaten Schwierigkeiten bereiten, und dass wir dann auch Kompromisslösungen gefunden haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hier stehen alle Türen offen. Jeder hier in diesem Haus schaut natürlich ganz akribisch darauf und fragt sich: Was passiert in Zukunft z.[nbsp ]B. mit der Inspektion von Motorrädern? Werden wir da einen gemeinsamen Kompromiss finden? Im Ausschuss haben wir der Kommission noch einmal die Gelegenheit gegeben, uns im Prinzip belastbare Daten darüber zu liefern, wie es bei der Verkehrssicherheit von Motorrädern und Mopeds aussieht, und auf dieser Basis dann erneut einen Vorschlag zu unterbreiten, mit dem wir weiter arbeiten können. Bei älteren Fahrzeugen, Herr Kommissar, sind wir gar nicht so weit auseinander.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist ein Riesenerfolg, dass wir die technischen Mindestanforderungen, die auf einem ganz hohen Niveau sind, durchbekommen haben. Das sind insgesamt 80[nbsp ]Seiten. Da geht es um Bremsen, um Lenkung, um Chassis, alles ist genau festgelegt, was innerhalb einer Periode von zwei Jahren ausgetauscht werden muss. Im Zusammenhang mit den Caravans können wir natürlich sagen, dass das z.[nbsp ]B. für Großbritannien ein hochkompliziertes System wird. Vier Jahre nach Herstellung wird ein Caravan erst zum ersten Mal inspiziert. Und dann steht er vielleicht in einer Scheune und wird nur einmal im Jahr benutzt. Dann werden die Hühnerfedern weggefegt und man weiß nicht, ob die Bremsen noch in Ordnung sind, ob die Beleuchtung funktioniert. Dann wird er angehängt oder er wird auch dem Enkel gegeben, der gerade 18 ist, mit den Worten: „Nun fahr mal los damit, Junge“. Ich glaube, dass es notwendig ist, dass nach den ersten vier Jahren alle zwei Jahre eine Inspektion durchgeführt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zu der elektronischen Plattform, Herr Grosch hat das vorhin erwähnt: Es ist ganz wichtig, dass wir – nicht um irgendetwas auszuspionieren – hier elektronische Daten haben, also eine Art Fahrzeugakte für jedes Vehikel, jedes Fahrzeug, in die nach einer Inspektion der Kilometerstand eingetragen wird. Und wenn es eine schwere Kollision gab, wird das auch verzeichnet. Denn der, der das Fahrzeug second hand erwirbt, soll ein vernünftiges Fahrzeug mit klaren Aussagen bekommen. Bei Kilometermanipulationen wissen wir selber, wie solche Dinge laufen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich freue mich also auf die weitere Diskussion, die ja im Trilog dann fortgesetzt wird.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner ist damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel[nbsp ]149 Absatz[nbsp ]8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Meine Frage ist schlicht und ergreifend: Wir sind uns ja alle einig, aber wie können wir denn die technische Überprüfung, die ja eindeutig dokumentiert werden muss und soll, auch fälschungssicher machen? Denn nur dann funktioniert das System. Jeder, der schon einmal ein Auto gekauft hat, weiß, wie schnell da am Kilometerstand manipuliert wird. Man staunt dann selber, dass das Auto wirklich viel älter ist, als es erscheint. Wie kann man das verhindern? Herr Kollege, haben Sie da eine gute Idee für mich?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-000" speaker_id="96767" name="Werner Kuhn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Antwort auf eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Herr Kollege Jahr! Es gibt keine hundertprozentige Sicherheit. Aber wenn wir eine solche Dokumentation tatsächlich durchführen mit einer Fahrzeugakte, mit einem Fahrzeugpass, dann ist die Wahrscheinlichkeit sehr hoch, dass man hier dann klare Verhältnisse hat, was den Kilometerstand, die Fahrleistung eines Fahrzeugs betrifft, und dies vernünftig dokumentiert ist. Denn zwischen den Inspektionen wird wohl niemand sagen: „Also ich lasse jetzt mal für 30, 50 oder 100 Euro meinen Kilometerstand zurücksetzen“, der dann vielleicht noch niedriger ist als bei der letzten Inspektion. Insofern ist das die richtige Lösung. Auch im grenzüberschreitenden Verkehr und Verkauf ist das dann eine sehr praktische Lösung.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga Sehnalová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">zpravodajka. - Pane předsedající, já v těch svých závěrečných minutách bych ráda zejména poděkovala za zajímavou debatu i všechny příspěvky, byť se týkaly zejména ostatních částí balíčku. Jsem přeci jen ráda, že u některých kolegů zazněla otázka zabezpečení nákladu, kterou i já samozřejmě považuji za nesmírně závažnou. O zařazení či nezařazení vozidel kategorie N1 rozhodneme zítra hlasováním. Nicméně dovolte mi, abych poděkovala ostatních kolegům, zpravodajům a samozřejmě také stínovým zpravodajům za skutečně konstruktivní a dobrou spolupráci při přípravě tohoto balíčku. Jsem přesvědčena, že jsme plně dostáli závazku, aby výsledkem našeho společného úsilí byl skutečně konzistentní balíček založený na jednotném základu. Stejně jako kolega Kuhn se budu těšit na spolupráci s litevským předsednictvím při schvalování jeho konečné podoby a věřím, a to zaznělo z úst mnoha kolegů, že bezpečnost silničního provozu a snižování nehodovosti na evropských silnicích zůstane i nadále jednou z našich priorit v dopravní oblasti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-000" speaker_id="97308" name="Vilja Savisaar-Toomast" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raportöör. - Ka mul on hea meel tõdeda, et me ei kuulnud täna olulisi või argumenteeritud vastuväiteid tehtud ettepanekutele, ja ma loodan, et me liigume nendega kiiresti edasi. Ma loodan, et me liigume kiiresti ka elektrooniliste andmebaaside loomise suunas üle Euroopa ja teeme need ka ligipääsetavaks volitatud isikutele, et suurendada kontrolli efektiivsust.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolleeg Sarvamaa väljendas kahtlust, kas ühtse suurusega registreerimisdokument üle Euroopa oleks õige mõte või mitte. Ma loodan siiski, et homme parlament toetab ühtset suurust registreerimisdokumendile, niimoodi liigume tõhusa sammu keskkonnahoiu ja tarbijasõbralikkuse suunas. Üks väike riik, nagu Eesti, saab siin olla eeskujuks, kuidas olla kokkuhoidlik ja säästev.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kuigi nõukogu esindajaid pole saalis, ma usun ka, et me suudame nii nõukogu, parlamendi kui ka komisjoni vahel jõuda sobivatele kompromissidele ja jõuda seadusandliku akti vastuvõtmiseni veel selle aasta jooksul. Ka mina tänan omalt poolt kõiki sellest diskussioonist osavõtjaid, loomulikult kõigepealt raportööre, variraportööre ja komisjoni asepresidenti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-000" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 2 July 2013.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-125" speaker_id="96798" name="John Bufton" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">This report proposes a series of amendments to the EU Roadworthiness Package that would see light commercial vehicles subject to technical roadside inspections using mobile inspection units or test centres. Parliament may not be aware of this but in the UK we already have a procedure for testing road vehicle safety – the great British institution that is the MOT. And this is a procedure that has worked perfectly well for us to date. So, why should we in the UK be forced to replace, or at the very least modify our existing, perfectly effective and reliable system by one imposed on us by the EU? Furthermore, why should we be forced to impose this new system on an industry that is already heavily under strain as a result of excessive taxing and incredibly high fuel prices? British lorry drivers are losing their jobs and haulage companies are going out of business at a rate of knots and the very last thing they need is to be tied up in yet more unnecessary EU red tape such as that proposed in this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-250" speaker_id="99325" name="Σπύρος Δανέλλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">γραπτώς. – Για την επίτευξη του στόχου περί μηδενισμού των τροχαίων δυστυχημάτων, απαιτούνται πρωτοβουλίες και επενδύσεις σε όλες τις πτυχές των οδικών μεταφορών. Η ασφαλής κατάσταση των ίδιων των οχημάτων είναι φυσικά ένα σημαντικό προαπαιτούμενο, αλλά πρέπει να πλαισιωθεί από άλλα μέτρα όπως την καλύτερη κατάρτιση των οδηγών, ασφαλέστερες υποδομές και δρόμους, και φυσικά την εφαρμογή έξυπνων συστημάτων. Ο περιοδικός έλεγχος οχημάτων ρυθμίζεται από την Οδηγία 2009/40/ΕΚ, η οποία τέθηκε σε ισχύ μόλις πριν τέσσερα χρόνια. Θα ήταν θεμιτό να εισέλθουν στο πλαίσιο εφαρμογής της νομοθεσίας τα δίκυκλα, τα οποία θα έπρεπε να υπόκεινται σε υποχρεωτικό έλεγχο. Από την άλλη πλευρά, η αλλαγή της συχνότητας ελέγχων για τη κατηγορία Μ1, δηλαδή τα Ι.Χ., από διετή σε ετήσια, πρέπει να εξεταστεί πιο διεξοδικά και σαφώς να συνυπολογιστεί το οικονομικό βάρος που θα συνεπαγόταν για τους πολίτες της Ε.Ε. στην παρατεταμένη περίοδο κρίσης που διανύουμε.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-375" speaker_id="96792" name="Bogdan Kazimierz Marcinkiewicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Szanowny Panie Przewodniczący! Biorąc pod uwagę powagę problemu badań technicznych pojazdów, powinniśmy skupić się między innymi na kategoriach pojazdów, rozszerzając je o skutery i motocykle, gdyż ich użytkownicy są pełnoprawnymi uczestnikami ruchu drogowego. Natomiast wątpliwy stan techniczny tych pojazdów może stanowić realne zagrożenie w ruchu drogowym. Należy także podkreślić, iż istotnym elementem naszego bezpieczeństwa jest również kwestia badania przydatności do ruchu drogowego. Powinny być one prowadzone przez odpowiednio wykształconych, wyszkolonych i niezależnych diagnostów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za słuszne posunięcie uważam również wyłączenie samochodów o wartości historycznej z zakresu prawodawstwa UE. Państwa członkowskie powinny mieć więcej swobody przy określaniu własnych wymogów krajowych dotyczących definiowania i badania takich pojazdów. Dodatkowo w moim odczuciu zaproponowana definicja pojazdów mających wartość historyczną jest dość rygorystyczna.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Road safety (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-112-000" speaker_id="1405" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on the oral question to the Commission on road safety 2011-2020 – First milestones towards an injury strategy (2013/2670(RSP)) by Brian Simpson, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism (O-000061/2013 – B7-0211/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-000" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism, I welcome this oral question which gives us the opportunity to revisit the important issue of road safety. Some Members may trivialise road safety but, armpits or not, I am glad to say that – thankfully – the majority of my committee take it far more seriously.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you know, Commissioner, the European Parliament adopted a road safety report back in 2011 pushing for ambitious EU targets to be set in reducing the number of needless accidents on our roads by 2020. We know that the setting of targets is key to pushing national, regional and local authorities to put in place specific measures to actually tackle the problems that we face on our roads. Specific targets on road safety have proved successful in raising the level of ambition and achieving effective implementation of road safety policies at national and local level.</p>
      <p sl="en">While there is no doubt that specific measures and initiatives can best be tailored and adapted at national and local level, EU leadership in this area has proved successful in the past in getting Member States to recognise the seriousness of the problem.</p>
      <p sl="en">While Parliament strongly welcomed at the time the commitment to cut 50% of road deaths by 2020, we also knew that this was only partly addressing the road safety problem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deaths are only one measure of the magnitude of road accident problems. Road deaths have been declining, in some part due to the improvements in medical care. As a result, non-fatal injuries are increasing. I think one-and-a-half million people are reported to be injured every year on EU roads, with 300[nbsp ]000 of those reported to be seriously injured.</p>
      <p sl="en">I fail to understand how we can continue to be so complacent about these figures: there seems to be simply an unacceptable complacency when it comes to road safety. If aviation or our railways had the accident figures that road transport has, there would be a public outcry.</p>
      <p sl="en">Across Europe there seems to be a general acceptance or refusal to acknowledge the danger we face as road users, so the more we can do to address this issue the better. Now is the time for us to stop taking a back seat and to stop pretending that a problem is not there.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the absence of a common definition across the EU for serious injuries, we were not able to set a target for local, regional and national authorities to work towards. That is why we so welcome the recent progress report from the Commission which announces a common definition of serious injuries and a system of collecting data.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we want to ensure that the important foundations laid in Dieter-Lebrecht Koch’s report are fully followed through. Parliament requested not only that the Commission came up with a common definition quickly but that, once established, an ambitious target would be set for cutting down on serious injuries in road accidents.</p>
      <p sl="en">Can I ask the Commission when it will set a target to reduce serious injuries by 2020 and – equally important – how will it make sure that Member States are working towards that target?</p>
      <p sl="en">What accompanying measures and initiatives will the Commission put forward to support tackling serious injuries, and what measures can specifically be put in place to help more vulnerable road users such as cyclists, pedestrians and young children?</p>
      <p sl="en">Can the Commission also indicate to us the importance of road surfaces and the lack of maintenance that is now rife in Member States, and what significant effect that has on road accidents?</p>
      <p sl="en">You will see from the motion for a resolution tabled by the committee as a follow-up to the oral question that we already have a few ideas on this. Given the continued leadership we hope to see from the European Commission on road safety, I would like to hear how it plans to follow up on the common definition of serious injuries.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 149(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-000" speaker_id="28477" name="Fiona Hall" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card question. – Mr Simpson, you mentioned the fact that we needed some concrete measures in relation to vulnerable road users. Would you agree that there could and should have been in this document something about cyclists and heavy goods vehicles, with some concrete measures particularly to do with lorry cab designs so that drivers can see cyclists and pedestrians nearby much more easily, and the need for mandatory cameras and sensors so that drivers are aware of all cyclists and pedestrians in the vicinity of their vehicles?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-000" speaker_id="1309" name="Brian Simpson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – Mr President, in answering that I would direct the honourable Member to some of the work which has already been done with regard to wing mirrors and side wing mirrors so that the visibility for lorry drivers is improved in respect of vulnerable road users like cyclists. It is very diffficult in an oral question to try and bring everything together in one issue, but there is certainly an issue with vulnerable road users.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, it has also got to be said that cyclists would do themselves a great favour if, while trying to get there quicker, they stopped moving up along the near side of a lorry when a lorry has stopped and also if they did not use the pavement.</p>
      <p sl="en">In some respects I would say that ‘God helps him that helps himself’, but that does not take away the fact that there are vulnerable road users – the cyclists – and we should do anything we can do to help them. But of course Members opposite, whose seats are now radically empty, will probably tell you: the cost, the cost, the cost! Well, what is the cost of a life?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, serious road traffic injuries are of course a real problem. Around a quarter of a million people are reported to be seriously injured on EU roads every year. Their lives are often changed forever.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is why the Commission made the goal of reducing serious road traffic injuries a new and a key element of our road safety strategy, which was reflected already in the White Paper of 2011.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I must say that this idea met with considerable opposition from experts. New initiatives on serious injuries must be based on fact and for that we need to know how many serious injuries happen every year. The figures we have today are not reliable or comparable. Member States use different definitions and methodology to gather data. There are also problems of misreporting and under-reporting.</p>
      <p sl="en">Two months ago, as Mr Simpson mentioned, we proposed a common EU definition of serious injuries. This is a very important step forward. This will allow us to carry out the necessary cost-benefit analysis and then choose the most effective ways to reduce injuries.</p>
      <p sl="en">A common EU definition and reliable data are also a pre-requisite for setting an EU target. I very much appreciate Parliament’s support for the idea of setting a strategic injury reduction target. That approach proved very useful for reducing fatalities, so I hope that we can repeat this success with reducing injuries.</p>
      <p sl="en">What happens now is that Member States will collect the first figures during 2014. Based on this information the Commission will propose an ambitious target for reducing injuries. The areas we may want to look into together could include tools and techniques to limit the impact of a collision, to reduce the severity of injuries which cannot be avoided. This has been included to a certain degree in our proposal for the amendment of the Weights and Dimensions Directive.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards first-aid and emergency services: the aid received in the first hour after a crash is crucial for reducing the risk of severe consequences. Again proposals have been made to introduce an eCall system and for in-depth crash injury research to support the development of safety measures and to better understand the causes of accidents.</p>
      <p sl="en">Progress made towards reaching the injuries reduction target will be monitored, as will the fatality reduction target. Here we have a common objective with Member States. The objective of achieving a reduction in road deaths has been a common one; the work towards it has been very united, with a voluntary commitment from all actors.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-000" speaker_id="2247" name="Mathieu Grosch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar! Ich glaube, dass alle Fraktionen sehr breit diese Initiative tragen, dass Verkehrssicherheit ein Hauptthema bei uns im Ausschuss bleibt und dass wir auf europäischer Ebene da weiter initiativ werden sollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das hat mindestens zwei gute Gründe: In der Vergangenheit haben wir durch ganz konkrete Programme und auch ganz konkrete Zielsetzungen beweisen können, dass die Anzahl zumindest der Toten auf den Straßen bis zu 40[nbsp ]% reduziert wurde. Und wenn wir den Mut haben, das auch weiter in diesem Bereich bei den Schwerverletzten zu machen, glaube ich, dass wir auch gleichartige Ziele erreichen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und lassen Sie sich von denjenigen, die meinen, dass Europa hier zu stark eingreift, nicht einschüchtern, denn ich glaube, wir können in jedem Land Gutes lernen und Gutes übernehmen, eventuell auch in einigen Gesetzgebungen. Da hat das Prinzip der Subsidiarität, wenn es um dieses heikle Thema geht, überhaupt keinen Platz.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir brauchen effektiv gute Zahlen – das haben Sie gesagt –, wir brauchen zuverlässige Zahlen. 70[nbsp ]% werden geliefert. Denn die Zahlen könnten ja auch die Debatten objektivieren. Gerade beim Thema Motorräder – Kontrolle ja oder nein? – könnten wir – wenn wir die Zahlen hätten – heute eine ganz konkrete Antwort geben, warum wir Vorschläge machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber die Zahlen können auch eine Orientierungshilfe bei Beschlüssen sein. Wenn wir morgen wissen, dass z.[nbsp ]B. in den Städten, in denen man 30 km/h fährt, viel weniger Unfälle sind, dann ist das eine Information, die für alle hilfreich ist. Das ist kein Einmischen in die Subsidiarität der Länder.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir brauchen natürlich ein besonderes Augenmerk für die weniger geschützten Teilnehmer. Aber es gibt eine ganz eindeutige Einsicht. Das Fahrverhalten bleibt einer der wichtigsten Aspekte bei Unfällen: 1. die Geschwindigkeit, 2. Drogen, Alkohol und nicht zuletzt auch Müdigkeit – das sind Aspekte, die wichtig sind. Aber was sehr oft unterschätzt wird und wo alle Behörden zusammenarbeiten können – von der europäischen bis zur kommunalen Ebene –, ist die Infrastruktur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir wissen, dass die Infrastruktur in vielen Ländern dazu geeignet sein kann, Verletzte und auch Tote auf der Straße zu verhindern. Und da hoffe ich, dass wir morgen nicht nur 4-Sterne-Autos unterstützen, sondern dass wir morgen vielleicht auch 4-Sterne-Straßen in allen Ländern unterstützen. Ich glaube, das würde uns allen zugute kommen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga Sehnalová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu S&amp;D. – Pane předsedající, v roce 2012 bylo na evropských silnicích při dopravních nehodách usmrceno 28 000 a vážně zraněno více než 250 000 osob. Každé desáté zranění je vyhodnoceno jako vážné. To je důvod, proč Evropský parlament v usnesení o evropské bezpečnosti silničního provozu pro léta 2011–2020 po Komisi požadoval, aby do konce roku 2011 představila konkrétní opatření v oblasti snižování vážných zranění při dopravních nehodách. Volali jsme po stanovení cíle, který by byl založen na jednotné definici vážných zranění.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jsem ráda, že Komise v březnu tohoto roku představila pracovní dokument s názvem „Směrem k jednotné strategii v oblasti vážných zranění“, kterému předcházelo stanovení společné definice pro vážná zranění na základě skórovacího systému MAIS a schválení jednotné evropské statistiky členskými státy v lednu tohoto roku. Minulý měsíc Komise představila dlouho očekávaný návrh na zavedení bezpečnostního systému eCall založeného na tísňové lince 112 do všech nových vozidel od roku 2015. Tato důležitá, byť dílčí opatření jednoznačně vítám.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nyní je ovšem čas stanovit si konkrétní cíl v oblasti snížení vážných zranění na evropských silnicích a konkrétní opatření, která k němu povedou. V souladu se zprávou Evropského parlamentu by jím mělo být snížení počtu vážných zranění o 40 % do roku 2020. Proto se dnes ptám: Ztotožňuje se Komise s tímto cílem? Kdy a jaká opatření zejména se zaměřením na nejzranitelnější účastníky silničního provozu v městských oblastech Komise plánuje? Nesmírně důležitou oblastí je i přednemocniční péče, včetně laické první pomoci na místě nehody. Jak hodlá Komise podporovat zlepšení znalosti v oblasti poskytování první pomoci zraněnému v místě dopravní nehody mezi občany Evropské unie? Dalších otázek je celá řada. Toto jsou jen některé z nich. Naším společným cílem by mělo být nejen předcházení vážným zraněním, ale i zlepšení kvality života těch, kteří tato zranění utrpěli a kterým, včetně jejich blízkých, se tak ze dne na den změnil život.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ALDE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! 1,5[nbsp ]Millionen Verletzte auf Europas Straßen pro Jahr, 300[nbsp ]000 davon schwerverletzt, von den Toten ganz zu schweigen – das ist entschieden zuviel. Und das ist schon eine reduzierte Zahl, wir hatten früher viel mehr Schwerverletzte, Verletzte und Tote auf den Straßen von Europa zu beklagen. Wir müssen da etwas tun, das ist vollkommen klar!</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben schon viele Absichtserklärungen von uns gegeben, aber es fehlt teilweise noch an konkreten Maßnahmen. Wir haben das schöne Ziel, keine Verkehrstoten und keine Schwerverletzten mehr zu haben, die Vision 0, das klingt natürlich toll. Ich wehre mich immer ein bisschen dagegen, weil ich denke, Ziele muss man erreichen können. Das werden wir wahrscheinlich leider nie erreichen. Wir müssen aber alles tun, um da hinzukommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Verkehrsunfälle sind eine der Hauptursachen für Menschen unter 45, ins Krankenhaus zu kommen. Auch das muss uns zu denken geben! Besonders gefährdet sind generell Kinder, ältere Menschen mit Behinderungen und alle, die auf zwei Rädern unterwegs sind. Auch das müssen wir berücksichtigen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nun kann man sich natürlich fragen: Wie schaffen wir das denn, das hinzubekommen? Bessere Umsetzung von Gesetzen ist ein Weg, ansonsten – es ist vorhin von meiner Kollegin Hall angesprochen worden – befassen wir uns jetzt damit, dass man Lkw-Nasen anders ausgestalten sollte – spitz zulaufend, länger gezogen –, dann gibt es weniger schwere Unfälle und hoffentlich generell weniger Unfälle. Dann sollten wir uns eben auch über das Notrufsystem Gedanken machen, E-call, genauso wie über die Notfallversorgung: Wie kann sie optimal vernetzt werden?</p>
      <p sl="en">Und ein letztes Beispiel: In Deutschland haben wir sehr gute Erfahrungen gemacht, da gerade Fahranfänger sehr gefährdet sind, mit einem begleiteten Fahren und einem Führerschein ab 17. So etwas kann vielleicht in anderen Ländern Schule machen. Alle die jungen Menschen, die ein Jahr lang begleitet fahren, sind in der Regel hinterher wesentlich weniger unfallgefährdet. Das ist eine tolle Sache, denn gerade junge Menschen, Fahranfänger, verunglücken leider sehr häufig.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-000" speaker_id="96639" name="Isabelle Durant" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, je ne sais pas, chers collègues, si l'un d'entre vous a déjà eu, dans le cadre d'un mandat antérieur, l'occasion ou la triste circonstance d'aller annoncer à une famille le décès d'un enfant, le décès d'une personne, d'un proche, dans un accident de la route. C'est une expérience traumatisante! Et même si les chiffres sont aujourd'hui meilleurs, la réalité cela n'en est pas moins une hécatombe, et une hécatombe avec des milliers d'orphelins, des milliers de parents désenfantés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous devons donc agir plus vite et plus fort. Et je voudrais personnellement insister sur un aspect. Je me réjouis de la stratégie de la Commission concernant les blessés. Je pense que c'est une excellente initiative et qu'elle va nous aider à avoir des chiffres et une approche plus standardisés, mais je voudrais aller plus loin sur un aspect précis, à savoir la protection des usagers de la route les plus faibles.</p>
      <p sl="en">En ce sens, c'est toute la manière de concevoir la place de la voiture dans la société et, singulièrement, dans nos villes qu'il convient de revoir. Cela requiert un travail sur la qualité et la conception des infrastructures, bien sûr, mais aussi des choix clairs sur la manière de partager l'espace public. Ce n'est pas seulement une question de place laissée à la voiture, mais également une question de vitesse et de comportement.</p>
      <p sl="en">De la même manière que la congestion du trafic nuit à l'attractivité des transports publics, la vitesse des automobiles et les dangers qui y sont liés sont un véritable obstacle pour la marche à pied ou pour le vélo et, en particulier, pour les déplacements scolaires quotidiens. Et c'est d'ailleurs pour cette raison que je soutiens l'initiative citoyenne européenne visant à la généralisation des 30[nbsp ]km/h dans les villes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais nous avons aussi besoin d'une approche plus globale encore pour la sécurité des usagers faibles dans les zones urbaines. Je m'adresse à vous, Monsieur le Commissaire, mais cette problématique concerne, d'ailleurs, peut-être aussi votre successeur. Je pense que nous avons été très loin, au niveau européen sur la question de la réglementation plus contraignante en matière de droits des passagers. C'est bien. Je crois aussi que c'est le moment d'aller un peu plus loin, dans la prochaine législature, sur le droit des usagers faibles à se déplacer en toute sécurité. Il est grand temps de considérer que le fait de garantir le droit de se déplacer en toute sécurité quand on est piéton ou cycliste, doit également constituer l'une des missions prioritaires de l'Union européenne.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-000" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Es klingt ja durchaus ermutigend, dass die Anzahl der im deutschen Straßenverkehr Verunglückten einen historischen Tiefstand erreicht hat. Vor allem, wenn man bedenkt, dass sich die Anzahl der Kraftfahrzeuge seither ja verdreifacht hat. Andererseits verlieren allein in Deutschland, um bei diesem Beispiel zu bleiben, im Schnitt nach wie vor zehn Menschen täglich ihr Leben im Straßenverkehr. Es bleibt also wirklich noch viel zu tun.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unverständlich ist angesichts dieser Tatsache die Haltung der Kommission hinsichtlich der Zulassung von Gigalinern. Abgesehen von den Milliarden von Infrastrukturkosten, die dadurch auf die Mitgliedstaaten zurollen würden, wäre dies eine offene Abkehr vom Ziel der Verkehrsverlagerung auf die Schiene und ein sicherheitstechnisches Desaster angesichts des entsprechend längeren Überholwegs und der viermal höheren Unfallgefahr mit Todesfolge. Die Kommission dürfte diesbezüglich nicht länger auf die Frächterlobby hören, und sie sollte dies auch im Hinblick auf ein anzudenkendes Überholverbot von Lkw untereinander auf zweispurigen Autobahnen nicht tun.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner ist damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel[nbsp ]149 Absatz[nbsp ]8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Ich habe eine ganz schlichte Frage, Herr Mölzer, weil Sie gesagt haben, die Verkehrstoten werden durch die längeren Lkw gesteigert. Haben Sie irgendeine Zahl dafür? Ich kenne nämlich keine Zahlen. Ich habe mich sehr ausführlich damit befasst, weil wir in Niedersachsen das viel getestet haben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-000" speaker_id="28255" name="Andreas Mölzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Antwort auf eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Frau Kollegin, ich glaube, dass die mir vorliegenden Zahlen durchaus etwas für sich haben. Es mag sein, dass empirisch die Werte erst nach dem wirklichen Auftreten dieser Gigaliner erhoben werden können. Ich glaube aber doch, dass die Gefährdung, die durch solche gewaltige Lastfahrzüge gegeben ist, evident ist, und die Kosten für die Infrastruktur sind es ohnedies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-000" speaker_id="96733" name="Antonio Cancian" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il tema della sicurezza stradale viene giustamente riportato al centro della discussione e gli obiettivi ambiziosi ma raggiungibili posti dalla Commissione europea e condivisi da questo Parlamento necessitano di azioni concrete a livello nazionale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo bisogno di infrastrutture intelligenti che possano dialogare con i mezzi e con i conducenti. L'implementazione dei sistemi di trasporto intelligente deve essere incentivata cercando poi una regia europea in modo da garantire l'interoperabilità dei sistemi. Dobbiamo fare attenzione al grande problema e causa di grandi occasioni di incidenti e agli elementi di distrazione del conducente: telefoni cellulari, schermi TV, navigatori satellitari: questo è il grandissimo problema che deve essere affrontato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lo stesso approccio deve essere adottato nella gestione dei dati sui veicoli e sui conducenti e l'applicazione transfrontaliera delle sanzioni deve essere rafforzata. Dobbiamo promuovere la ricerca nel settore dei dispositivi di protezione degli utenti più deboli: pedoni, ciclisti e motociclisti. Il casco, ad esempio, potrebbe integrare dispositivi di segnalazione luminosa di emergenza o di direzione aumentando la visibilità dei motociclisti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dobbiamo intervenire sull'abuso di sostanze stupefacenti e alcool. Esistono in Europa brevetti di sistemi che impediscono l'accensione del mezzo nei casi di abuso. Dobbiamo migliorare il percorso di formazione alla guida e i controlli di idoneità per il rinnovo delle patenti di guida, aumentare la consapevolezza del rischio nella circolazione in aree urbane; le campagne di sensibilizzazione a livello locale hanno dato risultati importanti nel programma scolastico e questo tipo di formazione deve avere lo spazio che si merita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-000" speaker_id="28238" name="Michael Cramer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ja, natürlich brauchen wir mehr und verbesserte Technik! Aber das ist nicht alles. Deshalb brauchen wir unbedingt die Erfahrung, wie das ist, wenn Tempo[nbsp ]30 eingeführt ist, weil überhöhte Geschwindigkeit das größte Unfallrisiko in der Europäischen Union ist. Uns ist dabei Subsidiarität ganz wichtig. Wir wollen nicht den Städten vorschreiben: Ihr müsst das so und so machen. Aber wir wollen den Städten die Möglichkeit geben, dass sie es tun können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich komme aus Berlin, das ist ein Stadtstaat. Dort konnte die Landesregierung entscheiden, 80[nbsp ]% der Straßen zu Tempo-30-Zonen zu machen. Das hat die Sicherheit enorm erhöht. Denn bei Tempo[nbsp ]30 haben wir 42[nbsp ]% weniger Unfälle, wir haben den Bremsweg im Verhältnis zu Tempo[nbsp ]50 von 28 auf 14[nbsp ]Meter halbiert. Und das Todesrisiko mit einem schwächeren Verkehrsteilnehmer ist bei Tempo[nbsp ]50 80[nbsp ]%, bei Tempo[nbsp ]30 10[nbsp ]%. Wer also Verkehrssicherheit will, kommt daran nicht vorbei. Das ist entscheidend. Tempo[nbsp ]30 lichtet den Schilderwald, Tempo[nbsp ]30 senkt die Kosten und Tempo[nbsp ]30 erhöht die Akzeptanz dieser Geschwindigkeit, die vorgegeben ist. Die Kommission hat vor mehr als 25[nbsp ]Jahren schon darauf hingewiesen und wollte Temporegulierungen auf europäischer Ebene einführen. Wir warten noch immer auf den Vorschlag Ihres Vorvorvorvorgängers, Herr Kommissar!</p>
      <p sl="en">Was wird sich ändern? Wenn wir in Berlin Tempo[nbsp ]30 als Regelgeschwindigkeit einführen, wie das Parlament mit großer Mehrheit auch beschlossen hat, dann wird sich für den Autofahrer gar nichts ändern. Denn 20[nbsp ]% der Straßen werden als Tempo-50-Straßen ausgewiesen, statt als Tempo-30-Straßen. Das einzige, was sich ändert: Sie werden in einer Tempo-50-Straße keinen Autofahrer finden, der 30 fährt und sagt: Oh, ich hab das Schild gar nicht gesehen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-000" speaker_id="97011" name="Γεώργιος Κουμουτσάκος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι αριθμοί μιλούν από μόνοι τους και είναι αιτία μεγάλης ανησυχίας και προβληματισμού. Αν και είναι γνωστοί, αξίζει να ακουστούν ακόμα μία φορά: Περισσότεροι από 30.000 άνθρωποι έχασαν τη ζωή τους και σχεδόν 1,5 εκατομμύριο έχουν τραυματιστεί. Μάλιστα απ’ αυτούς οι 250.000 σοβαρά, σε τροχαία ατυχήματα στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση μόνο το 2011. Σε κάθε θανατηφόρο ατύχημα αντιστοιχούν 4 ατυχήματα που προξενούν μόνιμες αναπηρίες και 10 που προξενούν σοβαρούς τραυματισμούς. Περισσότεροι από τους μισούς τραυματισμούς συμβαίνουν σε αστικές περιοχές. Το κοινωνικό και οικονομικό κόστος των τραυματισμών από τροχαία ατυχήματα ανέρχεται στο 2% του Ακαθάριστου Εθνικού Προϊόντος της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης ή σε 250 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ για το 2012.</p>
      <p sl="en">Από το 2001 έως το 2010 οι στοχευμένες δράσεις που πρότεινε η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή είχαν θετικά αποτελέσματα και πρέπει να το αναγνωρίσουμε. Ο αριθμός των θυμάτων σε τροχαία ατυχήματα μειώθηκε σημαντικά σε αρκετές χώρες. Είναι σημαντικό και ελπιδοφόρο ότι το 2010 η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή ανανέωσε τη δέσμευσή της για περαιτέρω μείωση των ατυχημάτων κατά 50% έως το 2020. Έχει δεσμευτεί για τη διαμόρφωση σφαιρικής στρατηγικής για θέματα όπως ο αντίκτυπος της σύγκρουσης, η στρατηγική διαχείριση ατυχημάτων, η παροχή πρώτων βοηθειών και υπηρεσιών έκτακτης ανάγκης καθώς και διαδικασίες αποκατάστασης σε βάθος χρόνου. Απαιτούνται όμως περισσότερο αποφασιστικές ευρωπαϊκές και εθνικές πολιτικές για την οδική ασφάλεια. Η απώλεια ακόμα και μίας ανθρώπινης ζωής στους δρόμους δεν είναι αποδεκτό ενδεχόμενο και οφείλουμε να χρησιμοποιήσουμε κάθε πρόσφορο μέσο και κάθε άλλο τεχνικό μέσο για να πετύχουμε να ανταποκριθούμε σε αυτή τη μεγάλη πρόκληση απέναντι στους Ευρωπαίους πολίτες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-000" speaker_id="99325" name="Σπύρος Δανέλλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Κύριε Επίτροπε, όπως υπογραμμίζει η Επιτροπή, έχουμε τη δυνατότητα να μειώσουμε δραστικά τους σοβαρούς τραυματισμούς που λαμβάνουν χώρα με ανησυχητική συχνότητα. Μόλις ακούσαμε ανατριχιαστικά νούμερα όσον αφορά τις αστικές περιοχές της Ένωσης. Σε ιδιαίτερο κίνδυνο βρίσκονται οι λεγόμενοι ευάλωτοι οδικοί χρήστες, και βεβαίως αναφερόμαστε στους πεζούς και τους ποδηλάτες ως ευάλωτους οδικούς χρήστες, επειδή καθίστανται ευάλωτοι από τα ίδια μας τα οδικά δίκτυα, που σχεδιάστηκαν με γνώμονα σχεδόν αποκλειστικό τη διευκόλυνση της μηχανοκίνησης.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η οδική ανασφάλεια, που απειλεί εκατομμύρια πολίτες που μετακινούνται με ποδήλατο, δεν μπορεί να αποσυνδεθεί από τις αποφάσεις που απαιτούνται για υποδομές και οδικούς κανόνες στις πόλεις της Ευρώπης, είτε πρόκειται για ποδηλατικές υποδομές είτε για όρια ταχύτητας είτε για εφαρμογή έξυπνων συστημάτων. Είναι καιρός για ουσιαστικότερη παρέμβαση της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης στην αστική μετακίνηση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-000" speaker_id="112014" name="Phil Bennion" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we have to remember that reducing road fatalities is something that the Member States in the European Union have already agreed to do. What we should now do is turn our attention to the number of seriously injured on our roads; this is also very important.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to mention three things. Firstly, it is important to collect and share data so that we can learn lessons from each other.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, others have mentioned the design of lorry cabs; this is something that I would have liked to have seen in the resolution.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, eCall is now on the way, but what we do not yet have is a real agreement on the emergency number. Before we bring in mandatory eCall, we must make it mandatory for the Member States to implement the 112 number, which is redirected to 999 in the UK. Otherwise bringing in the mandatory eCall for manufacturers is going to be completely irrelevant.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, is dóigh liom go bhfuil sé tábhachtach go bpléifimis an t-ábhar seo mar tá an iomarca daoine ag fáil bháis agus á ngortú ar ár mbóithre gach uile lá. D’ardaigh an t-uasal Simpson pointe an-suimiúil nuair a dúirt sé nach dtugaimid an méid aird ar thionóiscí a tharlaíonn ar na bóithre agus a thugaimid, mar shampla, nuair a tharlaíonn siad in eitleáin. Is fiú mar sin an t-ábhar seo a phlé.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think many people are virtually dependent on the roads to do their work and politicians are no exception. I myself do about 25 or 26 hours’ driving every weekend from the airport and across the constituency, so obviously road safety is a matter of major importance to us. I think it is good, as we discussed in the previous topic, that we should exchange best practice and try to bring in the best measures across Europe to guarantee safety on our roads.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-000" speaker_id="96915" name="Sergio Gaetano Cofferati" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, il numero di incidenti all'anno, il numero di morti, il numero di persone che rimangono invalide per effetto degli incidenti è inaccettabile per una comunità civile come la nostra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dunque bisogna agire e bisogna soprattutto superare le resistenze incomprensibili che vengono da parte di alcuni Stati membri. Quella che Lei ha ricordato è clamorosa: che ancora non sia possibile avere lo stesso criterio per identificare gli effetti gravi di un incidente è davvero cosa che si commenta da sola.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma io penso che ci siano tre direzioni nelle quali occorre lavorare alacremente. La prima è la riduzione drastica della velocità nei centri urbani, che è una delle cause maggiori degli incidenti. La seconda è quella della progettazione dell'assetto urbano: i soggetti vulnerabili non sono mai tenuti in considerazione quando si cambia la struttura o le direzioni di marcia in una grande città. Il terzo è la sicurezza dei veicoli che non si deve fare a posteriori, va immaginata quando si progetta un veicolo. Dunque già la ricerca deve essere orientata a garantire la sicurezza delle persone.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">O combate à sinistralidade rodoviária deve, antes de mais, reconhecer as múltiplas causas deste fenómeno, o que implica uma atuação a vários níveis na promoção da segurança rodoviária.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma estratégia que tenha em vista a substancial redução do número de feridos deve assentar num amplo debate envolvendo especialistas, populações e condutores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na atual conjuntura, a análise desta problemática não pode ignorar, entre outros fatores, o impacto do estado de degradação de muitas vias e o estado de manutenção de alguns veículos. Em Portugal, a instalação de portagens em várias autoestradas sem alternativas viárias de qualidade levou a um crescimento muito acentuado do tráfego em vias como menores condições de segurança.</p>
      <p sl="en">A importação por alguns países de veículos pesados que ultrapassaram já nos seus países de origem o tempo de vida útil e, em geral, a degradação do serviço público de transportes, o aprofundamento da liberalização da atividade de inspeção de veículos, favorecendo o negócio em detrimento da função certificadora e piorando as condições de trabalho dos técnicos, a insistência nas parcerias público-privadas rodoviárias, são fatores, entre muitos outros, que não podem também ser ignorados nesta discussão.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I should like to thank the honourable Members very much for their comments. Of course there is no silver bullet which can deal with all issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards speed in cities: I just visited a city in a very respectable European country where cars simply do not stop at zebra pedestrian crossings. So what can the European Union do in this case? Nothing. It is very much linked to people’s behaviour and their culture of driving as well. It is also very clear in this House that some people want to have more European regulation, some people less.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have tried to find a balance as to what needs to be done to address the issue of serious injuries. I think, especially during the last months, that we have made considerable progress. However, as I have said, this discussion on the definition of road injuries has been a substantial one.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have also proposed to amend the directive on weights and dimensions, introducing major improvements for vehicles – also concerning visibility and other elements.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have proposed eCall – which is not only the eCall itself but a huge system dealing with how the medical service should be linked to this call. The call system will be there; but who will take this call and in which language? How are we to address this? This is now also designed as a complete system, and I think that it will be received positively by Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">This road safety strategy has been successful because all actors have committed themselves to achieving tangible substantial results. I also think that we will move ahead on the issue of serious injuries. As I have said, it is a certain trade mark of the European Union to have high standards of road safety, aviation safety, passenger rights and all these issues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-000" speaker_id="39317" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Έχω λάβει μία πρόταση ψηφίσματος ƒÐύƒÊƒÓƒÖƒËƒ¿ ƒÊƒÃ ƒÑƒÍ άƒÏƒÆƒÏƒÍ 108 ƒÎƒ¿ƒÏάƒÁƒÏƒ¿ƒÓƒÍς 5 ƒÑƒÍƒÒ ƒ¨ƒ¿ƒËƒÍƒËƒÇƒÐƒÊƒÍύ.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση περατώνεται.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί την Τετάρτη 3 Ιουνίου 2013 στις 11.30.</p>
      <p sl="en">Γραπτές δηλώσεις (άρθρο 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-500" speaker_id="28114" name="Liam Aylward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">i scríbhinn. – Gortaítear 1.5[nbsp ]milliún duine sa bhliain ar bhóithre na hEorpa agus meastar go mbíonn ceithre dhianghortú (e.g. damáiste don inchinn nó do chorda an dromlaigh), 10[nbsp ]dtromghortú agus 40[nbsp ]mionghortú ann in aghaidh gach bás ar bhóithre na hEorpa, agus costas EUR[nbsp ]130 billiún sa bhliain i gceist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cé go bhfuil feabhas ag teacht ar staitisticí sábháilteachta in Éirinn, agus ceann de na rátaí báis ar bhóithre is ísle in AE againn, ní mór go leanfaimis ag déanamh iarrachta cúrsaí sábháilteachta a fheabhsú ar mhaithe le tiománaithe, rothaithe agus coisithe a chosaint.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chuir an Plean Gníomhaíochta maidir le Sábháilteacht ar Bhóithre 2001-2010 go mór le hiarrachtaí AE agus na mBallstát feabhas a chur ar chúrsaí sábháilteachta. Ní foláir go leanfaí leis an dea-obair sin faoin gClár Eorpach maidir le Sábháilteacht ar Bhóithre 2011-2020, a leagann síos pleananna uaillmhianacha i dtaca le laghdú de 50% ar na básanna ar bhóithre na hEorpa a bhaint amach sna deich mbliana atá amach romhainn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fearaim fáilte roimh an gceist thráthúil seo agus aontaím le mo chomhghleacaithe a mhéid a bhaineann le bearta chun dianghortuithe a laghdú faoi 2020. Tacaím go háirithe leo siúd atá ag iarraidh go mbeadh lámhleabhar ann do chúram leighis ar an láthair i gcás tionóiscí tráchta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-750" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz Obermayr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – Die Kommission wurde vom Parlament aufgefordert, bis Ende 2011 einen Maßnahmenkatalog zur Verringerung der lebensgefährlich verletzten Personen auf Europas Straßen zu erarbeiten. Deklariertes Ziel: eine Senkung der lebensgefährlich Verletzten um 40[nbsp ]% auf Basis einer einheitlichen Definition. Viel ist seither nicht passiert! Jedes Jahr 1[nbsp ]500[nbsp ]000[nbsp ]Verletzte auf Europas Straßen – darunter 300[nbsp ]000[nbsp ]Schwerverletzte! Bis dato hat die Kommission nur eine einheitliche Definition der „schweren Verletzung“ auf den Weg gebracht. Und ich frage mich auch, wie das mit der Zulassung von Gigalinern zusammenpasst? Die Kommission will die europaweite Zulassung dieser Riesen-Lkw, obwohl sie erwiesenermaßen die Verkehrssicherheit beeinträchtigen: durch schlechtere Sicht, längere Überholwege und erhöhte Unfallschwere bei Zusammenstößen. Soll das zur Verringerung der Unfallopfer beitragen?</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Priority substances in the field of water policy (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-139-000" speaker_id="39317" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Το επόμενο σημείο στην ημερήσια διάταξη είναι η έκθεση του Richard Seeber, εξ ονόματος της Επιτροπής Περιβάλλοντος, Δημόσιας Υγείας και Ασφάλειας των Τροφίμων, σχετικά με τις ουσίες προτεραιότητας στον τομέα της πολιτικής των υδάτων (COM(2011)0876 – C7-0026/2012 – 2011/0429(COD)) (Α7-0397/2012)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-000" speaker_id="28252" name="Richard Seeber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. - Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich möchte mich zuerst bei allen für die konstruktive Zusammenarbeit bei der Ausarbeitung dieser Richtlinie bedanken, die wir zwischen allen Fraktionen gehabt haben, aber auch mit dem Rat und vor allem auch mit Unterstützung der Kommission, so dass wir hier eigentlich recht schnell zu einer Lösung gekommen sind, die von allen Teilen unterstützt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte daran erinnern, dass Wasserpolitik eine langfristige Politik ist, dass es dabei darum geht, dass wir unseren Mitbürgerinnen und Mitbürgern sauberes Wasser in jeglicher Form zur Verfügung stellen; aber Wasser ist auch Lebensgrundlage für alle Lebewesen auf unserem Planeten und hat deshalb eine besondere Bedeutung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich darf daran erinnern, dass wir im Jahr 2000 die Wasserrahmenrichtlinie verabschiedet haben, die wirklich ein Grundsatz-Gesetzeswerk ist, die einen Meilenstein in der weltweiten Wasserpolitik darstellt und die durch drei Elemente gekennzeichnet ist. Erstens: Sie bezieht alle Gewässer ein. Zweitens: Sie arbeitet grenzüberschreitend, sprich: in Flussgebietseinheiten. Und drittens: Sie will bis 2015 einen guten ökologischen und chemischen Zustand für unsere Gewässer erreichen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und hier kommt nun diese Tochterrichtlinie dazu, die wir zusammen ausgearbeitet haben und in der konkrete chemische Qualitätsstandards festgelegt werden, damit dieser gute chemische Zustand erreicht werden kann. Leider zeigen Untersuchungen, dass noch ein weiter Weg zu gehen ist, was sowohl den ökologischen guten Zustand als auch den chemischen guten Zustand, hier insbesondere der Oberflächengewässer, anbelangt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Umweltqualitätsstandards, die jetzt in dieser neuen Richtlinie vorgeschlagen werden, betreffen 15[nbsp ]neue Stoffe. Wir haben bereits in früheren Richtlinien aus den Jahren 2003 und 2008 33[nbsp ]prioritäre Stoffe herausgefiltert, die als besonders gefährlich für die aquatische Umwelt und den Menschen gelten. Nun kommt der nächste Schritt. In einem langen Prozess wurden mit Stakeholdern weitere 15[nbsp ]Stoffe definiert, für die Umweltqualitätswerte festgelegt wurden, und für sieben bestehende Stoffe wurden die Umweltqualitätsstandards revidiert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Neu ist bei dieser Richtlinie auch, dass Messmethoden geändert worden sind, die insbesondere auch auf Biota abstellen. Es geht also nicht nur darum, dass wir sauberes Wasser für die Menschen, unsere Mitbürgerinnen und Mitbürger, zur Verfügung stellen, sondern auch konkret die Auswirkungen verschiedener Chemikalien, die als gefährlich eingestuft werden, auf die natürliche Umwelt prüfen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das Kompromisspaket, das wir zusammen geschmiedet haben, zeichnet sich durch folgende Punkte aus: Wir haben eine neue watchlist eingeführt, auf der Stoffe stehen, die besonderer Beobachtung unterzogen werden müssen, um sie in späterer Folge, wenn mehr Daten vorliegen, entweder als gefährlich und mit Qualitätsstandards zu versehen oder als ungefährlich einzustufen – also sprich: besonderes Monitoring für Stoffe auf dieser watchlist. Wir beginnen hier mit zehn Stoffen und jedes Jahr kommt ein Stoff dazu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zweitens: Wir haben erstmalig auch pharmazeutische Stoffe dazugenommen. Das ist – wie gesagt – ein erster großer Schritt. Es sind zwei Hormone und das Diclofenac – das ist ein Entzündungshemmer –, die, nicht wie von der Kommission vorgeschlagen, bereits mit EQS ausgestattet werden, sondern vorläufig auf die watchlist gesetzt werden und besonders beobachtet werden. Das wird in Zukunft ein besonders interessantes Feld werden, weil unsere Gewässer leider zunehmend mit Pharmazeutika belastet sind. Vom Zeitrahmen her sind wir dem Rat entgegengekommen. Das Erfüllungsdatum für die alten Stoffe ist 2021, für die neuen 2027.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und ein letzter Punkt: Das Parlament hat die so genannten cross links eingeführt. Sprich: Wenn Stoffe in anderen Gesetzgebungen zugelassen werden, müssen in Zukunft auch konkret ihre Auswirkungen auf Wasser geprüft werden. Gibt es hier Probleme, muss das Rückwirkungen auf die Zulassung haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Insgesamt, glaube ich, ein ausgewogenes Paket und ich zähle jetzt auf die Mitgliedstaaten, dass sie es zeitgerecht umsetzen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Janez Potočnik" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, first and foremost I would like to thank and congratulate the rapporteur Richard Seeber and his team for their thorough work on the Commission’s proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to thank the Committee on Environment, Public Health and Food Safety (ENVI) for largely backing the approach we put forward. Thanks to the committee’s support we have been able to maintain some of the proposal’s most significant objectives in the compromise text after negotiations, which I could best describe as being challenging.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission sees the proposal as important for at least three reasons. Firstly, it provides a much-needed update of the list of pollutants, the ‘priority substances’ under the Water Framework Directive. This update results from a review of the latest scientific evidence regarding a large range of chemicals, including those identified by Parliament when the Environmental Quality Standards Directive was adopted in 2008.</p>
      <p sl="en">The new list means regular monitoring of pollutants in all Member States. This is really important since a number of these substances are very persistent and bio-accumulative, toxic or highly toxic or suspected endocrine disrupters.</p>
      <p sl="en">Some measures will have to be taken to bring concentrations down to safe levels or to phase out emissions to water of those pollutants. The directive also ensures a level playing field in standards for the newly identified pollutants across the Union. This is important in view of the transboundary character of such pollution.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, the proposal introduces provisions to improve information on the chemical status of water. The public will be better able to understand the efforts made to improve water quality where they live and work. The European Parliament’s Environment Committee has complemented this by introducing a welcome requirement for timely electronic provision of information.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, the proposal includes a new monitoring mechanism to help improve the evidence base for identifying priority substances in the future. This new watchlist mechanism will see Member States monitoring additional substances to help assess the risk they pose to the environment or to human health via the environment.</p>
      <p sl="en">So the proposal marks an important step forward. However, the three pharmaceutical substances that the Commission proposed, on the basis of strong scientific evidence, including on the priorities substances list have been placed on the first watchlist. The compromise text recognises the risks posed by those three substances and makes clear that they will be on the watchlist to facilitate the identification of measures to address those risks. But I regret that, in the face of existing and clear scientific evidence, those substances will not be put directly on the priority list. It would have been the appropriate and proportionate approach.</p>
      <p sl="en">The concerns in relation to other pharmaceutical substances in the environment will be followed up by developing a strategic approach to the issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">A great deal of work lies behind this proposal, both the scientific review and the impact assessment. Numerous experts and researchers from the Member States, the Commission and the stakeholder groups as well as the Scientific Committee on Health and Environmental Risks have provided input. The scientific evidence on the risks from these substances would justify a shorter timetable for complying with the objectives set out in the proposal. The current economic pressures across the Union are not an adequate excuse for failing to deal properly with such risks. But in the interests of avoiding further delays, we accept the compromise agreement in order to ensure a first reading deal.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is committed to working with the Member States to ensure the smooth and effective implementation of the proposal. The common implementation strategy for the Water Framework Directive exists for that purpose. We have ensured that the necessary technical work on developing supplementary guidance on monitoring methods will be covered in the strategy’s work programme for 2013 to 2015.</p>
      <p sl="en">This directive will contribute significantly to improving water quality, and will thereby also have a positive impact on people’s health. However, a number of changes introduced in the Commission’s proposal during the first reading deliberations require the Commission to make declarations on three issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, the need to establish preliminary programmes of measures for the new priority substances and to address the risk posed by the three pharmaceutical substances. Secondly, the dependency of legal deadlines on the provision of non-binding guidelines. Thirdly, the use of the ‘no-opinion clause’ for the adoption of implementing acts. We will pass the full text of those declarations to the plenary service for recording in the minutes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite these declarations, the Commission sees the outcome of the negotiations as a positive move in the right direction and accepts the compromise text.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-000" speaker_id="1929" name="Christa Klaß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar Potočnik, verehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Beim Wasser sind wir alle sehr sensibel. Es war nicht das Geld und nicht der Euro, der das erste europäische Bürgerbegehren auf den Weg gebracht hat; es war das Wasser! Die Sorge um unsere Lebensader Wasser teilen Millionen europäischer Bürger. Der Wunsch nach reinem und gesundem Wasser vereint ganz Europa. Wir haben unser Wasser in vielen Verordnungen nicht nur unter Beobachtung gestellt, sondern fest im Gesetz verankert. Wir wissen, dass nur mit guter gemeinsamer Vorsorge einer Verunreinigung entgegengewirkt werden kann, dass jede Verunreinigung unserer Gewässer entweder gar nicht oder nur ganz schwer zu beseitigen ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Heute sprechen wir über die prioritären Stoffe im Wasser. Ich freue mich, dass nach drei Trilogen nun ein guter Kompromiss auf dem Tisch ist, und ich danke unserem Berichterstatter, Richard Seeber, der mit viel Umsicht die Verhandlungen für das Parlament geführt hat. Die Entwicklung neuer Stoffe, aber auch die Entwicklung neuer Techniken und Analysemethoden erfordert immer wieder ein Nachjustieren. Es gibt auch neue Sorgen und neue Bedenken, die aus neuen oder verstärkten Veränderungen bei Mensch und Umwelt resultieren, die wir ernst nehmen müssen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Beobachtungsliste ist ein Kernstück der Verordnung über die prioritären Stoffe im Wasser. Hier werden potenziell gefährliche Stoffe unter Beobachtung gestellt und Überprüfung unterzogen. Es ist richtig, dass die pharmazeutischen Stoffe jetzt auf dieser sogenannten Watchlist stehen. Hier können weitere Daten gesammelt und evaluiert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diese Beobachtungsliste selbst, Herr Kommissar, muss aber auch unter Beobachtung stehen. Sie muss immer wieder aktualisiert werden, und Stoffe müssen entweder in die prioritäre Liste aufgenommen werden oder sie müssen auch von dieser Liste gestrichen werden können. Nur so können Entwicklungen direkt beobachtet werden und kann auch direkt gegengesteuert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der vorliegende Kompromiss ist ein weiterer guter Schritt zur Sicherung unseres Wassers und damit auch zu unserer Gesundheit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-000" speaker_id="97009" name="Κρίτων Αρσένης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας S&amp;D. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, Επίτροπε, ζητήσαμε και καταφέραμε σε αυτή την οδηγία να είναι τα φάρμακα μέσα στη λίστα παρακολούθησης, ώστε να γνωρίζουν οι πολίτες τις συγκεντρώσεις συγκεκριμένων φαρμάκων και να είναι έτοιμη η Επιτροπή να ξαναφέρει το θέμα προς συζήτηση στην επόμενη αναθεώρηση. Αποφασίσαμε την αλλαγή και ζητάμε την αλλαγή του τρόπου αδειοδότησης των φαρμάκων, προκειμένου να λαμβάνονται υπόψη οι επιπτώσεις τους στο περιβάλλον. Πετύχαμε να υπάρχουν αυστηρότερα όρια για τις ουσίες που έχουν ήδη χαρακτηριστεί επιβλαβείς. Όμως είναι πραγματικά ντροπή για το Συμβούλιο ότι χαράμισε πραγματικά μια ευκαιρία για την Ευρώπη, για επενδύσεις για να βγούμε από την κρίση, δηλαδή επενδύσεις στις υποδομές διαχείρισης των υδάτων, μεταθέτοντας την ημερομηνία εφαρμογής των νέων υποχρεώσεων για τις ουσίες που έχουν αποδειχθεί επικίνδυνες και επιβλαβείς για το 2027.</p>
      <p sl="en">Όμως γενικότερα στην Ευρώπη το νερό είναι στο στόχαστρο. Σας έχω στείλει, συνάδελφοι, σε όλους με e-mail το γράμμα της Ευρωπαϊκής Ομοσπονδίας Συνδικάτων Δημοσίων Υπηρεσιών, που ζητά τη στήριξή σας με την υπογραφή σας στο κάλεσμα εναντίον της ιδιωτικοποίησης του νερού της Θεσσαλονίκης.</p>
      <p sl="en">Και, Επίτροπε, ένα θέμα που σας αφορά άμεσα: Στο Εθνικό Πάρκο Βόρειας Πίνδου, σε περιοχή Natura, προωθείται η εκτροπή ενός ποταμού. Μέσω των σχεδίων διαχείρισης της οδηγίας πλαισίου για τα ύδατα προωθείται η νομιμοποίησή της, προκειμένου να χρησιμοποιηθεί για την παραγωγή ενέργειας ίσης με πέντε ανεμογεννήτριες. Είναι πραγματικά ντροπή! Καταστροφή ενός εθνικού δρυμού μέσω των σχεδίων διαχείρισης! Σας παρακαλώ να το κοιτάξετε με προσοχή.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, good-quality water is a priority for us all, but we have to be realistic about what we can achieve and the timeframe in which we should be achieving it.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have always been against the Commission’s inclusion of the three pharmaceuticals in the list of priority substances, due to what I believe to be the unjustifiably large costs of treating wastewater to remove them. In the UK alone, the cost was estimated at EUR 35 billion over 20 years. I have to disagree with the Commissioner when he says that incontrovertible scientific evidence was put to us. If that were the case, we would all have been voting for it. It simply was not the case that it was incontrovertible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Inflicting such costs on households, through high water bills, at a time of economic difficulty is unacceptable. This proposal also highlighted the lack of consistency between the Water Framework Directive and other pieces of EU legislation. I am glad to say that on these key issues favourable compromises were reached at trialogue and acceptable agreements were reached on timetables for implementation and the watchlist. So I am happy to be able to vote – and for my group to be able to vote – in favour of this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-145-000" speaker_id="28310" name="Edite Estrela" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, a poluição da água constitui uma ameaça para o ambiente aquático, põe em risco a qualidade e a quantidade da água potável é uma das principais preocupações ambientais. A Diretiva da água fixou como objetivo atingir o bom estado ambiental químico e quantitativo das massas de água europeias até 2015 e definiu estratégias de combate à poluição.</p>
      <p sl="en">A revisão da lista das substâncias prioritárias permitiu identificar novas substâncias que representam risco para o ambiente aquático. O acordo alcançado não inclui os três fármacos na lista prioritária mas inclui na lista de vigilância. O importante é controlar a presença das substâncias farmacêuticas na água porque são perigosas para a saúde, e o estar na lista de vigilância permite fazer esse controlo e esse acompanhamento, assim esperamos.</p>
      <p sl="en">É positivo o alargamento progressivo do número máximo de substâncias na lista de vigilância, bem como a exploração de sinergias com outra legislação relevante, tal como o REACH ou a legislação relativa a pesticidas e biocidas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-000" speaker_id="23808" name="Csaba Sándor Tabajdi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Potočnik biztos úr! Richard Seeber úr kiváló jelentése a víztisztaság javításáról rendkívül fontos európai ügy. Magyarország számára is rendkívül fontos, hogy legyen közösségi szabályozás, mivel az összes magyarországi folyó az országhatáron túlról ered, és csak európai szintű szabályozással őrizhető meg vizeink minősége. 2000-ben ezt már a tiszai ciánkatasztrófa estében átéltük. Az is nagyon fontos, hogy országainkon belül javuljon a víz minősége. Már rengeteg eredményt értünk el a 2004-es uniós csatlakozás óta, mégis 2,5 millió magyar ember él olyan területen, ahol az ivóvíz minősége nem megfelelő. Főként a dél-alföldi megyékben az arzénra és a nitrátra vonatkozó egészségügyi határértékek rendkívül magasak. Ezért a mostani irányelv valamennyi uniós polgár, benne a magyar emberek érdekét is szolgálja.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, a água é um bem público inalienável. A sua boa conservação exige a observação de critérios exigentes que garantam um elevado nível de proteção da saúde pública e do ambiente, mas exige mais: exige serviços de água e serviços de extensão públicos, instituições públicas de investigação e de desenvolvimento, pessoal técnico e científico especializado, bem como um conjunto de medidas firmes para defender, garantir e proteger a água enquanto bem público estratégico.</p>
      <p sl="en">É tudo isto que hoje é posto em causa em diversos países, é o exemplo de Portugal, onde, através de uma intolerável e reiterada postura de ingerência, a Comissão Europeia, como a própria já admitiu, vem pressionando no sentido da privatização dos serviços de água, vem impondo políticas e medidas que debilitam seriamente a capacidade de monitorização e de intervenção em defesa da água, da sua qualidade e boa conservação. É uma atuação flagrantemente contraditória com todo o discurso justificador desta legislação, mesmo tendo em conta o seu patente enfraquecimento na sequência das negociações entre o Parlamento e Conselho.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Janez Potočnik" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, as Mr[nbsp ]Seeber knows, it was not an easy negotiation. More than 10 Council working party meetings, seven Coreper meetings, three trialogues and two technical trialogues were held with a view to reaching the first reading agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">You have done a very good job to make this possible. Without the European Parliament’s help, the deal on the watchlist and the strategy on pharmaceuticals would not be as good as they are.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the question of cost, which was raised today, whenever we make a proposal we do an impact assessment, and nothing comes for free. We always have to look at both sides of the question and determine firstly how much it would cost to remedy and secondly how much it would cost not to remedy. I can guarantee you that, if we do not remedy such problems, the next cost review in five to 10 years’ time and impact assessments will show that not remedying them will cost even more. So we would have even more reasons not to adopt that kind of solution.</p>
      <p sl="en">It makes all the more sense for us to compare the costs and benefits at all times. Whenever we do that we try to be balanced because we understand that this has to be done in a way that benefits human health and the environment but that is also cost-efficient.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concerning the science, all the proposals are science-based. We went through the whole list of proposals and, if I remember correctly, the list was very long. Science is constantly advancing and we will take into account whatever new evidence and data is shown to us in the future, whether from interested parties, the business sector, academia or wherever. This is such a serious issue that it simply cannot be done any other way.</p>
      <p sl="en">What is important now is to implement the proposal and to work as closely as possible with the Member States. That is exactly what the Commission intends to do. I would like to thank you all, and the rapporteur, for giving your support to the proposal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-000" speaker_id="28252" name="Richard Seeber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. - Frau Präsidentin! Wie gesagt, dieser Erfolg war nur möglich, da wir alle ausgezeichnet zusammengearbeitet haben. Ich möchte beim letzten Punkt anfangen, den der Herr Kommissar genannt hat, der Implementierung. Dieser Vorschlag ist nur so gut wie seine Implementierung. Das ist speziell im Wasserbereich ein besonderes Problem, weil dieser Vorschlag mit besonderen Kosten verbunden ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber wenn wir die Kostenseite ansehen, dann müssen wir auch die Nutzenseite sehen. Gerade was den Gesundheitseffekt anbelangt, ist es klar: Je sauberer die Gewässer sind, die wir den Menschen zur Verfügung stellen, desto höher ist auch der Nutzen für die Gesundheit. Und der Umwegnutzen ist ein Vielfaches der Kosten, die von den Gebietskörperschaften und den Mitgliedstaaten aufgewendet werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Auch noch kurz zu den pharmazeutischen Substanzen: Ich glaube, es ist ein wichtiger Schritt in die richtige Richtung. Natürlich müssen wir jetzt weiter Daten sammeln. Es ist nicht so, dass durch Wasserpolitik irgendein Medikament verboten werden soll. Es geht darum, dass wir alle – sowohl die Zulassungsbehörde als auch die Menschen, die diese Medikamente verwenden, als auch die Mitgliedstaaten und Gemeinden, die Sammelsysteme organisieren sollen – unsere Verantwortung wahrnehmen, damit Medikamentenrückstände nicht in das Wasser gelangen. Das bezieht sich natürlich auf Human- und Veterinärarzneimittel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am Schluss möchte ich auch noch, obwohl es nicht direkt hierher passt, eine Bitte an Herrn Kommissar Potočnik richten: Ich hoffe, dass das Kommissarskollegium dem Vorschlag von Kommissar Barnier folgt, den Wasserbereich aus der Konzessionsrichtlinie herauszunehmen. Ich halte das für politisch sehr klug. Wasser ist ein besonderes Gut, ist mit besonderen Sentimentalitäten und Emotionen verbunden. Ich glaube, es ist politisch derzeit besser, diesen Teil herauszunehmen. Es soll hier nicht, wie gesagt, ein eigenes Feld geschaffen werden, wo man besondere Transparenzvorschriften nicht einhält, aber in der derzeitigen Situation ist es besser, wenn das draußen bleibt. Ich hoffe, das Kommissarskollegium wird diesem weisen Vorschlag folgen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 2 July 2013.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 149)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-250" speaker_id="28247" name="Holger Krahmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – Ich begrüße den Kompromiss, der in den Verhandlungen mit dem Rat gefunden wurde. Es ist vernünftig, die drei Pharmazeutika auf die Liste zu beobachtender Substanzen zu setzen. Sogar eine Studie der WHO belegt, dass es keine für den Menschen bedrohliche Konzentrationen von Pharmazeutika in Trinkwasser gibt. Deshalb müssen diese auch nicht in eine Prioritätenliste eingestuft werden, wie die Kommission ursprünglich vorgeschlagen hat. Das hätte zu Einschränkungen bei der Verfügbarkeit wichtiger Medikamente, wie zum Beispiel Schmerzmittel oder der Anti-Baby-Pille, führen können. Es gibt keinen Grund für die EU, über die Empfehlungen der WHO hinauszugehen. Saubere Gewässer sind wichtig. Man muss allerdings Aufwand und Nutzen in Verhältnis setzen. Wir dürfen durch übertriebene Regulierung in einer Umweltgesetzgebung nicht die Verfügbarkeit von Arzneimitteln einschränken, insbesondere wenn eine Gefährdung der Umwelt nicht belegt ist. Daher ist die Herabstufung der Arzneimittel auf die Überwachungsliste zu begrüßen. Mehr mag wünschenswert sein, ist aber nicht immer finanzierbar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-500" speaker_id="96715" name="Pavel Poc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písemně. – Povědomí o dopadu léčiv na životní prostředí se za poslední roky značně zvýšilo, a Komise proto na základě nejnovějších vědeckých poznatků navrhla v roce 2012 zařadit mezi 15 nových prioritních látek v oblasti vodní politiky tři farmaceutické látky: přírodní hormon 17β-estradiol a syntetický hormon 17α-ethinylestradiol, které mají oba vlastnosti narušující endokrinní systém, a nesteroidní antiflogistikum Diclofenac. Je to vůbec poprvé, kdy měla být léčiva zařazena na seznam prioritních látek, považovaných za nebezpečné pro vodní prostředí. Návrh Komise nezpochybňoval jejich léčebné účinky, pouze se zaměřil na potenciálně škodlivé dopady jejich přítomnosti ve vodním prostředí. Přesto se Evropský parlament a členské státy rozhodly přesunout tato tři léčiva jen na seznam, který bude obsahovat nově se objevující znečišťující látky, tzv. watchlist, nebudou však na seznamu prioritních látek, jak navrhovala Komise. Tento výsledek je velmi neuspokojivý především v souvislosti se stále narůstající hrozbou tzv. endokrinních disruptorů v životním prostředí a jejich dopadem na lidské zdraví. Znečištění vod je podle občanů EU rovněž jedním z největších problémů životního prostředí. Podle průzkumu Eurobarometru z března 2012 se 68 % Evropanů domnívá, že problémy s kvalitou a kvantitou vody jsou závažné, a 80 % občanů je přesvědčeno, že chemické znečištění je hrozbou pro vodní životní prostředí.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. One-minute speeches (Rule 150)">
    <intervention id="1-155-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance (Rule 150).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-000" speaker_id="96814" name="Elena Băsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Bruxelles-ul recomandă, în ultimele rapoarte MCV, guvernului socialist de la Bucureşti să folosească ordonanţele de urgenţă strict în situaţiile prevăzute de Constituţie şi doar în caz de urgenţă. Deşi are în Parlament o majoritate reală de 70%, guvernul Ponta a început să preia atribuţiile legislativului, încălcând, astfel, principiul separaţiei puterilor în stat. De la începutul anului, Executivul a adoptat nu mai puţin de 80 de ordonanţe de urgenţă, care au modificat legi importante. Recordul absolut a fost bătut în şedinţa din 26 ianuarie, când, pe ordinea de zi a Executivului, s-au aflat nu mai puţin de 22 de ordonanţe de urgenţă. Precizez că ele vor fi dezbătute în Parlament, în toamnă, după vacanţa de vară. Prin comparaţie, guvernele de dreapta au adoptat în primele 5 luni ale anului trecut doar 14 astfel de ordonanţe. Prin acest mod de a guverna şi de a legifera, USL-ul nu face altceva decât să creeze un profund deficit de democraţie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-000" speaker_id="28338" name="Antonio Masip Hidalgo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, es absurdo buscar reindustrialización y propiciar cierre industrial, también hablar de competencia y entregarse a las industrias de fuera de Europa. Si hubiera de corregirse alguna financiación en el sector naval —lo que ya se hizo en 2011—, nunca debe hacerse hipotecando el futuro de una actividad por la que seguimos apostando.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión no ha de propiciar miseria y paro, sino actividad, dinamismo y trabajo. ¡Mucho cuidado, Europa! Mucho cuidado también, España y su Ministerio de Hacienda ejecutando resoluciones comunitarias. El trabajo de los astilleros, pasado y futuro, debe preservarse sin riesgo alguno de subrogaciones por supuestas faltas comunitarias.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-000" speaker_id="2155" name="Graham Watson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to draw the attention of the House to an incident on the evening of 23 June off West Beach in the Bay of Gibraltar. My constituent, Mr Dale Villa, was riding a new jet ski with family and friends when, without warning, a patrol boat of the Spanish Guardia Civil fired a shot at him, then chased him and fired three more shots, even though he was within waters the UN Convention on the Law of the Sea has determined as belonging to Gibraltar. It is lucky that Mr Villa was not killed or seriously injured.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gibraltar has been a member of the European Union for 40 years. Unlike any other territory it is fully compliant with EU rules. It is totally unacceptable that my constituent should have been attacked by police from Spain in this way when no offence has been committed and when he was not within their waters. This is one of many such incursions by the Guardia Civil in the past three years. I would ask President Schulz to take up this matter with the authorities of Spain, to protect my constituents.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-000" speaker_id="117477" name="Mark Demesmaeker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, als lid van de Commissie mensenrechten ben ik begaan met mensenrechten buiten de EU, maar ook binnen de Unie. De manier waarop Spanje de Baskische politieke gevangenen behandelt, is al langer omstreden. Er zijn rapporten over schending van mensenrechten, het specifiek gevangenisregime, het gevangen houden van terminaal zieke mensen. Vorige week was ik met enkele leden van mijn fractie in Baskenland. In de gevangenis van het naburige Logroño wilden we een bezoek brengen aan één van de prominente Baskishe politieke gevangenen. Hij heeft een nummer, maar hij heeft natuurlijk ook een gezicht en een naam: Arnaldo Otegi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Begin juni hebben we een officiële schriftelijke aanvraag ingediend bij de bevoegde diensten om hem te kunnen zien. We hebben nooit enig antwoord gekregen. Toen we contact zochten, zijn we van het kastje naar de muur gestuurd en aan de gevangenispoort zijn we tegengehouden. De manier waarop wij als Europarlementsleden door de Spaanse overheid zijn behandeld is zonder meer schandalig. Ik verzoek de Voorzitter van dit Parlement dan ook, de Spaanse autoriteiten te wijzen op deze onaanvaardbare houding en respect op te brengen voor het werk van parlementsleden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-000" speaker_id="113959" name="Martina Anderson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last month the north of Ireland drew further to the politics of exclusion by passing legislation barring politically motivated ex-prisoners from taking on the role of advisers to executive ministers. I must declare an interest in this issue as my husband is directly affected. Paul Kavanagh, an ex-prisoner who served 15 years in prison and who has been a political adviser for five years to the Joint First Minister Martin McGuinness, will be sacked. We now have a ludicrous situation whereby ex-prisoners can be ministers making decisions – like I was – but not advisers to ministers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite the Good Friday Agreement providing for the employment and reintegration of ex-prisoners, the SDLP and others have allowed the politics of exclusion to re-emerge, imposing a retrospective punishment in breach of Article 7 of the European Convention on Human Rights. It was, after all, discriminatory practices that fed the causes of the conflict in Ireland, so the Irish Government, as a co-signatory of the Good Friday Agreement, should support a challenge to this discriminatory law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-000" speaker_id="96786" name="Tadeusz Cymański" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Zwracam uwagę na trudną sytuację energochłonnej gałęzi przemysłu w Polsce. Obecne wysokie ceny energii oraz realna groźba ich podniesienia doprowadzą do upadłości wielu zakładów, zwiększą i tak już bardzo wysokie bezrobocie oraz wywołają drastyczny wzrost kosztów utrzymania. Już dziś w polskiej Hucie Częstochowa zapowiedziano zwolnienie 1500 pracowników. W zakładzie tym koszty energii na niektórych wydziałach przekraczają 50% kosztów produkcji. Dlatego też wszelkie działania w zakresie polityki klimatycznej nie mogą być oderwane od zróżnicowanych realiów gospodarczych i społecznych poszczególnych państw Unii Europejskiej. W tej sytuacji ponowna próba przeforsowania tzw. backloadingu i w konsekwencji drastyczne podniesienie cen energii jeszcze bardziej osłabi konkurencyjność energochłonnych sektorów przemysłu. Dlatego apeluję do Parlamentu o potwierdzenie w środowym głosowaniu już raz wyrażonego sprzeciwu wobec próby wycofania z rynku części zezwoleń na emisję CO2.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-000" speaker_id="23820" name="László Surján" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Örömmel köszöntjük Horvátországot! Sajnos az ő örömüket ellenpontozza az Unió szerte növekvő kiábrándulás, s a csökkenő választási hajlandóság. Lehet, hogy az euroszkeptikusok meghatározóak lehetnek a következő ciklusban. Növeli a polgárok csalódottságát, ha Párizsban két miniszter is tiltakozni kénytelen az Európai Bizottságnak a Szerződéseken túlterjeszkedő politikai nyomása ellen. Nem bölcs, ha a Bizottság tagjai olyan konferenciákra járnak, melyekről nem nyilatkozhatnak, mert ezzel is növelik a bizalmatlanságot. Nem jó, ha egy tagállam és egy biztos viszonya annyira megromlik, mint Magyarország és Reding elnökhelyettes esetén, olyannyira, hogy a biztos ellen felhozott akár képtelen vádak is hihetőnek tűnnek. A múlt héten a pénzügyi kerettervről való megegyezésben felcsillantak az Unió értékei: a kölcsönös megértés és a kompromisszumkészség. Ehhez kell mindannyiunknak visszatérnünk, akik sikeres Európában vagyunk érdekeltek.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-000" speaker_id="110984" name="Joseph Cuschieri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Id-dritt ta' trattament ta' pazjenti huwa minqux fil-Karta tad-Drittijiet Fundamentali tal-Unjoni Ewropea. L-Unjoni Ewropea għandha tkompli tfittex li taħdem b'kollaborazzjoni ma' organizzazzjonijiet Ewropej tas-saħħa li jirrappreżentaw lill-pazjenti Ewropej biex dawn ikollhom rikonoxximent sħiħ tad-dritt bażiku għal dijanjożi, trattamenti, terapiji u aċċess immedjat għall-mediċini.</p>
      <p sl="en">Għandna nirrispettaw l-importanza tas-sovranità nazzjonali dwar il-materja tas-saħħa, madanakollu, wasal iż-żmien li kull pazjent Ewropew li jmur fi sptar f'pajjiżu għandu jingħata perjodu definittiv ta' żmien raġonevoli ta' stennija. Fl-istess waqt, meta l-Istat jonqos milli jżomm kelmtu, il-gvern ta' dak l-Istat Membru għandu jkun marbut li jiżgura li l-pazjent ikun mibgħut għat-trattament fi sptar privat jew, jekk ikun hemm bżonn, anke fi sptar barra l-pajjiż. Huwa importanti li, f'ċirkostanzi bħal dawn, niggarantixxu d-dritt lill-pazjenti Ewropej li jkunu operati barra minn pajjiżhom, u jkollhom il-ħlas tal-ispejjeż tagħhom imħallas mill-Istat Membru tagħhom wara li jirritornaw f'pajjiżhom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Din il-garanzija għall-pazjenti, li huma ċittadini Ewropej, għandha tingħata mingħajr restrizzjonijiet sabiex b'hekk inħarsu aħjar l-interess għas-saħħa taċ-ċittadini tagħna. Nenfasizza li dan huwa punt kruċjali għad-drittijiet tal-pazjenti Ewropej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164-000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Am solicitat să intervin pentru a face un apel către Victor Ponta, liderul socialiştilor români şi Crin Antonescu, preşedintele PNL. Cei doi i-au obligat pe deputaţii români din Grupurile Socialist şi ALDE să voteze, în martie, împotriva Acordului din Consiliul European, referitor la Cadrul financiar multianual. Ei au lăsat să se înţeleagă că, astfel, ar putea căpăta mai mulţi bani pentru România în 2014-2020. Ţara mea obţinuse deja mai mult decât în 2007-2013 în Consiliul European din februarie. Ponta şi Antonescu nu au căpătat niciun cent în plus, nici nu se putea: demagogia nu te ajută să ai un buget mai mare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le cer să nu mai vândă iluzii şi să nu-i mai împingă pe eurodeputaţii pe care-i controlează să respingă bugetul pentru următorii 7 ani. Le cer, de asemenea, să elimine corupţia din gestiunea fondurilor europene. Corupţia este cel mai mare obstacol în calea folosirii acestor fonduri în profitul cetăţenilor, nu al reţelelor politice mafiotizate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-000" speaker_id="96986" name="Josefa Andrés Barea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, Galmed es una planta galvanizadora de la multinacional Thyssen situada en Sagunto (España). Tiene una plantilla de 165 trabajadores y va a cerrar. Los argumentos utilizados por la dirección del grupo son bastante dudosos y suscitan muchas preguntas. Una es que la empresa es rentable y los resultados son positivos, pero repliega su actividad hacia Alemania, precisamente hacia la zona de Westfalia-Renania. Se trata de un reparto del mercado entre dos grandes, Thyssen y Arcelor. Por último, a pesar de que Thyssen ha recibido, para su filial Galmed, fondos de la Unión Europea en concepto de I+D+I, ahora cierra.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión acaba de aprobar un plan de acción del acero. Prevé medidas específicas. Sin embargo, esta medida es una contradicción. Estamos hablando de 165 personas, 165 familias, una comarca, una región.</p>
      <p sl="en">Galmed ya ha comunicado la apertura de consultas y el cierre. ¿Qué medidas va a adoptar la Comisión ante este atropello, ante el atropello del empleo y la credibilidad de Europa?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, el futuro de 87[nbsp ]000 familias y el esfuerzo de centenares de empresas y miles de grandes profesionales no merece la decisión que se anuncia sobre el tax lease. De confirmarse, la construcción naval desaparecerá en Euskadi y en España, y con ella, empleo, competitividad e innovación en toda Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Una propuesta discutible, porque la anterior titular de competencia, Nelie Kroes, escribió el 9 de marzo del 2009 que el tax lease era legal; injusta, porque en un caso similar como el francés, Europa consideró que la seguridad jurídica y la confianza legítima justifican la no devolución de las ayudas; antieuropea porque el dumping social y ambiental y las ayudas públicas que perjudican la libre competencia no están en Bilbao o en Vigo, sino en el sudeste asiático.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello, recogiendo la preocupación que compartí el viernes con el sector, pido a la Comisión que el próximo día 17 rechace esta sanción y la convierta en lo que necesita toda la construcción naval europea: protección frente a la competencia desleal exterior para una industria que debe ser estratégica y puede seguir aportando empleo e innovación marca «2020».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-000" speaker_id="111823" name="Νίκος Χρυσόγελος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, η κρίση έχει θύματα και μεταξύ των μικρών νησιωτικών περιοχών και των ορεινών περιοχών. Εκτός αυτού, αυτό που βλέπουμε με την πολιτική λιτότητας είναι ότι σε περιοχές που είναι μικρές εγκαταλείπονται οι δημόσιες υπηρεσίες και επιβαρύνεται ο πληθυσμός, γιατί δεν έχει πρόσβαση στις υπηρεσίες υγείας, δεν υπάρχουν καλές συνδέσεις –υπάρχουν νησιά που δεν έχουν τακτική σύνδεση– κλείνουν σχολεία και φεύγουν δημόσιες εφορίες από περιοχές κοντινές.</p>
      <p sl="en">Αντί λοιπόν να μειώνεται η διαφορά, να υπάρχει σύγκλιση στην Ευρώπη, αυξάνεται η απόσταση μεταξύ περιοχών λόγω και της κρίσης και των πολιτικών λιτότητας. Θα έπρεπε λοιπόν η Επιτροπή να εξετάσει κατά πόσον υπάρχει ανάγκη για μια ειδική πολιτική για τις περιοχές αυτές που υποφέρουν σήμερα από τη βαθιά οικονομική, κοινωνική και οικολογική κρίση, είναι δε σημαντικό ο πληθυσμός που αφήνεται εγκαταλελειμμένος από στοιχειώδη και βασικά δικαιώματα να έχει πρόσβαση στην υγεία, στην εκπαίδευση, σε σωστό δίκτυο συγκοινωνιών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-000" speaker_id="112071" name="Emer Costello" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, there is no doubt that youth unemployment is the greatest challenge facing the EU, and Ireland in particular.</p>
      <p sl="en">I welcome last Friday’s agreement between Council and Parliament to frontload the EUR[nbsp ]6[nbsp ]billion budget for tackling youth unemployment in 2014-2015. I particularly welcome that the Council has conceded to Parliament’s demand on flexibility so that unspent EU funds can continue to be put into youth employment measures from 2016.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proper implementation of the Youth Guarantee will be crucial. I have met with many organisations working with young people from Tallaght, Ballyfermot, Coolock and Balbriggan. They have emphasised the necessity of focusing on what young people need and to ensure that we address shortcomings of existing ESF-funded projects. If the Youth Guarantee is to work then we must consult widely with grassroots organisations in drawing up plans.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we also need the learning from pilot projects, and I am calling on the European Commission to announce the results of the Youth Guarantee pilot projects without further delay. Project applicants like Ballymun in Dublin applied last year and have been waiting since last April for the results. It is imperative that the momentum which is now behind the Youth Guarantee is maintained and that we give hope to young people and show them that Europe can deliver for them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169-000" speaker_id="111589" name="Inês Cristina Zuber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, no passado dia 27 de junho, em Portugal, teve lugar uma greve geral com uma das maiores adesões de sempre em todo o país e nos diversos setores de atividade, na indústria, nos serviços, no setor privado e no setor público. Na indústria, paralisação de muitas empresas, como o Arsenal do Alfeite, os Estaleiros Navais de Viana do Castelo ou a Lisnave. Nas pescas, paralisação generalizada das lotas e frotas de pesca. Nos transportes, paralisação generalizada dos comboios e metros e dos portos marítimos nacionais e um enorme impacto na operação aeroportuária. Na administração pública, foram muitos os hospitais e centros de saúde onde a greve se fez sentir fortemente. Muitos jovens com vínculos precários que, apesar da situação de chantagem em que vivem, tiveram a coragem de defender os seus direitos. E muitos outros exemplos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sobre a greve geral em Portugal, que ilações retiram as instituições europeias? Nenhuma. Porque esta greve constituiu uma indesmentível exigência da rejeição das políticas de direita, plasmadas no acordo com a troica, ou seja, as políticas da União Europeia. Os trabalhadores portugueses querem a troica fora de Portugal e disseram-no bem alto, exercendo o seu direito à greve. A União Europeia é tão democrática que faz de conta que nada aconteceu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-170-000" speaker_id="38610" name="Слави Бинев" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">В България хората са на улицата. Парламентът отново не промени Избирателния кодекс, така че и най-заклетите скептици да имат вяра в изборите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Международните наблюдатели констатираха сериозни нарушения на най-нечестните и манипулирани избори, а откритите 350 000 бюлетини бяха само част от подготвената фалшификация.</p>
      <p sl="en">Под 50% гласуваха, а 25% от тях нямат представителство в парламента.</p>
      <p sl="en">Фалшивите избори създават фалшив парламент и фалшиво правителство, които водят до глад, мизерия и отчаяние.</p>
      <p sl="en">Най-ощетените от фалшификациите бяха от Националния фронт за спасение на България, които взеха 3.8 % и малко не им достигна, за да влязат в парламента.</p>
      <p sl="en">Те поискаха от съда касиране на изборите, предоставяйки безспорни доказателства за стотици нарушения във всички избирателни райони.</p>
      <p sl="en">Затова Европарламентът трябва да се намеси на страната на потърпевшите български партии, в противен случай се посяга на демокрацията в България.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-000" speaker_id="96751" name="Nick Griffin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I recently spent four days in Damascus, a city that is striking for its normality and religious tolerance. Contrary to the propaganda about repression, Sunni mosques are open and some women wear clothing which shows the Salafist sympathies of their husbands. Others wear mini-skirts. It is a secular society much like ours.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also met captured free-Syria army rebels not only from North Africa and Central Asia, but also from France and Spain. They spoke freely about their aim, once they were done in Syria, to bring their bloody jihad to Europe – to London, Paris, Madrid, Stockholm and Manchester. At least 600 EU-born Islamists are fighting with the rebels.</p>
      <p sl="en">If you send arms to Syria, they will go to men who will bring them back here and turn them against us. If you arm the rebels, you will not just help these cut-throats destroy the last tolerant secular state in the Middle East, you will also bring Wahabi terror to our streets. Stop and think before you plunge your hands in so much innocent blood.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-000" speaker_id="39726" name="László Tőkés" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök úr! Romániában Victor Ponta szocialista-liberális kormánya nyolc olyan közigazgatási nagyrégiót kíván létrehozni, melyek a hagyományos történelmi régiókat teljességgel figyelmen kívül hagyván, nyilvánvaló módon az erdélyi magyar vidékek román többségű térségekbe való beolvasztását célozzák.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az 1968-as megyei átalakítások idején ezt még a soviniszta Ceaușescu sem merte megtenni velünk. 1989-ben pedig éppen az ország erőszakos területrendezési tervébe bukott bele a kommunista diktátor. Mi, erdélyi magyarok, nem akarunk a kipusztuló romániai németek és zsidók sorsára jutni. Az Európai Unió nem nézheti tétlenül a posztkommunista Románia eurokonformnak álcázott regionalizációs, illetve asszimilációs polikáját.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-000" speaker_id="96990" name="Carmen Romero López" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, usted, señor Comisario, seguro que no sigue este asunto. La Comisión ha escrito una carta al Gobierno español, a instancias de este, para llamar la atención al Gobierno de mi Comunidad autónoma, Andalucía, por el proyecto de ley que se debate ahora para asegurar la función social de la vivienda.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nos parece miserable que la Comisión Europea se haya prestado a eso. Una cosa son las peleas políticas en mi propio país y otra es que la Comisión venga a interferir en nuestro debate cuestionando una medida que hace posible el uso temporal, durante tres años, de viviendas propiedad de los bancos para familias vulnerables y mujeres víctimas de violencia y con acuerdo tácito entre las partes.</p>
      <p sl="en">¿Cómo es posible que no hayan dicho ni una palabra sobre los errores y los fallos de nuestro mercado financiero e hipotecario, de las cláusulas abusivas, de los costes de los servicios, y vienen ahora a cebarse con las familias vulnerables y las mujeres más débiles? ¿No es una vergüenza para esta Comisión Europea? ¿No le parece que se deberían haber escrito muchas cartas antes y no haber cometido nunca este error? ¿No tienen, de verdad, ninguna sensibilidad política para lo que están pasando tantas familias y tantas personas en mi país y en mi Comunidad autónoma?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-000" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this week marks the 25th anniversary of the Piper Alpha tragedy. On 6[nbsp ]July 1988, a series of explosions on the Piper Alpha oil and gas platform turned the rig into an inferno. One hundred and sixty-seven men lost their lives and only 59 men survived. The Piper Alpha tragedy is still today not just Europe’s but also the world’s most deadly off-shore disaster.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is therefore fitting that this House remember those who lost their lives in the North Sea. As one of the survivors said: ‘Piper has never left me; it was yesterday and will always be yesterday.’ That is why we should always support the highest standards in health and safety, especially in the off-shore environment. Only yesterday a crane on the Brent Charlie platform and some of its support structures were damaged. No one was injured and an investigation has been launched.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, we should never forget the Piper Alpha disaster and we should do all we can across the EU and the world to ensure that such a disaster never happens again.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-000" speaker_id="28514" name="Κυριάκος Τριανταφυλλίδης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, πληροφορίες αναφέρουν ότι σε επίσημα έγγραφα της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, που χρηματοδοτεί σειρά έργων στην τουρκοκρατούμενη περιοχή της Κύπρου, κατεχόμενα χωριά αναγράφονται με την μετονομασία που τους έδωσαν τα κατοχικά στρατεύματα και όχι με τα αναγνωρισμένα ονόματα των χωριών αυτών. Υπενθυμίζω, κύριε Πρόεδρε, ότι, με βάση τη σχετική σύμβαση των Ηνωμένων Εθνών για τα γεωγραφικά ονόματα, η Δημοκρατία της Κύπρου έχει καταθέσει στα Ηνωμένα Έθνη κατάλογο των ιστορικών ονομάτων και τοπωνυμίων της χώρας, κατοχυρώνοντας έτσι τον μόνο σωστό και νομικά αναγνωρισμένο τρόπο γραφής και ονομασίας αυτών των χωριών. Η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή, υιοθετώντας τις υπό των κατοχικών αρχών επιβληθείσες μετονομασίες, καταστρατηγεί το διεθνές δίκαιο, συνεπώς γίνεται συνυπεύθυνη στην προσπάθεια της Τουρκίας για τη δημογραφική και πολιτιστική αλλοίωση μιας περιοχής που αποτελεί αναπόσπαστο μέρος της ευρωπαϊκής οικογένειας. Καταγγέλλω αυτή την πρακτική ως παράνομη και καλώ τον Πρόεδρο της Ευρωπαϊκής Επιτροπής να ενεργήσει για τον άμεσο τερματισμό αυτής της παρανομίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-000" speaker_id="97280" name="Claudio Morganti" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la scorsa settimana la Corte suprema americana ha pronunciato una sentenza che in molti hanno definito storica, aprendo di fatto a quello che comunemente viene definito il matrimonio omosessuale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Già la stessa definizione "matrimonio omosessuale" dovrebbe farci capire come questa sia una chiara forzatura: due parole che non possono, per natura, stare una accanto all'altra, un chiaro ossimoro linguistico. Il termine matrimonio contiene infatti un esplicito riferimento alla funzione materna di procreazione, cosa che è impossibile fra due persone dello stesso sesso e non è una legge o una consuetudine che lo dice, ma è la natura stessa. Lo scopo del matrimonio è la creazione di una famiglia che tra due individui omosessuali non può avvenire in maniera naturale.</p>
      <p sl="en">La stessa Dichiarazione universale dei diritti dell'uomo è chiara e all'articolo 16, parlando di matrimonio e famiglia, non usa il termine generico di individui, ma specifica chiaramente che si parla di uomini e donne. Si deve assolutamente bloccare questa tendenza pericolosa, che oltre ad essere contraria alla storia, alla civiltà e alla religione è soprattutto contraria alla stessa natura che ci ha creati uomini e donne, diversi ed è l'unione di questa diversità che permette la prosecuzione naturale della vita e della specie umana.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-000" speaker_id="5537" name="Juan Andrés Naranjo Escobar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, el sector privado naval de España corre riesgo de hundirse si el próximo día 17 la Comisión confirma la decisión del señor Almunia de declarar ilegales las ayudas del régimen de tax[nbsp ]lease. Estoy convencido de que hay margen suficiente y argumentos jurídicos solventes para tomar una decisión razonable que ponga de manifiesto que la ley y su interpretación están al servicio de la justicia y el sentido común, y no al revés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diecinueve astilleros pueden cerrar, ochenta y siete mil trabajadores, ir al paro. Y en esto coinciden las empresas, los sindicatos, los Gobiernos de las regiones afectadas. Declarar ilegales esas ayudas aduciendo que no afectan ni a los astilleros ni a los bancos es una equivocación. Supone abrir la caja de los pleitos y cerrar la del negocio. Sin financiación, sin inversores ni armadores, los astilleros cerrarán. En Europa se han perdido ya 3,8 millones de empleos en el sector industrial. La decisión, tal y como la ha anunciado el señor Almunia, aumentará aún más esta dramática cifra.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-000" speaker_id="28295" name="Antolín Sánchez Presedo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, el sistema de tax lease es compatible con el Derecho europeo de la competencia. La aprobación del nuevo sistema español y la protección de los astilleros frente a las cláusulas de reclamación de ayudas es un buen punto de partida para la Decisión que la Comisión debe adoptar próximamente sobre la aplicación del viejo sistema de tax lease español a la construcción naval, un sector vital para la economía y el empleo de mi país.</p>
      <p sl="en">El actual proceso de consultas debe permitir configurar una decisión que salvaguarde la competencia en lugar de eliminarla y que contribuya a alcanzar los objetivos europeos de sostener el crecimiento y el empleo.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Unión tiene que respetar la confianza legítima y la seguridad jurídica de los particulares sobre la base de un esquema fiscal publicado oficialmente. Si la Comisión, como guardiana de la legalidad, no contó entre 2002 y 2011 con elementos para la apertura formal de un expediente, no puede exigir un estándar diferente a los operadores que lo han utilizado y, menos aún, derivar consecuencias desfavorables para ellos de procedimientos con otros Estados miembros de los que no han sido parte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-000" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef Weidenholzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Die Europäische Bürgerinitiative ist eine wichtige Errungenschaft, weil damit versucht wird, Elemente direkter Demokratie zu implementieren. Das Bürgerbegehren Right to Water hat als erstes die vorgeschriebene Mindestzahl an Unterzeichnern übersprungen. Damit wurde deutlich gemacht, dass ein solches direkt-demokratisches Instrument Sinn macht, weil es bürgerschaftliches Engagement erfolgreich bündeln kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zum anderen zeigt es aber auch, dass viele Menschen in Europa um die Versorgung mit öffentlichen Gütern wie dem Trinkwasser besorgt sind. Es ist zu begrüßen, dass diese Sorgen bei den Trilogverhandlungen Gehör fanden und der zuständige Kommissar seine ursprünglichen Vorstellungen zurückzog. Dies sollte Anlass für die europäischen Institutionen sein, dem Thema der öffentlichen Dienstleistungen verstärkte Aufmerksamkeit zukommen zu lassen, vor allem im Hinblick auf Artikel[nbsp ]36 der Grundrechtecharta, wonach der Zugang zu Dienstleistungen von allgemeinem Wirtschaftsinteresse ein Grundrecht darstellt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-000" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fontos lépések történtek Szerbiát illetően az elmúlt napokban. Az egyik az európa tanácsi döntés volt, miszerint legkésőbb 2014 januárjáig megkezdődnek a csatlakozási tárgyalások ezzel az országgal.</p>
      <p sl="en">A másik lépés, ami Szerbiában történt az akár még hónapokkal ezelőtt is elképzelhetetlen lett volna. A múlt heti magyar és szerb közös államfői főhajtásra gondolok a vajdasági Csurogon, azon a történelmi emlékhelyen, melyet az 1942-es razzia szerb, valamint az 1944-es megtorlások magyar áldozatainak emlékére közösen állított a két állam. Az államfők által képviselve a két nemzet hivatalosan is bocsánatot kért a múltban egymás ellen elkövetett bűnökért. A szerb parlament azt megelőzően nyilatkozatban ítélte el az 1944–45-ös vajdasági vérengzéseket és a kollektív bűnösség szellemében hozott háborús határozatokat, amely a vajdasági magyar közösséget kollektívan bélyegezte meg. A magyar államfő pedig bocsánatot kért a szerb parlament előtt a magyarok által kivégzett ártatlan szerbekért.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az ilyen szimbolikus cselekedetek jelentik mindig a legnehezebb első lépést. Akkor valóban értékesek, ha a következő lépések szintén az együttélést segítik, ha úgy a magyarok, mint a szerbek mindennapjai válnak tőlük valóban jobbá.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-000" speaker_id="96803" name="Zbigniew Ziobro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! W najbliższą środę będziemy głosować sprawę back-loadingu. Jest to inicjatywa Komisji Europejskiej, która zmierza do tego, aby sztucznymi, administracyjnymi metodami podnieść cenę uprawnień do emisji gazów cieplarnianych. Jest to przedsięwzięcie wątpliwe z punktu widzenia reguł rynku – wolnego rynku – który zakłada, że nie powinno zmieniać się tych reguł w czasie gry, w czasie, kiedy one zostały już ustalone i wprowadzone w życie. Tak jest właśnie w tym wypadku i narusza to stabilność i pewność reguł podmiotów gospodarczych. Ale co niemniej ważne, a może nawet pierwszoplanowe w tej sprawie, to fakt, że niestety sprawa będzie miała daleko idące reperkusje, jeśli chodzi o sytuację gospodarstw domowych oraz europejskiej gospodarki, bo inicjatywa ta nieuchronnie będzie prowadzić do wzrostu cen energii, co odbije się na rachunkach tak zwykłych odbiorców europejskich, jak i tych, którzy zajmują się produkcją.</p>
      <p sl="en">I jeszcze jedna rzecz: jest uderzające, że gospodarki, które z nami konkurują, jak Stany Zjednoczone czy Daleki Wschód, mają znacznie niższe ceny energii, nawet o połowę niższe, a te zmiany spowodują wzrost cen energii i obniżą jeszcze konkurencyjność gospodarki europejskiej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-000" speaker_id="96811" name="Rosa Estaràs Ferragut" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, Marta Zabala, una mujer de treinta y tres años, viajaba de Bilbao a Madrid, en España. Ella tiene movilidad reducida —va en silla de ruedas— y una compañía, la segunda compañía aérea española en facturación, le prohibió el embarque por no ir acompañada, al hacer una interpretación errónea del Reglamento del año 2006 de este Parlamento, concretamente del artículo 4, apartado 1, del Reglamento sobre los derechos de las personas con discapacidad o movilidad reducida en el transporte aéreo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Evidentemente, esta interpretación es errónea, porque el principio que impera y el espíritu de toda la Unión Europea es el de no discriminación y el de que cualquier persona, aunque tenga movilidad reducida, pueda ir y pasear, y también viajar, por toda la Unión. Se trata, sin ninguna duda, de una discriminación clara y de una triquiñuela para discriminar, confundiendo la seguridad con la comodidad. Las compañías abusan de esta posibilidad de exigir un acompañante, obligando a la segunda persona a pagar el precio completo de su billete. Por eso, desde aquí, formulo una petición a la Comisión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dado que ha dicho y ha anunciado que está revisando toda la reglamentación en transporte aéreo, indico a la Comisión que es el momento de clarificar este artículo 4 del Reglamento, para que no vuelva a suceder un caso igual. También es un llamamiento a las compañías aéreas para que abandonen de inmediato estas malas prácticas, que ponen en entredicho el principio de no discriminación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-183-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the item.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. External aviation policy (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-185-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Marian-Jean Marinescu, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism, on the EU’s External Aviation Policy – Addressing future challenges (2012/2299(INI)) (A7-0172/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Raportor. - Transportul aerian susţine 5,1 milioane de locuri de muncă şi contribuie cu 365 de miliarde euro (2,4 %) la PIB-ul european. Are o contribuţie majoră la creşterea economică, dezvoltarea turismului şi la coeziunea regională şi socială a Uniunii. Unul din elementele-cheie ale competitivităţii este conectivitatea. Uniunea se bazează pe comerţul exterior. Transportul aerian, aeroporturile au un rol important în conectarea Europei cu restul lumii. De aceea, este necesară sprijinirea unei agende extrem de ambiţioase pentru acest sector. Liberalizarea este necesară şi are rolul său. În acealaşi timp, însă, Uninea trebuie să promoveze şi să apere propriile standarde şi interese. O atenţie specială trebuie acordată standardelor pentru muncă şi mediu, siguranţă şi securitate, drepturilor pasagerilor şi, în general, respectării regulamentelor europene. Comisia Europeană trebuie să definească un set minim de cerinţe care să fie incluse în acordurile bilaterale, pentru a apăra interesle, valorile şi bunele practici europene. În acealaşi timp, trebuie insistat pe acorduri cuprinzătoare la nivel european, bazate pe unitate europeană şi autorizate de Consiliu. Acordurile trebuie să includă condiţii referitoare la siguranţă, securitate, drepturile pasagerilor, şcolarizarea şi certificarea personalului. Eforturile depuse în ultimii 7 ani în implementarea unei politici externe pentru aviaţie, chiar dacă au fost la un nivel ridicat, s-au dovedit insuficiente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este necesară o abordare comună, coordonată de la nivel european, care să mărească şansele Uniunii de a pătrunde pe noi pieţe. Trebuie finalizate acordurile pentru servicii aeriene cu Brazilia, Australia şi Noua Zeelandă, este necesară negocierea unor acorduri cu zone cu economii emergente: China, India, ASEAN, statele din Golf. Acordurile cu state vecine ca: Ucraina, Liban, Tunisia, Adzerbaidjan, Algeria sunt oportunităţi de dezvoltare pentru aeroporturile regionale şi secundare şi pot contribui, în acelaşi timp, la descongestionarea principalelor hub-uri europene şi creşterea competitivităţii acestora pe plan global. Aglomerarea principalelor aeroporturi europene este evidentă şi creează dezavantaje faţă de noile hub-uri din ţările terţe. Este nevoie de infrastructuri noi şi de utilizarea eficientă a celor existente. Concurenţa trebuie să fie transparentă şi corectă. Există încă elemente care distorsionează piaţa, subvenţii, lipsa de transparenţă, nerespectarea standardelor sociale, abordarea inegală a drepturilor pasagerilor. Politica externă pentru aviaţie trebuie să respecte pe deplin principul reciprocităţii, inclusiv accesul pe piaţă, să abordeze toate activităţile legate de serviciile aeriene, o competiţie corectă şi transparentă şi să aibă două obiective principale: beneficiul pasagerilor şi al companiilor şi sprijinirea companiilor şi a aeroporturilor europene în efortul de a păstra poziţia de lideri pe piaţa mondială.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentul European cere Comisiei şi statelor membre să urgenteze implementarea celor două proiecte europene exrtrem de importante pentru sectorul aviatic: SES şi SESAR. În acest sens, vreau să salut propunerea Comisiei, SES2+, care, chiar dacă nu este suficient de ambiţioasă, poate fi îmbunătăţită şi poate constitui un pas foarte mare înainte pentru eficienţa transportului aerian în interiorul Uniunii. Cerem Comisiei să examineze măsurile care pot asigura reciprocitatea în ceea ce priveşte utilizarea spaţiului aerian între Uniune şi Federaţia Rusă. Acordul comercial între Statele Unite şi Uniune va afecta şi transportul aerian. Comisia trebuie să ia în calcul eliminarea restricţiilor în ceea ce priveşte proprietatea şi controlul companiilor aeriene, atât în relaţia cu Statele Unite, cât şi cu Canada.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188-000" speaker_id="99325" name="Σπύρος Δανέλλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Κύριε Επίτροπε, η εξωτερική πολιτική αερομεταφορών, που θεσπίστηκε το 2005, έχει ωφελήσει την Ένωση τα τελευταία χρόνια, αφού μόνο η συμφωνία με τις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες της Αμερικής δημιουργεί 80.000 νέες θέσεις εργασίας. Αλλά το εν λόγω θεσμικό πλαίσιο έχει περιέλθει σε μία περίοδο στασιμότητας εν αναμονή φιλόδοξων πολιτικών δράσεων και συμφωνιών με κύρια δεδομένα, πρώτον, ότι οι αεροπορικές εταιρίες της Ένωσης διανύουν μια παρατεταμένη περίοδο κρίσης και άρα αδυναμίας εκμετάλλευσης των ευκαιριών στην παγκόσμια αγορά, κυρίως στην Ασία, και δεύτερον, ότι απομένει να συναφθούν συμφωνίες με γειτονικά κράτη, όπως η Ουκρανία, η Τυνησία και ο Λίβανος, που μπορούν να δώσουν τόνωση στην ευρωπαϊκή αγορά, ενώ το Συμβούλιο ακόμη δεν έχει δώσει εντολή στην Επιτροπή για διαπραγματεύσεις με Τουρκία, Αρμενία και Λιβύη. Τέλος, να συμπληρώσω ότι οι εταιρίες του Περσικού Κόλπου, και όχι μόνο βεβαίως, συνεχίζουν να αντλούν άμεση και έμμεση κρατική χρηματοδότηση και επομένως να βρίσκονται σε αθέμιτο ανταγωνισμό προς τις ευρωπαϊκές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Unser Berichterstatter, Herr Marinescu, hat schon sehr viel Wichtiges gesagt. Ich möchte ihm ganz herzlich danken. Es ist tatsächlich so, dass es bei der externen Luftfahrtpolitik darauf ankommt, zum einen natürlich zu sehen, dass der Himmel international ist, dass wir uns im Luftverkehrsraum nicht nur in Europa bewegen, sondern wirklich weltweit. Da ist es wichtig, Abkommen zu treffen, das machen wir auch. Gleichzeitig ist es aber auch ganz entscheidend, dass wir mit unserer Gesetzgebung, auch mit dem, was wir hier für die Airlines bieten, auf unsere europäische Wettbewerbsfähigkeit achten. Die Airlines haben teilweise Schwierigkeiten, mit anderen zu konkurrieren. Emirates zum Beispiel hat einen ganz anderen finanziellen Hintergrund als unsere Airlines. Das heißt, wir sind da wirklich herausgefordert, jetzt zu sehen, wie man international agieren und trotzdem bei uns vor Ort eine gute Balance halten kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Als Letztes noch: Mir ist es ganz wichtig, den Einheitlichen Europäischen Luftraum noch einmal anzusprechen. Herr Marinescu erwähnte ihn. Den haben alle Mitgliedstaaten unterzeichnet, aber die Umsetzung ist kolossal schwierig. Wir fliegen in Europa immer noch im Zickzack statt gerade Linien. Das müssen wir unbedingt mit abbauen, denn das ist weder ökologisch noch ökonomisch sinnvoll.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-191-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Siim Kallas" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, I would like to thank the rapporteur Mr Marinescu for an excellent report and Mr Bach and Mr Sturdy for their contributions as rapporteurs for the opinion of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs and the Committee on International Trade.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aviation is a strategically important sector, as the rapporteur has already mentioned. The aviation industry supports over 5 million jobs and contributes more than EUR[nbsp ]350 billion to European GDP. Europe is a world leader in manufacturing and in aviation-linked research and development.</p>
      <p sl="en">But the European aviation sector is going through tough times. International competition, especially in air transport, is becoming fiercer and fiercer. The Commission believes that the EU’s external aviation policy needs to change to meet these challenges. Europe must maintain a strong and competitive aviation industry.</p>
      <p sl="en">Over the past 10 years, we have shown that Europe can make a difference. We have achieved results that never would have been possible without coordinated EU-wide action. But we can, and must, do much better.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is where the external aviation policy has an important role to play. So I am very pleased that this report strongly supports a more ambitious and better coordinated policy. It is time for the EU to act with one voice. This is a key issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to, if I may, single out one particular aspect: we need to be able to normalise our – difficult – aviation relations with Russia, including on the famous question of Siberian over-flights. I will therefore soon request a mandate from the Council to open negotiations on a comprehensive EU-Russia air transport agreement. Your support for this would be helpful.</p>
      <p sl="en">Russia seems to have been left out of paragraph[nbsp ]39 of the motion for a resolution which lists the countries with which the Commission should negotiate a comprehensive agreement. I encourage you to include Russia in that list.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-192-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 2 July 2013.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Blue growth - enhancing sustainable growth in the marine, maritime transport and tourism sectors (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-194-000" speaker_id="28323" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Spyros Danellis, on behalf of the Committee on Transport and Tourism, on blue growth: enhancing sustainable growth in the EU’s marine, maritime transport and tourism sectors (COM(2012)0491 – 2012/2297(INI)) (A7-0209/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-195-000" speaker_id="99325" name="Σπύρος Δανέλλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Εισηγητής. - Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Κυρία Επίτροπε, βασική αιτία της μεγαλύτερης κρίσης χρέους που έχει γνωρίσει η Ένωση καθώς και της συνακόλουθης κοινωνικής μάστιγας της ανεργίας, που με εφιαλτικούς ρυθμούς συνεχώς διευρύνεται, είναι το ότι η Ευρώπη έχει χάσει την ανταγωνιστικότητά της. Η ανάδυση νέων παγκόσμιων παικτών την εκτόπισαν από τις πρωτοπορίες της παγκόσμιας οικονομίας. Πρέπει λοιπόν κατεπειγόντως να στραφεί σε νέα αναπτυξιακά πεδία. Η στροφή στη θαλάσσια οικονομία και τους πλουτοπαραγωγικούς θαλάσσιους πόρους αποτελεί μία φιλόδοξη, οραματική αλλά ταυτοχρόνως ρεαλιστική πρόταση. Ανοίγει προοπτικές για ευρείες συνεργασίες μεταξύ οικονομικών κλάδων που δεν δραστηριοποιούνται μονάχα στις παράκτιες περιοχές της Ένωσης των 28, από σήμερα πλέον, χωρών μελών αλλά στο σύνολο της επικράτειάς της. Ο παράκτιος και θαλάσσιος τουρισμός σε όλες τις θεματικές του εκφράσεις, η υδατοκαλλιέργεια, η γαλάζια ενέργεια, η θαλάσσια βιοτεχνολογία, η θαλάσσια εξόρυξη ορυκτών καθώς και, μέσω αυτών, η ενίσχυση της ναυτιλίας και της χειμαζόμενης ευρωπαϊκής ναυπηγικής βιομηχανίας αποτελούν τους τομείς της γαλάζιας ανάπτυξης που μπορούν να αυξήσουν το μέγεθος της θαλάσσιας οικονομίας σε 590 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ μέχρι το 2020 και με κατάλληλες πολιτικές κατάρτισης που να εξασφαλίζουν ένα ευκίνητο εργατικό δυναμικό με επαρκή εξειδίκευση και εμπειρία, η συνολική απασχόληση στη γαλάζια ανάπτυξη δύναται να ξεπεράσει την εκτίμηση των 7 εκατομμυρίων θέσεων εργασίας μέχρι το 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι τοπικές περιφερειακές, εθνικές και ευρωπαϊκές αρχές θα πρέπει να δημιουργήσουν τις απαραίτητες προϋποθέσεις για βιώσιμη ανάπτυξη όπως συστήματα θαλάσσιου χωροταξικού σχεδιασμού και ολοκληρωμένης διαχείρισης των παράκτιων ζωνών, αναβάθμιση των υποδομών, πρόσβαση σε επαγγελματικές δεξιότητες, διάχυση πληροφοριών και βέλτιστων πρακτικών και βεβαίως εξασφάλιση επαρκούς χρηματοδότησης. Προκειμένου οι τομείς της γαλάζιας ανάπτυξης να εξελιχθούν και να ξεδιπλώσουν το σύνολο της δυναμικής συμβολής τους στην ευρωπαϊκή οικονομία, είναι αναγκαίος ένας στρατηγικός σχεδιασμός σε επίπεδο Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης σε ό,τι αφορά τον συντονισμό και τις συνεργασίες μεταξύ των υφιστάμενων πολιτικών καθώς επίσης και σε ό,τι αφορά την ανάπτυξη νέων πρωτοβουλιών και εργαλείων.</p>
      <p sl="en">Βεβαίως, για να επιτύχουμε τη μέγιστη δυνατή αξιοποίηση των δυνατοτήτων που παρέχει η γαλάζια ανάπτυξη, οι φορείς δημόσιας και ιδιωτικής σφαίρας πρέπει να ενώσουν τις προσπάθειές τους και να εργαστούν σ’ ένα ενιαίο πολιτικό πλαίσιο που να λαμβάνει υπόψη του τις νέες προτεραιότητες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Σε μία εποχή περικοπής δημοσίων επενδύσεων στα κράτη μέλη είναι επιτακτική ανάγκη οι αναπτυξιακές πολιτικές, και κυρίως τα έργα υψηλού κόστους, όπως είναι αυτά των μεταφορών, των επικοινωνιακών και ενεργειακών υποδομών, να εξασφαλίζουν επαρκή χρηματοδότηση κατά τη διάρκεια της προγραμματικής περιόδου 2014 – ’20 αλλά βεβαίως και μετά από αυτήν. Είναι ανάγκη να διοχετευτούν οι διαθέσιμοι πόροι των ευρωπαϊκών ταμείων και των χρηματοδοτικών μηχανισμών σε έργα της γαλάζιας οικονομίας, τα οποία είναι βέβαιο ότι θα αποδώσουν σε προστιθέμενη ευρωπαϊκή αξία. Πρωταρχική προϋπόθεση και βασική πρόκληση αποτελεί η διασφάλιση της ολοκληρωμένης βιωσιμότητας της γαλάζιας ανάπτυξης, ότι δηλαδή δεν θα βλάψει το ιδιαιτέρως ευάλωτο θαλάσσιο περιβάλλον και θα συμβάλει παράλληλα στην καταπολέμηση της κλιματικής αλλαγής.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι λαοί της Ευρώπης τα τελευταία εννιά χιλιάδες χρόνια στρέφονταν οργανωμένα στη θάλασσα αναζητώντας και διασφαλίζοντας καλύτερο μέλλον. Κυρία Επίτροπε, χαιρετίζουμε με ιδιαίτερη ικανοποίηση την ανακοίνωση της Επιτροπής για τη γαλάζια ανάπτυξη και ζητούμε την επίσπευση των διαδικασιών και την ανάληψη από μέρους σας κάθε πρωτοβουλίας που είναι αναγκαία για τη στήριξή της. Τέλος, θα ήθελα να ευχαριστήσω από καρδιάς όλους τους σκιώδεις εισηγητές για την εξαιρετική συνεργασία μαζί τους καθώς και όσους εργάστηκαν για την τελική διαμόρφωση της έκθεσής μας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-000" speaker_id="96902" name="Maria do Céu Patrão Neves" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, felicito a Comissão, o relator e relatores-sombra pelos seus respetivos contributos para o reforço do crescimento azul através dos transportes e turismo, assim como do ordenamento do espaço marítimo, a gestão integrada das zonas costeiras, pescas e aquicultura, construção naval e emprego, energia e biotecnologias, investigação e inovação, extração de minerais do fundo marinho.</p>
      <p sl="en">No que se refere a este setor, urge rever a posição defendida no relatório que compromete uma das nossas potenciais riquezas. Com efeito, a preconizada reciclagem de metais não se afigura suficiente para suprir as necessidades da indústria, pelo que não será argumento para prescindir da extração de minérios marinhos, pelo contrário, dever-se-á investir em estudos acerca da sua viabilidade e que legitimem a comparação da produção de metais por via da extração e da reciclagem, que avaliem o impacto desta atividade, promovendo tecnologias que garantam a sua sustentabilidade.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para tal, a União Europeia financia o projeto MIDAS - Gestão dos Impactos da Exploração dos Recursos de Alto Mar em cerca de 10 milhões de euros, entre 2014 e 2016. Esta é uma excelente oportunidade para recolher informação científica sólida e credível sobre a extração de minerais necessária para a tomada de decisão futura sobre este setor. Temos a obrigação social de usufruir das riquezas do nosso planeta, sob o dever ambiental de o fazer de uma forma sustentável.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198-000" speaker_id="37524" name="Маруся Любчева" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Поздравявам докладчика за пространния и много съдържателен доклад, обединяващ морските секторни политики.</p>
      <p sl="en">Искам да подчертая, че син растеж не би могъл да се формира, ако преди това не е формирана морска култура, която има водещо начало при неговото реализиране. Това е процес, в който участват много институции и организации, образованието също.</p>
      <p sl="en">В образователните планове обаче няма дисциплини, свързани с морето, професионалните училища, свързани с морско дело, не се радват на особен интерес, морските професии не се считат за атрактивни във висшето образование.</p>
      <p sl="en">За да се промени това, морските държави трябва да имат ясно формирани приоритети и стратегии и да водят силно интегрирана политика в областта на морското дело. Разпокъсването й в различни институции и несинхронизирана законодателна база я обрича на неуспех.</p>
      <p sl="en">Важно е да се спазва моделът на интегрираната морска политика на Европейския съюз. И тук не мога да не спомена, разбира се, че трябва да се върнем към проблема за Черноморската стратегия и нейното бъдеще, което е изключително важно.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Bis 2050 sollen wir neun Milliarden Menschen auf der Welt haben. Wenn man sich das vorstellt, ist vollkommen klar, dass das Festland allein nicht ausreicht, dass wir das Meer noch viel stärker als bisher brauchen. Europa war in gewisser Weise sehr weitsichtig, da wir schon vor sieben Jahren eine integrierte Meerespolitik entwickelt haben, denn wir haben gemerkt, es gibt immer mehr Wirtschaft, die um das Meer und mit dem Meer betrieben wird, und immer mehr Forschung um das Meer herum. Wir wollen das Meer in einer nachhaltigen Art und Weise nutzen und ganz lange noch etwas vom Meer haben. Darum gibt es diese integrierte Meerespolitik.</p>
      <p sl="en">Heute geht es um das blaue Wachstum. Das blaue Wachstum ist praktisch die maritime Säule der EU-2020-Strategie für mehr Jobs und mehr Wachstum. Dazu gehören die Energien aus dem Meer, der Küstentourismus, die blaue Biotechnologie – da sind bis jetzt erst 10[nbsp ]% der Möglichkeiten des Meeres erforscht –, die mineralen Rohstoffe und natürlich auch die Aquakultur, denn die Menschen essen immer gerne Fisch. Wir müssen viel mehr entwickeln, und wir sind auf einem sehr guten Weg dazu. Ich möchte mich ganz herzlich bei Herrn Danellis für seinen Bericht bedanken und bei Frau Damanaki, weil sie sich so engagiert für dieses Thema einsetzt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-000" speaker_id="111823" name="Νικος Χρυσόγελος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, θέλουμε πράγματι να αναπτυχθεί η γαλάζια οικονομία, αλλά αυτή πρέπει να είναι και πιο πράσινη. Γιατί σίγουρα πολλά επαγγέλματα εξαρτώνται από τη θάλασσα αλλά και πολλές φορές έχουμε και ρύπανση του περιβάλλοντος και υποβάθμιση της θαλάσσιας βιοποικιλότητας. Θέλουμε λοιπόν μία οικονομία γαλάζια, που θα ενισχύσει και θα αυξήσει τις δραστηριότητες γύρω από τον θαλάσσιο πλούτο αλλά διατηρώντας μακροχρόνια αυτόν τον πλούτο, θα βοηθήσει στην κοινωνική συνοχή και σε νέα επαγγέλματα που πολύ νέοι άνθρωποι τα έχουν σπουδάσει αλλά δεν βρίσκουν εφαρμογές στις σημερινές πολιτικές. Θέλουμε επίσης σωστά σχέδια θαλάσσιου χωροταξικού σχεδιασμού και ολοκληρωμένης διαχείρισης της παράκτιας ζώνης, έτσι ώστε πράγματι η γαλάζια οικονομία να αποβεί προς όφελος και του περιβάλλοντος και της απασχόλησης και της οικονομίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-000" speaker_id="97280" name="Claudio Morganti" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io vengo da una regione, la Toscana, che ha una forte vocazione marittima e sono quindi ben consapevole delle difficoltà e delle potenzialità di questo settore.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trovo doveroso il riferimento ai problemi che l'applicazione della direttiva Servizi può creare a migliaia di famiglie, piccoli imprenditori che con il loro stabilimento balneare contribuiscono alla prosperità, allo sviluppo e alla sicurezza di interi tratti di costa; un'eccellenza che abbiamo solo noi in Italia e che ci caratterizza per competenza e ospitalità. Non possiamo rischiare che questo patrimonio venga spazzato via, magari da qualche multinazionale della recettività e del turismo, perché il pericolo è questo e chi segue la vicenda da tempo come faccio io lo sa bene.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ben vengano, inoltre, misure a sostegno di aree insulari svantaggiate. L'istituzione di zone franche può essere una soluzione utile che vedrei molto bene applicata ad esempio all'isola d'Elba, un territorio che negli ultimi anni ha subito una forte recessione e che potrebbe trarre nuovo impulso da misure di agevolazione fiscale e di aiuto agli investimenti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-000" speaker_id="96682" name="Sari Essayah" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, juuri päättynyt Irlannin puheenjohtajuuskausi nosti esille sinisen kasvun eli EU:n meritalouden kestävän kasvun edistämisen. Täytyy sanoa, että tällä puheenjohtajuuskaudella on ollut niin paljon muitakin vaikeita asioita, että sininen kasvu on jäänyt vähän taka-alalle, mutta onneksi tämä esittelijän tekemä erinomainen mietintö nostaa nimenomaan monipuolisesti sinisen kasvun esille.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tästä mietinnöstä haluaisin erityisesti nostaa esille, paitsi tämän kalastus- ja vesiviljelyn alan, joka ensimmäisenä ehkä tulee aina mieleen, myöskin sinisen energian, joka tarkoittaa merituulivoiman ja vuorovesiaalto- ja merilämpöenergian hyödyntämistä. Tämä jos mikä on yksi tulevaisuuden ala, samoin kuin sininen bioteknologia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lyhyesti vielä mainitsisin sen, että merenkulku ja laivanrakennus puolestaan on Euroopassa tietyllä tavalla auringonlaskun ala, koska maailmanlaajuisesti monet valtiot, muun muassa Etelä-Korea, tukevat omaa telakkateollisuuttaan tavalla, joka on vääristänyt maailmanmarkkinoita. Tähän EU:n tulee esimerkiksi WTO:ssa kiinnittää huomiota.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-204-000" speaker_id="118710" name="Franco Bonanini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, volevo complimentarmi anch'io con il relatore e vorrei sottolineare due aspetti in particolare che mi sembrano meritevoli di essere messi in evidenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il primo problema – per una crescita sostenibile ed equilibrata – è quello di generare un'integrazione fra costa ed entroterra. Le fasce costiere sono troppo spesso sfruttate in maniera disorganica, c'è un consumo spropositato di territorio e c'è una logica bulimica che tende a calpestare valori e culture, mentre a pochi chilometri di distanza esistono zone dell'entroterra per le quali una piccola percentuale di opportunità può rappresentare invece uno stimolo per i residenti e garantire il presidio del territorio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Volevo solo fare un piccolo appunto per una maggiore cautela per quanto riguarda invece l'acquacoltura che – è ovvio – viene definita sostenibile. Infatti, come è noto, nell'acquacoltura l'apporto di tipi di mangime e di antibiotici genera effetti inquinanti sull'ecosistema in grado, nei casi più gravi, di portare a fenomeni di eutrofizzazione delle acque generati dall'utilizzo di prodotti contenenti azoto e fosforo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-206-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Maria Damanaki" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me first thank the rapporteur, Mr Danellis, the shadow rapporteurs and the members of the associated committees of the European Parliament for this report. I am referring here to the Committee on Transport and Tourism, the Committee on Regional Development and on the Committee on Fisheries. They have produced a very good report and I am happy that all speakers have recognised that this report and our initiative on blue growth contain a set of forward-looking proposals with a realistic and coherent framework.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to welcome the fact that the report endorses the five key areas identified by the Commission as having particular potential for job creation and the application of innovations. These five areas are: blue energy, aquaculture, maritime and coastal tourism, marine mineral extraction and blue biotechnology.</p>
      <p sl="en">Having said that, let me come to some specific points. With regard to shipbuilding and seaborne transport in general, it is true that we are facing some difficulties, as the rapporteur and other Members have underlined. But I would also like to underline that there are many ways to contribute to the sector’s sustainable growth, such as by reducing greenhouse gas emissions, removing administrative barriers, cutting red tape and promoting innovation. Here we still have a margin for improvement.</p>
      <p sl="en">On maritime and coastal tourism, I agree with the report that the first challenge here is making sure that the risk skills for the workforce are there. The Commission will come up with a communication on maritime and coastal tourism before the end of this year.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, on the importance of integrated sustainability, I share the concerns expressed here by some Members about the need for sustainability in all these actions. I fully agree that the environmental dimension needs to be mainstreamed into any blue-growth initiative.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need to preserve our natural environment if we want to benefit fully from the opportunities it offers, and not to destroy it as we have done in some cases. That is why a substantial research project on mineral extraction and its environmental impact is now being negotiated under the European framework programme. We expect this project to begin in the autumn.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is no denying that we need to step up our recycling efforts. I can agree on that, but despite this we will never manage to provide the steady supply of raw materials which our industry needs. We propose examining all options.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mineral extraction can create new jobs and new economic outlets, as well as spin-offs in technology developments and guarantees for a secure supply of raw materials. As the rapporteur and others have said, this must come with the precondition that this or any other emerging sector is part and parcel of a wider sustainability effort. More specifically, we need to make sure that, if a man-made tool of any kind touches the bottom of our seas, strict environmental standards are observed, no matter whom it belongs to.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is what we intend to do; this is what is going to happen. I would like once again to thank the rapporteur and all the speakers and all the Members of this House for their support on this blue-growth initiative.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-207-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Dienstag, 2.[nbsp ]Juli 2013, um 12.00[nbsp ]Uhr statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 149 GO)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-207-500" speaker_id="39714" name="Rareş-Lucian Niculescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – În contextul rezoluţiei referitoare la creşterea albastră - consolidarea creşterii durabile în sectoarele de transport marin, maritim şi de turism ale UE, doresc să subliniez importanţa pe care o joacă Strategia Dunării, care implică cele 14 state membre ale UE şi terţe din bazinul acestui fluviu. Regiunea Dunării reprezintă a doua macroregiune a UE, provocările legate de această zonă având impact nu doar asupra vieţii celor 115 milioane de oameni, ci asupra tuturor cetăţenilor europeni. Finanţarea de 100 de miliarde de euro prin politica de coeziune în perioada 2007-2013 a permis derularea unor proiecte importante, de aceea susţinerea financiară trebuie să continue într-un cadru eficient în următoarea perspectivă financiară. Subliniez, mai ales, importanţa continuării proiectelor demarate în domeniul protecţiei mediului, biodiversităţii, a resurselor halieutice, dar şi în domeniul transporturilor şi turismului. Dunărea poate contribui semnificativ la creşterea albastră, exploatarea întregului său potenţial fiind totodată esenţială pentru îmbunătăţirea condiţiilor de viaţă din regiune.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Contribution of cooperatives to overcoming the crisis (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-209-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Patrizia Toia im Namen des Ausschusses für Industrie, Forschung und Energie über den Beitrag der Genossenschaften zur Überwindung der Krise (2012/2321(INI)) (A7-0222/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-210-000" speaker_id="28340" name="Patrizia Toia" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatrice. - Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, nella crisi c'è una parte di imprese – le cooperative – che ha dimostrato di resistere di più e meglio delle altre, di essere capace di tenere duro, difendere l'occupazione – anzi di crescere nella crisi – anche in ragione del valore che si dà al lavoro e grazie al legame con il tessuto sociale e la comunità del territorio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le cooperative sono imprese che non perseguono prioritariamente il profitto, ma vogliono promuovere con una gestione economica equilibrata il lavoro, il welfare, i consumi e contribuire allo sviluppo locale anche con buoni progetti imprenditoriali come nel campo energetico. Tutto ciò è così vero che si è inaugurato il termine "resilienza" per dimostrare questa resistenza che oggi molti studi certificano. Resilienza più forte, voglia e determinazione di stare in piedi, capacità di difendere la propria attività e di generare occupazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">La nostra relazione di iniziativa vuole mettere in luce un fenomeno particolare in questo mondo, cioè il ruolo delle cooperative di fronte alle crisi produttive e alle ristrutturazioni aziendali. Quando un'impresa sta fallendo e vuole chiudere i battenti, ecco che si possono fare diverse trasformazioni: possono esserci processi di management leveraged buyout, ma ci possono essere anche forme di workers buyout – lavoratori che si mettono insieme, si fanno cooperativa, per continuare l'attività. Noi dobbiamo lasciare aperte tutte queste possibilità. L'Europa deve sostenerle, anche con appositi strumenti, perché c'è un ruolo attivo delle cooperative nelle ristrutturazioni per salvare le imprese dalla crisi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ci siamo dati una strategia di reindustrializzazione e di crescita di nuove imprese; dunque il primo passo è difendere le imprese che ci sono e accompagnarle nella crisi. Il modello cooperativo, con la sua dinamicità, la capacità di adattarsi al cambiamento, per flessibilità e sostegno delle reti locali è quantomai interessante per l'economia europea. È naturalmente la visione di economia sociale e di mercato che l'Europa rivendica come modello, ma per il quale non fa abbastanza. È una sfida di cultura economica, perché queste imprese sono una leva potente di sviluppo e possono essere molto competitive.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se l'Europa facesse di più in questo campo rafforzerebbe il proprio patrimonio economico e produttivo, perché è un grave errore relegare questo settore – anche se è solo una parte dell'economia continentale – nella marginalità o nella debolezza. C'è anzi uno studio – come segnala Scalvini che è un leader del settore – del Dipartimento del tesoro americano che evidenzia come, per Fannie Mae e Freddie Mac, una struttura cooperativa avrebbe evitato i disastri finanziari dai quali poi è partita la crisi globale. Interessante, io credo, come lezione per la nostra visione di economia e di finanza.</p>
      <p sl="en">In sintesi la relazione che si rifà alla risoluzione che votammo in questo Parlamento alla fine della precedente legislatura, proprio sulle imprese dell'economia sociale e di mercato, segnala le buone pratiche già esistenti in molti Stati membri dell'Unione – di casi di cooperative che hanno salvato imprese dal fallimento – e chiede che l'Europa faccia di più, la Commissione faccia di più e in maniera più calibrata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si chiede un rafforzamento degli uffici della Commissione – da dedicare a ciò, specificatamente – si chiede che si valorizzi il settore, lo si faccia partecipe del dialogo sociale e che in futuro si prevedano – passando dai progetti pilota – anche linee di bilancio dedicate al sostegno a queste pratiche di ristrutturazioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Penso che l'Europa debba avere più coraggio nell'indicare nuovi modi di fare economia e impresa, per valorizzare il suo capitale civile anche sul piano economico perché qui ci sono rilevanti vantaggi economici e si esce un po' da quella logica di assistenzialismo nella quale spesso il settore, ingiustamente, è relegato. Si deve fare di più per dare concretezza nel mettere in campo strumenti e misure concrete e adeguate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-212-000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A szövetkezetek az Európai Unióban nagyon fontos közösségi jellegű és bizonyítottan hatékony kezelőeszköz szerepét töltik be. A közép-kelet-európai térség államaiban státusuk és működésük a kommunizmus ideje alatt sajnos kissé kompromittálódott. A jelenlegi hosszantartó válság kezelésében megmutatkozó szerepük tagadhatatlan. Számuk és jelentőségük valamennyi tagállamban nőtt. A foglalkoztatottsági arány körükben felfelé ívelő tendenciát mutat, és az összetett válsághelyzet ellenére csődellenállóbbak a hagyományos vállalatoknál, sőt regionális szinten munkaerő-integrációs szerepük is hangsúlyos. A szövetkezetek nyitottabbak a hagyományos vállalkozásoknál. Flexibilitásuk az új és innovatív ágazatokban olyan alkalmazkodási képességről tanúskodik, mely révén sikerült fenntartani tevékenységüket. Sajátos stratégiájuk a kollektív megoldás. A szövetkezeti modellre jellemző pozitív mechanizmusok összehangolása révén számos, a szövetkezeti ágazat keretén belül szervezett tevékenység versenyképességét növelhetné egy egységes uniós szintű szabályozási keretrendszer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213-000" speaker_id="96976" name="Luís Paulo Alves" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Felicito a colega Toia por colocar na agenda europeia a extraordinária capacidade de desempenho que o setor cooperativo demonstra nestes tempos de crise que atravessamos. Saliento, sobretudo, a sua adequação e potencial para gerar respostas sustentáveis, que muito precisamos, nos domínios económicos sociais e ambientais, tão duramente atingidos. A maior resistência demonstrada pelas empresas cooperativas, inclusivamente pelas financeiras, resulta do seu modelo de empresas de pessoas que colocam em primeiro lugar os interesses de todos os seus membros, fazendo da sua participação e da sua segurança a médio e longo prazo princípios inalienáveis. Modelo claramente oposto as que se concentram na busca de lucros elevados de curto prazo para servir os interesses de uns poucos e que nos conduziram a esta crise. Apelo, por isso, a um impulso prático e ambicioso para que o modelo cooperativo sirva os que procuram emprego e todos os que tentam garantir a continuidade das suas empresas para que encontrem nele uma valiosa forma de se organizarem e financiarem a sua atividade.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-214-000" speaker_id="97016" name="Angelika Werthmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, there are more than 150[nbsp ]000 cooperative enterprises in the European Union owned by more than 120[nbsp ]million members. They provide jobs for over five million people. Our rapporteur is trying to support the development of such cooperatives.</p>
      <p sl="en">If I look at it in detail, I have to say that this report asks for too much, namely for too much regulation, although it has to be noted very positively that there are cooperatives which are active in the field of renewable energy. They should be strongly supported, especially in view of the 2020 priorities defined in the Renewable Energy Sources Directive of 2009.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-215-000" speaker_id="96682" name="Sari Essayah" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, osuuskuntatoiminnalla on hyvin erilaiset historialliset juuret eri EU:n jäsenvaltioissa. Samoin niiden lainsäädännöllinen kehys ja myöskin verotuskohtelu vaihtelevat maasta toiseen. Siksi tämä mietintö melko yleisluontoisella tavalla kuvailee osuuskuntien mahdollisuuksia eri maissa, erityisesti talouskriisin olosuhteissa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se, että osuuskuntamalli poikkeaa voitonjaossa muun muassa osakeyhtiöistä, on luonut kriisin aikana vakautta ja kestävyyttä, niin kuin täällä moni kollega on todennut. Se on vastapainoa osakeyhtiöitten kvartaalitaloudelle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erityisesti haluaisin nostaa esille työllisyys- ja yritysosuuskunnat, joissa työttömiksi jääneet henkilöt ovat voineet kehittää omaa toimintaansa vähitellen vastaamaan osallistuvien yrittäjien tarpeita ja myöskin kehittää omaa liiketoimintamallia sitä mukaan, kun muun muassa asiakaskunta on kasvanut. Esittelijä aivan oikein kehottaa jäsenvaltioita laatimaan sellaista sääntelykehystä, jolla helpotetaan yrityksen luovuttamista työntekijöille, esimerkiksi konkurssin uhatessa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-216-000" speaker_id="96986" name="Josefa Andrés Barea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, agradezco a la señora Patrizia Toia este informe sobre la resistencia de las cooperativas ante la crisis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las cooperativas son un éxito y se debe a su modelo de gobernanza por la gestión democrática y la participación directa, por la participación en los beneficios, por la educación, la formación y la información como base de la gestión; porque se arraiga en las comunidades haciendo cohesión social y cohesión territorial; por un enfoque de gestión a largo plazo que da una economía territorial más sostenible. Además, son innovadoras, porque crean nuevos sectores: servicios sociales, sanitarios, digitales, interés general.</p>
      <p sl="en">El marco financiero plurianual debería apoyar a las cooperativas y posibilitar el acceso al crédito, no recortar, no asfixiar. Esta Comisión, el Consejo y los Estados miembros deben trabajar para un crecimiento sostenible y social. Este informe va por ese camino.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-217-000" speaker_id="111823" name="Νίκος Χρυσόγελος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι νέοι συνεταιρισμοί, θα λέγαμε οι συνεταιρισμοί που ανταποκρίνονται στις εφτά βασικές αρχές, παίζουν ένα πολύ σημαντικό ρόλο και για την οικονομία και για την κοινωνική συνοχή αλλά και για την κοινωνική και περιβαλλοντική υπευθυνότητα. Οι χώρες που βρίσκονται σε κρίση είναι αυτές που χρειάζονται περισσότερο σήμερα τη στήριξη των συνεταιρισμών, ώστε να μπορέσουν να δημιουργήσουν νέες και βιώσιμες οικονομικές δραστηριότητες αλλά και να απορροφήσουν τα εκατομμύρια ανέργους που υπάρχουν σε χώρες όπως είναι η Ελλάδα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Από την άλλη μεριά όμως βλέπουμε ότι έχουμε τεράστιες δυσκολίες, αφενός γιατί το θεσμικό πλαίσιο αλλάζει συνέχεια. Στη χώρα μου για παράδειγμα, στην Ελλάδα, δημιουργήθηκε ένα θεσμικό πλαίσιο, το οποίο άλλαξε πολύ γρήγορα, πριν καν εφαρμοστεί. Διαλύθηκε η υπηρεσία η οποία ήταν υπεύθυνη να προωθήσει τις διευκολύνσεις για να αναπτυχθούν οι κοινωνικές συνεταιριστικές επιχειρήσεις. Βλέπουμε ότι οι συνεταιριστικές τράπεζες δεν εντάσσονται στην ανακεφαλαιοποίηση και δημιουργούνται πολύ μεγάλες δυσκολίες για την επιβίωσή τους και, ενώ η Τρόικα θα έπρεπε να έχει από την πρώτη στιγμή συναντηθεί μαζί τους, μόλις πρόσφατα δέχτηκε να συναντηθεί με εκπροσώπους των ελληνικών συνεταιριστικών τραπεζών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-218-000" speaker_id="111589" name="Inês Cristina Zuber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, o cooperativismo é uma forma de organização económica com especificidades, valores e princípios que se opõem à lógica do mercado privado. A socialização dos lucros em prol da empresa cooperativa, os princípios da igualdade entre os membros que a integram, a forte ligação económica e social ao meio em que se integram, o respeito pelas relações laborais são valores que, no quadro do acentuar das políticas neoliberais, urge defender e apoiar. Por isso, estamos em geral a favor deste relatório.</p>
      <p sl="en">No entanto, há todo um enquadramento no relatório com o qual discordamos: a inclusão do cooperativismo no mercado único, que se baseia nas lógicas da competitividade e da colonização das economias mais fragilizadas pelos mais fortes, vai diametralmente contra os princípios que regem o cooperativismo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por outro lado, seria importante que se tivesse clarificado que, aquando de um processo de transformação de uma empresa em solvência numa cooperativa, não fossem os trabalhadores a herdar as dívidas que não foram criadas por eles, mas sim pelos gestores privados. O estímulo às cooperativas deve fazer parte da estratégia do crescimento das economias, mas não pode servir para transferir as dívidas e todos os problemas dos empresários para os trabalhadores.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-219-000" speaker_id="118710" name="Franco Bonanini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, verrei congratularmi con l'onorevole Toia, non per solidarietà fra italiani, ma perché ha svolto una relazione veramente completa e molto precisa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il modello cooperativo è un modello che, in questa difficile fase che stiamo vivendo, rimette al centro l'economia reale dopo anni di finalizzazione delle attività economiche, stimolando la diffusione di una microeconomia che rappresenta un'importante forma di economia sociale. Le cooperative sono spesso anche intimamente legate allo sviluppo e alle produzioni locali e gestiscono spesso servizi essenziali per i cittadini, svolgendo una funzione importante nel segno di uno sviluppo sostenibile e inclusivo improntato alla valorizzazione delle produzioni locali, delle culture di appartenenza e dei presidi umani in tempo di globalizzazione a volte sfrenata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io posso solo dare un consiglio, ossia occorre individuare un quadro normativo in grado di contrastare e individuare quei tentativi strumentali che intendono inserirsi nel mondo cooperativo senza rappresentarlo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-221-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Maria Damanaki" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission would like to thank Ms Toia for her excellent report which gives us the opportunity to explain briefly our policy on the promotion of cooperatives.</p>
      <p sl="en">The key goal of the Commission’s policy is to create a stable legal and administrative environment at European level but also in every Member State. I agree with the rapporteur and most of the speakers who underlined that cooperative and other social economy enterprises create jobs for millions of our people, including vulnerable citizens facing the crisis. I also agree with the fact that these cooperative businesses are more resilient to the crisis itself.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is therefore paying particular attention to ensuring that these particular principles, specific needs, goals, efforts and the working style of cooperatives are taken into account and respected. This is done in all areas of Union policy, such as in state aid, accounting, company law, competition, social services of general interest and others.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why we very much welcome the comments in the report and the calls for action. The policy in favour of cooperatives has always been high on the Commission’s agenda. At present there are a number of ongoing initiatives and activities to which I believe it is worthwhile to draw your attention.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vice-President Tajani is currently organising a working group on cooperatives which will hold its first meeting in his presence on 10 July. This meeting will be followed by two more meetings during the year. At the end of this action the Commission expects to have a number of innovative solutions to the most urgent problems faced by cooperatives, which can be supported by concrete European actions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The aim of the working group is to assess the specific needs of these organisations in relation to all the issues found in Ms Toia’s report. Examples of these needs are a stable regulatory framework, financial and business support, promotion of the cooperative model among young people, internationalisation and business transfers, especially of enterprises in difficulty. All these issues are mentioned in the report we are discussing today and the Commission is aware of them.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding in particular business transfers and restructuring, which constitute a whole chapter in Ms Toia’s report, in February 2013 the Commission convened the first session of the transfers of business expert group. The group met for the second time last week and its work will proceed at a meeting which will soon take place.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Confederation of Worker Cooperatives participates in this expert group. It is also invited to give input to a parallel study which will gather data about the various facets of a business transfer. A final conference is planned for early 2014; it will showcase the good practices identified by the expert group in the study. We hope that we will then have a concrete programme corresponding to the report’s conclusions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-222-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Dienstag, 2.[nbsp ]Juli 2013, um 12.00[nbsp ]Uhr statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 149 GO)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-222-500" speaker_id="95281" name="Vasilica Viorica Dăncilă" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – În ultimii ani, s-a observat că, în ciuda crizei cu care se confruntă economia europeană, au existat şi există o serie de entităţi care au rezistat la recesiune, respectiv cooperativele. Permiţând micilor antreprenori, deseori grupuri de cetățeni, să își asume responsabilități antreprenoriale, inclusiv în domenii precum serviciile sociale și de sănătate, serviciile școlare, serviciile comerciale, comunicațiile, cooperativele au reuşit să promoveze în mod eficace antreprenoriatul la scară microeconomică, mai ales în zone îndepărtate sau dezavantajate. Cooperativele reprezintă astfel un model de dezvoltare capabil să răspundă unor nevoi noi. Ele stimulează crearea de locuri de muncă mai bine decât alte modele datorită capacității lor de a se adapta la schimbare şi de a-și păstra activitatea, în caz de risc, sunt ancorate în economia locală, aducându-și aportul la dezvoltarea locală durabilă și garantează faptul că activitatea lor nu este delocalizată, chiar și atunci când operează la nivel internațional. În plus, au fost create cooperative în sectoare noi și inovatoare și există dovezi că asemenea structuri au reuşit să reziste la criză, în special în ceea ce privește băncile cooperatiste și cooperativele din industrie și din sectorul serviciilor (cooperativele de lucrători, cooperativele sociale și cooperativele formate de IMM-uri).</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. A bioeconomy for Europe (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-225-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Paolo Bartolozzi im Namen des Ausschusses für Umweltfragen, öffentliche Gesundheit und Lebensmittelsicherheit über Innovation für nachhaltiges Wachstum: eine Bioökonomie für Europa (COM(2012)0060[nbsp ]–[nbsp ]2012/2295(INI)) (A7-0201/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-226-000" speaker_id="21818" name="Paolo Bartolozzi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore. - Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, nel febbraio[nbsp ]2012 la Commissione europea ha presentato la sua comunicazione su una bioeconomia per l'Europa, dove proponeva di avanzare verso un uso maggiore e più sostenibile delle risorse rinnovabili e auspicava il passaggio da una società basata sulle risorse fossili ad una società basata sulle risorse biologiche, con il sostegno di ricerca e innovazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">A poco più di un anno di distanza dall'adozione di tale comunicazione, il Parlamento ha elaborato la propria relazione di iniziativa, accogliendo molte di quelle istanze per poi potenziarle e approfondirle. In questo senso il testo che ci apprestiamo a votare domani in questa sessione – riflesso dell'approvazione unanime della commissione ENVI – rivolge un chiaro messaggio alla Commissione in vista della presentazione da parte della stessa di una prossima proposta legislativa in tema di bioeconomia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono convinto infatti che la bioeconomia abbia in sé un grandissimo potenziale. Considerando tutte le grandi sfide che l'Unione europea si troverà a dover affrontare, la bioeconomia può essere, da un lato, la risposta alle dipendenze dai combustibili fossili e la strada da intraprendere verso una crescita intelligente; dall'altro, in un'ottica di più lungo periodo, anche la risposta alla sicurezza alimentare, alla riduzione dell'impatto ambientale, al riciclaggio di rifiuti, all'uso sostenibile ed efficiente delle risorse e all'incremento dell'occupazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">In quest'ottica, la bioeconomia potrebbe inoltre offrire un contributo importante contro il processo di deindustrializzazione che oggi affligge l'Europa, invertirne il corso e rilanciare un nuovo modello europeo di industrializzazione, tramite il quale favorire la creazione di nuove catene di valori e arginare i fenomeni di abbandono dei siti industriali nonché sostenere lo sviluppo economico e sociale con un ritorno, in termini occupazionali, estremamente alto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per permettere il pieno dispiegamento di questo potenziale, è necessario sviluppare un approccio onnicomprensivo e guardare al modello della bioeconomia come alla sintesi nella quale si realizzi l'incontro sinergico tra le politiche europee per l'agricoltura, l'industria e l'ambiente, la ricerca e l'innovazione e tra i diversi livelli decisionali – da quello comunitario a quello regionale e locale – in modo tale da realizzare un contesto armonico e coordinato nel quale sia possibile un continuo scambio di conoscenze, competenze, informazioni e know-how.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allo stesso tempo, sarà importante garantire e sviluppare programmi di ricerca e innovazione interconnessi e coerenti, prevedere strumenti di sostegno agli investimenti industriali e assicurare che i risultati raggiunti abbiamo il massimo impatto sulla società e siano perfettamente compresi dai cittadini europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">In questo contesto, anche le nuove forme di partenariato in grado di coinvolgere in contributo congiunto gli enti pubblici e privati possono concorrere fortemente alla ripresa economica e allo sviluppo sostenibile soprattutto nell'attuale contesto di crisi. Far leva sugli investimenti privati attraverso la creazione di un partenariato pubblico-privato dedicato alle bioindustrie permetterebbe infatti di sostenere e favorire lo sviluppo di nuovi prodotti e realizzarne il fondamentale ed effettivo trasferimento sul mercato, limitando il rischio che condizioni più favorevoli incentivino la migrazione di eccellenze e di progetti innovativi fuori dall'Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il modello della bioeconomia sviluppato all'interno di tale strategia – ne sono certo – non solo permetterà di risolvere le cronicità contingenti, ma sul più lungo periodo potrà porre in essere modelli di produzione, consumo, sviluppo e stili di vita più sostenibili ed efficienti riattivando il processo di crescita europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-228-000" speaker_id="97016" name="Angelika Werthmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Europa sieht sich in Zukunft vor konstanten und zahlreichen Herausforderungen, denn unsere Weltbevölkerung wächst ja schließlich ständig. Wir sehen einem Anstieg der Lebensmittel- und Energienachfrage entgegen. Es gilt jedoch auch, die weltweite Knappheit an natürlichen Ressourcen zu reflektieren. Für uns in Europa bedeutet dies, nachhaltige Optionen zu finden. Eine dieser Möglichkeiten ist definitiv die Bioökonomie. Sie fördert Nachhaltigkeit und stellt ländliche Entwicklungen, die Treibhausgase reduzieren, sicher. Ich teile die Ansicht des Berichterstatters, dass in diesem Bereich noch wesentlich mehr getan werden muss, um weitere Fortschritte erzielen zu können. Vor allem möchte ich hervorheben, dass Europa auch einen Platz in der Spitzenforschung und in der Innovation hat und alles getan werden muss, um eine eventuelle Abwanderung zu verhindern und vor allem zu vermindern.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-229-000" speaker_id="96682" name="Sari Essayah" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, esittelijä tuo hyvin selkeästi esille sen, että biotalousala tarvitsee selkeän strategian ja vakaat sääntelypuitteet. Tällä hetkellä tuntuu siltä, että komissiossa tehdään maatalous-, teollisuus-, energia- ja ympäristöpolitiikkaa lähestulkoon täysin toisistaan tietämättä. Myöskin eri jäsenvaltioiden tukitoimenpiteet, muun muassa bioenergian tuottamiseksi ja teollisuuden tukemiseksi uusiutuvan energian alalla, ovat myös melkoinen tilkkutäkki. Kuitenkin biotalous voisi olla EU:lle tulevaisuudessa kannattava investointi, niin ruokaturvan kuin myöskin energiateollisuuden alalla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erityisesti haluaisin vielä nostaa esille tämän huolen, mikä tässä kehitysyhteistyövaliokunnan lausunnossa tuodaan esille, eli sen, että biotalous ei tulevaisuudessa saa heikentää kehitysmaiden elintarviketurvaa, eikä myöskään sitä, että viljelymaata aletaan käyttää muuhun kuin ravinnon tuotantoon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-230-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, num quadro de inexorável e progressiva escassez de recursos e de crescente acumulação nociva no ambiente dos subprodutos resultantes do seu consumo, a eficiência do uso de recursos e a valorização e tratamento de resíduos são indiscutivelmente domínios prioritários para a intensificação dos esforços de investigação e desenvolvimento. Mais do que um meio para a mera valorização de ideias inovadoras suscetíveis de serem transformadas em produtos e serviços a lançar no mercado, o esforço de investimento nestes domínios constitui um meio necessário para responder a problemas e desafios com que a humanidade hoje se confronta. A inovação deve constituir um elemento-chave das políticas públicas em áreas como o ambiente, a água, a energia, a agricultura, os transportes e outras, mas não podemos esquecer que, em muitos países, e muito especialmente nos países alvo de intervenção da União Europeia e do FMI, a limitação, e mesmo a destruição, da capacidade técnica e científica que decorre das políticas ditas de austeridade comprometem irremediavelmente os investimentos neste e noutros domínios.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-231-000" speaker_id="118710" name="Franco Bonanini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, apprezzo la relazione dell'on. Bartolozzi perché, in un momento di crisi come quello che stiamo attraversando, investire con decisione nella direzione della bioeconomia acquista una valenza ulteriore.</p>
      <p sl="en">È necessario dunque che l'Unione europea investa anche finanziariamente, ad esempio attraverso il nuovo programma Orizzonte[nbsp ]2020, per fornire gli strumenti adeguati in vista di una progressiva trasformazione dell'economia nel segno dell'innovazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vorrei in particolare sottolineare il forte accento posto dalla relazione sull'importanza della dimensione regionale e locale della bioeconomia, quale strumento per assicurare uno sviluppo sostenibile, rispettoso e inclusivo delle realtà locali e quale mezzo per assicurare in particolar modo la qualità e la sicurezza della catena alimentare, con particolare riferimento alla valorizzazione. Mi permetto di suggerire al relatore che a pagina[nbsp ]6 aggiungerei oltre alla promozione anche la tutela legislativa delle produzioni locali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-233-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Máire Geoghegan-Quinn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wish to thank the rapporteur, Mr Bartolozzi, for his comprehensive proposal and for Parliament’s strong support for the bioeconomy strategy and action plan. We fully endorse the view that a modern, well-functioning bioeconomy is a prerequisite for achieving the objectives of the Europe 2020 Strategy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Like Parliament, the Commission sees in the bioeconomy a convergence of opportunities and objectives: a smart use of our biological resources from land and seas; a low-carbon, resource-efficient economy; a reindustrialisation of Europe based on innovation and the latest scientific knowledge; food security for all; and the development of new jobs and new sources of economic growth, not least in rural and maritime regions. All these aspects are especially relevant in the context of the economic difficulties currently facing Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Since the adoption of the bioeconomy strategy and action plan in early 2012, considerable progress has been made. The bioeconomy is still developing, so one of our important objectives has been to establish a Bioeconomy Observatory, to provide policy-makers, primary producers, industry and other stakeholders with authoritative, up-to-date information about relevant research, policy, and market developments.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is the first time in the world that an observatory of this kind has been set up. It will require the positive engagement of many different organisations to make this initiative a success. The Commission’s Joint Research Centre is already working hard to get the observatory up and running and producing results.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have also committed to establish a Bioeconomy Panel, to facilitate discussion, joint actions and exchange of experience between different stakeholder groups: researchers, producers, industry, civil society, and public administrations at regional, national and EU level.</p>
      <p sl="en">The 30 members of the panel have been selected, and the first meeting is scheduled to take place in September. I am pleased to confirm our invitation to Parliament to nominate an observer to this Bioeconomy Panel. This will help to further consolidate the alignment between our two institutions on issues related to the bioeconomy.</p>
      <p sl="en">In February this year we organised, together with the Irish Presidency, the second annual European stakeholders’ conference on the bioeconomy, bringing together over 500 people representing a wide variety of different interests related to the bioeconomy.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are grateful to MEPs Paolo Bartolozzi and Mairead McGuinness for the valuable contributions that they made to this event. Many of the conclusions of the conference are echoed in the report that you are debating today, such as the need for a coherent, coordinated policy; the need for investments in skills and training; and, the need for transparent and inclusive dialogue to ensure that the bioeconomy is built on broad-based public support. We look forward to working with the Italian Presidency of the EU in organising the next conference in the second half of 2014.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you all know, just last week the European Parliament and Council, together with the Commission, reached political agreement on Horizon 2020 – the next funding programme for research, innovation and science. Let me assure you that within Horizon 2020 there will be a substantial budget for bioeconomy-related research and innovation.</p>
      <p sl="en">This will include a significant proportion of funding for a new Public- Private Partnership (PPP) on bio-based industries. The Commission very much appreciates the clear support that the Parliament report gives to this PPP and to the bioeconomy research budget as a whole. This PPP in particular will help to finance pilot and demonstration activities of the kind that the draft resolution calls for.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I would like to underline that the Commission is very pleased that the draft resolution repeats the call to EU Member States to develop their own national and regional bioeconomy strategies. I could not agree more. While there is much we can and will do at an EU level, the bioeconomy will only realise its full potential if actors at national and regional level understand the opportunities that this presents for them and put in place the appropriate policies, funding, and governance mechanisms.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-234-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Dienstag, 2.[nbsp ]Juli 2013, um 12.00[nbsp ]Uhr statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 149 GO)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-235-000" speaker_id="96753" name="Jolanta Emilia Hibner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Stale rosnąca liczba ludności na świecie, gwałtowny wzrost zapotrzebowania na żywność i energię oraz niewielka ilość światowych zasobów naturalnych sprawiają, że należy szukać nowych rozwiązań systemowych. Jednym z nich jest z pewnością biogospodarka, która promując ideę zrównoważenia, może przyczynić się do rozwoju obszarów wiejskich, zapewnić trwały i inteligentny wzrost gospodarczy oraz bezpieczeństwo żywnościowe i podwyższenie poziomu zatrudnienia. Inne przewidywane korzyści to wprowadzenie dzięki innowacjom przemysłowym cykli produkcyjnych, bardziej przyjaznych środowisku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na uznanie zasługuje fakt, że dzięki biogospodarce promowane będą badania, innowacje i umiejętności oraz poprawi się synergia polityczna oraz rozwój rynków i konkurencyjność. Aby osiągnąć spodziewane efekty, należy postawić na harmonizację polityki rolnej, przemysłowej i środowiskowej w powiązaniu z badaniami i innowacyjnością. Niezbędne jest również promowanie partnerstwa publiczno-prywatnego funkcjonującego w dziedzinie przemysłu i opartego na biotechnologii, które mogłoby stanowić wsparcie dla realizacji nowych projektów, umożliwić opracowanie innowacyjnych produktów oraz przyczynić się do ich rzeczywistego wprowadzenia na rynek. Biogospodarka pojmowana w sposób efektywny to niezwykle skuteczne narzędzie kreowania zrównoważonego wzrostu i zwiększenia aktywności społecznych przy jednoczesnym zmniejszonym oddziaływaniu na środowisko naturalne.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Member States' export credit agencies (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-237-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Yannick Jadot im Namen des Ausschusses für internationalen Handel über den ersten Jahresbericht der Kommission an das Europäische Parlament über die Tätigkeiten der Exportkreditagenturen der Mitgliedstaaten (2012/2320(INI)) (A7-0193/2013).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-238-000" speaker_id="96734" name="Franziska Keller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="deputising for the rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on behalf of the rapporteur, Yannick Jadot, who unfortunately cannot be present here, I would like to convey his thoughts to you:</p>
      <p sl="en">It is to my great pleasure that this House will vote tomorrow on the report on the first annual report from the Commission on the export credit activities of Member States. This own-initiative report finishes, at least for this legislature, work which started more than three years ago, and I am deeply grateful and indebted to all shadow rapporteurs for their very constructive cooperation in this long-lasting endeavour.</p>
      <p sl="en">More than three years ago, an innocent dossier came to us in the Committee on International Trade (INTA): the transposition of the latest OECD arrangements on export credit activities into EU law. It was one of those ‘thumbs-up’ dossiers, but it came to us under the ordinary legislative procedure shortly after the entry into force of the Lisbon Treaty. It was the time at which Parliament was testing its new powers and becoming aware of its responsibilities, not only towards European citizens but also towards filling the spirit and the letter of the new Treaty with concrete life. It was also the time at which the financial and economic crisis was unfolding in Europe, and along with this came much higher tension over public spending.</p>
      <p sl="en">As the rapporteur for Parliament, I asked myself what we as Parliamentarians knew about the activities of the ECAs of the Member States, which to a large extent operate with public funds. It is not that I was in doubt about the usefulness of ECAs for European companies; I only noticed that we knew very little. Moreover, I detected no inherent relation between the work of the ECAs of the Member States and the new requirement of the Lisbon Treaty that all external activities of the Union and its Member States shall be conducted in the spirit of the Union’s external action goals as enshrined in Article 3 and Article 21 TEU.</p>
      <p sl="en">To my surprise, my thoughts were widely shared by all my colleagues in the International Trade Committee. While we might have deeply-rooted controversies about trade policy matters, we found – and still find ourselves – united under the roof of the Lisbon Treaty and its prerogatives. Hence, I found almost full support across the entire political spectrum to ask the Commission to provide Parliament with an annual report about the ECAs of the Member States, and on its own activities, so as to get the emerging economies to adhere to the OECD arrangements for ECAs.</p>
      <p sl="en">This new reporting requirement entails, in particular, an evaluation by the Commission as to whether or not Member States in their ECA policies are applying the principle of fostering the Union’s external action goals with regard, among other things, to the promotion of democracy and human rights and the achievement of the Millennium Development Goals.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission showed itself very helpful in conveying our message to the Council. My thanks go therefore also to the Commission, and in particular to Mr Denis Redonnet. The report that will be voted tomorrow evaluates the Commission’s first annual report on the reports of the Member States on ECA activities for the year 2011. We have to acknowledge that we are at the very beginning of this exercise. Member States find it difficult to frame a report on such non-financial issues as to how they ensure their spending is used to foster human rights and democracy, or on how ECAs screen environmental risks into the setting of their premiums. Therefore, in the report, we make suggestions as to how such reporting could be done in future, and how the Commission should be enabled to evaluate such reporting.</p>
      <p sl="en">The next set of reports by the Member States will for sure be better, and I want to thank again all of my colleagues who in this legislature have laid the ground for making sure that, one day, Europe will be a more consistent global actor for democracy and human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-240-000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Num contexto político e económico de aprofundamento da globalização capitalista, de crescente interdependência assimétrica das economias, de desmantelamento dos instrumentos de regulação e controlo da produção e do comércio, os créditos às exportações podem constituir-se como mais um fator de aprofundamento das desigualdades, sejam as desigualdades norte-sul, sejam as desigualdades no seio de blocos económicos heterogéneos, como a União Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">É evidente a contradição de práticas como esta e os bondosos objetivos insistentemente proclamados em áreas como a cooperação para o desenvolvimento, apenas para dar um exemplo. Os defensores do sacrossanto princípio da livre concorrência capitalista não prescindem destas mãozinhas bem visíveis que sempre deitam por terra o mito da mão invisível, introduzindo fatores de distorção da dita concorrência, introduzindo inequívocos fatores de disrupção dos sistemas produtivos mais débeis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-242-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Máire Geoghegan-Quinn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, on behalf of Commissioner De Gucht I wish to thank you, and in particular the rapporteur, Mr Yannick Jadot, represented by Ms Keller, for this report and the highly interesting views on export credits which are reflected in it.</p>
      <p sl="en">The global financial crisis has demonstrated in an impressive manner how essential the availability of adequate financing is for global trade flows. Export Credit Agencies play a vital role in this process. They are therefore instruments of strategic importance in our wider efforts to support the interests of European exporters.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is, however, also vital to ensure that there is appropriate transparency at European level on how Export Credit Agencies operate and what they achieve. This has been one of the objectives of Regulation (EU) No 1233/2011 and in particular of the reporting mechanisms which it has established. Looking at the outcome of the first reporting exercise under this regulation, let me make the following observations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Commission shares the view expressed in the present report that Member States in their annual activity reports have made available the financial and operational information on export credits requested in Regulation 1233/2011. The European Commission confirms its commitment to conduct external policies in accordance with Article 21 of the Treaty on European Union. We take particular note of the observations on the policies applied to export credit transactions contained in the present report. We will further analyse them and see how – in due consideration of the wording of the regulation and in agreement with all parties involved – appropriate follow-up can be given to them.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission would also like to take this opportunity to thank you for the support expressed in the present report for our ongoing efforts to engage the major emerging economies in the establishment of the new International Working Group on Export Credits. Countries like China, India and Brazil have become major new players in export credits in recent years. Engaging them in a constructive dialogue will be an important challenge. Commission De Gucht will duly keep Parliament informed on further developments in this field.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-243-000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Dienstag, 2.[nbsp ]Juli 2013, um 12.00[nbsp ]Uhr statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem25" title="25. Agenda for next sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="26. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
