<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20140915.EN" lang="en" date="2014-09-15" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die am Donnerstag, dem 17. Juli 2014, unterbrochene Sitzungsperiode für wieder aufgenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Announcements by the President">
    <intervention id="1-006-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich habe die traurige Ankündigung zu machen, dass unser ehemaliges Mitglied Ian Paisley am vergangenen Freitag im Alter von 88 Jahren gestorben ist. Er war seit 1979 25 Jahre lang Abgeordneter dieses Parlaments und am Ende seiner Karriere Erster Minister in Nordirland.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meine Damen und Herren! Ich möchte Sie davon unterrichten, dass mich mehrere Kolleginnen und Kollegen darauf aufmerksam, gemacht haben: In diesen Minuten erhalten wir erneut dramatische Berichte von Flüchtlingsunglücken im Mittelmeer. Vor der libyschen Küste sollen 250 Flüchtlinge bei einem Bootsunglück ums Leben gekommen sein. 36 können möglicherweise gerettet werden, aber es gibt wahrscheinlich 250 Tote. Vor Malta ereignete sich eine Tragödie, bei der möglicherweise 500 Menschen ums Leben gekommen sind.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich teile das mit, weil wir in der moralischen Pflicht stehen, alles zu tun, um zu verhindern, dass es zu solchen humanitären Katastrophen kommt, die wir uns sicher nicht erlauben dürfen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meine Damen und Herren! Ich habe Ihnen in der vergangenen Woche mitgeteilt und möchte das jetzt wiederholen, dass am Mittwoch kurz vor der Abstimmung hier eine sogenannte 360-Grad-Aufnahme stattfindet. Dabei werden vor allen Dingen für die Bilder in unserem Parlamentarium alle Mitglieder hier im Saal einmal durch eine Rundum-Kamera aufgenommen. Sie kennen das. Es wird einmal eine 360-Grad-Aufnahme gemacht. Seien Sie bitte alle da, weil das für viele Leute, die die technischen modernen Einrichtungen nutzen, eine Möglichkeit ist, zu schauen, wo Sie als Abgeordnete oder als Abgeordneter hier im Plenum sitzen, wo Sie sich befinden. Unsere Besucher, die im Besucherzentrum des Parlaments sind, können dann auch alle ihre Abgeordneten einzeln ausfindig machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also: Mittwoch, 12.00 Uhr 360-Grad-Aufnahme!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Composition of Parliament : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Request for the waiver of parliamentary immunity : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Announcement by the President – Election of the European Ombudsman">
    <intervention id="1-012-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich bitte Sie nun um Aufmerksamkeit für einen wichtigen formalen Vorgang, meine Damen und Herren, den ich Ihnen aus Gründen der Rechtssicherheit in voller Länge vorlesen muss. Also, machen Sie es sich schon mal bequem, das dauert ein bisschen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wie ich Ihnen bereits am 5. September per E-Mail mitgeteilt habe, werden wir gemäß Artikel 219 der Geschäftsordnung eine neue Bürgerbeauftragte bzw. einen neuen Bürgerbeauftragten wählen. Ich möchte Ihnen jetzt den Ablauf des Wahlverfahrens erläutern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am 2. September 2014 wurde im Amtsblatt ein Aufruf zur Einreichung von Kandidaturen veröffentlicht. Die Kandidaturen sind bis spätestens 30. September einzureichen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gemäß Artikel 219 Absatz 2 der Geschäftsordnung müssen die Kandidatinnen oder Kandidaten eine Reihe von Bedingungen erfüllen. Ich will hier nur an die Bestimmungen erinnern, die Sie direkt betreffen: Jede Kandidatur muss von mindestens 40 Mitgliedern aus mindestens zwei Mitgliedstaaten unterstützt werden. Es ist nicht möglich, mehrere Kandidaturen gleichzeitig zu unterstützen. Sollte ein Mitglied mehrere Kandidaturen mit seiner Unterschrift unterstützen, so zählt seine Unterschrift für keine dieser Kandidaturen, was gegebenenfalls zur Folge haben könnte, dass eine solche Kandidatur nicht zulässig ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sobald mir eine Kandidatur übermittelt worden ist, ist es auch nicht mehr möglich, eine Unterschrift zur Unterstützung hinzuzufügen oder eine Unterschrift zurückzuziehen. Also wenn Sie sich einmal entschieden haben, haben Sie sich entschieden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gemäß Artikel 219 Absatz 3 der Geschäftsordnung werde ich die Kandidaturen, die alle festgelegten Kriterien erfüllen, dem Petitionsausschuss übermitteln. Dieser wird wahrscheinlich im Dezember Anhörungen der Kandidatinnen und Kandidaten organisieren. Diese Anhörungen des Petitionsausschusses stehen allen Mitgliedern offen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Wahl wird während der Plenartagung im Januar 2015 stattfinden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Dienste der Generaldirektion Präsidentschaft stehen Ihnen selbstverständlich für alle weiteren Fragen zur Verfügung.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Corrigenda (Rule 231): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Signature of acts adopted under the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 78): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Calendar of part-sessions : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Action taken following a request for waiver of immunity: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Texts of agreements forwarded by the Council: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Action taken on Parliament’s positions and resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-023-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Der endgültige Entwurf der Tagesordnung dieser Tagung, wie er in der Konferenz der Präsidenten in ihrer Sitzung vom Donnerstag, dem 11. September 2014 gemäß Artikel 149 der Geschäftsordnung festgelegt wurde, ist verteilt worden. Zu diesem Entwurf wurde folgende Änderung beantragt:</p>
      <p sl="en">Mittwoch:</p>
      <p sl="en">Die ALDE-Fraktion beantragt, für Mittwoch eine Aussprache über Erklärungen des Rates und der Kommission zu Demokratie, Rechtsstaatlichkeit und den Grundrechten in Ungarn als ersten Punkt auf die Tagesordnung von Mittwochnachmittag zu setzen. Zur Begründung hat Frau in't Veld das Wort.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-000" speaker_id="28266" name="Sophia in 't Veld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, Hungary is certainly not the only country where violations of the rule of law and fundamental rights take place, but we had debates earlier and are very concerned about recent statements by the Prime Minister and the raids on offices of NGOs. I know it has been proposed to debate this issue in the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, but I think it is much wider than that, and also concerns other committees. We feel it would be appropriate to have a debate here in plenary to show the citizens that we stand for the protection of democracy, the rule of law and fundamental rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, nous entendons tous les jours nos concitoyens critiquer l'Europe parce qu'elle n'est pas assez démocratique, parce que finalement elle ne s'applique pas à elle-même les valeurs qu'elle professe à l'extérieur. En effet, je pense que le cas qui a été soulevé par le groupe ALDE, que nous soutenons, est particulièrement emblématique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons parfois l'impression que nous avons en quelque sorte importé le fils ou le neveu de Vladimir Poutine à l'intérieur même de l'Union européenne. Je pense que c'est un sujet qui mérite d'être débattu, non seulement en commission LIBE, mais également en plénière.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026-000" speaker_id="125027" name="Esteban González Pons" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, el Grupo Popular no se opone al debate, solo decimos que debe hacerse donde corresponde reglamentariamente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ya se ha hablado en el Pleno sobre Hungría y se ha hecho muchísimas veces. Lo cierto es que no hay ningún hecho nuevo que justifique que el asunto vuelva a venir al Pleno solo porque estemos en vísperas de unas elecciones en ese país.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay un acuerdo en la Comisión LIBE, de todos los coordinadores de la Comisión LIBE, para que allí se debata esto, y un acuerdo de la Conferencia de Presidentes para que se debata en la Comisión LIBE. El Pleno no debería desposeer a las comisiones de sus competencias sin que exista una causa muy justificada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sí, hay que debatir, pero hay que debatir donde corresponde, no donde no toca.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-000" speaker_id="96768" name="Enrique Guerrero Salom" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, mi Grupo comparte la preocupación expresada por el Grupo Liberal y por Los Verdes sobre la situación en Hungría. De hecho, todavía es más grave la evolución de esa situación, porque en la pasada legislatura ya tuvimos que enfrentarnos con ella.</p>
      <p sl="en">No creo que sea verdad, como se acaba de señalar, que no haya acontecimientos nuevos. Los hay. Y preocupantes: ataques a organizaciones no gubernamentales y otro tipo de quiebras de los derechos democráticos. Por tanto, creo que este Parlamento tiene que debatir sobre esa cuestión, pero creo que no es el momento para llevarla al Pleno. Mi Grupo apoyará un debate en el Pleno inmediatamente después –y lo más pronto posible– de que se realice otro en la Comisión de Libertades Civiles, con participación de interlocutores sociales y de organizaciones no gubernamentales.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Impact on European agriculture of the trade ban on agricultural products and foodstuffs from the EU, imposed by the Russian Federation (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-030-000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung an die Kommission über Auswirkungen des Importverbots der Russischen Föderation für landwirtschaftliche Erzeugnisse und Lebensmittel aus der EU auf die europäische Landwirtschaft von Czesław Adam Siekierski im Namen des Ausschusses für Landwirtschaft und ländliche Entwicklung (O-000063/2014 - B8-0032/2014)-(2014/2835(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-000" speaker_id="23787" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. - Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Na początku sierpnia Federacja Rosyjska wprowadziła embargo na import produktów rolnych i żywnościowych z Unii w odwecie za nasze sankcje przeciwko Rosji będące skutkiem roli odegranej przez Rosję w kryzysie i działaniach wojennych na Ukrainie. Embargo importowe jest powodem znacznych strat po stronie naszych producentów. W niektórych sektorach, takich jak owoce, warzywa, oraz ser i masło, dotknięta została ok. 1/3 eksportu naszej Unii, a producenci, którzy nie byli i nie są w stanie sprzedać swoich produktów, poniosą straty, a niektórzy mogą nawet zbankrutować.</p>
      <p sl="en">Komisja Rolnictwa uważa za niezbędne, aby uzupełnić swoją debatę o pytanie ustne skierowane do Komisji Europejskiej z nadzieją na szerszą debatę z panem komisarzem na plenum. Panie Komisarzu! Nasza komisja pozytywnie odbiera działania podjęte przez Komisję Europejską po wprowadzeniu embarga. Uważamy jednak, że przeznaczone na ten cel środki finansowe są dalekie od wystarczających w obliczu skali i wpływu embarga na naszych producentów. Co więcej, jako że kryzys ten jest przede wszystkim natury politycznej i nie powstał w wyniku załamania rynku ani też niepomyślnych warunków pogodowych, konieczna jest solidarność ze strony innych sektorów. Komisja Rolnictwa Parlamentu jest przekonana, że ciężar pomocy finansowej wymaganej celem udzielenia pomocy poszkodowanym rolnikom nie powinien być ponoszony w całości z linii budżetowej przeznaczonej na rolnictwo oraz że udostępnione mogłyby zostać dodatkowe środki z innych linii budżetowych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szanowni Państwo! Doszło również do naszej wiadomości, że środki pomocowe dla sektora owoców i warzyw zostały w ubiegłym tygodniu zawieszone, gdyż zgromadzone wnioski o wsparcie przekroczyły dostępny limit. W krajach, gdzie rolnicy są niezrzeszeni, a produkty skupują od nich pośrednicy, rolnicy często zgłaszają całą powierzchnię upraw, bo nie wiedzą, jaka część produkcji idzie na eksport, w tym do Rosji, a jaka na spożycie krajowe. Większość rolników, szczególnie drobnych, w nowych państwach członkowskich nie przynależy jeszcze do grup producentów czy zrzeszeń branżowych, dlatego nie należy różnicować poziomu wsparcia pomiędzy rolnikami zrzeszonymi a niezrzeszonymi. Należy przemyśleć uruchomienie już kolejnego etapu zbierania powiadomień od rolników, co nie jest w sprzeczności z dokonanym zamknięciem i prowadzeniem kontroli i oceny wniosków, bo sytuacja w tym względzie jest dynamiczna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Panie Komisarzu! W imieniu komisji AGRI chcielibyśmy prosić Pana o przekazanie posłom do Parlamentu Europejskiego aktualnych informacji o działaniach już podjętych i planowanych przez Komisję Europejską. Czy zamierza Pan uzupełnić pierwszy zestaw działań? Wzmocnić je? Zwiększyć przypisane im środki finansowe oraz potencjalnie rozszerzyć ich zakres, aby obejmowały również dodatkowe sektory, np. sektor mięsny? W szczególności – czy zamierza Pan wprowadzić specjalne środki kompensacyjne dla tych gospodarstw, które mogą być zagrożone upadłością?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dacian Cioloş" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Membre de la Commission. - Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs, tout d'abord merci beaucoup de créer cette opportunité de tenir un débat sur un sujet qui est important, qui a l'attention de la Commission européenne, c'est-à-dire l'impact de cet embargo russe sur le secteur agricole, agroalimentaire européen et sur le marché européen.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'embargo décrété par la Russie début août touche notamment trois grands secteurs agricoles de l'Union: les fruits et légumes, le secteurs laitier et celui de la viande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour remettre les choses dans leur contexte, je souhaite souligner que la Russie est le deuxième marché d'exportation du secteur agroalimentaire européen et que les exportations vers la Russie représentent environ 10 % des exportations de l'Union européenne. Mais pour certains secteurs et notamment pour les secteurs cités, le marché russe représente environ un tiers de ce que l'Union européenne exporte, à savoir surtout pour les fruits et légumes et les produits laitiers et parfois même pour la viande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les exportations visées par l'embargo se chiffrent à 5 milliards d'euros et touchent les revenus de millions d'agriculteurs dans l'Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous sommes donc confrontés à une crise européenne à laquelle il convient de donner une réponse proportionnée mais cohérente et efficace.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les outils de la politique agricole commune réformée que nous venons d'adopter ensemble il y a quelques années, nous donnent les moyens de réagir de manière cohérente, solidaire et rapide. C'est pourquoi j'ai décidé d'agir vite, dès le mois d'août, dès que ces mesures ont été annoncées, notamment sur trois axes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout d'abord, notre objectif était d'éviter la déstabilisation du marché européen par des produits qui ne seraient plus exportés et qui risquaient de revenir sur le marché européen et donc d'entraîner des chutes de prix. Un deuxième objectif des mesures envisagées était de soutenir les filières européennes dans la recherche de nouveaux marchés. Même si nous sommes conscients que cela peut prendre du temps, il est important de donner aussi vite que possible un signal et un soutien aux producteurs afin qu'ils commencent à diversifier les marchés de l'exportation. Le troisième objectif de nos mesures était d'ouvrir le débat sur la question d'éventuelles compensations ciblées, comme le demande le secteur et comme le mentionne la question que vous avez soulevée, en tenant compte bien sûr des implications politiques et financières des compensations que nous pouvons envisager.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour ce qui est du premier paquet de mesure c'est-à-dire la stabilisation rapide du marché suite à cette décision de la Russie, la Commission a opté pour des réponses immédiates dans les deux secteurs qui étaient les plus touchés immédiatement par cette décision russe, c'est-à-dire le secteur des fruits et légumes et le secteur laitier. Pour ces deux secteurs, les exportations vers la Russie, comme je l'ai déjà dit, représentent environ un tiers du total des exportations européennes. Les fruits et légumes constituaient la première urgence, puisque nous avons là des produits périssables qui ne peuvent pas être stockés et pour lesquels il fallait proposer des solutions rapidement afin d'éviter que les prix chutent et donc que les revenus de tous les producteurs de fruits et légumes au niveau européen en soient affectés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Des mesures ont été mises en place dès le 11 août pour le secteur des pêches et des nectarines et, une semaine après, soit le 18 août, nous avons été en mesure de proposer un paquet plus large pour d'autres fruits et légumes particulièrement périssables dont la Russie était un acheteur clef. Ces mesures exceptionnelles bénéficiaient d'un budget de 125 millions d'euros, avec un plafond de 82 millions d'euros pour les pommes et les poires et un plafond de 43 millions d'euros pour un certain nombre d'autres fruits et légumes. Nous avons calculé ce montant sur la base notamment des quantités exportées vers la Russie que nous supposions devoir être retirées du marché d'une manière ou d'une autre, mais nous avons aussi prévu une marge supplémentaire au cas où il risquait d'y avoir des effets indirects. Nous avons donc proposé des mesures de retrait du marché en encourageant la distribution gratuite, mais aussi des mesures de récolte en vert ou de non-récolte de certaines productions qui ne pouvaient pas être vendues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Étant donné que les notifications des États membres couvrant la période du 18 août jusqu'au 3 septembre pour les opérations envisagées ont dépassé ces plafonds, la Commission a dû décider, conformément à l'acte délégué, de suspendre cette mesure.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je peux vous assurer, comme je l'ai déjà annoncé publiquement, que nous n'envisageons pas de nous arrêter là, nous sommes conscients qu'il y aura d'autres produits que nous devrons viser dans le secteur fruits et légumes. La Commission est en train de préparer une nouvelle mesure pour ce secteur, que, je l'espère, nous serons en mesure d'annoncer dès cette semaine. Mes services travaillent maintenant avec d'autres services de la Commission pour présenter cette proposition qui sera, je peux vous l'assurer, également substantielle compte tenu des réalités du marché. Cela sera sans doute une mesure plus ciblée afin d'éviter justement qu'il y ait des notifications qui ne soient pas justifiables.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour le secteur laitier, dès l'apparition des premiers signes révélateurs d'un impact sur ce secteur, j'ai décidé d'activer le filet de sécurité prévu dans le règlement sur la gestion des marchés en complétant par des mesures exceptionnelles. Ainsi, une aide est désormais disponible pour le stockage privé de produits laitiers qui peuvent être stockés: il s'agit du beurre, du lait en poudre dégraissé, mais aussi de certains fromages. En parallèle avec ce stockage privé qui a été déclenché nous avons également décidé de prolonger l'intervention publique jusqu'à la fin de l'année pour le lait en poudre et pour le beurre, laquelle devait normalement s'arrêter le 30 septembre, pour le cas où il faudrait retirer des produits du marché.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans le secteur de la viande, la situation est plus nuancée puisque la Russie avait déjà placé la viande porcine européenne sous embargo depuis le début de l'année, du fait de la peste porcine dans certaines régions de l'Union européenne. Les opérateurs ont trouvé en partie de nouveaux débouchés en Asie, parallèlement à une production intérieure qui a été limitée de ce fait.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans le secteur de la viande bovine, la production et la consommation se trouvent depuis un certain temps en baisse structurelle, ce qui peut entraîner une certaine fragilité de ce secteur et de l'équilibre du marché, malgré une demande mondiale croissante. La fermeture du marché russe requiert une intensification des efforts en cours pour ouvrir d'autres marchés qui demeurent fermés en raison de barrières sanitaires injustifiées et qui pourraient aussi apporter une réponse pour ce secteur à moyen terme. Pour ce secteur de la viande, j'ai demandé à mes services d'assurer un suivi rapproché. Si la situation sur le marché des prix ou des marges des producteurs montre des signes de déstabilisation, nous sommes aussi prêts à réagir puisque nous disposons des instruments nécessaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je souhaite d'ailleurs vous dire que la Commission examine en permanence, secteur par secteur, l'évolution des marchés et l'impact des mesures qui ont été prises. J'ai décidé de constituer une Task Force au sein de la DG AGRI dès début août pour suivre ce marché. Depuis le mois d'août, nous organisons des réunions hebdomadaires avec les experts des États membres afin de suivre l'évolution des marchés et de prendre des décisions sur cette base aussi rapidement que possible. Cette réaction rapide de la Commission a été possible notamment grâce aux pouvoirs délégués que le législateur – le Parlement et le Conseil – a accordés à la Commission dans le cadre de la réforme de la PAC. Rappelez-vous, nous avions discuté, avec certains d'entre vous, de la nécessité d'une réaction rapide de la Commission en situation de crise. Le fait que nous ayons pu réagir rapidement prouve que ce que nous avons décidé dans la réforme de la PAC sur la partie "gestion de marché" semble fonctionner puisque en prenant des mesures immédiates, nous limitons tant le coût pour le budget que les pertes pour les producteurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parallèlement à ces actions immédiates de gestion de marché, il nous faut aussi préparer l'avenir. C'est pourquoi nous accordons désormais une attention particulière aux actions de recherche de nouveaux marchés, notamment aux actions de promotion sur des marchés à l'extérieur de l'Union européenne. Pour cette raison, la Commission a décidé de doubler l'enveloppe budgétaire pour le financement des programmes promotionnels qui étaient prévus pour une session de projets qui doit se clôturer le 30 septembre. Nous avions prévu initialement un financement européen de 30 millions d'euros pour ces paquets relevant du programme de promotion. Nous avons encore ajouté 30 millions d'euros, ce qui fait un financement communautaire de 60 millions d'euros, auquel se rajoutent des financements privés. Nous aurons donc un paquet de 120 millions d'euros qui pourront financer assez rapidement des actions de promotion et aider le secteur agroalimentaire à s'orienter vers d'autres marchés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quelles mesures la Commission envisage-t-elle de prendre pour la suite? À côté de ces mesures de stabilisation de marché que nous avons prises et que nous pouvons prendre si nécessaire, nous envisageons aussi d'étudier la possibilité d'accorder des compensations ciblées aux producteurs, destinées notamment à éviter la disparition d'entreprises agricoles qui seraient parfaitement rentables dans une situation normale sur les marchés, et bien entendu des emplois qui y sont afférents.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette question de compensation implique une discussion politique réelle, puisque nous devons examiner notamment deux éléments: tout d'abord, comment cibler les catégories de bénéficiaires qui pourraient obtenir ces compensations puisqu'il faut s'adresser à ceux qui en ont vraiment besoin, ceux qui sont vraiment touchés, par catégorie d'exploitations mais aussi par secteur; ensuite comment assurer la couverture financière de ces compensations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains d'entre vous ont demandé de financer ces mesures non pas sur le budget de la PAC mais sur d'autres budgets. Je souhaite vous dire – mais mon collègue en charge du budget aura sans doute aussi l'occasion de le dire – que nous ne pouvons pas agir autrement que dans les marges du budget prévu par le législateur. Or vous savez que les marges du budget que nous avons sont très réduites. Nous utilisons actuellement les marges que nous avons sur le budget de la PAC. Nous avons également cette réserve de crise.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous devons donc tenir cette discussion politique pour voir non seulement vers qui orienter ces compensations mais aussi comment les financer, compte tenu des restrictions budgétaires et des limitations budgétaires. La Commission est d'avis qu'il faudrait prendre cette décision aussi rapidement que possible puisque, pour que des compensations financières soient utiles, elles doivent arriver rapidement aux agriculteurs. Je souhaiterais éviter la situation que nous avons eue lors de la crise laitière en 2009, quand des compensations financières pour les producteurs laitiers ont été décidées un an après la crise: pour certains producteurs l'argent est arrivé trop tard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans les prochains mois, selon l'évaluation de l'impact que nous allons faire avec les États membres, mais de manière ciblée, il faudra prendre cette décision. Sachez que la Commission est ouverte, mais nous avons besoin de cette discussion politique que nous devons assumer sur l'allocation budgétaire afin de soutenir ce type de mesures.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voilà les sujets que je voulais soumettre à votre analyse, à votre débat et bien sûr en fonction des questions que vous poserez et d'autres sujets que vous soulèverez, je serai prêt à répondre à la fin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-000" speaker_id="102886" name="elnök asszony" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Köszönöm szépen a biztos úrnak a nagyon részletes és minden részletre kiterjedő válaszát. Most a képviselőcsoportok vezérszónokai következnek. Elsőként Deß képviselő urat szeretném szólítani az Európai Néppártból. Parancsoljon, képviselő úr, két percben öné a szó.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich möchte schon mit dem Hinweis beginnen, dass die heutige Diskussion eine Folge der völkerrechtswidrigen Annexion der Krim durch Putin und Russland ist und auch des unausgesprochenen Krieges, den Russland gegen die Ukraine führt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Antwort der EU und westlicher Staaten waren Gott sei Dank nicht Panzer und Soldaten, sondern Boykottmaßnahmen gegen Putin und sein Regime. Es war zu erwarten, dass Russland mit Gegenmaßnahmen reagiert. Der Boykott von Lebensmitteln aus der Europäischen Union und anderen Partnerländern hat unterschiedliche Auswirkungen. Es gibt Länder und Bereiche, die sehr stark betroffen sind. Ich bedanke mich bei der Kommission und besonders bei Ihnen, Herr Kommissar Cioloș, für die schnelle Reaktion und die Ankündigung von Hilfen für betroffene Landwirte und Unternehmen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sie haben gerade eine ganze Latte von Maßnahmen aufgezählt. Vor allem in den baltischen Staaten, in Polen und einigen anderen Staaten ist dringend Hilfe gefordert. Es ist jetzt notwendig, nicht nach einem Gießkannenprinzip, sondern sehr gezielt zu helfen. Die im Haushalt vorhanden Mittel reichen sicher nicht aus, um zumindest dort zu helfen, wo ohne eigenes Verschulden eine existenzgefährdende Situation eingetreten ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Situation zeigt, dass die EU im Haushalt viel zu wenig Mittel für Krisensituationen eingeplant hat. Wir brauchen hier Umschichtungen im Haushalt. Ich sage es auch als Landwirt: Wenn die Mittel nicht ausreichen, ist auch die Solidarität aller Landwirte gefordert, über Direktzahlungsmittel den in ihrer Existenz gefährdeten Berufskollegen zu helfen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Besonders verwerflich ist das Verhalten von großen Handelsketten, die die russischen Boykottmaßnahmen sofort missbraucht haben und Preisdruck gegen die Erzeuger von Lebensmitteln ausgeübt haben. Es ist schon interessant, dass die Verbraucher in der EU die Gewinner der Boykottmaßnahmen sind, da die Lebensmittelpreise sinken. Deshalb ist es auch verantwortlich, Steuerzahlermittel einzusetzen, um den Betroffenen zu helfen, damit sie in ihrer Existenz nicht gefährdet werden.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel 162 Absatz 8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Herr Kollege Deß, wären Sie nicht auch der Auffassung, dass jetzt die Mitgliedstaaten auch ihre nationalen Hilfsprogramme aktivieren dürfen sollten? Da brauchen wir eine Genehmigung von Brüssel, dazu gehören Konsolidierungsdarlehen, Liquiditätsdarlehen und Beihilfeprogramme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und zweitens: Wäre es nicht endlich an der Zeit, auch das Schulmilch- und das Schulobstprogramm endlich einmal ordentlich zu entbürokratisieren, damit wir auf diesem Weg endlich mehr Produkte in die Schulen bekommen könnten?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Antwort auf eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Vielen Dank, lieber Kollege Peter Jahr! Selbstverständlich ist es notwendig, bevor man um Hilfe aus Brüssel bittet, dass alle nationalen Programme beantragt werden und ausgeschöpft werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Du hast ja einige Maßnahmen aufgezeigt, es gibt noch weitere: Es können für die Betroffenen Steuern gestundet werden, es gibt viele Maßnahmen. Besonders wichtig wäre es, Herr Kommissar Cioloș, dass das Schulmilch- und Schulobstprogramm wirklich massiv entbürokratisiert wird. Hier wäre ein guter Weg, um schnell für Obst und Gemüse und auch für Milchprodukte Absatz zu finden. Viele wenden dieses Programm nicht an, weil es viel zu bürokratisch ist. Hier muss schnell etwas verändert werden, und dies kann auch mit dazu beitragen, die Situation zu entschärfen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-000" speaker_id="96891" name="Paolo De Castro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo S&amp;D. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario, la crisi con la Russia è una crisi politica, ma fin qui a pagarne le conseguenze sono principalmente gli agricoltori europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le risorse messe a disposizione della Commissione – e in questo mi unisco anch'io ai ringraziamenti del Commissario Cioloş – centoventicinque milioni di euro, sono sicuramente una risposta tempestiva, ma assolutamente insufficiente a compensare i danni ingenti per i nostri produttori, soprattutto se l'Unione europea continuerà a emettere sanzioni e la Russia continuerà a rispondere allargando l'embargo. Un ping-pong drammatico per i nostri agricoltori.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ricordo anch'io che per dare le dimensioni del problema basta citare il 39 per cento delle esportazioni di ortofrutta europea che vanno in Russia o il 33 per cento delle esportazioni di formaggi europei che vanno verso la Russia. Siamo quindi a chiedere alla Commissione più fondi per far fronte a una crisi di cui purtroppo non si vede la fine in tempi rapidi. Tuttavia è importante ricordare che queste risorse non devono essere prese dalla riserva di crisi del bilancio agricolo. Lo voglio ricordare, come in parte ha detto il Commissario, perché a causa dell'accordo sulle prospettive finanziarie quei fondi sono stati azzerati di fatto. Quindi, attingere fondi dalla riserva di crisi significa di fatto tagliare gli aiuti diretti agli agricoltori.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se la crisi è politica, gli agricoltori evidentemente non hanno alcuna colpa per addossarsi il peso finanziario dell'embargo russo. Dobbiamo riuscire, colleghi, a trovare altri fondi dal bilancio europeo che vadano al di là di quello agricolo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine vorrei sottolineare che lo stop all'erogazione dei fondi fatto dalla Commissione a seguito di richieste sproporzionate di alcuni Stati membri dimostra che si deve trovare un metodo più razionale del semplice first come-first served al fine di distribuire gli aiuti compensativi in modo equilibrato come si è fatto in altre occasioni, penso all'escherichia coli.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-000" speaker_id="23784" name="Janusz Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, first of all thank you for agreeing to include this question of the Russian import ban today and for accepting the proposal of the Committee on Agriculture and Rural Development initiated by the ECR Group, and especially the Polish delegation, the Law and Justice Party, in this group.</p>
      <p sl="en">Six years ago the Polish President, Lech Kaczynski, organised successful political action in Tbilisi against the Russian invasion of Georgia. He said at the time that it was Georgia today, Ukraine tomorrow, the Baltic States the day after tomorrow and then Poland. Now we have gone one step further: Georgia yesterday, Ukraine today, the Baltic States tomorrow, and Poland the day after tomorrow.</p>
      <p sl="en">Economic sanctions are the best way to stop the aggressive and imperial policy of Russia, but sanctions are costly for both sides. The highest price is paid by farmers, especially those from the eastern part of the EU – from neighbouring countries like Finland, the Baltic States and my country, Poland. We need European solidarity. The cost of the sanctions should be paid by the whole Union, not only by farmers and immediate neighbours.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner, my question is, although we have a financial reserve for the crisis (we have a serious crisis – not a disturbance, but a crisis), why was the reserve under Article 25, Regulation (EU) No 1306/2013, not used? Why was this reserve not used? We need to use it. Why was the proposal of the Polish Government on this not accepted? Please answer. European farmers are waiting for real support and real help.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-000" speaker_id="96877" name="Zoltán Balczó" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kékkártyás kérdés. – A képviselő úrtól szeretnék kérdezni: azt állította, hogy a helyzet javítása érdekében, Ukrajna biztonsága érdekében a gazdasági szankciókat tartja a legjobb eszköznek. Szeretném megkérdezni, hogy az eddig alkalmazott gazdasági szankciók eredményét hogyan látja? Úgy ítéli meg, hogy ezek a szankciók segítették a megoldást? Közelebb hozták az ukrajnai helyzet megoldását, a biztonságot? Vagy talán éppen ellentétesen, elmérgesítették a helyzetet. Kérem, hogy erre válaszoljon a szankciók tapasztalatai alapján.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-000" speaker_id="23784" name="Janusz Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odpowiedź na pytanie zadane przez podniesienie „niebieskiej kartki”. – Tak, Panie Przewodniczący! Uważam, że konsekwentnie stosowane sankcje gospodarcze mogą skutecznie wpłynąć na powstrzymanie imperialnej, agresywnej polityki Rosji. Tak było w przeszłości, kiedy polityka Ronalda Reagana, polegająca na stanowczym stosowaniu sankcji gospodarczych, doprowadziła do załamania się do imperialnej potęgi dawnego Związku Sowieckiego. Tak i dzisiaj imperialna polityka Putina może być powstrzymana przez konsekwentne sankcje gospodarcze.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ALDE. – Gospođo predsjednice, Komisija je u ovom slučaju zaista brzo i dobro reagirala na embargo kojeg je Rusija nametnula, pomoć koja se direktno ili indirektno daje apsolutno je neophodna i očito u ovom domu postoji politička volja da se ta politika Komisije do kraja podrži.</p>
      <p sl="en">Izvoz u Rusiju u postocima naizgled čak i nije velik. Međutim, za neke zemlje je iznimno velik, a za svakog poljoprivrednika koji doživljava katastrofu naravno dovodi u pitanje i njegov opstanak. Zato pitam Komisiju što ćemo učiniti ako embargo i dalje potraje, kakav odgovor imamo u strateškom smislu na to pitanje te predlažem da se prvo potraže nova tržišta, da agresivno idemo na nova tržišta i dobro je da u tom smislu ulažemo u marketing.</p>
      <p sl="en">Drugo, da se zaista uključe i sve države i zemlje članice Europske unije i treće, da se ovo zaista "iskoristi", provede i voće dovede u škole.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na kraju želim reći da se embargo odnosi na proizvode koje ćemo uskoro brati, pa tako i u mnogim mediteranskim državama uskoro ćemo brati mandarine i druge proizvode te se nadam da će Komisija imati isti stav prema tim proizvodima kao što je imala i do sada.</p>
      <a text="(Govornik je pristao odgovoriti na pitanje postavljeno podizanjem plave kartice (članak 162. stavak 8. Poslovnika))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pitanje koje je podizanjem plave kartice postavio. – Gospodine Jakovčiću, pomno sam slušala vaše izlaganje. Zanima me, mislite li vi osobno i vjerujete li da ove gospodarske sankcije mogu utjecati na imperijalističku politiku Rusije i jesu li poljoprivrednici ti i baš jedini koji prvi moraju osjetiti sankcije, a ovdje posebice mislim na poljoprivrednike iz Hrvatske.</p>
      <p sl="en">Spomenuli ste mandarine. Povjerenik je upravo rekao da to nije kvarljivo voće, agrumi su izuzeti. Na koji način možemo utjecati da i agrumi uđu u ovu kategoriju te da agrumi također postanu kvarljivo voće, jer oni to jesu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odgovor na pitanje postavljeno podizanjem plave kartice. – Gospođo Šuica, radi se političkoj krizi, znači radi se o činjenici da je politika dovela, u ovom konkretnom slučaju, politika Rusije do ove situacije. Mi ovdje govorimo o politici. Govorimo o poljoprivrednim proizvođačima i ako postoji politička volja, a čini mi se da u ovom domu postoji politička volja da se svim poljoprivrednicima koji će biti u problemima zbog činjenice da imamo embargo, vjerujem da se može pomoći i kad su u pitanju agrumi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mislim da je Komisija dosad to pokazala i očekujem da nastavi s tom politikom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-000" speaker_id="125049" name="Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señora Presidenta, señor Comisario, el campesinado europeo somos víctima de una decisión que nosotros no hemos tomado. Somos víctima de una decisión irresponsable que la Unión Europea ha tomado, ya sabemos, para favorecer los intereses del Gobierno de los Estados Unidos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero esta crisis, además, muestra igualmente la inseguridad y la fragilidad económica en que la política actual europea ha sumido al campesinado en la Unión Europea: una política agraria común con vocación exportadora y de ahí tenemos ahora esta situación.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creemos que es urgente ahora mismo que lleguen las ayudas al campesinado, a todos los campesinos y campesinas sin discriminaciones, a todos los sectores de producción —todos los sectores de producción estamos afectados por esta crisis—, y también que las ayudas sean en cuantía suficiente como para cubrir los costes de producción y también el trabajo campesino.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero necesitamos con urgencia, señor Comisario, abrir un debate para una nueva PAC, una PAC que ponga en el centro los derechos y los intereses del campesinado, la vida del campesinado, que ponga en el centro …</p>
      <a text="(La Presidenta retira la palabra a la oradora)"/>
      <a text="(La oradora acepta responder a una pregunta formulada con arreglo al procedimiento de la «tarjeta azul» (artículo 162, apartado 8, del Reglamento))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonașului albastru”. – Ați afirmat aici că a fost o decizie iresponsabilă luată de Comisie. Aș vrea să ne explicați care ar fi fost decizia pe care o propuneați dumneavoastră.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-000" speaker_id="125049" name="Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">respuesta de «tarjeta azul». – Yo creo que, como he dicho, la irresponsabilidad de la Comisión ya viene de atrás, de una política exportadora que nos llevó a estas conclusiones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso creo que es urgente, por ejemplo, en el sector lácteo, dar marcha atrás y poner fin a esa decisión de abandonar las cuotas. Creo también que tenemos que ir hacia una política que establezca mecanismos de gestionar públicamente la oferta, y también hacia una política que garantice que los campesinos y campesinas vamos a cobrar precios correctos por nuestro trabajo. En definitiva, una política agraria común en el marco de la soberanía alimentaria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-000" speaker_id="96752" name="Martin Häusling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Ich darf der Kommission zunächst einmal danken, dass sie schnell Maßnahmen ergriffen hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Denn hier ist europäische Solidarität nötig. Genauso, wie wir gemeinsam auch die Sanktionen beschlossen haben, müssen wir jetzt, wo es Gegenreaktionen gibt, dann auch als Europäer gemeinsam handeln. Deshalb ist das Handeln der Kommission hier durchaus zu begrüßen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es gibt unterschiedliche Betroffenheit in den Mitgliedstaaten. Natürlich sind die baltischen Staaten, Polen und andere am stärksten davon betroffen, aber auch Produzenten von Südfrüchten, die ihre Absatzmärkte verloren haben. Aber das ganze trifft jetzt natürlich auch auf eine Situation fallender Preise, die schon vorher da waren. Aber wir sind jetzt quasi genötigt zu schauen, dass die Landwirte jetzt nicht alleingelassen werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Märkte zu stabilisieren ist eine Maßnahme. Aber ich warne davor, dass wir jetzt sozusagen unsere Probleme in andere Länder exportieren und Überschüsse jetzt irgendwo hinschicken, wo sie auch gar nicht erwünscht sind. Das heißt, es kann jetzt keine Lösung sein, dass wir jetzt am Ende vielleicht wieder über Exporterstattungen nachdenken, sondern wir müssen die Situation innereuropäisch lösen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen natürlich auch genau hinschauen, wo die Hilfen jetzt ankommen. Da ist es – scheinbar auch, weil es die Kommission ja zunächst ausgesetzt hat – nötig, zweimal genau hinzuschauen, wer jetzt wirklich bedürftig ist und wer das Geld bekommt. Es gibt in diesem Bereich Trittbrettfahrer, und es kann nicht sein, dass wir jetzt Geld an Leute auszahlen, die es vielleicht gar nicht brauchen. Wir brauchen natürlich auch eine Politik, die verhindert, dass jetzt der Handel Kapital daraus schlägt und die Preise noch weiter nach unten drückt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gestatten Sie mir auch ein Wort in Richtung der Exportorientierung der europäischen Agrarpolitik. Wir als Grüne haben ja immer davor gewarnt, nur auf Exporte zu setzen, sondern wir müssen langfristig hinschauen, dass wir den europäischen Markt bedienen und nicht angewiesen sind auf solche unzuverlässigen Partner, die uns am Ende alle gemeinsam in den Abgrund reißen.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel 162 Absatz 8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-000" speaker_id="124742" name="António Marinho e Pinto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pergunta segundo o procedimento "cartão azul". – Senhor Deputado, Senhores Deputados, estamos a discutir aqui os danos diretos na população da União Europeia, nos agricultores europeus, de uma situação que me parece a mim foi criada pela irresponsabilidade dos dirigentes da União.</p>
      <p sl="en">Havia um problema político em relação ao qual a União Europeia declarou uma guerra económica, e estamos agora a discutir os danos dessa guerra.</p>
      <p sl="en">A questão que eu coloco é esta: não será de encontrar uma solução política para o problema político que originou esta guerra económica, em vez de estarmos a aprofundar as consequências? Porque, Senhor Deputado, o que me parece, seguindo a metodologia do colega polaco, ontem era uma guerra política, era um problema político, hoje é uma guerra económica, amanhã que guerra será?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-000" speaker_id="96752" name="Martin Häusling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Antwort auf eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Lieber Herr Kollege, ich glaube, Sie verwechseln hier Ursache und Wirkung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Aggressor ist eindeutig zu benennen und dem muss die Europäische Union solidarisch entgegenwirken. Ich glaube, die Europäische Union hat sich noch nie so solidarisch gestellt wie bei der Verhängung von Sanktionen. Wenn es dann Gegenreaktionen gibt, auch dann ist eine Solidarität der Europäischen Union gefordert. Ich würde jetzt nicht mit der Begründung, es gibt hier in der Europäischen Union Betroffene, sagen, deshalb war die Sanktionspolitik der Europäischen Union falsch. Ganz im Gegenteil, wie hätten wir denn sonst handeln sollen?</p>
      <p sl="en">Dass es jetzt Branchen gibt wie die Landwirte, die davon betroffen sind, erfordert wiederum unsere innereuropäische Solidarität, um die Auswirkungen für die Betroffenen zu mildern. Ich kann das nur begrüßen, wie die Europäische Union gehandelt hat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-000" speaker_id="125237" name="Marco Zullo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, abbiamo visto che il valore dei prodotti agroalimentari interessati dall'embargo russo è stimato dalla Commissione europea in cinque miliardi di euro e incide sul reddito di nove milioni e mezzo di produttori europei, che sono nove milioni e mezzo di famiglie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tale valutazione, purtroppo, è ottimistica. Per la sola Italia, la cifra indicata di centosessanta milioni di euro è inferiore ai duecento milioni calcolati invece dalle associazioni di categoria. Valutazione ottimistica perché non sono considerate le conseguenze indirette come quella sul commercio a triangolazione, che riguarda i prodotti europei venduti alla Russia passando prima tramite paesi terzi. Valutazione ottimistica perché non è considerata la perdita di quote di mercato sul lungo periodo, perché il consumatore russo potrebbe abituarsi ad altri gusti e non riprendere più i prodotti europei. Valutazione ottimistica perché non sono considerati gli squilibri nel mercato interno, dovuti all'immissione di prodotti a basso costo che non trovando più sbocco sul mercato russo saranno riversati sul mercato europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">È molto probabile quindi che gli aiuti stanziati, già inferiori rispetto alle necessità, non saranno sufficienti. Il Movimento 5 Stelle chiede che la Commissione europea preveda nelle prossime misure una distribuzione delle risorse più attenta e si adoperi per costruire finalmente un vero mercato unico europeo armonizzato in grado di assorbire contraccolpi ed emergenze, gestendo in modo lungimirante i flussi commerciali interni.</p>
      <p sl="en">O tutti noi ci adoperiamo per creare un vero sistema Europa, oppure vuol dire che se sono solo le emergenze a dettare le linee guida possiamo permetterci di dire che le Istituzioni europee stanno fallendo il loro compito.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-000" speaker_id="124755" name="Jean-Luc Schaffhauser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je voudrais simplement souligner que cette politique agricole, qui me paraît mal préparée et ne pas correspondre à la finalité recherchée, s'inscrit dans la durée. Il faut comprendre que la Russie a préparé récemment des accords avec le Brésil, l'Argentine et des pays d'Amérique latine pour, une fois pour toutes, ne plus dépendre de ces productions …</p>
      <a text="(La Présidente interrompt l'orateur)"/>
      <p sl="en">Est-ce que la Commission a intégré dans la durée que ces aides ne sont pas ponctuelles mais seront sans doute pérennes? Est-ce que les responsables qui ont pris ces décisions ici-même, sont d'accord que, dans un an, les agriculteurs sachent que la situation pérenne tient à leurs décisions?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-000" speaker_id="125072" name="Ελευθέριος Συναδινός" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, σε μια Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, της οποίας πολλά κράτη μέλη μαστίζονται από την οικονομική κρίση, η επιβολή εμπάργκο από τη Ρωσία, στα αγροτικά κυρίως αλλά και σε άλλα προϊόντα, είναι η κορυφή του παγόβουνου. Ως Έλληνες πολίτες, ανησυχούμε και παρακολουθούμε τις εξελίξεις σχετικά με το εμπάργκο στα προϊόντα της χώρας μου, το οποίο επηρεάζει αρνητικά και άμεσα την εθνική μας οικονομία σε μια δύσκολη, όπως σήμερα, συγκυρία.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι επιπτώσεις και οι συνέπειες του ρωσικού αποκλεισμού είναι αλυσιδωτές. Τα πλεονάζοντα τρόφιμα θα παραμείνουν ανεκμετάλλευτα, με κίνδυνο να συντρίψουν τις τιμές των προϊόντων. Οι ήδη εξευτελιστικά χαμηλές τιμές θα υποστούν μεγαλύτερη μείωση και οι επιπτώσεις της κερδοσκοπίας θα είναι άμεσες και ορατές. Είναι απαράδεκτο να μπαίνουν στο στόχαστρο προβληματικές οικονομίες, όπως η ελληνική, και να χρεώνονται το τίμημα της ρωσο-ουκρανικής κρίσης. Τα μεγάλα πολιτικά και επιχειρηματικά συμφέροντα ξεκίνησαν αυτή την κρίση ερήμην μας, πάντα στο όνομα της δημοκρατίας και των ελευθεριών, και εμείς τώρα συζητάμε για λύσεις προς αποκατάσταση των ζημιών σε καρκινοπαθείς οικονομίες όπως αυτή της χώρας μου.</p>
      <p sl="en">Υποψήφιες προς ένταξη στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση τρίτες χώρες, και μάλιστα μέλη του ΝΑΤΟ, οι οποίες μετέχουν á la carte στην ευρωπαϊκή πολιτική, επωφελούνται από το κόστος που καταβάλλουν τα κράτη μέλη. Οι αποζημιώσεις με κοινοτικό χρήμα δεν μπορούν να αποτελούν πολιτική στρατηγική. Χρειάζεται χάραξη νέας πολιτικής, στρατηγική προσέγγιση μεταξύ της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και της Ρωσίας, χρειάζεται ενδυνάμωση των εταιρικών και εμπορικών σχέσεών μας. Τα γεγονότα επιτάσσουν αναθεώρηση και αλλαγή στην εφαρμοζόμενη πολιτική. Η συνέχιση της σύγκρουσης με τη Ρωσία θα επιφέρει περισσότερα δεινά και προβλήματα παρά οφέλη για τα κράτη μέλη της Ένωσης.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președinte, agresiunea asupra Ucrainei constituie o amenințare extrem de serioasă la adresa păcii în Europa. Trebuie să se înțeleagă că nu este un conflict între Rusia și Ucraina, este o agresiune a Federației Ruse și o amenințare pentru toate statele membre, indiferent dacă sunt în estul sau în vestul Uniunii. Din păcate, nu cred că Rusia se va opri. Republica Moldova, gurile Dunării pot constitui viitoarele ținte. Un conflict militar nu este o soluție. Sancțiunile economice și politice sunt singura armă care poate fi utilizată.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este necesară o atitudine fermă și comună a tuturor statelor membre. Diferențele de opinie între statele membre nu duc la o rezolvare a situației. Cu toate că sancțiunile, cum ar fi cele din sectorul agricol, au efecte negative și asupra economiei Uniunii sunt convins că Uniunea are capacitatea să reducă la maxim astfel de efecte și să ia măsurile necesare, atât de compensare, cât și de orientare pe alte piețe. Noua politică agricolă comună dispune de instrumentele necesare, bugetare și legale, pentru a sprijini producătorii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Adaug și eu mulțumirile mele domnului comisar, atât pentru politica agricolă, cât și pentru măsurile luate foarte repede. Important este ca Uniunea să ia decizii comune, care să nu depindă de interesele individuale, ci de interesele comunitare, și care să conducă la o rezolvare cât mai rapidă a situației.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-000" speaker_id="114279" name="Isabelle Thomas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, je tiens d'abord à vous féliciter pour votre réactivité sur l'embargo russe, pour pallier les conséquences que risque de subir l'agriculture européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Malheureusement, une fois de plus, la pêche est la grande oubliée des politiques alimentaires de l'Union. Pourtant, l'embargo russe affectera les pêcheurs européens pour une valeur estimée à 144 millions d'euros. Votre collègue, la commissaire Damanaki, nous a fait savoir que certaines lignes budgétaires du FEAMP, notamment les fonds prévus pour le stockage, pourraient être utilisées par les pêcheurs victimes de l'embargo. Mais contrairement à l'agriculture, aucun moyen supplémentaire n'est pour l'instant alloué à la pêche. Cette défaillance conduirait à sacrifier des projets essentiels comme la sélectivité pour éviter les rejets ou la vente directe, qui auraient dû être financés sur ces mêmes montants.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Commissaire, comment justifier le traitement inégal de deux secteurs pourtant comparables. Ne peut-on avoir une position coordonnée pour traiter ces deux secteurs alimentaires de manière équitable?</p>
      <p sl="en">J'ai déposé avec mon groupe une série d'amendements demandant une augmentation exceptionnelle du budget 2015 pour la pêche, comme c'est le cas pour l'agriculture. J'espère que nous pourrons compter sur le soutien de la Commission. Pour être fermes par rapport à l'extérieur, il faut être solidaires à l'intérieur.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-000" speaker_id="124900" name="Beata Barbara Gosiewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Ja pochodzę z Polski, regionu, gdzie biedne rolnictwo zostało szczególnie dotknięte przez embargo rosyjskie, i powiem tak: Putin się cieszy, bo Komisja Europejska nie potrafi podjąć skutecznych działań zapobiegających embargu rosyjskiemu. Komisja powinna udzielić rolnikom realnego wsparcia, a nie tworzyć iluzję, że podejmuje działania. Nie ulega wątpliwości, że środki, które Komisja chciała przeznaczyć na rekompensaty dla rolników dotkniętych rosyjskim embargiem, były śmiesznie małe od samego początku. Zeszłotygodniowa decyzja o wstrzymaniu przyjmowania wniosków od rolników jest skandaliczna i pozostawia ich bez jakiejkolwiek pomocy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie rozumiem i w imieniu moich wyborców pytam Komisję, dlaczego w obliczu jednego z najpoważniejszych kryzysów nie sięga po środki z unijnej rezerwy przeznaczonej na te cele. Z tego miejsca apeluję również do Komisji o konkretne i całościowe działania w walce z kryzysem, który nie tylko dotyka producentów owoców, ale również sektor mleczny. W obecnej sytuacji zniesienie kar za przekroczenie kwot mlecznych jest konieczne. Powtarzam: konieczne! Nałożone na Rosję sankcje nie są skuteczne, dlatego Unia Europejska powinna zrewidować swoją politykę w tym zakresie oraz podjąć zdecydowane i solidarne działania.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-000" speaker_id="124708" name="Dita Charanzová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane komisaři, vy sám jste na číslech demonstroval závažnost situace na evropském trhu. Při sledování dopadu embarga na evropský trh docházíme nutně k závěru, že je nutné výrazně přizpůsobit jak ta krátkodobá opatření, tak ale i naši dlouhodobou obchodní strategii. Kompenzační a další opatření Evropské komise bohužel nepokrývají všechny postižené podniky a už dnes je jasné, že tato opatření nebudou dostatečná.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je evidentní, že embargo má dopad i na ty podniky, které přímo do Ruské federace nevyvážejí. Proto při vyhodnocování přijatých opatření vás žádám, abyste bral v úvahu celkové dopady jak na jednotný trh Evropské unie, na společnou zemědělskou politiku, tak i na společnou obchodní politiku. V této chvíli je nutná vaše úzká spolupráce</p>
      <p sl="en">s DG TRADE tak, aby se zabránilo zaplavení evropského trhu. Je nezbytné hledat mimoevropské trhy, a to nejen pro oblast zemědělství, ale pro všechny sektory, které jsou embargem zasaženy. Musíme mít plán B, pokud by se takováto situace znovu opakovala. Naše podnikatelské subjekty nesmí strádat, když máme nástroje, jak tomu zabránit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-000" speaker_id="125031" name="Pablo Iglesias" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, creo que en política exterior hay algo mucho más importante que la ideología de cada uno, y es la responsabilidad. Y me da la impresión de que en los últimos meses hemos visto de todo menos responsabilidad: hemos visto a dirigentes europeos hacer belicistas discursos contra Rusia y les hemos visto apoyar desplazamientos de poder ilegales en Ucrania, que han tenido como consecuencia, entre otras cosas, que haya neonazis en el Gobierno de ese país y que se ilegalicen partidos políticos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las consecuencias para los agricultores europeos se cifran en un veto ruso que equivale a 2 000 millones de euros, mientras que la Comisión Europea prevé una ayuda de tan solo 125 millones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es fácil darse golpes en el pecho; es fácil evocar, como hemos escuchado en esta Cámara, nada más y nada menos que a Ronald Reagan, lo cual es muy «tranquilizador». ¿Qué va a ser lo próximo? ¿Recordar la trágica época de los euromisiles?</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo no tengo ninguna simpatía por el señor Putin, pero creo que la política exterior de la Unión no puede ser jugar al Risk con los intereses de los agricultores europeos y que, para bien o para mal, los europeos se merecen una relación pacífica y responsable con Rusia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-000" speaker_id="124859" name="Giulia Moi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario, purtroppo l'embargo con la Russia ha creato gravi problemi a tutti gli agricoltori e non è giusto che siano loro a pagarne le conseguenze. Stanno già soffrendo riguardo alla legge che voi avete approvato con le arance dal Marocco, per cui soffrono tantissimo questa crisi. Ora questo embargo ha causato problemi ancora più gravi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io vorrei chiedere alla Commissione cosa ha intenzione di fare per aiutarli. Gli aiuti che avete dato non sono stati sufficienti. Inoltre, non sono stati controllati né erogati con un criterio razionale. Sono stati distribuiti a pioggia come siete soliti fare, per cui non è giusto, in quanto ora sono già finiti e molti non hanno ricevuto nessun compenso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allora i miei colleghi stanno richiedendo altri fondi: non è giusto erogarne altri senza alcun criterio, senza aver prima valutato chi ne ha veramente bisogno, ma distribuirli non si sa in base a quale criterio. Noi chiediamo che venga rivalutato il vostro sistema di distribuzione di questi compensi, chiediamo che tutti ne usufruiscano e non solo alcuni paesi in particolare e chiediamo alla Commissione che utilizzi questa crisi in modo costruttivo, ossia utilizzi la sovrapproduzione dei prodotti agricoli in modo che venga distribuita alle scuole come programma educativo all'uso dei prodotti ortofrutticoli.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-000" speaker_id="21817" name="Mario Borghezio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, che cosa si aspettava la Commissione europea, che la Russia di Putin avrebbe reagito con delle cartoline di ringraziamento per i provvedimenti adottati? Era largamente prevedibile questa politica di ritorsione che, non era difficile capire, si sarebbe impattata molto gravemente sull'economia delicatissima che riguarda il comparto agroalimentare della nostra esportazione di paesi produttori, fra i quali il mio paese.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io sottolineo le conseguenze dirette e indirette presenti e anche future – pensiamo soltanto al problema dell'Expo 2015. Noi, come Unione europea, stiamo assistendo un po' come Alice nel paese delle meraviglie, questa è l'impressione che ha dato il rappresentante della Commissione europea. Ci parla di modestissimi aiuti di fronte a quello che può diventare un dramma per la produzione agricola e per la produzione lattiera dell'intero comparto europeo, a fronte del quale mi pare che la titubanza, la genericità e la debolezza dei provvedimenti assunti siano veramente in contrasto con la superficialità con cui, per esempio, il governo Renzi non ha saputo discutere preventivamente con la Commissione europea degli aiuti che si sarebbero e si dovrebbero dare ai nostri produttori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-000" speaker_id="96787" name="Herbert Dorfmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, geschätzter Herr Kommissar! Wir erleben derzeit eine tiefe Krise in unseren Beziehungen mit Russland. Leider bezahlen die Bauern dafür derzeit die Zeche. Ich bin überzeugt, dass die Sanktionen ein richtiger und wahrscheinlich der einzige vernünftige Weg sind, um hier Verbesserungen herbeizuführen. Aber andererseits sollten wir doch auch bedenken, dass höchstwahrscheinlich nur ein entschiedenes Handeln von unserer Seite die Russen auch zum Einlenken bringen wird. Deshalb sind einige Maßnahmen, die Sie, Herr Kommissar, vorgeschlagen haben, vollkommen richtig, aber auch ungenügend. Und auch das Aussetzen der Maßnahmen in den letzten Tagen ist nicht der richtige Weg.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich komme aus einer Region, in der rund 10 % der Äpfel in Europa hergestellt werden. Verbunden mit der Tatsache, dass wir auch in diesem Jahr eine Rekordernte erwarten, ist es derzeit so, dass der Preis für frische, jetzt geerntete Äpfel derzeit die Hälfte ist verglichen mit dem Preis vor einem Jahr. Da kann man sich den Schaden, den unsere Bauern erleiden, sehr deutlich ausrechnen. Deswegen sollten die Hilfen – und es freut mich, dass Sie angekündigt haben, dass neue Maßnahmen in den nächsten Tagen folgen werden – unverzüglich wieder aufgenommen werden und wir sollten entschieden auch mit neuen und frischen Geldmitteln der Situation entgegentreten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, Señor Comisario, estamos en un debate importante y de gran relevancia para el sector agroalimentario europeo y, por supuesto, para mi país, España.</p>
      <p sl="en">La innegable inmediatez de las medidas —con la respuesta de los dos Reglamentos que hemos visto durante el mes de agosto— no ha sido tan inmediata para el sector pesquero como se ha referido la señora Thomas, ya que, aunque no hemos visto ninguna de estas medidas de su compañera la Comisaria Damanaki, sí es innegable la inmediatez que usted ha tomado en estas medidas, pero quizás el resultado, desde luego, en mi opinión, no es el adecuado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es quizá prematuro hacer una estimación de pérdidas global. Lo que es evidente es que en la PAC no hay fondos que puedan atenuar o limitar el impacto que se puede producir. Entre las valoraciones que hace la Comisión, de 5 000 millones de euros, y los 125 que ha puesto la Comisión para los productos perecederos, se ve que falta mucho. Probablemente, Señor Comisario, lo peor no lo hemos visto aún.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero destacar que es habitual una especial sensibilidad hacia las producciones continentales y menos hacia las mediterráneas. No me ha parecido adecuada la determinación de incluir unos productos perecederos en la lista y otros no, estando en producción, lo que genera desconcierto y discriminación.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ahora nos encontramos con la suspensión del Reglamento, que es necesario que, cuanto antes, se ponga en marcha. Necesitamos mejorar los mecanismos de crisis. Yo viví en mi tierra, en Andalucía, la crisis de la E. coli: cómo, injustamente, se acusó a las producciones agrícolas andaluzas. Y vi lo que es una crisis y el tiempo que se tarda en superarla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero quiero decirle que debemos analizar también algo que está sucediendo con la gran distribución. Hay un colapso del mercado. Se ha dado especialmente en el mes de agosto, con bajadas de precios. Pero los consumidores no vemos los precios más bajos. ¿Quién se está llevando el beneficio de esta crisis? ¿Quizá la gran distribución?</p>
      <p sl="en">De mantenerse el veto ruso, probablemente, ¿no consideraría usted revisar los acuerdos de asociación y las preferencias comunitarias?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, of course we are all concerned about the impact on European farmers, I no less than anyone else. Even those Member States which are not heavily affected directly will be affected in time by market impacts such as falling prices. The ramifications of these political sanctions are very wide-reaching.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have been using the language of emergency and crisis, all of which implies a reaction to the unexpected. I would like to ask the Commissioner why the impact on farmers seems to have been so badly thought through. Is it a surprise that Russia has retaliated? No, of course not. Of course they would hit back in the area of fresh and perishable produce for maximum short-term impact.</p>
      <p sl="en">We hear about further sanctions being imposed by Brussels, so my question is: ‘What is the plan?’ Even if the EUR 430 million crisis reserve is mobilised it is not going to last long: we have already earmarked EUR 155 million in less than a month. Clearly, just calling for more and more financial support is not the answer: it cannot be, because that would simply be a bottomless pit. I would like to know from you, Commissioner, what the Commission’s medium-term and long-term plans are. Are you discussing this as a Commission? I know you are in a state of flux but are you actually looking clearly at the implications of foreign policy?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-000" speaker_id="124763" name="Antanas Guoga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I should like to thank the Commissioner for coming in. Commissioner, it is a pleasure to have you here.</p>
      <p sl="en">Colleagues, I am from a very small country: Lithuania. A lot of you have said today – surprisingly – that we need an alternative policy with Russia. If only we were diplomatic with them, they might stop. They might have forgotten to hit that plane in the sky that just fell down. No one has even talked about that plane. There were a lot of Dutch people on it.</p>
      <p sl="en">Russia will not stop. Lithuanians will keep supporting sanctions until they stop. Russia will stop when they realise that we are united – that we are Europe together and that we will not tolerate losing a few million here and there. We will not tolerate them doing this to us, because we are united: we are a real Europe. Look at Eurostat – 20 % of agricultural exports to Russia are from Lithuania and we endorse these sanctions. We want more sanctions. We want Russia to stop in Ukraine.</p>
      <p sl="en">So, Commissioner, please consider declaring the Baltic States an area of specific need. Look at the direct European support to the Baltic States. We receive the least. Is it fair? It is time for Europe to wake up and unite and also to be fair. Commissioner, please consider this – and everybody, it is time to unite against Russia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-065-000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the ban imposed by the Russian Federation on agricultural products from the EU is a very worrying development. It reflects the failures of both Russian and European diplomacy that have impacted most on the people of Ukraine but will now undoubtedly be felt by farmers and businesses across the regions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU’s agri-food sector is in crisis and these sanctions will mean that those already struggling to survive will no longer be able to do so. Questions that therefore need to be addressed this evening by the Commission include: what further measures will the Commission take to ensure that our small family farmers do not pay the price for political decisions they did not ask for; will the crisis reserve cover their losses; and will compensation be put in place for scenarios where there is a long-term impact on farmers beyond the sanctions period?</p>
      <p sl="en">Small farmers now need a friend in the European Commission, not a bureaucracy which fails to act while their livelihoods suffer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-000" speaker_id="124756" name="Davor Škrlec" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, pogoršanje odnosa s Rusijom te uvođenje ekonomskih sankcija snažno je pogodilo poljoprivredni sektor u cijeloj Europskoj uniji. Poseban problem za Hrvatsku predstavlja izuzimanje mandarina iz subvencioniranih proizvoda.</p>
      <p sl="en">Više od 2 000 obiteljskih poljoprivrednih gospodarstava direktno je pogođeno sankcijama, odnosno gotovo 20 000 ljudi koji su egzistencijalno vezani za ovu proizvodnju. Direktne subvencije nikada nisu najbolje rješenje, posebno ako nisu pravedno raspodijeljene. U izvanrednim situacijama tržište se pokazuje kao loš upravljač. Kako bi se novac zadržao unutar Europske unije, potrebno je stvoriti potražnju na europskom tržištu poticanjem otkupa svježih proizvoda i njihove prerade unutar Unije. Potrebno je kreirati instrumente za indirektno poticanje tržišta s ciljem stvaranja potražnje na europskom tržištu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pitanjem Komisiji već sam skrenuo pozornost kako je riječ o svježim proizvodima te su potrebne trenutne mjere kako bi se omogućio otkup svježih mandarina na unutarnjem tržištu Europske unije ili njihova prerada u polutrajne ili trajne proizvode. Bilo koje druge dugoročne mjere su hvalevrijedne, ali prekasne za ovogodišnju berbu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-000" speaker_id="124777" name="Tiziana Beghin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario, dallo scorso agosto la Russia ha bloccato l'importazione dei prodotti agricoli europei, una misura che interessa cinque miliardi di euro di generi alimentari che almeno per un anno non potranno essere venduti in quei paesi.</p>
      <p sl="en">I produttori europei perdono quindi un mercato prezioso e i prodotti restano invenduti sugli scaffali. Tonnellate di carne, latte, frutta e verdura lasciati a marcire. Ma dove c'è un problema, normalmente si può trovare anche un'opportunità. La crisi economica e l'austerità hanno portato milioni di europei sotto la soglia della povertà, e le sanzioni russe stanno minacciando la sopravvivenza di centinaia di piccole e medie imprese agricole in Europa. Milioni di persone non hanno nulla da mangiare, mentre tonnellate di cibo marciscono sugli scaffali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allora io, signor Commissario, in qualità di portavoce del Movimento 5 Stelle, chiedo che la Commissione e gli Stati membri istituiscano un programma serio ed efficace – serio ed efficace – di acquisto di generi alimentari da destinare in beneficienza.</p>
      <p sl="en">I fondi ci sono, li possiamo trovare dal budget della PAC, che prevede un fondo di riserva, e poi possono essere integrati dagli Stati. Con un semplice gesto noi possiamo dare una risposta a milioni di cittadini che sono colpiti dalla crisi e possiamo anche dare una risposta a migliaia di produttori. C'è solo una domanda che le faccio: che cosa stiamo aspettando, di cosa stiamo discutendo?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-000" speaker_id="96661" name="Krisztina Morvai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Szerettem volna litván képviselőtársamat megkérdezni, hogy honnan tudja biztosan, hogy mi történt azzal a bizonyos géppel. Honnan tudja, hogy – úgymond – az oroszok lőtték le? Tény az, hogy az Európai Unió erre fel vetette be ezeket a bizonyos átgondolatlan szankciókat. Amire természetesen ellenszankciók jöttek, és ezen ellenszankciók következményeit nem a politikusok, hanem a gazdák szenvedik el. Magyarország vonatkozásában a következőket tudom mondani: Magyarországgal együtt több más tagállam is elvesztette már egyszer az orosz piacait, utána nagy nehezen valamennyire újraépítettük. Most megint elvesztettük az átgondolatlan szankciók miatt. Ez az egyik problémánk.</p>
      <p sl="en">A másik pedig, és erről Cioloş urat, az Európai Unió mezőgazdasági biztosát szeretném kérdezni. Mi a garancia arra, hogy a másik 27 tagállamban, és különösen a politikailag erős, első osztályúnak tekintett centrumországokban a felhalmozódott mezőgazdasági többletek – nyersanyag-, illetőleg feldolgozottélelmiszer-többlet – nem kerülnek tömegesen beáramlásra a periféria országainak piacaira. És ezzel duplán is nehéz helyzetbe hozzák a mi gazdáinkat. Hogyan óhajtják megvédeni a perifériaországokat tehát attól, hogy a centrumországok szankciók következtében felhalmozódott mezőgazdasági termékei, terményei náluk landoljanak, még nehezebb helyzetbe hozva a gazdákat. És én is kérem azt, hogy magyar honfitársaim hazai élelmet fogyasszanak, és így is fejezzék ki szolidaritásukat a nehéz helyzetben lévő gazdákkal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-000" speaker_id="22418" name="Esther Herranz García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, señor Comisario, lamento que mi primera intervención en el Pleno en esta legislatura sea para denunciar los daños que está sufriendo el sector agrícola y ganadero como consecuencia del embargo impuesto por el Gobierno ruso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que la Unión Europea debería actuar de una forma más responsable, teniendo en cuenta que se trata de un asunto muy grave cuyas causas son totalmente ajenas al sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las ayudas de emergencia deberían ser destinadas a los verdaderamente afectados por esta crisis, ampliándose a los sectores que vayan siendo necesarios —como, por ejemplo, ahora ya a los cítricos— y teniendo en cuenta el efecto cascada de unos productores sobre otros —y me refiero, por ejemplo, al champiñón—.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es de dominio público que la actual suspensión de las ayudas se debe a ciertos abusos detectados en algún Estado miembro en el proceso de solicitud de las ayudas. Esa suspensión ha sido acogida con mucho desasosiego por los productores, que necesitan ver claro el apoyo de la Unión en este contexto, por lo que le quiero pedir ahora mismo, Comisario, que cumpla con lo anunciado y mañana, día 16 de septiembre, presente un sistema de reparto de las ayudas de emergencia que no dé lugar a situaciones desequilibradas.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión Europea, a mi juicio, debería estar ya estudiando seriamente la posibilidad de emprender un nuevo recurso contra Rusia ante la Organización Mundial del Comercio, y en cuanto al tema de los recursos económicos, los fondos no deberían circunscribirse al presupuesto agrícola, sino que deberían proceder igualmente de otros capítulos del presupuesto de la Unión, teniendo en cuenta que, como hemos dicho, se trata de un problema generado por circunstancias totalmente ajenas al sector.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-000" speaker_id="125113" name="Μιλτιάδης Κύρκος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κύριε Επίτροπε, εμείς πιστεύουμε ότι ήταν απαραίτητες οι κυρώσεις για να καμφθεί η ρωσική επιθετικότητα, χωρίς να ξεχνάμε βέβαια και τις ευθύνες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και των Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών της Αμερικής στην τροπή που πήρε η εξέγερση του Μαϊντάν.</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεν ήταν όμως αναμενόμενη η απάντηση της Ρωσίας; Ήταν!</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεν έπρεπε η Επιτροπή να είχε αμέσως έτοιμο ένα σχέδιο για την προώθηση των ευπαθών τουλάχιστον προϊόντων σε νέες αγορές, για την προώθησή τους στον δευτερογενή τομέα ή σε σχολεία, σε νοσοκομεία; Πού είναι τα νέα αναβαθμισμένα εργαλεία που προβλέπει η μόλις ψηφισθείσα Κοινή Γεωργική Πολιτική; Γιατί καθυστερεί η χρήση του Ταμείου αντιμετώπισης κρίσεων, αφού υπάρχουν οι πιστώσεις; Καν σαν να μην έφταναν αυτά, κόβουμε και τα 125 εκατομμύρια ευρώ που προορίζονται για ευπαθή αγροτικά προϊόντα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι οικονομίες του Νότου δεν θα αντέξουν χωρίς βοήθεια μία τέτοια κρίση. Οι αγρότες βλέπουν τη σοδειά τους να σαπίζει, και θα εξακολουθούν να τη βλέπουν να σαπίζει γιατί η κρίση θα κρατήσει πάνω από ένα χρόνο. Οι μεταφορές, στις οποίες κανείς δεν έχει αναφερθεί, δεν χάνουν μόνο ένα ποσοστό κέρδους, αλλά κινδυνεύουν με συνολικό αφανισμό.</p>
      <p sl="en">Τέλος, επιθυμώ να τονίσω στον κύριο Επίτροπο ότι αν καθυστερήσουν οι αποζημιώσεις ένα χρόνο είναι πιθανό να μην υπάρχουν πια αγρότες να τις λάβουν και ότι ο χρόνος φαίνεται να περνάει διαφορετικά από την Επιτροπή και διαφορετικά από τους αγρότες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-000" speaker_id="28389" name="Zbigniew Krzysztof Kuźmiuk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Skutki rosyjskiego embarga na żywność pochodzącą z 28 krajów Unii Europejskiej są coraz bardziej dotkliwe dla europejskich rolników, natomiast Komisja Europejska zachowuje się tak, jakbyśmy mieli do czynienia z jakimś niewielkiej wagi problemem. Ceny produktów rolnych, zarówno roślinnych, jak i zwierzęcych, w moim kraju, Polsce, w wyniku tego embarga spadły średnio o 30-40% w stosunku do roku ubiegłego, a reakcją Komisji Europejskiej jest zaledwie zapowiedź użycia rezerwy na zakłócenia na rynku. Rosyjskie embargo spowodowało autentyczny kryzys na większości rynków rolnych w tych krajach Unii, które były dużymi eksporterami na ten rynek, natomiast Komisja zdecydowała o niewykorzystywaniu rezerwy kryzysowej w ramach WPR.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proszę o wyjaśnienie, dlaczego w sytuacji najcięższego od lat kryzysu na rynkach rolnych Komisja nie zaproponowała użycia na wypłaty rekompensat tegorocznej rezerwy kryzysowej stworzonej w ramach WPR. Czy polski minister rolnictwa wnioskował o jej wykorzystanie? Jeśli tak, to dlaczego ten wniosek nie został uwzględniony? Kiedy zostaną odblokowane środki z rezerwy na zakłócenia na rynku i co było powodem tej blokady?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-000" speaker_id="125100" name="Miguel Viegas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Começo por registar que nós não acompanhamos a União Europeia nesta guerra comercial porque registamos uma dualidade de critérios face a outras regiões e a outros países como, por exemplo, Israel, que ainda recentemente cometeu crimes e violou normas elementares do direito internacional.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em segundo lugar, gostaria de vos transmitir a profunda indignação dos agricultores portugueses porque Portugal viveu três anos de intervenção da troica, sofreu um profundo processo de desvalorização interna com quebra dos salários - alegadamente para relançar a competitividade das suas exportações - e este embargo veio, naturalmente, causar inúmeros prejuízos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Porque é preciso também ir ao concreto, às situações reais. Quando um país como Portugal, ou outro qualquer, pretende exportar para fora do espaço europeu - Brasil, Rússia, seja qual for - são meses de negociações, são visitas das autoridades sanitárias que se deslocam aos países para aferir, enfim, das condições de produção local, etc., e, portanto, este embargo tem prejuízos incalculáveis e, portanto, a questão que eu tenho para pôr é esta: que medidas, que resposta poderemos dar a esses agentes que se esforçaram e que veem agora as suas expectativas completamente defraudadas?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-000" speaker_id="96882" name="Elisabeth Köstinger" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, geschätzter Herr Kommissar! Mit dem russischen Importstopp für Lebensmittel aus der Europäischen Union ist allein in Österreich in kürzester Zeit ein unmittelbarer Schaden von über 4,5 Millionen Euro entstanden, und die langfristigen Schäden für die Agrarwirtschaft sind dabei noch gar nicht abschätzbar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daher ist es auch dringend notwendig, dass die Europäische Kommission rasch und effizient auf die Marktausfälle reagiert. Zum ersten Mal seit der Reform der Gemeinsamen Agrarpolitik werden jetzt die neuen Instrumente für den Krisenfall eingesetzt und Soforthilfemaßnahmen auch beschlossen. Allerdings haben wir auch schon erfahren müssen, dass beispielsweise die Unterstützungsgelder für Obst und Gemüse bereits ausgeschöpft sind. Ich sehe darin aber nicht nur einen Mangel an Geld, sondern insbesondere einen Mangel an Solidarität mit unseren Bäuerinnen und Bauern und den Erzeugern in Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daher ich möchte gleich zwei konkrete Fragen an die Kommission richten. Zum Ersten: Hat die Kommission außerhalb des Agrarbudgets Mittel für die Maßnahmen in der Europäischen Union im Hinblick auf Marktauswirkungen bzw. zur Marktauslastung vorgesehen? Zweitens: Denkt die Kommission an vorbeugende Maßnahmen, um beispielsweise Krisen in den Sektoren erst gar nicht entstehen zu lassen?</p>
      <p sl="en">Geschätzter Herr Kommissar! Die europäischen Landwirte haben es hier nicht mit einem Ausfallsrisiko zu tun, das man lapidar unter Berufsrisiko subsummieren kann. Das hier ist kein unerwartetes, aber kalkulierbares Schlechtwetter. Das hier ist eine politische Krise für Europa. Europas Landwirte werden diese Krise nicht alleine stemmen können. Die Hilfeleistungen dürfen also nicht im Nachhinein zu drastischen Kürzungen der Direktzahlungen führen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Comissário, Senhor Representante da Presidência do Conselho de Ministros, caros Colegas e caras Colegas, as medidas de intervenção para o setor do leite recentemente aprovadas para fazer face ao embargo russo são obviamente bem-vindas, mas temo que possam não ser suficientes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não há dúvida de que este é um problema europeu e a repercussão em toda a Europa não tardará a fazer sentir-se com efeitos negativos sobre o preço pago ao produtor. A ser o caso, as medidas até agora aprovadas não serão suficientes.</p>
      <p sl="en">O setor reclama medidas de apoio para a promoção e eventual exploração de outros mercados. É necessário agilizar as trocas comerciais com alguns potenciais parceiros, mas tal não pode, obviamente, constituir qualquer precedente relativamente às negociações atualmente em curso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu venho de uma região, os Açores, em que a produção do leite representa 30 % da produção nacional, e, por esta razão, e por ser uma região ultraperiférica, o setor corre sérios riscos de sofrer com este embargo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gostaria de fazer um apelo aos colegas e às colegas, aos responsáveis políticos europeus, para não desperdiçarmos esta oportunidade para questionar, sem preconceitos, o fim das quotas leiteiras e as consequências que a falta de um mecanismo eficaz de regulação dos mercados trará aos produtores de leite da Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-000" speaker_id="4507" name="Bas Belder" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Het importverbod treft onze landbouwsector en ook de Europese visserijsector hard. En welke sector is de volgende? Het bedrag van 125 miljoen euro is niet voldoende. Ik vraag de Commissie om minimaal één miljard euro vrij te maken en dat bedrag mag niet ten koste gaan van de begroting voor de landbouw, dat wil ik onderstrepen. Dit is immers een politieke crisis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Onder hoofdstuk 4 op de begroting is geld voor internationale politieke ontwikkelingen. En daar zijn nog veel ongebruikte middelen beschikbaar. Ik heb hierover een amendement ingediend bij de Begrotingscommissie dat ik u, mijnheer de commissaris, graag zal toezenden. Ik hoop op uw steun, collega's!</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot twee korte vragen: is de Commissie in staat om het onrechtmatig gebruik van de middelen uit te sluiten en is de Commissie bereid toestemming te geven voor crisiskartels om zo het aanbod op de markt te beperken? Graag een update hierover.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-000" speaker_id="1654" name="Εμμανουήλ Γλέζος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Επίτροπε, σας ερωτώ ευθέως αν, όταν οι αρχές της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης λάμβαναν τα μέτρα αυτά, γνώριζαν ή όχι - είχαν προβλέψει ή όχι - ότι θα υπήρχαν αντίμετρα από τη Ρωσία; Και πώς είχαν προβλέψει να αντιδράσουν στα αντίμετρα της Ρωσίας;</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεύτερον, γνώριζαν ή δεν γνώριζαν ότι τα μέτρα αυτά αφορούν κυρίως και πλήττουν την αγροτική οικονομία, δηλαδή τον πρωτογενή τομέα; Ήξεραν ή όχι ότι τα μέτρα πλήττουν ιδιαίτερα τους Έλληνες παραγωγούς οι οποίοι είναι παραγωγοί οπωρών; Τα οπωροφόρα δέντρα δεν είναι όπως τα μπρόκολα και τα λάχανα. Δεν είναι εύκολο να καταστρέψεις το δέντρο και να το αντικαταστήσεις με λάχανα και μπρόκολα. Έχει τεράστια σημασία αυτό.</p>
      <p sl="en">Και συνεχίζω: τί κονδύλια διαθέτει και τι ποσά χορηγεί το ταμείο διαχείρισης της κρίσης; Και το κυριότερο, στην "κοκορομαχία" αυτή ανάμεσα στη Ρωσία και την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, στο πλαίσιο δηλαδή της ατλαντικής κυρίως συμμαχίας, ποιός πληρώνει τα έξοδα μεταφοράς των στρατευμάτων του ΝΑΤΟ προς την Ουκρανία;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-000" speaker_id="124749" name="Marijana Petir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, moram istaknuti da ovo nije poljoprivredna kriza, već politički problem, stoga smatram da bi se poljoprivrednicima šteta nastala zbog ruskog embarga trebala nadoknaditi izvan poljoprivrednog proračuna koji ionako nedovoljno pokriva sve potrebe europskih poljoprivrednika.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dosadašnjim mjerama koje je poduzela Europska komisija nisu obuhvaćeni svi poljoprivredni proizvodi koji također čine znatan dio izvoza u Rusiju poput mlijeka, mesa ali i agruma. Dosad sam već nekoliko puta pozvala Europsku komisiju da pomogne proizvođačima mlijeka koji su ionako u teškoj krizi, a sukob s Rusijom samo im je dodao sol na ranu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nama u Hrvatskoj, ali i u ostalim mediteranskim zemljama važan udio izvoza u Rusiju čine mandarine koje se nisu našle na popisu proizvoda za koje će se nadoknaditi šteta, pa ja ovdje još jednom javno pozivam Europsku komisiju da napravi točne kalkulacije vodeći računa o specifičnostima država članica i da osigura sredstva za sve poljoprivrednike koji su se, ne svojom krivnjom, našli u teškoj situaciji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poljoprivrednim proizvođačima treba osigurati nova tržišta i Europska unija mora naći način kako zaštiti vlastitu proizvodnju hrane pa je nužan oprez kod zaključivanja novih trgovinskih sporazuma koji bi u konačnici mogli biti nepovoljni za europske poljoprivrednike. Jedno od zanimljivih tržišta za mlijeko, voće i povrće svakako su škole, stoga bi Europska komisija trebala povećati financijska sredstva kojima se subvencioniraju tzv. zdravi obroci za djecu u školama. Tu ponovo podsjećam na nužnost promjene kriterija kako bi se i Hrvatskoj, kao novoj državi članici, omogućilo da sudjeluje u tim programima, jer su sadašnji kriteriji diskriminirajući za nas i našu djecu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-000" speaker_id="112744" name="Tonino Picula" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, zabrana izvoza u Rusiju znači velik udarac europskoj poljoprivredi, jer je samo prošle godine Europska unija izvezla u Rusiju poljoprivredne proizvode vrijedne 12 milijardi eura. Usporedba vrijednosti izvoza s iznosima kompenzacija jasno pokazuje da će europski proizvođači biti snažno pogođeni ovim embargom. Posebno ističem male proizvođače koji cjenovno nisu konkurentni velikima s gotovo dumpinškim cijenama njihovih proizvoda, a koji su često i upitne kvalitete. Oni se teže prilagođavaju izvozu na druga svjetska tržišta jer ne raspolažu s dovoljno resursa. A upravo mala poljoprivredna gospodarstva u Hrvatskoj čine čak 90 % ukupnog broja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mandarine su tek jedan od hrvatskih proizvoda koji se nije našao na kompenzacijskoj listi, a na rusko je tržište trebalo otići gotovo 40 % ukupne proizvodnje. Snažno su pogođeni i proizvođači jabuka - sankcije su ozbiljno pogodile i Hrvatsku zbog čega se moraju pronaći adekvatnija rješenja.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-000" speaker_id="124820" name="Bernd Lucke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Ich möchte eigentlich im Wesentlichen eine Frage an die Kommission richten. Ich teile natürlich das hier ausgedrückte Bedauern über das Schicksal, das die Landwirte durch das russische Embargo erleiden, die unverschuldet Opfer dieses russischen Embargos werden, wobei dieses Opfer bis hin zur Existenzgefährdung gehen kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber meine Frage ist die: Hat die Kommission das und andere Verwundbarkeiten der Europäischen Union nicht bedacht, als sie Sanktionen entwickelt hat, als sie Sanktionen vorgeschlagen hat? Hat der Rat nicht bedacht, dass diese Verwundbarkeiten vorliegen und welche Auswirkungen das dann eben auf europäische Landwirte oder andere betroffene Wirtschaftsgruppen haben wird? Wenn das bedacht worden ist, warum ist das Europäische Parlament nicht darüber informiert worden und auch von Anfang an darüber informiert worden, welche Ausgleichsmaßnahmen möglich sind, damit man solidarisch diese Lasten auch abfängt? Ich habe den Eindruck, dass hier im Augenblick sehr holterdipolter versucht wird, in einer Form von Stückwerk Ausgleichsmechanismen zur Verfügung zu stellen, dass das aber nicht Teil einer wirklich von Anfang an durchdachten Strategie ist, und die wäre geboten gewesen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-000" speaker_id="96936" name="Gabriel Mato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, el embargo ruso a las producciones europeas no solo está teniendo serios efectos para nuestros agricultores y ganaderos, con especial incidencia en regiones más frágiles como Canarias, sino también para el sector pesquero y de la acuicultura, que se está viendo seriamente afectado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tengo que reconocer que en estos sectores me habría gustado que se hubiera actuado con la diligencia con que lo ha hecho el Comisario Cioloș, porque no debemos olvidar que las exportaciones de productos pesqueros a Rusia suponen el 5 % del total de la Unión Europea. De hecho, Rusia es nuestro sexto mercado en importancia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por esa razón, desde aquí, hoy quiero llamar la atención de la Comisión sobre los agricultores, pero también sobre nuestros pescadores, para que tenga en cuenta y actúe sobre las posibles consecuencias de esta crisis en los mercados, así como para que establezca las ayudas que puedan ser necesarias para el sector pesquero y de la acuicultura.</p>
      <p sl="en">Insto a la Comisión a que ponga en marcha todos los medios necesarios para ayudar al sector, incluyendo, en su caso, la modificación temporal de las cuotas asignadas anualmente, así como el establecimiento de ayudas, ya sea en relación con el almacenamiento —y un claro ejemplo de esta necesidad lo tenemos en la especie del marujito, de suma importancia para Galicia— o en la promoción de nuevos mercados o ayudas extraordinarias no incluidas en el Fondo Marítimo y de Pesca.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Unión Europea debe actuar en este sector con inmediatez. Tanto el sector agrario como el pesquero confían en ello.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, cela a été dit tout à l'heure, la Commission a réagi avec rapidité et dans les limites budgétaires qui sont les nôtres au niveau du budget agricole. Cela a été fait de manière rapide et efficace mais on sait que ce n'est pas suffisant.</p>
      <p sl="en">La première question fondamentale qui vient à l'esprit, c'est qu'il s'agit d'une crise politique dérivée d'une situation difficile, mais que ses conséquences, aujourd'hui, sont vécues, notamment et surtout par les producteurs de fruits et légumes, et par les producteurs de lait également. N'y a-t-il donc que le budget agricole qui doive être sollicité et ne peut-on pas en faire intervenir un autre, de manière à répondre efficacement? Il y a urgence puisque la récolte des fruits, notamment des pommes et des poires, c'est maintenant et dans quelques jours.</p>
      <p sl="en">D'autre part, on ne peut pas pénaliser tous les producteurs de divers pays parce que dans certains on n'a peut-être pas comptabilisé correctement les ayants droit. Donc, la récente suspension de l'aide de 125 millions n'est sans doute pas le signal approprié.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a deux points essentiels en ce qui me concerne. En tant qu'ancien rapporteur sur l'aide aux plus démunis, je veux rappeler que beaucoup de citoyens européens vivent sous le seuil de pauvreté et que, très clairement, on peut très bien – c'est Mme Tiziana Beghin qui l'a dit avant moi – racheter la production et la mettre à disposition des banques alimentaires, en tout cas pour une distribution efficace. C'est fondamental.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxième point: je me suis transformé en vendeur de poires et de pommes sur un marché de ma région et j'ai mesuré la réceptivité des citoyens à consommer autrement et à aider les producteurs. Par conséquent, ne pourrions-nous profiter de l'occasion – et je sais que ce dossier sera examiné dans ce Parlement – pour commencer et réinitialiser un nouveau programme, un programme d'alimentation au niveau de l'école, de rééducation à l'alimentation qui serait fondamental. Il est bien légitime d'aller conquérir d'autres marchés extérieurs mais il faut aussi renforcer la demande intérieure.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, θα ήμουν και εγώ ευτυχής αν είχε σταματήσει το ρολόι για να μπορώ να μιλήσω παραπάνω. Κύριε Επίτροπε, δεν μας πείσατε με τις απαντήσεις που δώσατε και μάλλον δημιουργήσατε μεγαλύτερες ανησυχίες στους αγρότες στον ευρωπαϊκό Νότο. Η ζημιά που έχουν υποστεί είναι τεράστια! Και τα ποσά τα οποία προβλέψατε, αυτά τα 125 εκατομμύρια ευρώ, είναι ψίχουλα, αλλά ακόμη και αυτά δεν έχουν δοθεί. Πέραν τούτου, δεν μας έχετε εξηγήσει για ποιον λόγο δεν προωθείται η καταβολή ποσών από το αποθεματικό Ταμείο. Σε μια φάση που φτωχοποιείται ο ευρωπαϊκός Νότος, όταν με τις πολιτικές λιτότητας οι αγρότες μας είχαν αναζητήσει τουλάχιστον μία διέξοδο, είχαν επιδιώξει να βγουν τα προϊόντα τους, και το είχαν πετύχει, στις αγορές της Ρωσίας. Σήμερα λοιπόν καταστρέφονται οι παραγωγοί ροδάκινων στην Πέλλα, στην Ημαθία, όσοι παράγουν οπωροκηπευτικά στην Κρήτη.</p>
      <p sl="en">Σας είχα λοιπόν υποβάλει ερώτηση ήδη από τις αρχές Αυγούστου για να απαντήσετε στο θέμα αυτό. Καταθέσαμε κοινή δήλωση, εγώ και οι συνάδελφοι από τα Πέντε Αστέρια, τι μέτρα πρέπει να ληφθούν για την αντιμετώπιση του προβλήματος, για να σώσουμε τους αγρότες μας. Πρέπει να έχετε ρεαλιστική πολιτική. Φτωχοποιείται ο Νότος και δεν είναι δυνατόν οι αγρότες μας να υφίστανται, ως παράπλευρες απώλειες, τις συνέπειες μιας παράλογης ψυχροπολεμικής πολιτικής μεταξύ της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και της Ρωσίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-000" speaker_id="96978" name="Nuno Melo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, com brevidade só para, em boa verdade, interpelar a comissão numa oportunidade privilegiada porque de forma direta e tem que ver com um documento que foi distribuído recentemente na reunião da COM AGRI a propósito da reação a adotar em relação a este embargo russo e a dado passo nesse documento pode ler-se na nota informativa que no caso de redução de, enfim, no caso de decidirem compensações diretas ao nível nacional ou ao nível europeu, poderá ser decidida a redução dos pagamentos diretos aos agricultores.</p>
      <p sl="en">O que me parece sensato no caso de dificuldades para com os agricultores em razão das medidas de combate ao embargo é que aos pagamentos diretos pudessem acrescer estas compensações. E eu confesso que dessa reunião da Comissão da Agricultura ficou-me essa dúvida. Eu já interpelei o Sr. Comissário por escrito mas, por se tratar de um instrumento fundamental para combater as consequências do embargo - e eu percebo que, do ponto de vista externo, tenha que haver uma consequência para a Rússia por aquilo que está a acontecer na Ucrânia - mas, porque essas consequências têm um impacto financeiro direto relativamente aos agricultores nas compensações que possam ser atribuídas aos agricultores para debelar o problema do embargo, justificar-se-ia, parece-me, que uma coisa não implicasse a exclusão da outra, ou seja, decidindo a comissão compensações diretas, essas compensações não deviam diminuir os pagamentos diretos aos agricultores. E, no fundo, era esse esclarecimento que eu gostaria de ter do Sr. Comissário.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Egy olyan kérdésről beszélgetünk jelen pillanatban, amelynek csak az elejét láttuk, nem tudjuk, hogy mi ennek a közép vagy hosszú távú kifutása. Azt viszont határozottan tudjuk – és ez talán tanulságként levonható –, hogy az orosz piac bizony hosszú távon is bizonytalannak tekintendő. Az európai szankciók egyébként olyanok voltak, amelyek nem fájtak a mindennapok embereinek. Az orosz oligarchákat, az orosz pénzügyi és hadiipari csoportokat sújtották. Szerintem ez okos lépés volt. A Putyin által bevezetett embargó ugyanakkor nemcsak az európai agrártermelőknek, de bizony az orosz embereknek is fáj. Éppen ezért azt nyugodtan a politikai következtetések sorába emelhetjük, hogy ez ügyben Vlagyimir Putyin mérhetetlen bűncselekményt követett el. Ugyanakkor az egyes európai termelőknek különböző módon fáj ez az embargó. A lengyel almatermelőknek talán a legjobban, de akár a skót, igen a skót mezőgazdasági termelőknek is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az élelmiszer ugyanakkor nem arra való, hogy megsemmisítsük, nem arra való, hogy be se takarítsuk, és még csak arra se való, hogy raktározgassuk drága pénzen. Hanem arra való, hogy megegyük! Európa válasza az kell legyen erre az orosz embargóra, hogy megesszük a saját élelmiszerünket. Rengeteg éhes ember van itt is. Tarabella képviselőtársam is és mások is világosan elmondták, fiatalok, gyerekek, idősek, szociálisan hátrányos helyzetben lévők nagyon-nagyon hamar meg tudják enni ezt az élelmiszerfelesleget. Az 500 milliós belső piac értékét ne becsüljük alá! Képviselőtársaim, fejenként, európai polgáronként tízeurós problémáról beszélünk. Nekem ne mondja senki, hogy nem tudunk tíz eurónyival több élelmiszert adni a gyermekeinknek. De ha már olyan nehéz szülés ez a gondolat, akkor annyit mondok, legrosszabb esetben vigyük oda az éhező ukránoknak, Kelet-Ukrajnában nagyon sokan vannak!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-000" speaker_id="124732" name="Angélique Delahaye" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, l'Union européenne a engagé un bras de fer avec la Russie, bras de fer qui a des conséquences désastreuses pour nos agriculteurs: ce sont les effets collatéraux d'une crise diplomatique. Sans remettre en cause l'action qui est menée, j'estime qu'il est de notre devoir de les soutenir. Bien que la Commission européenne ait réagi rapidement en mettant à disposition une enveloppe de 125 millions d'euros pour les fruits et légumes, cela est clairement insuffisant. L'enveloppe a déjà été dépassée.</p>
      <p sl="en">J'aimerais aussi lancer quelques pistes de réflexion. Le prix de retrait des produits est beaucoup trop bas et ne couvre pas, dans de nombreux pays, le coût de production. C'est le cas de la France. Cette mesure est inutilisable pour certains États membres. Que compte faire la Commission européenne à ce sujet?</p>
      <p sl="en">Concernant les mesures de promotion, il n'est pas acceptable qu'elles soient cofinancées par les producteurs. Demander un euro aux producteurs pour que la Commission puisse en mettre un est injustifiable et n'est absolument pas compris par les producteurs. Surtout que je rappelle que ce n'est pas une crise de marché, ni une crise sanitaire mais bien une crise diplomatique.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Commission européenne réfléchit-elle également à la possibilité d'un déplafonnement des de minimis? En effet, ces plafonds ont été atteints ces dernières années par de nombreuses crises rencontrées par les entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains ont parlé d'aides aux plus démunis, de distribution de fruits et légumes à la récré … Monsieur le Commissaire, votre proposition de fusion des deux dispositifs "lait" et "fruits et légumes" est juste une fausse bonne idée. Je suis prête à en reparler avec vous.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, les actions qui sont aujourd'hui proposées sont des actions d'urgence pour les besoins directs du marché mais ce n'est que la partie émergée de l'iceberg. Les producteurs auront besoin d'actions à long terme, notamment pour reconquérir les marchés qui ont été perdus. Y a-t-il des réflexions dans ce sens?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario, la crisi russa minaccia il settore agroalimentare europeo in modo drammatico. I numeri delle esportazioni dei paesi UE verso la Russia sono impressionanti, ma altrettanto impressionanti sono gli effetti negativi di questo embargo, sia in termini di perdite già subite dal settore sia per la chiusura delle prospettive di crescita tanto necessarie per il rilancio del settore agroalimentare.</p>
      <p sl="en">È evidente quindi l'urgenza di provvedere ad individuare misure urgenti di incentivazione, in particolare nei settori dell'ortofrutta, lattiero-caseario e della carne, affinché le imprese del settore possano risollevarsi dagli effetti di una crisi tutta politica e vengano aiutate ad individuare altri mercati di sbocco, così come è opportuno un intervento per cambiare in tempi rapidi le modalità di applicazione e di ripartizione tra i diversi paesi degli aiuti già stanziati. Penso che si debba lavorare per provvedere allo stanziamento di compensazioni mirate, così come, verificate le disponibilità di bilancio da parte della Commissione europea, auspico l'adozione di misure straordinarie, nonché misure per l'anticipazione del pagamento agli agricoltori dei fondi della PAC, come già ipotizzato dal ministro dell'Agricoltura Maurizio Martina.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quanto detto dal Commissario Cioloș è senz'altro apprezzabile, ma non è sufficiente. Quello che chiedo però è la tempestività dell'azione dell'Unione europea. Gli agricoltori europei non possono attendere, anche perché, come si dice dalle mie parti, mentre il medico studia, il malato rischia di morire.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-000" speaker_id="96771" name="Jarosław Kalinowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Skutki embarga są bardzo poważne dla rolnictwa całej Unii Europejskiej, szczególnie jednak dotkliwe są one dla państw Europy Środkowo-Wschodniej, zwłaszcza dla rolników z Polski. Widać wyraźnie, że proponowane kwoty wsparcia są daleko niewystarczające, stąd cieszę się z zapowiedzi Pana Komisarza dotyczącej kolejnych działań w tym zakresie.</p>
      <p sl="en">W ostatnim tygodniu, co zrozumiałe, najwięcej uwagi poświęcaliśmy kwestii owoców i warzyw, musimy jednak pamiętać o stratach producentów mleka i mięsa. Apeluję nie tylko do Komisji Europejskiej, ale również do państw członkowskich, które blokowały zmianę, korektę współczynnika tłuszczowego, aby w sytuacji drastycznego spadku cen na mleko nie karać producentów mleka dodatkowo za przekroczenie kwot produkcyjnych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uważam również stosowanie nawet o połowę mniejszych rekompensat dla producentów niezrzeszonych w grupach producentów za działanie wręcz dyskryminujące. Oczywiście, preferowanie tworzenia grup producentów, wspieranie tworzenia grup producentów jest działaniem ze wszech miar dobrym, natomiast karanie w sytuacji tego kryzysu związanego z embargiem jest absolutnie złym rozwiązaniem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-000" speaker_id="94282" name="Jean-Paul Denanot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, je considère, comme beaucoup de collègues, qu'il était nécessaire d'agir vite, de manière concertée et solidaire au niveau européen et je voudrais vous en remercier.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'est l'avenir même d'un certain nombre d'exploitations, notamment de petites exploitations, qui était en jeu. Nous avons pu le faire, je le rappelle, grâce aux outils de gestion et de soutien du marché dont nous avons fermement défendu le maintien au sein de la PAC. Mais l'aide financière disponible doit être délivrée aux agriculteurs les plus touchés par cette crise. Sa gestion doit être la plus efficace et la plus transparente possible. Une suspension d'une partie de ce soutien était décidée, je vous le rappelle, la semaine dernière à cause de certains abus. Il convient de corriger au plus vite cette situation en ciblant davantage le soutien apporté et en le rendant le plus efficace possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, je voudrais vous dire qu'il y aura sans doute d'autres produits pour lesquels le soutien de l'Europe sera nécessaire. Je pense notamment à la viande sur pied et à la viande bovine sur pied, qui étaient exportées en Russie et qui sont interrompues aujourd'hui. Je pense aussi qu'il faudra travailler sur la question de l'aide humanitaire, comme beaucoup de collègues l'ont rappelé. Pour cela il faudra des financements complémentaires. Et je pense à la mise en place de la taxation sur les transactions financières, qui devient une urgence.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-000" speaker_id="125030" name="Annie Schreijer-Pierik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ik wil de commissaris hartelijk danken voor hetgeen hij gezegd heeft, maar in Nederland is er veel gebeurd. Het vliegtuigongeluk op donderdag 17 juli met de MH17 bracht de oorlog in Oekraïne voor Nederland dichtbij. Nederland is diep geraakt door die vreselijke gebeurtenis. Kort daarna werden wij getroffen door de Russische handelsboycot, die vele van onze boeren, tuinders en vissers in de problemen bracht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Afgelopen week heeft de Russische regering opnieuw sancties aangekondigd tegen de westerse landen, waardoor Europa opnieuw hard zal worden getroffen. Omdat de Russische sancties een directe reactie zijn op de economische strafmaatregelen van het westen, is het creëren van draagvlak onder de Europese bevolking van groot belang. Want alleen met behulp van politieke en economische druk kunnen wij hopen op vrede en stabiliteit. Daarom verzoek ik de commissaris om uitdrukkelijk te vragen morgen de voorgedragen resolutie voor meer geld duidelijk te ondersteunen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik bepleit dat niet zomaar, want alleen al in Nederland hebben wij meer dan een miljard euro nodig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot moet het onrechtmatig gebruik worden uitgesloten. Als het gaat om het crisiskartel - want onze staatssecretaris in Nederland heeft nogal kritiek op u - zou dit duidelijk kunnen zorgen voor snelle oplossingen. Want men heeft het gevoel dat dit in Europa veel te lang duurt en onze boeren en tuinders met de gevolgen blijven zitten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule comisar, felicitări pentru felul în care ați gestionat dificila problemă cu Rusia, dar doresc să ridic problema impactului real al embargoului impus de Rusia asupra produselor alimentare din Uniunea Europeană și, în acest context, trebuie discutată, evident, chestiunea despăgubirilor și a modului în care acestea vor fi calculate și acordate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu doar prin imposibilitatea de a livra aceste mărfuri către Rusia s-au înregistrat pierderi, ci și prin anularea unui număr mare de comenzi pe piața intracomunitară. Practic, alimentele europene refuzate de Rusia, rămase în Europa au saturat piețele interne și au făcut imposibilă derularea în condiții normale a unor schimburi comerciale practicate în mod curent în anii anteriori. De exemplu, un producător român care vindea în mod tradițional pe piața germană găsește în acest an o piață suprasaturată, la fel ca alte piețe europene. Prin urmare, în depozite s-au adunat stocuri uriașe, iar marfa se strică. Practic, producătorii români au pierdut până acum jumătate din recoltă. Dacă alte state au pierdut piața rusească, România a pierdut piețele pe care s-au redirijat alimentele destinate Rusiei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu putem gândi simplist. Trebuie să acceptăm că toate statele au pierdut pentru că piețele au fost bulversate. De aceea, orice ajutor acordat trebuie să aibă în vedere acest aspect al crizei: blocarea comerțului agricol și alimentar intracomunitar și nu doar vânzările efective către Rusia. De aceea, domnule comisar, solicit un punct de vedere pe această chestiune.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-000" speaker_id="124767" name="Edouard Ferrand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je vous remercie de me donner la parole malgré mon retard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Force est de constater, Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, que nous nous sommes tiré une balle dans le pied et que nous sommes tombés dans le piège des sanctions.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Union européenne ne propose que 125 millions d'euros au secteur maraîcher, alors que l'embargo russe touche la totalité des productions agricoles. Votre action est catastrophique chez nous, en France. Voici quelques chiffres: - 12 % pour les fruits, - 13 % sur les légumes, - 20 % sur les pommes, les poires, les melons, les pêches. La tonne de poudre de lait est passée de 2 900 à 2 300 euros. La tonne de beurre de 3 500 à 3 000 euros. Je ne saurais également oublier nos amis hollandais qui, avec leurs 250 000 tonnes d'Edam, exportent également vers la Russie. Enfin, les éleveurs de porcs chez nous, d'après les évaluations du comité régional porcin de Bretagne, ont déjà perdu 15 euros par porc, soit 70 000 euros pour un éleveur moyen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Messieurs de la Commission européenne et du Conseil, il est grand temps de mettre fin à cette politique irresponsable de l'Union européenne. La France est le troisième fournisseur de la Russie pour les produits agro-alimentaires, pour un montant annuel d'un milliard d'euros. Je n'ai qu'un seul conseil à vous donner ce soir: changez de politique! Pensez à nos agriculteurs, levez l'embargo!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-092-000" speaker_id="38605" name="Илияна Йотова" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Благодаря, г-н Комисар, че се опитахте да търсите бързи решения в създалата се криза. Но Европейският съюз не е намерил ефективното лекарство за лечението на последиците от ембаргото.</p>
      <p sl="en">За малки страни като България преките и косвени загуби са огромни. Фалитите чукат на вратите на много фермери. Днес ние не можем да им отговорим нито за сроковете на ембаргото, нито дали ще има промяна в политиката, нито дали бюджетът на ОСП за обезщетение ще стигне и докога.</p>
      <p sl="en">Казвате, че ще има нови мерки. Чуйте този път и българските земеделци, защото това, което предлагате, не отчита спецификите в държавите членки. Обезщетенията трябва да са достъпни и бързи, но бюрокрацията ги убива. Обещанията за нови пазари са все още само обещания и не са заменили руските. Трябва да се компенсират и съвместните програми с Русия, съфинансирани от Европейския съюз, защото иначе загубите ще са огромни.</p>
      <p sl="en">Спиралата на икономическите санкции е безкрайна, но до този момент не е решение на нито един проблем.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-000" speaker_id="125068" name="Μανώλης Κεφαλογιάννης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, είχατε γρήγορα αντανακλαστικά, όταν πήρατε τα μέτρα τον προηγούμενο Αύγουστο. Αλλά η κρίση δεν άρχισε με το εμπάργκο στη Ρωσία. Η κρίση άρχισε με την εμπόλεμη κατάσταση στην Ουκρανία. Για αυτό πολλές φορές, και κυρίως οι χώρες της Νοτιοανατολικής Ευρώπης, αντιμετώπισαν τεράστια προβλήματα. Κάθε χώρα έχει τη δική της ιστορία. Για παράδειγμα, για την Ελλάδα οι επιπτώσεις επικεντρώνονται στον τομέα των οπωροκηπευτικών. Το 65% των εξαγωγών οπωροκηπευτικών από την Ελλάδα πηγαίνει στη Ρωσία. Για την Ελλάδα είναι αδύνατη η προσέγγιση των αγορών στη Ρωσία και, κυρίως, στη Νότια Ρωσία. Χρειάζεται να διανύσουν 1.500 χιλιόμετρα για να πάνε μέσα από τη Λευκορωσία. Έτσι και το κόστος μεγαλώνει και οι τιμές των προϊόντων συμπιέζονται. Παραδείγματος χάριν, για τα ροδάκινα, που επλήγησαν περισσότερο από οποιοδήποτε άλλο προϊόν στη χώρα μας, οι τιμές έχουν μειωθεί από τα 70 και 80 λεπτά στα 15 και 20 λεπτά. Η ζημιά που θα ακολουθήσει αφορά και άλλα προϊόντα: τα ακτινίδια, τα εσπεριδοειδή, τα αχλάδια, τις ντομάτες, τα αγγούρια, ένα σωρό προϊόντα που παράγονται κυρίως στον ευρωπαϊκό Νότο.</p>
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Επίτροπε, αυτό που θα θέλαμε και αυτό που σας ζητούμε είναι να ληφθούν άμεσα νέα μέτρα. Και στα άμεσα αυτά νέα μέτρα να μην υπάρχει διάκριση μεταξύ των μεμονωμένων παραγωγών και των παραγωγών που είναι οργανωμένοι. Ζητούμε να ενεργοποιήσετε όλα τα ταμεία που προβλέπονται στους κανονισμούς της ΕΕ για να ενισχύσετε τους παραγωγούς σε όλη την Ευρώπη και κυρίως στη Νότια Ευρώπη.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-000" speaker_id="112748" name="Biljana Borzan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, zadnji sastanak Vijeća ministara je pokazao da mjere koje je odredila Komisija nisu dostatne ni sredstvima ni obimom. Uz to, mjere koje bi pomogle proizvođačima određenih vrsta voća i povrća u vrijednosti 125 milijuna eura su obustavljene zbog prevelikog broja zahtjeva. U ovakvim situacijama ključne su dvije stvari: razrađene mjere i brza reakcija.</p>
      <p sl="en">U zajedničkom nam je interesu da svi zajedno što prije i što kvalitetnije riješimo nastalu situaciju, ali naglašavam, uvažavajući međusobne specifičnosti. Hrvatska izvozi 1,3 % poljoprivredno-prehrambenih proizvoda na rusko tržište. Posebno smo zabrinuti zbog izvoza voća, ponajprije mandarina, koji je višestruko porastao u zadnjih nekoliko godina. Unatoč tome, agrumi zasad nisu uključeni u shemu Komisije.</p>
      <p sl="en">Smatram da je nužno što prije reagirati na specifične zahtjeve svih država članica zbog egzistencije gospodarstvenika koja ovisi o pravovremenoj reakciji, ali i zbog činjenice da se poremećaji na tržištu jedne države članice prelijevaju na druge čime uvećavaju njihove posljedice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, ruski odgovor na sankcije dolazi u obliku ove zabrane koja je vrlo bolna za europske proizvođače hrane. Mnogi će od njih vjerojatno postaviti pitanje: „Je li Europskoj uniji bio potreban angažman oko Ukrajine koji nas sad prilično skupa košta?” Vjerujem da jest, jer smatram da treba činiti pravu stvar unatoč posljedicama.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pozdravljam Komisijin paket interventnih mjera u sektoru voća i povrća te držim da ne smijemo dozvoliti da ovaj teret padne isključivo na leđa europskih proizvođača. Također pozivam Komisiju da u paket uključi i mandarine, jer će hrvatski proizvođači mandarina ovom zabranom biti posebno pogođeni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naime, 50 % izvoza hrvatskih mandarina odlazi na rusko tržište što znači da će u postojećim okolnostima hrvatski proizvođači izgubiti više od 10 milijuna eura. Takav gubitak može ostaviti devastirajuće posljedice na sektor poljoprivrede u maloj zemlji kao što je Hrvatska.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, creo que el debate que plantea esta pregunta es tan necesario como las sanciones que se están imponiendo a Rusia por su actuación en el conflicto de Ucrania. Espero que la vía del diálogo —más clara hoy que en agosto— dé sus frutos; mientras, los productores y transformadores de productos agropecuarios y pesqueros no pueden ser los paganos de estas medidas. Quiero insistir especialmente en el sector pesquero.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rusia importó productos frescos o transformados de pesca desde Europa por valor de 115 millones de euros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quisiera saber si, efectivamente, como anunció la Comisaria en su blog, se van a movilizar, sin más trámite, recursos del Fondo Marítimo y de Pesca para compensar estas pérdidas; si parte de los productos no almacenables a medio plazo pueden dedicarse de modo sistemático a paliar las necesidades de los europeos más afectados por la crisis; y, finalmente, cómo se va a concretar la propuesta sobre las cuotas no usadas el año pasado para poder mejorar las expectativas de renta para el sector en 2015.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Scottish whisky exports to Russia do not seem, on the face of it, very much at GBP 25 million. However, another GBP 200 million worth of Scottish whisky gets to Russia via Germany, Latvia and Estonia. It is a direct carousel. If there is any compensation going begging, Commissioner, it ought to go to the producers of Scottish whisky in Scotland and not to those who simply trade it on. As you know, the UK is a very substantial net contributor to the common agricultural policy, and some of that money coming back to Scotland would be very useful. Scotland is an important part of the United Kingdom.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are 143 million people living in Russia. They are not going to stop eating. Food originally produced in the European Union will find its way there somehow. I urge the Commission not to obstruct these rather unofficial processes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-000" speaker_id="96951" name="Diane Dodds" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in Northern Ireland the greatest impact of the Russian import ban is on the dairy sector. I am therefore calling on the Commission to review the prices set for intervention and to reintroduce export refunds as a priority. Introducing these measures would protect the industry and stabilise markets across the EU. I would also call on the Commission to ensure that these safety-net tools and compensation are delivered quickly, effectively and fairly, and not just to Member States which border Russia.</p>
      <p sl="en">A final word for the Commissioner: please do not give in to those Member States which have broken the rules and over-produced milk which they will be releasing into a market which is already experiencing a downward spiral in prices, thereby penalising farmers like those in Northern Ireland who have kept to the rules.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">V Ukrajini poteka vojaško - politični konflikt, umirajo nedolžni ljudje v Ukrajini, umrli so ljudje, ki so se peljali nedolžni v potniškem letalu, naslednje žrtve pa so evropski kmetje, ki izgubljajo trg.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ključna rešitev tega konflikta in te krize je, da sede diplomacija za mizo in da se ta vojaški konflikt čim prej konča in da se najde politična rešitev.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kar se tiče ukrepov na področju kmetijstva pozdravljam ukrepe, ki jih je pripravila Komisijia, komisarju Cioloşu in njegov ekipi čestitam za te ukrepe in naj še naprej tako budno, tedensko spremljajo, kaj se na teh trgih dogaja, in tudi ukrepajo podobno, kot so doslej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sam zelo podpiram, da gredo ukrepi v smer stimuliranja iskanja novih trgov in pa nikakor ne v uničenje izdelkov, ampak rajši, da te izdelke, kot je v ukrepih predvideno, podarimo tistim, ki so te hrane potrebni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato pozdravljam ukrepe, spremljajte naprej, politika pa naj čim prej najde političo rešitev, da se konča vojaški konflikt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-000" speaker_id="125044" name="José Blanco López" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora Presidenta, es indudable que yo no cuestiono el embargo a Rusia, las sanciones a Rusia, pero es indudable que la respuesta que ha dado la Comisión Europea no es ni eficaz ni suficiente para sectores que, en algunos territorios, son sectores estratégicos por el peso que tienen: por ejemplo, el sector lácteo o el sector pesquero en la región de la que soy natural, Galicia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por lo tanto, es necesario demandar a la Unión Europea una mayor dotación de recursos. Estamos hablando de exportaciones de mucha entidad frente a unos recursos presupuestados, por parte de la Unión, más bien insuficientes. Por lo tanto, son necesarios mayores recursos. Lo que está ocurriendo es consecuencia de una decisión de la Unión Europea y por lo tanto, no debe recaer sobre la política agraria común. Deben asignarse recursos extraordinarios y debe hacerse con mayor celeridad y con mayor eficiencia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dacian Cioloş" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. - Madame la Présidente, en effet, il y a beaucoup de questions. Je vais essayer de répondre au maximum d'entre elles de manière synthétique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout d'abord, certains d'entre vous – et uniquement certains, heureusement – s'interrogent sur l'utilité des sanctions et se demandent si la Commission a prévu les conséquences des décisions qu'elle a prises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je veux juste souligner – mais vous le savez – que ce n'est pas la Commission qui a pris les sanctions contre la Russie, c'est l'Union européenne. Et c'est le Conseil qui a clairement décidé à une très large majorité politique. Donc je ne peux pas commenter davantage cette décision qui a été prise et qui a été assumée politiquement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce que nous avons fait concernant l'impact de l'embargo russe, c'est aussi d'assumer notre responsabilité en tant qu'Union européenne envers le secteur agricole.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains d'entre vous disent que la Commission n'a pas réagi suffisamment rapidement. L'embargo a été décidé le 7 août et le 11 août, nous avons déjà lancé la première mesure pour le secteur "pêches et nectarines" qui était déjà d'ailleurs touché, comme certains d'entre vous l'ont dit, même avant l'embargo russe, mais dont la situation a été aggravée par ce dernier. Donc, après quelques jours seulement, nous avons pris la première mesure, dix jours après le gros paquet pour les fruits et légumes et encore dix jours plus tard, toujours au mois d'août, les mesures pour le secteur laitier. Je rappelle ce que j'ai dit dans mon introduction, c'était le secteur qui était le plus touché.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pourquoi n'avons-nous visé que certains fruits et légumes et non pas tous? Nous avons visé tout ce qui rentrait dans la catégorie "produits de saison". Je vous le rappelle, tout ce que nous avons mis sur la liste de produits devant faire l'objet d'une intervention était convenu avec les États membres. En effet, dès la mi-août, nous avons organisé la première réunion avec les experts des États membres et c'est seulement après ce type de réunions avec les États membres que nous avons décidé quelle était la liste. J'ai clairement dit au moment où nous avons pris ces premières mesures que, si nécessaire, d'autres mesures suivraient. Donc, les agrumes, y compris les mandarines, suivront sur cette liste. Il y aura aussi plus de pommes, il y aura des poires ainsi que d'autres produits de saison qui seront intégrés dans ce que la Commission proposera.</p>
      <p sl="en">Par conséquent, nous avons pris en compte l'urgence et nous avons pris en compte, en termes d'enveloppe, tout ce que nous avons estimé nécessaire. Vous avez retenu 125 millions d'euros parce que c'était le chiffre qui était le plus véhiculé par la presse. Mais avant de mobiliser les 125 millions d'euros pour les fruits et légumes, nous avions déjà mobilisé 30 millions d'euros pour les pêches et les nectarines, qui étaient donc dès le 11 août à la disposition des producteurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">À ceci se rajoutent aussi les mesures pour le secteur laitier, pour le stockage privé pour lequel nous avons estimé les besoins à environ 30 millions d'euros. Mais le stockage privé pour le fromage, le beurre et le lait en poudre est toujours ouvert. Là, nous n'avons pas de limites, parce que c'est le principe de cette mesure. Nous estimons les besoins mais quand la mesure de stockage privé est ouverte pour une certaine période, nous prenons en compte tout ce que le producteur décide de stocker et de ne pas vendre. Le producteur prend la décision de stocker s'il considère que le prix du marché est trop bas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains ici ont dit que les mesures sont insuffisantes pour le secteur laitier. Nous avons mobilisé toutes les mesures que nous avions dans les filets de sécurité et qui sont à la disposition des producteurs. Ce sont eux qui décident s'ils les utilisent ou pas en fonction de l'évolution du marché.</p>
      <p sl="en">J'en conclus que la Commission a agi rapidement, le plus vite possible, qu'elle a agi de manière proportionnée puisque le montant que nous avons proposé, par exemple, pour les fruits et légumes, est de 125 millions d'euros plus 30 millions d'euros pour les pêches et les nectarines. Je vous rappelle que c'est l'estimation de la valeur de ce que nous avions exporté vers la Russie et qui devait être retiré. Quand on retire du marché, quand on n'utilise pas cette production dans l'industrie, nous couvrons le coût de ce retrait.</p>
      <p sl="en">Là aussi, je souligne que nous avons surtout insisté, dans le retrait du marché, sur la distribution gratuite. Certains d'entre vous ont proposé différentes idées sur ce qui devrait être fait à l'échelle européenne pour cette distribution gratuite en faveur des personnes les plus démunies. Les producteurs et notamment les organisations de producteurs ont toute liberté d'utiliser pour la distribution gratuite la quantité qu'ils souhaitent de tous les produits qu'ils retirent. Pour tous les produits retirés et qui sont distribués gratuitement, la compensation financière prévue par le règlement est un financement européen à 100 %. C'est seulement pour les produits qui sont retirés et qui sont dédiés au compostage ou à la biodégradation qu'un cofinancement est nécessaire de la part des producteurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc, nous avons clairement encouragé la distribution gratuite et les États membres ont toute liberté en la matière puisque c'est ce que prévoit le règlement du législateur, à savoir du Conseil et du Parlement. Ce sont les États membres qui mettent en œuvre le programme de distribution gratuite de fruits et légumes et de lait dans les écoles et les États membres ont donc toute la liberté d'utiliser toutes les marges qu'ils ont à leur disposition pour augmenter les quantités de distribution gratuite. De ce point de vue, nous avons aussi fait le maximum pour que les produits qui sont retirés puissent être distribués gratuitement.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'était l'urgence et nous avons agi rapidement et de manière proportionnée. En termes de dotations budgétaires, comme je vous le disais, nous préparons pour les prochains jours – j'espère être en mesure de l'annoncer cette semaine – un nouveau paquet de mesures pour les fruits et légumes, qui va prendre en compte une nouvelle enveloppe substantielle calculée sur la base des réalités sur le terrain. Demain, nous tiendrons une autre réunion avec les États membres où nous discuterons de ces propositions. Nous annoncerons ensuite le nouveau paquet de mesures qui inclura les autres produits de saison, dont vous avez cité certains.</p>
      <p sl="en">Que faudra-t-il faire après si l'embargo se prolonge? D'une manière ou d'une autre, au-delà des mesures urgentes que nous avons prises, nous devons aussi envisager de diversifier encore plus nos marchés. Mais la chose la plus importante que nous pouvons faire, c'est encourager les producteurs, puisque ce sont eux qui décident où ils vendront – on ne peut les obliger à vendre dans un endroit et à ne pas vendre dans un autre. Ce que nous pouvons faire, c'est mettre à leur disposition les moyens pour qu'ils puissent chercher de nouveaux marchés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous envisageons des actions de promotion et des actions de communication mais aussi la diplomatie commerciale. La Commission actuelle fera tout ce qui est en son pouvoir jusqu'à la fin de son mandat pour essayer d'ouvrir d'autres marchés dont l'accès est maintenant limité pour les exportations de produits européens pour des raisons phytosanitaires. Moi-même, je ferai les démarches nécessaires. Le commissaire Karel De Gucht, ici présent, a déjà entamé ces démarches et je sais qu'il continuera. Nous conduirons ces mesures en parallèle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains d'entre vous ont dit que nous devrions peut-être renforcer la consommation sur le marché intérieur. Nous avons des moyens pour les actions de promotion et de communication sur le marché intérieur aussi. Je vous rappelle que le Parlement et le Conseil ont adopté récemment, au mois de juin, un règlement; c'était en fait le mandat du Parlement précédent, qui a adopté un nouveau règlement européen pour la promotion des produits agro-alimentaires. Nous allons ainsi augmenter l'enveloppe budgétaire pour la promotion entre 2014 et 2020, tant sur le marché intérieur que sur le marché extérieur.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'est donc cela que nous envisageons pour la suite. Tout d'abord, s'assurer que, pour les produits qui ne peuvent pas être revendus, notamment les produits périssables, nous avons des solutions immédiates. Et pour l'année prochaine, les agriculteurs sauront quelle est la situation du marché et ils prendront des décisions en matière de production, de type de production, de ciblage des marchés en fonction de la situation de l'embargo – selon qu'il continue ou non. Mais pour ce qui est de nos exportations vers la Russie, je pense que nous avons les moyens de réorienter cette production au fur et à mesure vers d'autres marchés.</p>
      <p sl="en">S'agissant du budget, beaucoup d'entre vous ont déclaré que le budget n'est pas suffisant et que la Commission doit mettre davantage d'argent. Il a même été suggéré de prévoir non pas quelques centaines de millions d'euros mais un milliard d'euros. Mais on mettra deux milliards d'euros, trois milliards d'euros si les États membres donnent cet argent à la Commission. Je vous rappelle que la Commission, quant à elle, n'a pas d'argent. Elle gère un budget décidé par les législateurs. Si, dans les perspectives budgétaires de 2014-2020, la décision a été de réduire le budget et, notamment, de réduire les marges de paiement de la Commission, elle ne peut aller au-delà. Ces dernières semaines, la Commission a essayé de gérer l'urgence en attribuant l'argent nécessaire. Ce n'est pas parce qu'on n'avait pas assez d'argent qu'on a mis 180 millions d'euros au total jusqu'à maintenant. C'est parce que, selon nos estimations avec les États membres, c'est le montant que nous avons jugé nécessaire. Mais nous avons toujours dit que nous étions prêts à prévoir davantage. Nous le ferons dans les prochains jours. Mais pour les compensations, il faudra clairement aller au-delà des marges dont dispose la Commission dans le budget et mobiliser la réserve de crise.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pourquoi n'avons-nous pas mobilisé jusqu'à maintenant la réserve de crise? Parce que ce n'était pas nécessaire tant que nous avions des marges dans le budget que nous avions décidé d'utiliser. C'est le principe de ce qu'on appelle en anglais le sound management, la gestion efficace du budget. Nous utilisons d'abord les marges et, ensuite, le cas échéant, nous mobilisons la réserve de crise. Je crois, effectivement, que nous aurons besoin de la mobiliser afin, notamment, de couvrir des mesures compensatoires dont nous devons discuter, nous, l'actuelle Commission ou la prochaine Commission. En tout cas, nous assumons notre responsabilité. C'est pour cette raison que la réserve de crise n'a pas été mobilisée mais rien n'empêche de la mobiliser et, si c'est nécessaire, il va de soi que nous le ferons.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous dites qu'il faut des critères de distribution plus justes. Nous avons des critères très clairs et, avec les propositions que nous ferons dans les prochains jours pour le secteur "fruits et légumes", ils seront encore plus clairs pour éviter justement des abus et des notifications qui ne sont pas tenables compte tenu des réalités sur le terrain.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains d'entre vous ont parlé de l'impact indirect de cet embargo russe. Ainsi, les États touchés sont non seulement ceux qui exportent vers la Russie, notamment les pays baltes, la Finlande, la Pologne, mais aussi l'Espagne, l'Italie, la Belgique, les Pays-Bas, qui sont également touchés tant directement qu'indirectement. Nous prenons en compte cet impact indirect en proposant des mesures de marché pour tous les États membres et pas seulement pour les États membres touchés. Mais, bien entendu, nous l'avons fait de manière proportionnée.</p>
      <p sl="en">S'agissant du secteur de la pêche – certains d'entre vous ont soulevé cette question –, je peux vous indiquer de la part de ma collègue, Maria Damanaki, qu'elle a déjà commencé les discussions avec les États membres et le secteur de la pêche. Des évaluations sont en cours pour voir quels types de mesures nous aurons besoin de mobiliser. Mais, clairement, nous ne pouvons pas comparer l'impact sur le secteur agricole et sur le secteur de la pêche. Dans l'agriculture, l'impact sur nos exportations était de l'ordre de milliards d'euros alors que pour le secteur de la pêche, il était – si je ne me trompe pas – de l'ordre de quelque 100 millions d'euros. Si cela est nécessaire pour le secteur de la pêche, nous prendrons des mesures, mais nous avons bien sûr ciblé en priorité le plus important, à savoir le secteur agricole.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certains d'entre vous ont demandé de lever les sanctions sur les quotas laitiers. À mon avis, ce serait totalement contreproductif: lever les sanctions sur le lait et avoir encore plus de lait sur le marché alors que nous avons déjà un surplus du fait de cet embargo russe. Par conséquent, je ne pense pas du tout que, dans la situation actuelle, la chose à faire soit de lever les sanctions sur les quotas et d'ouvrir le robinet pour la production.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vais m'arrêter là car j'ai l'impression d'avoir répondu à toutes les questions. Il y avait des questions plus précises sur lesquelles je suis prêt à discuter avec ceux d'entre vous qui seraient intéressés, notamment celles, plus techniques, sur le prix de retrait, sur le cofinancement, etc.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous remercie beaucoup pour le soutien que vous apportez aux mesures prises par la Commission et j'espère pouvoir compter sur le même soutien par la suite.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-500" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Wojciechowski, zur Geschäftsordnung, aber bitte nur zur Geschäftsordnung.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-000" speaker_id="23784" name="Janusz Wojciechowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commissioner did not answer the question. It was an …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Wojciechowski! Ich kann keinen weiteren Debattenbeitrag zulassen. Das ist nicht zur Geschäftsordnung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162 GO)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-500" speaker_id="96680" name="Zigmantas Balčytis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Viena gera žinia, kurią išgirdome iš Komisijos šįvakar, yra tai, jog parama nuo Rusijos embargo nukentėjusiems ES ūkininkams bus atnaujinta, ir dar šiemet paramos gali tikėtis sezoninių vaisių ir daržovių augintojai. Nors Komisija efektyviai sureagavo priimdama priemones minėtiems sektoriams, tačiau lygiai taip pat nuo Rusijos embargo kenčia ir mėsos bei pieno sektoriai. Kai kurių ES valstybių narių ūkininkų situaciją dar labiau apsunkina ir kiaulių maro problema, kuriai Komisija, – skirtingai nei 2011 m. kilus E. coli bakterijų sukeltai krizei, kai nuo jos nukentėjusioms didelėms ES valstybėms narėms buvo skirta skubi parama, – iki šiol nepasirengusi skirti deramo dėmesio ir paramos. Rusijos embargas ir pačios ES viduje iškilę pastarojo meto sunkumai yra išbandymas, kuris parodys, kaip ES laikosi solidarumo principo savo valstybių narių atžvilgiu. Rusijos embargas yra rimta problema visoms ES šalimis ir tikiuosi, kad Europa jį atlaikys solidariai ir vieningai.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-000" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Lietuvai ir kitoms Baltijos šalims Rusijos embargas smogia stipriausiai. Ir čia turime kalbėti ne tik apie verslo nuostolius. Svarbios ir socialinės pasekmės, kurias per mažėjančias pajamas ar net darbo vietų naikinimą, neabejotinai patirs jautriausios mūsų šalių socialinės grupės. Todėl raginu Komisiją įvertinti papildomos paramos teikimo poreikį šalims, kurių darbo rinkos nukentės nuo Rusijos embargo. Šiame kontekste siūlyčiau apsvarstyti paramos teikimo iš Europos Globalizacijos fondo galimybes, kad šio fondo lėšos galėtų būti operatyviau ir veiksmingiau panaudotos padėti darbuotojams, kurie ateityje gali būti atleisti iš įmonių, nukentėjusių nuo Rusijos sankcijų. Taip pat noriu paraginti Komisiją Baltijos šalis paskelbti išskirtinių poreikių zona ir įsteigti specialių fondą šioms šalims, skirtą remti Baltijos ūkininkus ir kompensuoti jų nuostolius. Įvertinus iššūkius, su kuriais jau susiduria Baltijos šalių ūkininkai dėl vis dar gaunamų mažiausių tiesioginių išmokų visoje Europos Sąjungoje, bei neproporcingai didelį Rusijos importo draudimo poveikį, darosi akivaizdu, kad Estijos, Latvijos ir Lietuvos žemės ūkio sektoriui yra reikalinga ypatinga ES parama. Taip pat, nereikia pamiršti, kad Rusijos veiksmų susidariusios krizės akivaizdoje ne mažiau svarbus ir reikalingas yra ir ilgalaikis problemos sprendimas. ES pagalba reikalinga ir tam, kad padėtų žemdirbiams persiorientuoti į kitas žemės ūkio šakas ir rasti alternatyvių rinkų produkcijai.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-250" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Con l'embargo russo sono state bloccate per 12 mesi le importazioni del comparto alimentare proveniente da Stati Uniti, Unione Europea, Canada, Australia e Norvegia. Il rischio è quello di mettere totalmente in ginocchio i nostri comparti già vessati dalla crisi. Il valore dei prodotti agroalimentari interessati dall'embargo è stimato dalla Commissione Europea in 5 miliardi di Euro, incidendo sul reddito di 9 milioni di europei. Questi dati sono assolutamente ottimistici in quanto non si tiene conto di numerosi fattori quali il commercio a triangolazione, la perdita di mercato sul lungo periodo, e non si considerano gli squilibri nel mercato interno. Gli aiuti stanziati non saranno quindi sufficienti. L'Unione Europea deve prevedere una distribuzione di risorse più attenta e si deve adoperare per costruire un vero mercato unico europeo armonizzato, in grado di assorbire contraccolpi ed emergenze, gestendo in modo lungimirante i flussi commerciali interni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-000" speaker_id="124711" name="Norbert Erdős" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Értékelem az Európai Bizottságnak a kárt szenvedett gazdák kártalanítása érdekében tett igyekezetét. A jelen állás szerint ez azonban nem elég. Az eddig felszabadított pénzforrásokra már most túljelentkezés van, ezért a források kifizetését felfüggesztették. További uniós források bevonására van szükség.</p>
      <p sl="en">A termelők kártalanítására minden rendelkezésre álló uniós forrást fel kell felhasználni. Támogatom a Parlament Mezőgazdasági Bizottságának a törekvését, hogy az agrárpénzeken kívül az idei és a jövő évi uniós költségvetés tartalékából is csoportosítsunk át pénzeket az európai gazdák megsegítésére. A kizárólag külpolitikai okból kivetett orosz szankciókat leginkább a gazdáink sínylik meg. Az EU-nak kötelessége szolidárisnak lennie velük. Ezért kell az agrárforrásokon felül uniós forrásokat találni a termelők kártalanítására.</p>
      <p sl="en">A mezőgazdasági krízisalap forrásait azonban csak a legvégső esetben használjuk fel, ha már minden más lehetőség kimerült. A közvetlen támogatások nem csökkenhetnek.</p>
      <p sl="en">A termelők segítése érdekében a 2015-ös uniós költségvetés tárgyalása során Deutsch Tamás képviselőtársammal együtt kezdeményeztük az iskolagyümölcs program keretének jelentős növelését. Ez jó eszköz lehet a gyümölcstermelőket sújtó orosz szankciók miatti terményfeleslegek egy részének az értékesítésére.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-500" speaker_id="96934" name="Sandra Kalniete" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">rakstiski. – Eiropas zemnieki šobrīd pārdzīvo grūtus laikus dēļ Krievijas lēmuma aizliegt lauksaimniecības produktu importu no Eiropas Savienības. Piemēram, piena iepirkuma cena Latvijā dažu nedēļu laikā ir nokritusies par 30% vai 40% un šobrīd ir zem 19 centiem par litru. Arī piena pārstrādes uzņēmumi Krievijas tirgus slēgšanas dēļ cieš ievērojamus zaudējumus. Pašlaik Latvijas zemnieki par 99,1 % ir izpildījuši piena kvotas. Govs nav mašīna, kuru var izslēgt. Tā turpina ražot pienu. Tāpēc es uzskatu, ka ES institūcijām ir jāpieņem lēmums nepiemērot soda naudu par kvotas pārsniegšanu atlikušajos mēnešos līdz kvotas atcelšanai 2015.gadā. Šāds lēmums palīdzētu saglabāt daudzas piena saimniecības Centrālajā un Austrumeiropā. Taču šodien embargo apstākļos tas nav tikai ekonomisks lēmums, tam ir nepieciešama politiska griba. Mani interesē Eiropas Komisijas viedoklis par to, vai varētu atcelt soda naudas valstīm, kuras būs pārsniegušas piena kvotas, un kāds atbalsts būtu pieejams piena ražotājiem (t.i. lauksaimniekiem), jo KLP paredzētie pasākumi attiecas tikai uz piena apstrādi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-750" speaker_id="124868" name="Alessia Maria Mosca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – La Russia rappresenta circa il 10 per cento delle esportazioni agricole dell'Unione europea, per un valore di 12 miliardi di euro all'anno, e da più di un mese oramai ha vietato l'importazione di un certo numero di prodotti agro-alimentari. Vorremmo rassicurare i nostri produttori chiedendo alla Commissione europea quali misure intenda adottare sia, nel breve periodo, per attutire i danni al settore agricolo europeo sia, in una prospettiva più lunga, per risolvere questa situazione in modo che a farne le spese non siano i produttori e le piccole e medie imprese del settore. Sembra, infatti, che la Russia si stia organizzando, sia aumentando la propria produzione interna sia trovando partner commerciali alternativi, per non dover più dipendere dall'importazione europea: diventa necessario trovare una soluzione che permetta di perseguire la nostra politica estera senza danneggiare quella commerciale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">в писмена форма. – Уважаеми господин Председател, Недопустимо е всички производители да бъдат поставяни под общ знаменател, в конкуренция за безкрайно недостатъчните компенсации от 125 милиона евро, които бяха изчерпани за по-малко от десет дни. Производителите от новите държави членки изпадат в неравностойно положение и с риск от тежки социални последствия, в конкуренция със стоките от по-старите държави членки, които са и обект на по-големи земеделски субсидии. Призовавам Комисар Чолош да обърне особено внимание и на факта, че тази година в България имаше редица опустошителни наводнения, които допълнително носят тежки последствия за земеделското производство в региони, където то е основен поминък. В следствие на тях и последвалата по-слаба реколта, българският земеделски пазар е изложен на огромен натиск от земеделска продукция от другите държави членки. Искам да изразя неодобрение и към дискриминацията относно самостоятелните производители, за които субсидията е по-малка от тези на членуващите в браншови организации. От тази мярка потърпевши са отново новите земеделски предприемачи на Съюза. Призовавам Европейската комисия да вземе тези фактори под внимание при оформянето на следващите си предложения и делегирани регламенти. Благодаря, господин Председател!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-500" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga Sehnalová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písemně. – Oceňuji rychlou reakci Komise na situaci v sektoru zemědělství po zavedení embarga na dovoz zemědělských produktů, zejména v oblasti ovoce a zeleniny a mléčných výrobků do Ruska. Konkrétní opatření jsou zaměřena na zmírnění dopadu na vnitřním trhu, současně však představují pouze opatření přechodného charakteru. Přetlak na vnitřním trhu však může znamenat také rozkolísaní vnitřního trhu zvýšením sekundárních dovozů. Je třeba zabránit cenovému dumpingu a zajistit kvalitu produktů v zájmu ochrany spotřebitelů. Je nutné nadále intenzivně sledovat vývoj situace a kompenzace zaměřit cíleně a efektivně i s ohledem na střednědobý a dlouhodobý výhled.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-750" speaker_id="125016" name="Claudia Schmidt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vorab möchte ich der Kommission ein Lob dafür aussprechen, dass sie sehr schnell auf die neue wirtschaftliche Lage reagiert und den Betroffenen Hilfe zugesichert hat. Nun ist es aber wichtig, den klein- und mittelständischen Unternehmen, gerade außerhalb von industriellen Ballungszentren, schnelle, unbürokratische und zielorientiere Hilfe zukommen zu lassen. Diese Unternehmen werden am stärksten durch die Sanktionen getroffen. Um Wirtschaftsstandorte und Arbeitsplätze zu sichern, müssen wir gezielte Hilfestellungen leisten!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Trade with Euromed countries (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-111-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Erklärung der Kommission zum Handel mit den Euromed-Staaten (2014/2836(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karel De Gucht" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members of the European Parliament, Europe’s southern neighbourhood has gone through unprecedented change since 2011 and, in this context, trade and investment must play a role as a factor of stability: a factor of stability in your relations with the southern Mediterranean region.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are currently focusing on three trade objectives vis-à-vis the southern Mediterranean region. The first one is the deepening of EU trade relations with some of these partners on the basis of a differentiated approach. In December 2011 the Council adopted negotiating directives for deep and comprehensive free trade areas (DCFTAs) with Egypt, Jordan, Morocco and Tunisia. The main objective of these agreements will be the progressive integration of the economies of these partners into the EU single market.</p>
      <p sl="en">These agreements will be comprehensive and will cover regulatory areas of mutual interest such as trade facilitation, sanitary and phytosanitary measures, public procurement and competition policy. They will also include investment protection and further liberalisation of goods, services and establishments, as appropriate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Negotiations on a DCFTA were launched with Morocco in March 2013 and are progressing apace. The preparatory process for the negotiations with Jordan and Tunisia is very advanced, and negotiations could be launched as soon as the preparatory process is completed. The immediate priority for countries where a DCFTA is not immediately possible – such as Libya, Lebanon or Algeria – is their accession to the World Trade Organisation, and contacts continue in this respect. We also need to define the most appropriate trade framework for our relations with Libya in due course.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second focus is support for south-south regional integration. The level of intra-regional trade in the southern Mediterranean is still lower than anywhere else in the world. An integrated Mediterranean market will be much more attractive to investors. We continue to support efforts to reinforce the Agadir Agreement between Egypt, Jordan, Morocco and Tunisia and to extend it to other regulatory areas: to trade and services, investments or public procurement. This also includes providing financial assistance and expertise. The ongoing revision of pan-Euromed rules of origin should be accelerated. This is not an easy task, given the diverging views of the partners participating in this process.</p>
      <p sl="en">The third key element is the regional Euro-Mediterranean trade partnership, which will be revitalised at the upcoming 10th Union for the Mediterranean Trade Ministerial Meeting on 30 September. This is an important meeting, since it will be the first in four years.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is doing its utmost to keep the trade relationship with the EU’s Mediterranean neighbours up to date and to sustain long-term peace and stability in the region. We count on Parliament’s continued dedication to this shared goal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-000" speaker_id="96848" name="Mariya Gabriel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe PPE. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, je vous remercie pour votre présentation sur l'état actuel et les perspectives du commerce avec les pays Euromed. Il me semble qu'aujourd'hui le bilan est le suivant – et vous venez de le tracer: le commerce entre l'Union européenne et les pays de la rive sud de la Méditerranée offre toujours des perspectives prometteuses mais le chemin est encore long pour que les partenariats ne restent justement pas à géométrie variable.</p>
      <p sl="en">J'aimerais souligner trois éléments: tout d'abord, il est nécessaire de poursuivre le travail vers les accords de libre-échange et en particulier par l'élimination des barrières non tarifaires. L'élimination des barrières non tarifaires et techniques doit se faire en partenariat et avec la pleine implication et appropriation de nos pays partenaires. À ce propos, et comme vous venez de le rappeler, le partenariat avec le sud de la Méditerranée doit se fonder sur une dynamique d'intégration régionale forte. Or aujourd'hui, les échanges entre les pays du sud de la Méditerranée restent très faibles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxième élément: afin de renforcer les échanges commerciaux avec les pays partenaires de la Méditerranée, il est capital de rester pragmatique, de travailler directement avec et pour ceux qui réalisent les échanges. Deux exemples: mettre notre politique des visas au service de la politique économique, c'est-à-dire faciliter les procédures de délivrance des visas pour le monde de l'entreprise, comme avec l'accord de partenariat de mobilité signé avec le Maroc en juin 2013. Deuxième idée: encourager davantage la mise en réseau des entreprises des deux côtés de la mer Méditerranée, notamment par la création de chambres de commerce bilatérales qui peuvent organiser des forums ou des formations conjointes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, l'approfondissement des relations commerciales et les accords de libre-échange ne sont pas une fin en soi. Le commerce n'est pas la seule clef du développement, mais il demeure un instrument susceptible de permettre à ces pays de s'insérer pleinement dans une économie mondiale ouverte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous devons donc veiller à ce que le développement des entreprises et des échanges favorise aussi le renforcement des États et des structures administratives, car on ne peut pas perdre de vue l'instabilité politique et sociale dans ces régions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc oui au commerce au service de la paix et de la stabilité.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, M. De Gucht, dans votre exposé, vous n'avez pas parlé du partenariat entre l'Europe et Israël. Or il me semble important de pouvoir rappeler certains principes dans cet échange commercial avec Israël, particulièrement le principe de l'illégalité de l'occupation des territoires en Cisjordanie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour ce faire, nous avons effectivement, avec les instruments de commerce, la possibilité de faire deux choses. La première est bien entendu d'encourager les États membres qui ont dès aujourd'hui pris des dispositions par rapport à ces produits issus des territoires occupés, c'est-à-dire de pouvoir garantir la labellisation de ces produits. Il est vrai que cela existe aujourd'hui de manière volontaire au Royaume-Uni et également en Belgique. Mais nous souhaitons qu'au niveau de l'Europe nous puissions activer des mesures contraignantes en matière de labellisation des produits issus des territoires occupés qui sont des produits illégaux. Cela permettrait ainsi aux consommateurs européens de faire les choix adéquats en matière de consommation, cela permettrait de changer des habitudes et d'exercer des pressions économiques par rapport à la situation injuste telle qu'elle est vécue aujourd'hui.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concernant les autres pays – vous avez cité le Maroc et la Tunisie – je pense qu'il est également important de rappeler un certain nombre de principes. Le premier c'est que ce sont des pays en transition démocratique – je parle ici de la Tunisie – et il est important d'associer la société civile à ces accords de libre-échange. Il est aussi important d'inclure des clauses sociales et des clauses environnementales qui soient, là aussi, contraignantes dans les accords commerciaux.</p>
      <a text="(L'orateur accepte de répondre à une question &quot;carton bleu&quot; (article 162, paragraphe 8, du règlement))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-000" speaker_id="96661" name="Krisztina Morvai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kékkártyás kérdés. – Szeretném megkérdezni képviselőtársnőmet, hogy egyetért-e azzal, hogy egy fél órával ezelőtt itt Oroszországgal kapcsolatban azt állapította meg a Parlament, hogy Oroszország agressziót követett el egy másik ország sérelmére, ezért szankciót kell vele szemben alkalmaznia az Európai Uniónak. Egyetért-e tehát azzal – nagyon nehéz beszélni, mert itt többen kávéháznak használják megint az üléstermet, és hangosan beszélnek, de próbálok őket túlkiabálva rákérdezni, hogy – alkalmazhatunk-e kettős mércét, vagy azt kell mondani, hogy a Gáza ellen agressziót el … (Az elnök megvonta a szót a képviselőtől.)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">réponse "carton bleu". – Je demande qu'il puisse y avoir la traçabilité des produits, cela permettrait de faire des choix par rapport à nos consommations. S'il n'y a pas de traçabilité, il est impossible de savoir d'où viennent ces produits aujourd'hui et je ne plaide pas pour un boycott de tous les produits tant israéliens que palestiniens mais je plaide pour que nous puissions savoir si ces produits sont élaborés dans l'illégalité à savoir dans des territoires occupés.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας ECR. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι οικονομικές σχέσεις της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης με τις μεσογειακές χώρες πρέπει να στηρίζονται στις αρχές του αμοιβαίου οφέλους και να μην είναι ετεροβαρείς. Η δημιουργία μιας ελεύθερης οικονομικής ευρωμεσογειακής ζώνης πρέπει να μην δημιουργεί προβλήματα σε χώρες οι οποίες αντιμετωπίζουν οικονομικά προβλήματα, όπως είναι οι χώρες του Νότου, χώρες που πλήττονται από τη μερκελική λιτότητα, από τα μνημόνια. Και αυτό ισχύει και για την Ελλάδα και την Ιταλία, πολύ δε περισσότερο τώρα που όπως είδαμε η αγροτική οικονομία της Ελλάδας και των άλλων χωρών του Νότου πλήττονται από το ρωσικό εμπάργκο. Επίσης ορισμένες χώρες της Μεσογείου δεν πρέπει να έχουν μια πολιτική á la carte. Αυτό ισχύει για την Τουρκία, η οποία ενώ έχει εισβάλει στην Κύπρο, ενώ έχει καταλάβει ένα μεγάλο μέρος του νησιού, εντούτοις δεν αναγνωρίζει την Κυπριακή Δημοκρατία, και παρά ταύτα απαιτεί τα προϊόντα της να κυκλοφορούν ελεύθερα και χωρίς εμπόδια στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πρέπει επίσης, κύριε Πρόεδρε, να αντιμετωπίσουμε και το ζήτημα των παράνομων μεταναστευτικών ροών …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, trade is an essential part of our common foreign policy and it should be a more integral part. Its political significance was underlined by the responses to the EU-Ukraine Association Agreement. Last summer a wake-up call was given, for those who still needed one, as to the importance of a strong Europe in today’s world.</p>
      <p sl="de">We have a lot to win by expanding the scope of existing agreements in the Euromed region. A few years after courageous people – many of them young – defied repression in calling for democracy, rights and opportunities, not enough positive change has been realised. Sadly, the countries in North Africa and the Middle East face major threats of instability. Still, we must continue with an ambitious trade agenda. It should be at the heart of finally giving meaning to the notion of more for more: more market access, with more reforms towards human rights and democracy. We must be firm, including with Israel, on existing conditionalities, and we must see trade as a means towards more opportunities and rights, towards the prevention of corruption, the more equal distribution of wealth and the empowerment of individuals – the latter especially in combination with education, which should be used to tackle the massive youth unemployment. Increasing opportunities may also help to prevent radicalisation, although clearly it is not the only solution. Certainly it can help curb migration.</p>
      <p sl="de">This is not just a matter of exports and innovations. We should look at ourselves, and at the negative impact that agricultural subsidies have on the opportunities for farmers in the Euromed region, hampering growth there. The EU should also play an active coordinating role, so as to avoid duplication of activities on the ground, and it should support regional integration, which would greatly help economic growth in the Euromed region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-000" speaker_id="96735" name="Patrick Le Hyaric" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, ce que vous appelez le voisinage avec les pays du sud de la Méditerranée, dont une partie cherche les voies de la justice et de la liberté, appelle je crois un nouveau type de coopération avec eux: coopération et non concurrence.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est donc nécessaire de changer d'approche vis-à-vis de ces pays, qui ne doivent ni constituer de nouvelles zones d'expansion économique, ni une arrière-cour industrielle pour exploiter une main-d'œuvre à bon marché, ni une zone migratoire tampon dont ils seraient les gardiens pour notre compte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Au contraire, leurs souverainetés économique et alimentaire doivent être respectées, un grand plan d'aide au financement d'investissements durables incluant des clauses sociales et environnementales et mobilisant en commun un crédit peu cher pour des actions de codéveloppement, devrait être discuté et élaboré.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les politiques de coopération doivent s'accompagner de progrès significatifs pour le respect des droits humains et la démocratie et non du conditionnement des aides selon les critères du Fonds monétaire international. De même, l'accord de coopération avec l'État d'Israël devrait être suspendu après les massacres de Gaza et la poursuite …</p>
      <a text="(Le Président retire la parole à l'orateur)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-000" speaker_id="124818" name="Klaus Buchner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar! Die Situation bezüglich der Menschenrechte in Ägypten verschlechtert sich laufend. Natürlich müssen wir mit der Regierung dort zusammenarbeiten und im Gespräch bleiben und versuchen, unseren Einfluss geltend zu machen, damit sich diese schlimme Situation verbessert. Trotzdem: Die Fortsetzung der Verhandlungen zu DCFTA ist mehr als nur ein Kontakt, sie sind mehr als nur eine technische Diskussion. Sie bedeuten, dass wir die zahlreichen schweren Menschenrechtsverletzungen ignorieren und die Regierung stützen, ihr internationale Anerkennung verleihen. Das ist für alle, die unter den gegenwärtigen Menschenrechtsverletzungen leiden, wirklich ein Schlag ins Gesicht. Deswegen möchte ich Sie, Herr Kommissar, fragen, ob Sie die Verhandlungen dazu so lange aussetzen, bis ein Fortschritt bei den Menschenrechten in Ägypten zu sehen ist oder bis man zumindest den Willen dazu erkennen kann.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-000" speaker_id="124777" name="Tiziana Beghin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, la riunione ministeriale dell'Unione per il Mediterraneo del 30 settembre sarà l'occasione ufficiale di riprendere le discussioni su diversi accordi tra l'Unione e i paesi del Mediterraneo e sarà anche l'occasione per far valere davvero gli interessi di tutti gli europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signor Commissario, ho ben noto l'accordo già firmato con il Marocco, quello stesso accordo che ha invaso il nostro mercato di prodotti agricoli a bassissimo costo in diretta concorrenza con quelli del mio paese, un accordo firmato per permettere ad alcuni pesi massimi europei di esportare i loro prodotti industriali in Marocco, sacrificando quindi la produzione agricola degli Stati mediterranei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chiedo quindi alla Commissione di negoziare per l'Europa, e non solo per alcuni Stati, e di richiedere ai futuri partner di adeguarsi ai nostri standard di diritti e di sicurezza, soprattutto alimentare, per tutelare i nostri consumatori e rendere la concorrenza più equa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chiedo di insistere sui diritti dei lavoratori e sulla regolarizzazione del lavoro in nero nelle piccole e medie imprese d'oltremare, perché condizioni di lavoro così diverse danno vita a una concorrenza che le nostre piccole e medie imprese in Europa non sono in grado di sostenere. I nostri piccoli e medi imprenditori investono sempre di più oltremare. Per questo motivo dobbiamo lavorare per creare quadri normativi solidi che garantiscano investimenti sicuri, rendere loro più facile l'ottenimento dei visti, come già detto, per motivi di lavoro e coordinare le diverse strategie europee destinate alle piccole e medie imprese. Garanzie, finanziamento, distribuzione delle informazione e messa in rete, pensando alla creazione di camere di commercio bilaterali e ad un'estensione del mandato della Banca europea per la ricostruzione e lo sviluppo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine vi invito a non dimenticare l'importanza dei servizi culturali: potenziamento dei settori turistici, erogazione di borse di studio e potenziamento dei programmi Erasmus e Da Vinci Euromed sono necessari per creare i legami e le conoscenze che muoveranno l'economia del futuro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signor Commissario, da questi accordi c'è molto da guadagnare o molto da perdere; tutto dipende da come l'Europa saprà giocare le sue carte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-000" speaker_id="30190" name="Louis Aliot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, une coopération entre États de l'Union européenne et la Méditerranée, oui! La mise en place d'une zone de libre-échange, c'est-à-dire l'effacement progressif des frontières économiques d'abord, humaines ensuite, non!</p>
      <p sl="en">Que l'Union européenne investisse dans les pays du Sud dans un souci de développement équilibré, dans une volonté aussi de desserrer l'étau migratoire et, à terme, d'inverser les flux du Nord vers le Sud, est aujourd'hui un investissement pour notre avenir. Pour défendre nos paysans, nos ouvriers, nos industries mais aussi nos cultures et notre civilisation, le développement du Sud est une nécessité vitale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais pas à n'importe quel prix! Nous devons d'abord nous assurer de notre sécurité en conditionnant ces aides à la stabilité politique, au respect des minorités et à la lutte contre l'immigration sauvage. Enfin, nous devons nous assurer que chaque euro dépensé là-bas soit utilisé avec des entreprises et de la main-d'œuvre locales ou, à défaut, avec des entreprises européennes, ce qui nous évitera de financer indirectement les économies chinoises ou américaines.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-000" speaker_id="96729" name="Santiago Fisas Ayxelà" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, los objetivos de la política de vecindad son crear un área de estabilidad, prosperidad y democracia y un marco que favorezca la resolución pacífica de conflictos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta tarea no es sencilla: los retos políticos y económicos a los que deben enfrentarse nuestros vecinos son enormes y nuestro compromiso para apoyar una transición en estos países hacia sociedades democráticas debe ser más firme que nunca.</p>
      <p sl="en">Razones para este compromiso no nos faltan: la presión migratoria, que no cesa de aumentar; la amenaza para nuestra seguridad a causa de la inestabilidad de la zona; los problemas energéticos que nos obligan a mirar hacia el Magreb; o el potencial económico que tendría para nuestras economías la consecución de una unión mediterránea con países estables y en crecimiento.</p>
      <p sl="en">En este proceso de cambio, el comercio juega un papel esencial: debemos seguir reforzando el proceso de integración comercial entre los países de la ribera sur del Mediterráneo y también de estos con la Unión Europea. En las negociaciones para lograr estos acuerdos, la Comisión debe garantizar un nivel de liberalización ambicioso en áreas claves, como son los servicios, las inversiones y la contratación pública.</p>
      <p sl="en">En estos momentos en que gran parte de los esfuerzos y de los recursos de la agenda comercial y exterior de la Comisión se están centrando en otras áreas geográficas, creo que reforzar la integridad y la integración comercial con Euromed debe ser una de prioridades de la Comisión Europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, le partenariat euroméditerranéen entre l'Union et les pays du sud de la Méditerranée a été initié en 1995 par le processus de Barcelone. Il s'agit là d'un partenariat politique, économique et social fondé sur les principes de réciprocité, de solidarité, de codéveloppement, thèmes qui nous sont chers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le respect des principes démocratiques et des droits fondamentaux constitue un élément essentiel des accords d'association. Ce type d'accords souligne l'importance d'une coopération économique, commerciale et financière mais aussi, et tout autant, d'une coopération sociale, culturelle et en matière d'éducation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je souhaite m'exprimer ici en tant que membre de la commission des droits de la femme et de l'égalité des genres de ce Parlement pour rappeler que cet accord commercial doit être l'occasion d'améliorer le respect des droits de la femme en général et, plus précisément, l'accès des femmes à l'éducation et à l'emploi, le rôle de la culture, des médias comme instruments clés pour faire évoluer les opinions sur l'égalité hommes-femmes. Il doit également faciliter la création et la gestion des entreprises par des femmes, améliorer l'accès des femmes aux mécanismes et aux outils de financement et développer la formation professionnelle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Par ailleurs, je tiens à saluer le courage justement de ces femmes qui ont été en première ligne des mouvements des sociétés civiles en faveur de la démocratie et des droits de l'homme dans les pays arabes. Malheureusement, les retombées de toutes ces révolutions font craindre une marginalisation accrue de ces femmes, de la femme en général. Elles se sont aussi traduites par une augmentation de la violence à leur égard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comme vous avez pu le constater, des progrès restent évidemment à faire et nous avons, je pense – j'espère que vous partagez cette idée –, un rôle déterminant à jouer. C'est notre devoir de partenaire dans ces accords.</p>
      <a text="(L'orateur accepte de répondre à une question &quot;carton bleu&quot; (article 162, paragraphe 8, du règlement)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-000" speaker_id="124767" name="Edouard Ferrand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">question "carton bleu". – Monsieur Tarabella, lorsque vous soutenez les révolutions arabes, ne pensez-vous pas que le rôle et la domination des femmes ont été sérieusement mis en cause malheureusement dans les pays que vous citez?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">réponse "carton bleu". – Monsieur Ferrand, je ne sais pas si vous avez bien entendu mon propos. J'ai parlé du rôle clé des femmes dans une lutte pour plus de démocratie, plus de droits pour elles, mais aussi pour la démocratie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Malheureusement, en effet – je l'ai dit très clairement et textuellement –, on peut être déçu des conséquences de ces mouvements. Il ne faudrait pas que les femmes soient marginalisées. Aujourd'hui, elles semblent plus marginalisées qu'avant dans certains pays, et leur rôle semble plus marginal également. Nous devons donc, j'estime, au niveau européen, tenir compte de cette situation pour faire jouer aux femmes un rôle important dans l'économie de leur pays.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, kad već govorimo o pravima žena, mislim da su u tzv. arapskom proljeću žene odigrale vrlo važnu ulogu, ali nažalost kasnije to nije pošlo pravcem kojim je trebalo. U svakom slučaju zalažem se za ovaj sporazum - treba stvoriti područje mirnog susjedstva, jer to je okvir za riješavanje sukoba. Moramo pomoći zemljama u tranziciji te smatram da gospodarstvo treba biti u službi politike. Jačanje suradnje je prioritet, a temelj svega ovoga bio je Barcelonski proces 1995. godine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ističem suradnju na svim područjima, ali posebno na području okoliša, jer to nismo puno spomenuli, a smatram da nam je svima zajednička briga voditi računa o Sredozemnom moru i očuvanju okoliša. Smatram da tu puno mogu učiniti i pojedine zemlje s državne razine, ali isto tako regionalna je suradnja vrlo važna te očekujemo rezultate sastanka 30. rujna gdje će se pokazati što se može učiniti na razini lokalne uprave, samouprave i regija.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-000" speaker_id="88882" name="Victor Negrescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, Uniunea Europeană reprezintă și trebuie să reprezinte în continuare la nivel mondial un reper de dezvoltare economică și democratică. Pentru a face acest lucru, Europa trebuie să ofere în continuare perspective de integrare și de colaborare cu toate țările vecine, atât din sud, cât și din est.</p>
      <p sl="en">Provenind dintr-o țară fostă comunistă, care a cunoscut o tranziție dificilă, vă pot spune că este absolut necesar pentru democratizarea și dezvoltarea acestor țări să menținem frontierele deschise, mai ales pentru cei care vin din tânăra generație. Doar printr-o colaborare continuă și schimburi comerciale putem conduce aceste țări în direcția corectă, dar acest lucru nu înseamnă să facem rabat de la propriile principii și trebuie să depunem în continuare eforturi pentru a le impune, pentru că porțile deschise înseamnă și, din partea acestor țări, acordul pentru a respecta valorile noastre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cred, de asemenea, că este foarte important ca Comisia, Uniunea Europeană și țările membre să implice mai mult pe viitor țările din est în această colaborare. Experiența noastră poate reprezenta un element benefic în construirea unei colaborări între întreaga Uniune Europeană cu țările din sud, pentru că și țările din est au experiența care poate fi de ajutor în această direcție.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, radovao sam se kada je pokrenuta inicijativa Unija za Mediteran, imao sam i prilike raditi u sklopu ARLEM-a, zastupati Europu u tom dijelu i moram reći da sam se dobro upoznao sa svim potrebama naših prijatelja na jugu Mediterana. Definitivno podržavam ovaj sporazum, podržavam pregovore, ali zaista je apsolutno točno i neophodno da zaštitimo i naše interese, kako one globalne, one generalne od ljudskih prava do svega onoga što su vrijednosti Europe tako i do onih sasvim konkretnih i bit ću vrlo, vrlo konkretan - problem maslinovog ulja je na primjer jedan od onih problema koji postoje kad govorimo o konkurentnosti našeg proizvoda na svjetskom tržištu, odnosno bolje je reći, u samoj našoj Europi jer znam da se puno maslinovog ulja uvozi s juga Mediterana, miješa s našim maslinovim uljem i onda prodaje kao europsko maslinovo ulje. Naravno, tu govorim o kvaliteti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takvih primjera sigurno ima još, ali za taj primjer znam i zato želim istaknuti da je vrlo važno da znamo zemlju porijekla svakog proizvoda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-000" speaker_id="125100" name="Miguel Viegas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, nós somos a favor da diversificação das nossas relações comerciais. O que reclamamos é que não sejam apenas critérios puramente económicos a reger estas relações. E, portanto, tudo o que seja a eliminação das tarifas, etc., naturalmente que isto só irá criar enormes dificuldades a estas economias, como em Portugal nós dolorosamente sabemos. E, portanto, o que reclamamos são outros critérios, critérios sociais, critérios baseados no respeito pelos direitos humanos, no respeito pela soberania de cada país, enfim, e lógicas de complementaridade que tragam efetivamente vantagens mútuas para todos os países envolvidos. E, enfim, subscrevo também a questão sobre Israel, que é exatamente um exemplo acabado onde creio que a União Europeia deveria ir muito mais longe, e não apenas na rotulagem, isso é apenas uma ingenuidade, porque existem muitas maneiras de contornar esse aspeto. Um embargo eficaz, continuamos a acreditar que é uma das soluções possíveis para resolver o problema …</p>
      <a text="(O Presidente retira a palavra ao orador)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-000" speaker_id="124832" name="Udo Voigt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Wir haben viel über Grundrechte und Grundwerte in Europa gehört. Ich frage mich, warum die Kommission nicht darüber berichtet, was in den Mittelmeerländern den Staat Israel betrifft.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Vereinten Nationen geben die Zahl der seit Juli 2014 getöteten Kinder mit 500 an. Des Weiteren hat Israel mindestens 244 Schulen bombardiert, darunter auch 45 Schulen der Vereinten Nationen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Angesichts dieses eklatanten Bruchs des Völkerrechts und insbesondere des Genfer Abkommens über den Schutz von Zivilpersonen in Kriegszeiten ist das Nachbarschaftsabkommen mit Israel auszusetzen, oder man sollte zumindest einmal darüber debattieren, ob man die Israelis nicht ähnlich mit Sanktionen dazu bewegen kann, die Schuldigen zur Verantwortung zu ziehen und eventuell dem Internationalen Gerichtshof in Den Haag zu überstellen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karel De Gucht" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me try to answer a number of questions that have been raised, some of them repeatedly.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, there were a number of questions on Egypt and the question as to whether we should negotiate a deep and comprehensive free trade agreement (DCFTA) at all, given the current human rights abuses. The Council gave the Commission a negotiating mandate for a DCFTA with Egypt in 2011. The actual launch of negotiations depends on the completion of a preparatory scoping process which has barely even started, so launching negotiations will depend on a joint decision by the EU and Egypt, and the Commission will keep Parliament informed in real time. It is very difficult to suspend something that has not yet started.</p>
      <p sl="en">As with any other prospective trade agreement, the Commission has commissioned an external consultant to undertake a trade sustainability impact assessment. This will examine the potential economic, social and environmental impact of an agreement. It will include a specific chapter on implications in the field of human rights, and on the side-lines of the Union for the Mediterranean Trade Ministerial Conference on 30 September I will have a bilateral meeting with the Egyptian Minister.</p>
      <p sl="en">On Morocco, we launched DCFTA negotiations in March 2013. They have progressed well in the course of the four negotiating sessions that have already been held and both sides share the common objective of concluding a DCFTA as soon as possible. Of course we will have to take into consideration mutual interests and priorities. Morocco has decided to launch accompanying studies on certain sectors that will be covered by the future DCFTA. Morocco has agreed with its business sector and civil society to take into consideration the results of these studies during the next negotiating rounds. In that context we have therefore agreed to postpone the fifth round of negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, there is no suspension of negotiations. Technical contacts will continue during this period to ensure the continuity of the negotiating process. The Union for the Mediterranean Trade Ministerial Conference will be an opportunity for further discussion with the Moroccan Trade Minister. I hope that we can resume the formal negotiations this year and that we will be in a position to conclude them next year. The DCFTA negotiations with Morocco are politically important since they will set a precedent for other partners in the regions such as Tunisia, Jordan and Egypt.</p>
      <p sl="en">On Israel, the EU has a very clear position on the illegality of Israeli settlements. Therefore we have already ensured that products originating in the Israeli settlements do not benefit from preferential treatment when entering the EU market. An additional step is to follow the practice of certain Member States and further clarify the labelling of these products so that consumers are fully aware, when making their choice, that the product originates in Israel or in an Israeli settlement. The Commission, together with the European External Action Service, is gradually revising existing legislation on mandatory labelling, mostly for agricultural products, and has started the preparation of more general guidelines on the labelling of these products in order to help Member States to implement existing legislation on voluntary labelling.</p>
      <p sl="en">More generally, on a number of remarks that have been made about the principle of ‘more for more’, let me say that in all these DCFTAs and in the mandates for negotiating them, as in other trade agreements, meaningful reciprocal commitments on human rights will be included. In fact, we want to use these agreements to promote a strong human rights agenda. The DCFTA mandates were adopted on an individual basis to reflect the ‘more for more’ principle.</p>
      <p sl="en">On a political point, regarding ‘more for more’, what it means is more aid and more investment if more is done on political reform. What it also means is that we ourselves have to open our markets to the partner countries. This is not always easy to do in the context of these agreements, and Member States are not too flexible on the matter. On the other hand, I think we should also have a somewhat different approach in relation to visas, which is one of the very clear demands, and then, of course, the countries concerned should also agree to open their markets progressively. They have to assume their responsibilities: we also have to do that – in other words, the European Union also needs to assume its responsibilities and introduce more flexibility with these countries than is presently the case.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau Kollegin Morvai, ich habe mir gerade schon die Mühe gemacht, Ihnen eine kleine schriftliche Antwort zu geben auf das, was Sie mir da geschrieben haben. Sie melden sich nicht zur Geschäftsordnung zu Wort. Ich habe erstens klar erklärt, dass hier Kollegen nicht nur deshalb da sind, weil sie im Catch-the-eye-Verfahren Redezeit bekommen, und zweitens – das habe ich mir hier schon aufgeschrieben – versuche ich, alle Kollegen gleichermaßen fair zu behandeln. Auch dieses Mal hatte ich mehr Kollegen, die sich zu Wort gemeldet hatten, als ich zu Wort kommen lassen kann. Ich kann auch nicht eine halbe Stunde vorher sagen, wen ich drannehme, denn das würde nicht dem Charakter des Catch-the-eye-Verfahrens entsprechen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162 GO)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-000" speaker_id="124868" name="Alessia Maria Mosca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – La Primavera Araba ha determinato cambiamenti e sfide significative per le popolazioni dei Paesi che si affacciano sul Mediterraneo, insieme ad una crescente aspettativa nei confronti dell'Unione Europea che dovrà rispondere in modo commisurato agli impegni assunti nei confronti dei suoi vicini meridionali, ciò nel quadro della Politica europea di vicinato ed in linea con il Trattato di Lisbona che prevede politiche unionali capaci di promuovere la pace, la democrazia, lo sviluppo e la giustizia sociale. Accogliamo con favore, quindi, la futura creazione del meccanismo euro-mediterraneo di facilitazione del commercio e degli investimenti che dovrebbe fornire agli operatori economici, segnatamente le PMI, le informazioni necessarie per operare nella regione. Sottolineamo la necessità di promuovere la sicurezza degli investimenti nella regione mediterranea attraverso un sistema che coordini le strategie destinate alle PMI e riguardi vari settori, vale a dire garanzie, finanziamento, informazione e messa in rete. Auspichiamo, inoltre, progressi riguardo ai servizi culturali, che hanno importanti vantaggi potenziali, in particolare nel settore del turismo, rilevando l'importanza generale degli scambi culturali, la previsione di borse di studio per gli studenti e la possibile istituzione di programmi specifici Erasmus (compreso un Erasmus per imprenditori) e Leonardo Da Vinci Euromed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine Vergiat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">par écrit. – "Comme toute réponse aux aspirations populaires exprimées lors de ce qu'il est convenu d'appeler les printemps arabes, l'UE répond commerce et libre-échange. Les accords d'association deviennent de purs accords de libre-échange, même s'ils sont doublés d'accords dits de mobilité où les seules certitudes, c'est que l'on veut plus que jamais faire des Etats du Sud des gendarmes de l'Europe avec les conséquences que l'on sait pour les droits des migrants. Et dans l'intérêt de qui : des Européens et surtout des multinationales, au mépris de ceux des populations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Au Maroc, la société civile se bat car elle craint que l'on favorise les exportations de produits européens au détriment des droits économiques, sociaux et environnementaux des Marocains.</p>
      <p sl="en">En Tunisie, l'UE tente de passer en force avant les prochaines échéances électorales avec les mêmes craintes qu'au Maroc, notamment pour les produits agricoles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et ne parlons pas d'Israël où l'on ferme les yeux sur les violations du droit international au mépris des clauses de l'Accord d'Association. Les dérives ultralibérales de l'UE se poursuivent des deux côtés de la Méditerranée alors que d'autres politiques sont possibles, favorisant la coopération, le développement durable et la libre circulation des travailleurs. "</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. GSP+ (Generalised Scheme of Preferences) and compliance with the Minimum Age Convention: case of Bolivia (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-139-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung an die Kommission von Daniel Caspary, Christofer Fjellner, Salvatore Cicu, Santiago Fisas Ayxelà, Gabrielius Landsbergis, Franck Proust, Godelieve Quisthoudt-Rowohl, Tokia Saïfi, Adam Szejnfeld, Iuliu Winkler, Bendt Bendtsen, Reimer Böge, Seán Kelly, Gabriel Mato, Fernando Ruas, József Szájer, Jarosław Leszek Wałęsa, Pablo Zalba Bidegain, im Namen der Fraktion der Europäischen Volkspartei (Christdemokraten) und von Emma McClarkin im Namen der Fraktion Europäische Konservative und Reformisten über APS+ (Allgemeines Präferenzsystem) und Einhaltung des Übereinkommens über das Mindestalter für die Zulassung zur Beschäftigung: der Fall Boliviens (O-000062/2014 - B8-0031/2014) – (2014/2837(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-000" speaker_id="119435" name="Davor Ivo Stier" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. - Gospodine predsjedniče, prema podacima UN-a, rad djece je u stalnom padu od 2000. godine; smanjen je za trećinu. I dok u ovom aspektu globalno napredujemo, Bolivijski kongres je 2. srpnja ove godine donio novi zakon o dječjim pravima u kojem je najniža dob za zaposlenje smanjena sa 14 na 12 godina, a u slučaju samozapošljavanja na 10 godina starosti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Time je Bolivija jedina zemlja na svijetu koja dozvoljava rad desetogodišnjaka. Ta djeca u Boliviji rade, u nekim slučajevima, teške fizičke poslove poput rada u poljima šećerne repe ili u rudnicima. Argument je bolivijske vlade pridonošenju ovog zakona kako je rad djece neophodan u Boliviji da bi se smanjilo siromaštvo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Međutim, rad djece možda se nekima čini kao rješenje - ono može biti samo kratkoročno, jer zapravo takvo rješenje samo amplificira, samo povećava siromaštvo na duge staze. Zato je i UNICEF izrazio zabrinutost zbog neusklađenosti bolivijskog zakona s međunarodnom konvencijom o najnižoj dobi za zaposlenje. A to je jedna od konvencija koje države moraju ratificirati ako žele zadovoljiti kriterije za dobivanje i korištenje GSP-a, odnosno općeg sustava povlastica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bolivija je ratificirala konvenciju o najnižoj dobi i od 1. siječnja ove godine koristi carinske povlastice. Međutim, nedugo nakon što je počela koristiti carinske povlastice, vlada Eva Moralesa ipak je promijenila ovaj zakon i time ostavlja dojam da su Europska unija i Europski parlament bili prevareni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato smo iz Europske pučke stranke uputili ovo pitanje Europskoj komisiji, pročitat ću ga u originalu na engleskom jeziku:</p>
      <p sl="en">‘Does the Commission believe that this new legislation prima facie puts Bolivia in breach of the Minimum Age Convention, which is one of the conventions that must be complied with in order to benefit from GSP+? Furthermore, can the Commission indicate whether it will analyse in detail the content of Bolivia’s new children’s rights bill, taking this analysis into account in Bolivia’s GSP+ “scorecard” in order to decide whether or not any serious failure has been identified in its effective implementation of this convention?’</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karel De Gucht" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission is aware of Bolivian Law No 548 on Children and Adolescents, adopted on 17 July 2014, which aims to ensure a high level of protection for children in Bolivia. For example, UNICEF has commended this law for reinforcing Bolivia’s commitments under ILO Convention No 182 on the ‘prohibition and immediate action for the elimination of the worst forms of child labour’, which Bolivia ratified in 2003. Moreover, the Bolivian Ombudsman found that the law has strengthened the legal framework in key areas relating to the protection of children, such as infanticide, access to health and education, identity, and the right to childhood and life.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, both organisations have expressed concerns over the provisions which lowered the minimum working age for children in an apparent contradiction of Bolivia’s commitments under ILO Convention No 138 concerning the minimum age for admission to employment. The Commission shares these concerns. We are actively engaging the Bolivian Government on this issue, and in parallel it is consulting the ILO to assess these provisions in the light of Convention No 138.</p>
      <p sl="en">The GSP monitoring is an integral part of the revised GSP+ system and its aim is to help the Commission assess GSP+ beneficiaries and the effective implementation of the GSP+ conventions. In the case of Bolivia, the Commission has already issued a scoreboard to Bolivia in February 2014 addressing aspects of the implementation of relevant GSP+ Conventions which require further work or clarification. Bolivia has been cooperating with the Commission and provided a reply in May 2014.</p>
      <p sl="en">Following this initial exchange, the Commission officially communicated with the Bolivian authorities on 18 July 2014 – one day after the adoption of the Bolivian law that is of concern to honourable Members of the European Parliament. The Commission is expecting Bolivia’s comments on the issue by today. The Commission will review Bolivia’s response and liaise with the ILO – the monitoring body for Convention No 182 – before deciding on the next steps. We will keep Parliament and the Member States informed accordingly.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-000" speaker_id="108080" name="Franck Proust" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe PPE. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, à travers la Bolivie, nous nous retrouvons en face de la réalité d'un pays en voie de développement. Nous soutenons la Bolivie en la faisant bénéficier d'un accès privilégié au marché de l'Union européenne et ce dans le cadre d'engagements liés au système de préférences généralisées SPG+.</p>
      <p sl="en">Or, la nouvelle législation de juillet 2014 en Bolivie permet donc à des enfants de 10 ans et plus de travailler dans un cadre qui les protège. Certes, au regard de la situation actuelle, il s'agit d'une avancée, d'autant plus qu'il s'agit d'une revendication des enfants travailleurs, mais une avancée vers quoi?</p>
      <p sl="en">Parmi les engagements de la Bolivie, il est clairement établi que la convention sur l'âge minimum doit être ratifiée, voire même respectée. Ma question est donc de savoir si la Bolivie respecte toujours ses engagements.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les valeurs que nous défendons privilégient l'accès à l'éducation plutôt que le travail des enfants. En Europe, nous avons des fédérations étudiantes. En Bolivie, ils ont des fédérations d'enfants travailleurs. Cette réalité, Monsieur le Commissaire, on ne peut la nier même si elle est dérangeante. Il y a bien sûr une décision technique et juridique à prendre. La Bolivie respecte-t-elle ses engagements au regard des accords? Mais il y a aussi une réponse politique à apporter. Exclure la Bolivie du SPG+, c'est la condamner encore un peu plus. Mais laisser nos pays partenaires déroger aux règles n'est pas acceptable. Imaginer bientôt que l'on verra sur notre territoire des produits issus du travail d'enfants de 10 ans est également intolérable.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Commissaire, le choix est …</p>
      <a text="(Le Président retire la parole à l'orateur)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-000" speaker_id="97078" name="Ramón Jáuregui Atondo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, yo estoy de acuerdo con su prudencia. Creo que su respuesta ha sido prudente. Y creo que una decisión por parte de la Comisión respecto a Bolivia, por esta ley, sería precipitada y provocaría males mayores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Precipitada porque, como usted ha dicho, hay que esperar la explicación del Gobierno de Bolivia, que la tiene. Segundo, porque la OIT, como usted ha dicho, va a elaborar un informe que va a ser el informe más importante respecto a cuál es esta vulneración de este Convenio fundamental del derecho al trabajo de los niños. Y, en tercer lugar, porque creo que, honradamente, hay que reconocer que el Gobierno de Bolivia ha querido dar respuesta a un problema real y es que el 60 % de los niños en Bolivia trabajan, Señorías. Y es que, desgraciadamente, el 90 % del trabajo de los niños en Bolivia es informal, está fuera de la ley. El problema, ciertamente, es que la duda que tenemos todos es si es bueno que haya una ley protectora del trabajo infantil o, por el contrario, es mejor que no la haya. Yo creo que hay que ser prudentes y sobre todo, hay que respetar a esos países.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo he sido nombrado Presidente de la Delegación del Parlamento en la Asamblea EuroLat hace unos días. Conozco América Latina, hablo con los embajadores de América Latina y nos piden que no les demos todos los días lecciones de democracia. Y esto ya es muy importante. Respetémosles. Hablemos con ellos. Trabajemos en favor de que avancen en el cumplimiento de los derechos fundamentales. Pero, sobre todo –y recordar esto me parece muy importante–, no condenemos a los niños en Bolivia a un trabajo esclavizado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que tenemos que tener en cuenta esta realidad para tomar la decisión más adecuada y más prudente, y mi Grupo está, señor Comisario, con sus palabras de prudencia y de espera.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-145-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor Presidente, la normativa sobre trabajo infantil en Bolivia incumple plenamente los convenios internacionales en la materia, tanto en lo que se refiere a los asalariados como al trabajo autónomo, pero es obligatorio llamar la atención sobre dos cuestiones.</p>
      <p sl="en">La defensa de los derechos de los menores es una causa universal que no entiende de fronteras; tampoco debería depender de la potencia económica, la dimensión o los intereses que tengamos en los países que consienten una explotación infantil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por otra parte, es muy llamativo que una norma como la que nos ocupa se considere en Bolivia un avance para las víctimas de la explotación y sea fruto, además, del acuerdo con algunas de las organizaciones que se asocian a los menores que trabajan, nada menos que porque hace visible y dota de derechos a una parte de la población que, por muy diversas razones culturales, económicas o sociopolíticas, es parte de la fuerza laboral de Bolivia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Entre los niños que trabajan en aquel país están los más de novecientos que se abandonan en las calles cada año, adolescentes que viven del maltrato o de la miseria y hasta quienes consideran que trabajar a los diez años es parte del proceso educativo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso pregunto si, además de la posición sancionadora, se plantean otras actuaciones para atacar la raíz de este mal en los países en los que se produce, y si pasos como este, al visibilizar este problema, pueden contribuir a solucionarlo.</p>
      <p sl="en">También quiero saber cuántos países incluidos en el SPG tienen problemas planteados por incumplimiento del Convenio sobre el trabajo infantil, y cuántos de los que aspiran a integrarse podrían tenerlos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-000" speaker_id="96646" name="Helmut Scholz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar und insbesondere Herr Kollege Stier! Das neue Kinder- und Jugendgesetz gibt den Kindern in Bolivien Rechte, wie sie in den meisten Mitgliedstaaten der Europäischen Union nicht existieren oder nicht umgesetzt sind.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kinder sind dort eigenständige Rechtssubjekte. In meinem eigenen Land – in Deutschland – ist die Umsetzung der Kinderrechtskonvention noch nicht so weit wie in Bolivien.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bolivien hat statt Bevormundung einen Weg gewählt und gefunden, der die Kinder an der Ausarbeitung des Gesetzes direkt beteiligte. Im Einklang mit der ILO-Konvention 138 hat Bolivien zum Ziel erklärt, bis 2020 die Gesellschaft so zu entwickeln, dass es kein Kind mehr nötig hat zu arbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Heute sieht, wie es schon gesagt wurde, die Realität leider noch anders aus: 750 000 Kinder müssen arbeiten. Sie haben sogar deshalb eine eigene Gewerkschaft gegründet und darauf gedrängt, dass ihr Status der Illegalität beendet wird. Das ist erreicht. Gefährliche Arbeiten bleiben entsprechend der ILO-Konvention 182 verboten. Für Arbeiten, denen Kinder aus der Not nachgehen, sind Ausnahmeregelungen möglich, jedoch nur, sofern ihr Recht auf Bildungszugang und Gesundheit nicht eingeschränkt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich meine, wir sollten …</p>
      <a text="(Der Präsident entzieht dem Redner das Wort.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-000" speaker_id="124993" name="Bodil Ceballos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Herr talman! I min grupp ser vi lagen, som har en del brister, ändå som ett bra första steg för att förbättra barns och ungdomars rättigheter generellt i Bolivia, inte minst eftersom den har ett rättighetsbaserat fokus och ser barn som subjekt i stället för objekt.</p>
      <p sl="en">De 348 artiklarna innehåller bland annat förbud mot diskriminering på grund av kön eller funktionshinder, en klagomöjlighet, barns och ungas rätt till en säker miljö, utbildning, information, personlig integritet m.m.</p>
      <p sl="en">I stället för att hota med indragna stöd tycker vi snarare att kommissionen ska delta mer finansiellt, för att faktiskt stötta implementeringen av lagen och för att också kunna bidra till barns skolgång. Är det någonting som kommissionen skulle kunna tänka sig att göra?</p>
      <p sl="en">Någon har också nämnt den här organisationen för barnarbetare som också har deltagit i detta arbete med att ta fram lagen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karel De Gucht" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me first of all say that the EU is not the monitoring body in this respect. We are not the monitoring body for the Minimum Age Convention; that is the task of the International Labour Organisation (ILO) and we rely on the ILO’s report before taking the next steps. This is done to keep the Generalised Scheme of Preferences (GSP+) objective because it grants tariff preferences unilaterally.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, you should not ignore the leveraging power of GSP+. Our partners know that there are legal conditions and that if they are not met we can temporarily withdraw the benefits of the scheme. That is why we are in touch with the Bolivian authorities to remind them not to take GSP+ status for granted.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the matter itself, at first sight it would seem that this law could be in contravention of ILO Convention No 138, which stipulates 15 years as the minimum working age for children but allows developing countries, such as Bolivia, to reduce that limit to 14 years. At the same time, ILO Convention No 138 specifies that children between the ages of 13 and 15 – or 12 and 14 for developing countries – may do light work as long as it does not hinder their education or harm their health.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bolivia ratified ILO Convention No 138 in 1997. When the new law was adopted, Vice-President Álvaro García Linera stated that the lower working age reflected the reality in Bolivia, one of the poorest countries in South America. On the other hand, the Bolivian law overall has been praised by UNICEF and by the Bolivian Ombudsman as reinforcing the protection of children, with the exception of two provisions lowering the working age.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, the ILO supervisory system has not yet been in a position to assess the compatibility of the law with Convention No 138. The ILO Committee of Independent Experts on the Application of Conventions and Recommendations (CEACR) will assess the compatibility of the Bolivian law with ILO standards in its November-December 2014 session. CEACR is the competent authority within the ILO to make such an assessment.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is fully aware of the issues raised in the European Parliament questions and is taking the necessary steps to ensure that Bolivia’s actions are fully in line with its GSP+ commitments. It has officially expressed its concerns in writing to the Bolivian authorities and expects a reply by mid-September. We have not received it yet. Similarly the Commission is in contact with the ILO, seeking advice on the interpretation of the new Bolivian law.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-000" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban.– Nem először tárgyalunk Bolíviáról, mint amelyik állam nem tartja be a nemzetközi kötelezettségvállalásait, és meglehetősen nagyvonalúan alakítja belső törvényeit. Így fontos, hogy a Bizottság következetesen kérje számon a gyermekmunkát már 10-12 évtől megengedő legújabb törvényt, hiszen ez nyíltan szembemegy a nemzetközi elvárásokkal. Ehhez az Unió nem járulhat hozzá közvetve sem programjain keresztül.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ez visszavezet azokhoz a nemzetközi kötelezettségek megszegéséhez, amelyek tisztességes bírósági eljárást írnak elő, és amelyeket Bolívia folyamatosan megszeg, mint Tóásó Előd esetében, aki immáron öt és fél éve van börtönben e latin-amerikai országban anélkül, hogy jogerős ítélet született volna ügyében. Ezúton szeretném megerősíteni az Európai Parlament vonatkozó határozatának felhívását, hogy Bolívia tartsa be a legalapvetőbb emberi jogok tiszteletét - legyen szó gyermekekről vagy olyan jogellenesen fogva tartott állampolgárokról, mint Tóásó Előd.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. One-minute speeches (Rule 163)">
    <intervention id="1-152-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgen die Ausführungen von einer Minute zu wichtigen politischen Fragen (Artikel 163 GO).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-000" speaker_id="124926" name="József Nagy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Engedjék meg, hogy az első felszólalásomban bemutatkozzam. Nagy József vagyok és Szlovákiából érkeztem, ennek ellenére anyanyelvemen, magyarul fogok felszólalni. A mai eseményeket vizsgálva számomra hátborzongató Európa békéjének a jövőjére gondolni. Ukrajna, Gáza, Szíria, Irak nincsenek olyan messze, mint azt sokan gondolnánk. Az Ukrajnával való kapcsolatunkat Putyin határozza meg, mert Európa széthúz. Az én országom polgárai és a szlovákiai magyarság tíz éve azért örült az uniós csatlakozásnak, mert a negyven év kommunista és orosz fennhatóság után itt látták biztosítottnak a szabadságot és a jövőt. És ehelyett ma az európai értékek és az integráció napi politikai érdekek miatt kerül veszélybe. Sőt, populista szólamok akadályozzák az egységet. Kérdezem például Farage képviselő urat, aki ebben a házban hevesen az Európai Unió integrációja ellen érvel, hogy mit üzen az eheti skót népszavazás résztvevőinek? Jobban járnak-e egy leszakadással? Vajon miért …</p>
      <a text="(Az elnök megvonta a szót a képviselőtől.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-000" speaker_id="124948" name="Siôn Simon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Europe needs to focus more of its resources on advanced manufacturing and engineering. Making things has become terribly unfashionable but it is actually what we are good at in this part of the world. By ‘this part of the world’ I mean Europe and particularly my constituency of the West Midlands. Firms like Jaguar Land Rover, Hadley Industries and East End Foods are exporting all over the world and creating thousands of jobs as they do so, but they are desperate to fill those jobs with more and better science, technology, engineering and maths (STEM) graduates.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have got to be more active on skills if we are serious about growth. That is why the European Semester and the Youth Guarantee must prioritise training whatever the other pressures. Our young people need sustainable, quality jobs and we need to give them the tools.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Bardzo często w naszych krajach martwimy się tym, że działalność Parlamentu Europejskiego nie budzi dostatecznego zainteresowania, nawet narzekamy na niedostateczną frekwencję w wyborach do Parlamentu Europejskiego.</p>
      <p sl="en">Natomiast w ubiegłym tygodniu do naszej siedziby w Brukseli przybyło trzech zwykłych ludzi z Polski, którzy jednocześnie dokonali rzeczy zupełnie niezwykłej. Roman, Wojciech i Grzegorz przeszli pieszo w pielgrzymce całą Europę.Wyruszyli z Knox w Irlandii, z Monte Cassino i z Głogowca w Polsce. Przynieśli do Parlamentu Europejskiego orędzie pokoju i ikonę św. Benedykta napisaną i pobłogosławioną na ogarniętej wojną Ukrainie. Myślę, że to orędzie, ich miłość, z jaką przyszli do siedziby instytucji europejskich, ich poświęcenie, ich wysiłek powinien być wzorem i natchnieniem dla nas wszystkich. I mam nadzieję, że ikona św. Benedykta, którą przynieśli, znajdzie godne miejsce w naszym …</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, mada je danas potpuno jasno da u našem mandatu neću imati nove kolegice i kolege, tj. očito će proces pregovora o proširenju trajati svih ovih 5 godina, ipak mislimo da nikako ne smijemo zaustaviti proširenje, odnosno proces pregovaranja. Dapače, mislim da ga trebamo intezivirati jer zemlje u jugoistočnoj Europi imaju konkretne ambicije.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naravno, da tu prije svega mislim na Srbiju, Crnu goru i Albaniju i upravo ljetošnji razgovori koje sam imao s premijerom Vučićem i premijerom Đukanovićem pokazuju odlučnu volju da Srbija i Crna gora, a naravno znamo i da je ista situacija u Albaniji, posebno naše kolegice i kolege u parlamentu, odnosno da i oni dobiju zastupnice i zastupnika.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naravno da to znači ispunjavanje svih obaveza koje oni imaju i o tome nemamo što diskutirati. Vjerujem da upravo Balkan treba mir, a mir se može nazvati imenom Europska unija. Zato pozivam da građanima tih država damo svoju perspektivu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-000" speaker_id="125051" name="Iosu Juaristi Abaunz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, la mayoría de la sociedad vasca tiene dos prioridades políticas: la paz y la autodeterminación. Y una mayoría electoral clara lo respalda, como refleja también nuestra presencia en este Parlamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es la hora de conseguir todos nuestros derechos como personas y como pueblo, incluido también el derecho de la ciudadanía vasca a ser lo que decida democráticamente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y la resolución del conflicto político vasco es, también, un asunto europeo. Este Parlamento tiene la oportunidad de instar, de nuevo, a los Gobiernos español y francés a ser valientes, a favorecer soluciones y no a mantener políticas y estrategias del pasado basadas en el «no» y en la venganza, como retratan el enésimo juicio político que empezará la semana que viene en la Audiencia Nacional española contra veintiocho jóvenes o el accidente sufrido por familiares de presos este fin de semana, fruto de la política de dispersión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Animo a este Parlamento a trabajar por la paz y la autodeterminación en sintonía con la mayoría de la sociedad vasca.</p>
      <p sl="en">¡Ese es nuestro compromiso!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-000" speaker_id="124933" name="Ernest Maragall" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <a text="(El orador comienza su intervención en catalán)"/>
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, Catalunya es una vieja nación europea, un sujeto político, consciente de que lo es y aún más de lo que pretende conseguir actuando en dicha condición. Y desde Catalunya llega una voz potente y clara, una vía democrática para legitimar la decisión que quiere tomar sobre su propio futuro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Europa no puede ni debe desentenderse de la aspiración libremente expresada por una sociedad comprometida en la construcción de su propio futuro, tanto como en el de la propia Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Europa está cambiando. Escocia y Catalunya son también ilustración positiva de ese cambio profundo: el cambio que se plantea en la distribución de poder entre la «Europa nueva» en construcción y cada uno de sus pueblos, naciones y Estados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nosotros queremos más Europa para ser mejor Catalunya. Y queremos ser Estado para ser mejor Europa, para darle nuestra más valiosa aportación social, cultural y económica.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege! Ich möchte Sie darauf hinweisen, dass wir hier 24 Amtssprachen liefern, und wenn Sie hier eine andere Sprache benutzen, dann sind die Dolmetschkabinen weder bereit noch in der Lage, dies zu übersetzen. Wenn Sie also möchten, dass man Sie auf dem ganzen Kontinent versteht – und dafür ist diese Bürgerkammer da –, dann bedienen Sie sich bitte einer der Amtssprachen der Europäischen Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-000" speaker_id="99650" name="Tim Aker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on 16 August 2014, 35 migrants crammed themselves into containers and docked themselves at Tilbury in my constituency. Sadly one died and, as tragic as this episode is, they have since tried to claim asylum. I think it would be wrong, and here is why. We are already known across Europe as ‘soft-touch Britain’, and this would only add to the United Kingdom being a soft touch.</p>
      <p sl="en">If we give asylum here, many more will put themselves in harm’s way in containers to come to the United Kingdom. We have proper processes in place to claim asylum in the UK and to migrate to the UK, and this is unfair to the wider community and to genuine migrants and asylum seekers. Next May, the British people and my constituents will be able to judge soft-touch Britain. They will be able to vote for UKIP, a party that rejects this Union and that will get our borders and our country back.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-000" speaker_id="124879" name="Janusz Korwin-Mikke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Europe was never united. The European states were fighting against each other but we were doing well, we were developing. Now, Europe under the occupation of the European Union, is at a standstill, it has zero growth – and the reason is the European Union. The acquis communautaire is the reason why we do not develop. The European Union is the exact opposite to Europe. The acquis communautaire is the exact opposite of European values. What in Europe was called ‘good’, in the European Union is called ‘bad’. We can see the reason very clearly. We will see the first caliphate not from ISIS, we will see the caliphate in the south of France. Normality must be returned. The European Union is an artificial product and it stops the development of Europe. The reason is the European Union and the acquis communautaire.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-000" speaker_id="118658" name="Brian Hayes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to refer to a long-running dispute involving a number of Irish construction companies which have had a very difficult time with the Polish authorities in the last few years. This dispute goes back to 2012. In excess of EUR 250 million has been lost. Many hundreds of jobs in Ireland have been lost through poor procurement procedure and poor contract procedure, and this was also the subject of a letter by five other European Union countries to the Polish authorities.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am looking for three things: firstly I would like the Polish roads authority to engage with the complainants in a fair and honest way; secondly, I am asking the Polish authorities to enter immediately into independent mediation to resolve this dispute; and thirdly I would ask the Commission, in the presence of one of the Commissioners here this evening, at the very least to consider this matter more closely. We are talking about EU funds, EU structural funds, the funds of the EU taxpayer, and we need to ensure that those funds are spent properly, with proper procurement procedures. There are issues in this case that need to be resolved.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-000" speaker_id="124949" name="Lucy Anderson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission’s consultation on water closes next week so today, as a new Member, I am pleased to support the work done by everyone in this Parliament and beyond on the Right to Water Campaign. Partnerships with the private sector for expertise, innovation and research can be beneficial, but exploitation of water resources for commercial profit is not.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my city of London we are still facing first-hand, through massive water bill rises, the shocking consequences of privatisation. We have a poorly-regulated monopoly private provider of water which last year paid well over EUR 100 million in dividends and interest payments to shareholders, and in the countries hardest hit by recession our own institutions in the EU have been attempting to insist on water privatisation despite international evidence against it.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is time for the Commission to be bold. We want no more excuses about the lack of legal base or application of principles of neutrality. EU-wide measures to promote democratic public control of water are the only answer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164-000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, los problemas territoriales que se viven en naciones europeas como Euskadi, Cataluña o Flandes, necesitan soluciones como la que se va a aplicar esta semana en Escocia: no imponer una solución que, por impuesta, nunca lo es y no impedir que la ciudadanía pueda debatir y decidir. En definitiva: política y democracia. En definitiva: diálogo, acuerdos y ratificación ciudadana. Por eso, reivindico el contenido de la Declaración de Estrasburgo para que un arbitraje europeo iguale los derechos de todos los ciudadanos de la Unión cuando algún Estado miembro se niegue a seguir este sencillo guión. Esas tensiones territoriales son un síntoma más del declive de los Estados tradicionales y una oportunidad para renovar el concepto de nación y para construir la Europa federal en la que partidos como el mío llevamos trabajando siete décadas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, 31 August 2014 last marked the 20th anniversary of the IRA’s cessation of military activity in Ireland – the pivotal moment in the Irish peace process – and, despite early setbacks, an inclusive talks process led to the historic Good Friday Agreement which created the space for those of different aspirations to strive for them through peaceful means. It was this inclusive dialogue that led to meaningful progress.</p>
      <p sl="en">In recent times, the principle of engaging in such dialogue has been found wanting within political unionism, and both the Irish Government and the British Government, but especially the latter, have largely disengaged from the process. EU institutions which have supported the Irish peace process need to be aware that flag protests, the breakdown of the Haas negotiations and the walkout by unionists from all-party talks some weeks ago threaten the political institutions that underpin the peace process in Ireland.</p>
      <p sl="en">I ask people here to encourage political unionism and the Irish and British Governments to re-engage in meaningful all-party talks to ensure that all outstanding elements of the Good Friday and subsequent agreements are implemented in full, so that the Irish peace process can continue to provide an example to conflicts around the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-000" speaker_id="4531" name="Jean Lambert" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wanted to draw attention to the horrific floods now hitting India and Pakistan, and not least the divided state of Kashmir, where we have seen hundreds of deaths, the displacement of thousands of people, and a huge loss of livelihood. These floods are likely to continue, and we are being told that they are the worst floods to hit Kashmir in decades.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are all aware of the fact that Kashmir is a flashpoint area, and we have seen recent incidents along the line of control – even during this current emergency. However, I think that we should be welcoming the mutual offers of assistance between the governments of India and Pakistan during these floods. I really want to urge the European Union to actively support engagement between those two governments over the questions of improved water management and disaster preparedness in that area. This is a real opportunity to bring governments together to actually work for the benefit of their people, rather than pursuing this ongoing conflict.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-000" speaker_id="124833" name="Laura Ferrara" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la crisi economica italiana unita all'emergenza immigrazione rischia di compromettere la tutela di diritti fondamentali ingenerando una lotta darwiniana tra i più deboli: da un lato, la disperazione dei cittadini in difficoltà economica, che finiscono col reclamare una priorità nella tutela dei propri diritti, dall'altro, la disperazione di chi è costretto a fuggire da persecuzioni e conflitti, disposto a rischiare la vita sfidando il Mediterraneo a bordo di un gommone.</p>
      <p sl="en">È notizia di ieri l'ennesima tragedia: duecentocinquanta persone affondate al largo delle coste libiche. L'Europa e i singoli Stati membri stanno destinando fiumi di denaro a un sistema di gestione di flussi non sempre trasparente e non privo di criticità e speculazioni. Cosa fare allora? Occorrono interventi più incisivi nei paesi di origine e di transito dei migranti. Occorre controllare la corretta gestione di fondi europei negli Stati membri per scongiurare frodi e sprechi. Occorre rivedere il regolamento di Dublino, al fine di attuare una reale solidarietà e cooperazione tra gli Stati membri. Occorre istituire corridoi umanitari affinché i migranti possano raggiungere direttamente la meta ambita senza rischiare la propria vita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι αποφάσεις της πρόσφατης συνόδου του ΝΑΤΟ στην Ουαλία στρέφονται ενάντια στους λαούς γιατί εντείνουν την επιθετικότητα της ιμπεριαλιστικής συμμαχίας και αυξάνουν τους κινδύνους ενός γενικευμένου ιμπεριαλιστικού πολέμου που θα πληρώσουν ακριβά οι λαοί με το αίμα τους. Το αποδεικνύουν ήδη οι στρατιωτικές ασκήσεις ΝΑΤΟ, Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών και Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης στο έδαφος της Ουκρανίας, κλιμακώνοντας την αντιπαράθεση με την καπιταλιστική Ρωσία για το μοίρασμα αγορών, ενεργειακών πηγών και εδαφών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η σημερινή διάσκεψη στο Παρίσι για τον συντονισμό της στρατιωτικής δράσης των ευρωνατοϊκών προθύμων κατά των λεγόμενων «τζιχαντιστών» που οι ίδιοι εξόπλισαν, δίνει ώθηση στους σχεδιασμούς για επαναχάραξη των συνόρων και γενίκευση της αντιπαράθεσης στην ευρύτερη περιοχή. Αποτελεί στρατηγική επιλογή της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης ή ακόμη μεγαλύτερη διασύνδεση με το ΝΑΤΟ.</p>
      <p sl="en">Είναι τεράστιες οι ευθύνες της ελληνικής κυβέρνησης γιατί συμμετέχει σε όλους τους επιθετικούς σχεδιασμούς της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και του ΝΑΤΟ. Το Κομμουνιστικό Κόμμα Ελλάδας απαιτεί να σταματήσει άμεσα κάθε συμμετοχή των ελληνικών ενόπλων δυνάμεων στις αποστολές της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και του ΝΑΤΟ και παλεύει για την αποδέσμευση της χώρας και από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και από το ΝΑΤΟ για λαϊκή εξουσία και κυριαρχία …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169-000" speaker_id="39726" name="László Tőkés" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A romániai magyarság egyöntetűen kiáll az erdélyi Székelyföld területi autonómiája mellett. A román pártok és maga a román kormány élesen ellenzi a kisebbségi önrendelkezés bármely formáját, és a többségi média magyarellenes sajtópropagandájával egybehangzóan ellenséges hajszát folytat a félmilliónyi székely-magyar közösség autonómiatörekvései ellen. A román hírszerző szolgálat a régi kommunista politikai rendőrség módjára uszít a magyar autonómia ellen. A Legfelsőbb Bírói Tanács a hatalmi ágak függetlenségének elvét durván megsértve, alkotmányellenes támadásként bélyegzi meg a legitim magyar törekvéseket. Kérem az elnök urat, az Európai Parlamentet, hogy védje meg az erdélyi magyarokat az alaptalan, soviniszta támadásoktól, és részesítse támogatásában jogos és demokratikus autonómiatörekvéseinket.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-170-000" speaker_id="124723" name="Péter Niedermüller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ma délután rövid vitában fölvetődött, hogy érdemes-e még a plenáris ülésen Magyarországgal foglalkozni. Az egyik kollégám, egyik képviselőtársam azt mondta, hogy nincs új fejlemény. Szeretném mondani, hogy van! A magyar miniszterelnök például a civil szervezeteket nemrég idegen hatalmak ügynökeinek nevezte. A magyar NGO-kat az adóhatósággal és a rendőrséggel zaklatja. Ennél fontosabbnak tartom leszögezni, hogy nem egyszerű magyar ügyről van szó, európai ügyről van szó! Most történik meg először, hogy egy uniós ország miniszterelnöke saját politikai hatalmát az európai közösség alapértékeivel, elveivel és eszméivel szemben igyekszik megszilárdítani. Azt gondolom, hogy nekünk, európai parlamenti képviselőknek alapvető feladatunk, hogy ebben az ügyben kieresszük a hangunkat, szólásra emelkedjünk, és azt mondjuk: ez egy európai ügy, nekünk kell megvédeni az európai politikát, az európai közösséget!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, ένα μεγάλο μέρος του δημοσίου χρέους της Ελλάδας βρίσκεται στα χέρια της Ευρωπαϊκής Κεντρικής Τράπεζας, η οποία αγόρασε, κατά τη διάρκεια της κρίσης, ομόλογα του ελληνικού δημοσίου στη δευτερογενή αγορά με έκπτωση τουλάχιστον 40%. Έτσι, η ΕΚΤ κατέβαλε 35 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ, πλην όμως απαιτεί να εξοφληθεί η ονομαστική αξία των ομολόγων αυτών, η οποία ανέρχεται σε 53 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ. Δηλαδή, κέρδος 22 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ. Με τον τρόπο αυτό ο κύριος Ντράγκι και η παρέα του, πουλώντας «αέρα κοπανιστό» κερδοσκοπούν ασύστολα και ανενδοίαστα σε βάρος του φτωχοποιημένου ελληνικού λαού.</p>
      <p sl="en">Μόνο για εφέτος, ο ελληνικός λαός θα πληρώσει «καπέλο» στην ΕΚΤ ύψους 4 δισεκατομμυρίων ευρώ και, για τον λόγο αυτό, η μνημονιακή κυβέρνηση στην Αθήνα έχει επιβάλει με τον ΕΝΦΙΑ δυσβάστακτους φόρους στην ακίνητη περιουσία των Ελλήνων. Όμως, ο ρόλος της ΕΚΤ δεν είναι να κερδοσκοπεί σε βάρος των πολιτών της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Έτσι, είναι και νόμιμο και ηθικό να «κουρευτούν» αυτά τα ομόλογα της ΕΚΤ και να πληρωθεί από την Ελλάδα μόνο το κεφάλαιο που κατέβαλε η ΕΚΤ για να αγοράσει τα εν λόγω ομόλογα, συν ένα επιτόκιο 0,15%.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-000" speaker_id="28116" name="Marian Harkin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in June 2012 the EU Council agreed to break the link between banks and sovereigns. The Summit statement spoke of the Euro Group examining the situation of the Irish financial sector in the context of using the ESM to retrospectively recapitalise Irish banks. Subsequently, there was some roll-back on this agreement, but just one month later a joint statement from Enda Kenny and Angela Merkel said that Ireland was a special case. Jean-Claude Juncker said earlier this year: ‘I think there must be some degree of retroactivity’ in the ESM, ‘otherwise it will lose most of its sense’.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yet to this day we have made no progress on this issue and, in case you did not know, Eurostat confirms that Ireland, which has less than 1% of the population of the EU, carried 43% of the net cost of the banking crisis. We now have banking union therefore the EU cannot renege on its promises. The ESM must be used to retrospectively recapitalise Irish banks – otherwise we will have been betrayed by our partners.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-000" speaker_id="124984" name="Lynn Boylan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, an EU and Irish citizen, 17-year-old Ibrahim Halawa, was arrested in August 2013 amongst clashes between pro- and anti-Morsi supporters while on holiday in Egypt. One year on, he is still languishing in an Egyptian jail with no charges brought against him. No book of evidence has been submitted and Ibrahim has had to endure horrific conditions including physical abuse. Both Amnesty International and the human rights organisation Reprieve have investigated Ibrahim’s case and have found no justification for his incarceration.</p>
      <p sl="en">On 12 August Ibrahim’s case was due to be heard as part of the notorious mass trials which take place without legal representation. Due to the hundreds of defendants presented before the judge in one go, he walked out in protest, leaving a teenager jailed without charge, unable to finish his final exams at school and progress to further education with his friends. So I am calling on the EU to explicitly request his release and I will be seeking a meeting with the new High Representative as soon as possible to ensure that everything that can be done at an EU level is being done.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-000" speaker_id="84175" name="Petr Mach" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, na tomto zasedání budeme debatovat o rozpočtu Evropské unie na rok 2015 ve výši asi 150 miliard EUR. Uvědomme si, že je to 150 miliard EUR sebraných z kapes občanů, že to nejsou peníze spadlé z nebe. Mnoho z vás si možná myslí, že peníze takto přerozdělované přes Brusel pomáhají k lepšímu životu v Evropě. Já si myslím, že to je velká domýšlivost, a myslím si pravý opak. Já se domnívám, že takto přerozdělované peníze škodí ekonomice, že zvyšují korupci a že zvyšují státní dluh.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za prvé, dotace jsou peníze, které získá podnikatel na úkor někoho jiného. Na trhu tedy vítězí ten, kdo získá dotace, a ne ten, kdo nabízí lepší služby spotřebitelům. Čím více peněz se přerozděluje, tím větší bude korupce. A za třetí, platí, že zejména chudší země si berou další a další půjčky, jenom aby mohly získat peníze na kofinancování těchto evropských dotací. Stručně řečeno, podle mě škodí tyto přerozdělované peníze ekonomice a myslím si, že bychom se obešli bez …</p>
      <a text="(Předsedající řečníkovi odebral slovo.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-000" speaker_id="124988" name="Deirdre Clune" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, small, regional airports have a vital role to play in the economic development of their regions. I would like the new Commission-designate to focus on those airports and to ensure that investment is provided so that they can continue to be the engines of the regions in which they are located and can contribute to an efficient and effective transport system that allows regions to take full advantage of the internal market and to trade on a global scale.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU enlargement means there are greater travel distances within the Union, so it is more important than ever that regions are served by airports. We also need to promote global accessibility: it is well known that, when companies are locating to or investing in an area, international accessibility is very important and the availability of a local airport is key to their location requirements. As the Union enlarges, tourism is another area where we can create great employment opportunities. I would like the Commission, in its next term, to ensure investment in our airports …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-000" speaker_id="38605" name="Илияна Йотова" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-н Председател, над 300 милиона евро са загубите от безпрецедентните валежи и наводнения в България само за последните 3 месеца. Бедствията оставиха стотици хора без покрив. Икономиката и селското стопанство ще се възстановяват години напред. За съжаление от промяната на климата са засегнати не само Югоизточна Европа и Балканите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Природата опровергава верността на собствените ни бюджетни сметки и драстичното намаляване на фонд „Солидарност“. Въпреки това, в началото на тази година ние променихме регламента тук в Европейския парламент, за да направим по-гъвкаво усвояването на средствата.</p>
      <p sl="en">До края на този месец Европейската комисия трябва да направи и правилника, по който страните ще усвояват тези средства. В лицето и на г-н де Гухт, който е тук, призовавам Европейската комисия да направи всичко възможно за един работещ документ, да има възможност за авансови плащания на най-засегнатите райони, а също така и за допълнителни средства там, където излизат дори извън рамките на регламента.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-000" speaker_id="112755" name="Andrej Plenković" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, večeras želim emancipirati pitanje prava Hrvata u Srbiji, Hrvata kao manjine kojih ima prema popisu iz 2011. godine nešto više od 57 000. Povod je recentna donacija predsjednika Srbije, Nikolića, udžbenika za Hrvate Bunjevce u Subotici i osnovnoškolce na ćirilici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Riječ je o potezu koji predstavlja kontinuitet razvodnjavanja hrvatskog korpusa i hrvatske manjine u Srbiji. Smatramo kako to nije dobro; to je politika koja se vodi od početka 90-ih, smatram da Europska komisija treba inzistirati u okviru pregovora o pristupanju - poglavlja 23 i 24, da pitanje poštivanja bilateralnog sporazuma između Hrvatske i Srbije iz 2004. godine bude jedan od sastavnih elemenata za daljnji put Srbije prema Europskoj uniji. Očekujemo vidjeti Hrvate i u predstavničkim tijelima Srbije te da se osiguraju sredstva i za jezik, obrazovanje, kulturu Hrvata u Srbiji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la crisi dei rifiuti in Italia, e soprattutto nel Sud Italia, è diventata ormai ciclica ed il sistema di smaltimento non funziona, nonostante le popolazioni diano prova di buona volontà, come dimostra il dato sull'aumento delle percentuali di raccolta differenziata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si assiste quindi ad un progressivo ed inesorabile aggravarsi delle condizioni di vita e delle già note responsabilità in tema di smaltimento e riciclo dei rifiuti, tanto che l'Italia è stata dichiarata inadempiente per violazione delle direttive sui rifiuti pericolosi e sulle discariche. La sanzione è meritata, e come potrebbe non esserlo se vi sono quattrocento ventidue aree a rischio, duecento diciotto discariche illegali e numerosi siti dimenticati e mai bonificati? È altrettanto vero però che una sanzione esemplare deve accompagnarsi ad un tentativo di cambiamento dell'intervento dell'Unione, finora forse non abbastanza efficace.</p>
      <p sl="en">È ora allo studio una proposta di direttiva su rifiuti ed imballaggi. È la nostra occasione per rinforzare l'azione europea, utilizzando i principi dell'economia circolare, un più rigoroso allineamento delle definizioni e dei controlli preventivi e della responsabilità estesa del produttore, delle restrizioni dei rifiuti urbani entro il 2030. Sono sicuro di trovare il consenso di tutti voi, onorevoli colleghi, al fine di trasformare un dramma in una risorsa delle nostre comunità.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">V Sloveniji smo že večkrat nasprotovali netransparentnemu umeščanju plinskih terminalov v Tržaškem zalivu, v neposredni meji med Slovenijo in Hrvaško.</p>
      <p sl="en">To je območje, kjer prebiva okoli sto tisoč ljudi, to je območje, kjer sta dve pomembni pristanišči – Koper in Trst, območje, ki je zaznamovano s turizmom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato je tudi zadnji postopek umeščanja plinskih terminalov nekaj stran od meje za Slovenijo nesprejemljivo, nesprejemljivo pa je predvsem postopek po katerem se ti terminali umeščajo, kajti slovenske okoljske organizacije, vlada Republike Slovenije in ostali pomembni akterji niso bili vključeni v ta postopek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato v Sloveniji pričakujemo, da se Slovenija, Italija pa tudi Hrvaška dogovorijo o umestitvi plinskih terminalov in da postopek poteka v skladu z evropskimi normami.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, am cerut să intervin pentru a semnala o declarație recentă a prim-ministrului Victor Ponta. Citez: „Efectele asupra societății românești lăsate de cei zece ani de regim Traian Băsescu sunt destul de asemănătoare cu cele lăsate de regimul nazist în Germania”.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mă adresez colegilor socialiști, familia politică a premierului român. Este vreunul dintre dumneavoastră de acord cu o asemenea afirmație? Poate fi comparată o democrație din Uniunea Europeană cu un regim totalitar? Sunteți de părere că o critică la adresa unui adversar, liberal sau conservator, poate merge până la trivializarea crimelor regimului nazist? Este criza traversată de Europa sinonimă cu Holocaustul? Credeți că Victor Ponta reprezintă o sensibilitate socialistă?</p>
      <p sl="en">Dacă răspunsul dumneavoastră, dragi colegi socialiști, e „nu”, ar fi bine să o spuneți public, fiindcă premierul Ponta vrea să fie, peste două luni, președintele Ponta. Nu îl puteți opri, doar alegătorii români o pot face. Aveți însă posibilitatea să explicați regulile confruntării democratice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Damit ist dieser Tagesordnungspunkt geschlossen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Agenda of the next sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
