<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20161003.EN" lang="en" date="2016-10-03" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die am Donnerstag, 15. September 2016, unterbrochene Sitzungsperiode für wieder aufgenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Statement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-006-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin Schulz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sehr geehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Am vergangenen Freitag nahm die Welt Abschied von Shimon Peres, von diesem außergewöhnlichen Staatsmann und unermüdlichen Verfechter des Friedens. Staatspräsident Peres hatte eine Vision von einem befriedeten Nahen Osten, in dem Israel mit seinen palästinensischen Nachbarn und den arabischen Staaten gewaltfrei zusammenleben sollte. Shimon Peres verfolgte diese Vision, und er setzte sie mit seinem Mitwirken am Osloer Friedensabkommen im September 1993 um. Für diesen Meilenstein im Friedensprozess im Nahen Osten wurde er 1994 neben Yitzhak Rabin und Jassir Arafat mit dem Friedensnobelpreis ausgezeichnet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Shimon Peres war ein Freund Europas. Er hat uns mehrere Male hier im Europäischen Parlament mit seiner Anwesenheit beehrt und zu uns gesprochen. Ich denke, Sie werden mir zustimmen, wenn ich sage, dass seine Persönlichkeit, sein Charisma und seine Ideen uns jedes Mal, wenn er bei uns war, inspiriert haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Seine Nachricht war einfach und klar: Gebt niemals auf, für den Frieden zu kämpfen! Das Erbe von Shimon Peres ist gewaltig, und es liegt nun in der Verantwortung der nächsten Generation von Politikern in Israel, seinen Weg von Diplomatie, Dialog und Versöhnung weiterzugehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Namen des Europäischen Parlaments möchte ich seiner Familie, seinen Freunden, den ihm nahestehenden Menschen und dem israelischen Volk unser tiefes Mitgefühl aussprechen. Ich darf Sie bitten, sich zu Ehren von Shimon Peres von Ihren Plätzen zu erheben.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament erhebt sich zu einer Schweigeminute.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Announcement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Martin Schulz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Am morgigen Dienstag werden wir den Generalsekretär der Vereinten Nationen, Herrn Ban Ki-moon, und die Umweltministerin der Französischen Republik, Frau Ségolène Royal, in ihrer Eigenschaft als amtierende Präsidentin der COP-21-Klimakonferenz bei uns begrüßen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich werde Ihnen nachher eine Änderung der morgigen Tagesordnung vorschlagen, um eine kurze feierliche Sitzung zur möglichen Ratifizierung des Pariser Klimaschutzabkommens morgen hier im Hause abzuhalten, bei der der Generalsekretär der Vereinten Nationen zu uns hier im Plenum sprechen möchte. Nach der feierlichen Sitzung soll dann die Abstimmung hier im Plenum über die Zustimmung unseres Hauses zur Ratifizierung dieses Abkommens erfolgen. Diese Abstimmung ist natürlich davon abhängig, ob heute Abend der Umweltausschuss in seiner Sitzung eine positive Empfehlung für die Beschlussfassung morgen im Plenum abgibt. Es wird dann morgen an uns liegen, hier den letzten politischen Schritt auf dem Weg zur förmlichen Ratifizierung dieses Abkommens durch die EU und ihre Mitgliedstaaten zu gehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sollte morgen hier in diesem Hause die Ratifizierung erfolgen, könnte das Pariser Übereinkommen weniger als ein Jahr nach seiner Verabschiedung in Kraft treten – noch rechtzeitig vor der COP-22-Klimakonferenz in Marakkesch. Mit der Abstimmung morgen hier und dem bindenden Charakter für die Mitgliedstaaten der Europäischen Union wäre auch das Mindestquorum, das die Vereinten Nationen brauchen, um das Klimaschutzabkommen weltweit in Kraft zu setzen, erreicht. Deshalb kommt der morgigen Abstimmung sicher eine außerordentliche Bedeutung zu.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Verification of credentials : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Request for the waiver of parliamentary immunity : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Corrigenda (Rule 231): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-018-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Der endgültige Entwurf der Tagesordnung dieser Tagung, wie er in der Konferenz der Präsidenten in ihrer Sitzung vom Donnerstag, dem 29. September 2016 gemäß Artikel 149 der Geschäftsordnung festgelegt wurde, ist verteilt worden. Zu diesem Entwurf wurden folgende Änderungen beantragt:</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019-0000" speaker_id="124801" name="Cécile Kashetu Kyenge" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, prima di passare all'ordine del giorno di questa settimana, ho chiesto la parola per ricordare il 3 ottobre 2013, una giornata in cui hanno perso la vita molti migranti al largo di Lampedusa. Questa giornata viene ricordata come una giornata della memoria e dell'accoglienza di tutte le persone che perdono la vita quando lasciano il proprio paese e anche per ricordare coloro i quali soccorrono queste persone. Io chiedevo di ricordare questa giornata anche qui in Aula.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Kyenge, Sie haben ganz sicher Recht. Ich glaube, dass im Verlauf der Sitzungswoche die Flüchtlingsproblematik und auch die tragischen Fälle sicher zur Sprache kommen werden. Im Übrigen ist nach meinem Kenntnisstand auch Frau Nicolini, die Bürgermeisterin von Lampedusa, in dieser Woche hier im Hause. Ich werde auch mit ihr zusammentreffen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-0000" speaker_id="96852" name="Cornelia Ernst" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich denke, es ging um eine Gedenkminute. Das, denke ich, sollten wir doch wenigstens tun – unabhängig von den Debatten. Und das beantrage ich jetzt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Schönen Dank.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir kommen nun zur heutigen Tagesordnung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Montag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Einvernehmen mit den Fraktionen schlage ich folgende Änderungen des endgültigen Entwurfs der Tagesordnung vor:</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Bericht von Isabelle Thomas für heute über die Möglichkeiten zur Vereinheitlichung der Fischereikontrolle in Europa, der für eine kurze Darstellung heute Abend vorgesehen war, wird im Einvernehmen mit den Fraktionen auf die Oktober-II-Tagung vertagt.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament nimmt die Änderung an.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Dienstag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich hatte eben schon bei meiner Einführung darauf hingewiesen: Der Umweltausschuss stimmt heute Abend über den Bericht von Herrn La Via über den Abschluss des Pariser Übereinkommens im Namen der Europäischen Union im Rahmen des Übereinkommens der Vereinten Nationen über Klimaänderungen ab. Wenn der Bericht im Ausschuss heute Abend angenommen wird, dann wird er am Dienstag hier in die Abstimmungsstunde aufgenommen. Das muss ich zunächst feststellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meine Damen und Herren! Der Generalsekretär der Vereinten Nationen – ich sagte das eben – hat eine Einladung zur Teilnahme an der morgigen Abstimmung angenommen, mit der Begründung, dass mit der morgigen Abstimmung hier und der damit verbunden Weiterleitung des Abstimmungsergebnisses an den Rat und der Hinterlegung der Ratifizierung bei den Vereinten Nationen das Mindestquorum, das die Vereinten Nationen brauchen, um das Klimaschutzabkommen weltweit in Kraft zu setzen, erreicht wird. Das ist ganz ohne Zweifel ein besonderer Vorgang. Ich beabsichtige deshalb, morgen zu Beginn, um 12.00 Uhr, Herrn Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon das Wort zu geben. Er hat darum gebeten, eine kurze Ansprache an die Abgeordneten halten zu können. Ich würde Sie also bitten, um zwölf Uhr zu dieser feierlichen Sitzung hier zu sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Danach gibt es vor der Abstimmung eine kurze Runde der Fraktionsvorsitzenden. Dann stimmen wir über die Ratifizierung des Klimaschutzabkommens ab. Wenn die Abstimmung eine Mehrheit hier im Hause findet – was ich unterstelle –, werde ich anschließend im Beisein von Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon, Kommissionspräsident Juncker, dem zuständigen Energie- und Umweltkommissar und der Ratsseite sowie Frau Royal als amtierender Vorsitzender der Konferenz COP 21 den Übermittlungsbrief an den Rat hier unterschreiben. Mit dieser Unterschrift kann der Rat unmittelbar handeln, und damit ist der Weg frei gemacht für die Inkraftsetzung des Klimaabkommens, rechtsverbindlich für alle Staaten der Vereinten Nationen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das ist morgen ganz sicher ein außergewöhnlicher Tag, weil durch den Beschluss des Europäischen Parlaments das Mindestquorum hier erreicht wird. Ich würde mich freuen, wenn Sie morgen die Anwesenheit von Generalsekretär Ban Ki-moon durch Ihre Anwesenheit auch verstärken könnten.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament nimmt die Änderungen an.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Mittwoch:</p>
      <p sl="en">Die ECR-Fraktion beantragt, die Erklärung der Kommission zu Frauenrechten in Polen, die als vierter Punkt am Nachmittag vorgesehen ist, von der Tagesordnung abzusetzen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-0000" speaker_id="96796" name="Ryszard Antoni Legutko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Wnoszę o usunięcie punktu dotyczącego tzw. praw kobiet w Polsce. Po pierwsze, ingerencja instytucji unijnych w tę kwestię jest niedopuszczalna na gruncie art. 5 ust. 1 i 2 Traktatu o Unii Europejskiej, gdzie czytamy: „wszelkie kompetencje nieprzyznane Unii w Traktatach należą do państw członkowskich”. Otóż nie ma w przepisach Traktatów niczego, co przyznawałoby Unii kompetencję do spraw aborcji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po drugie, wykładnię tę potwierdził Trybunał Sprawiedliwości Unii Europejskiej w sprawie 150/90 Society for the Protection of the Unborn Children v. Grogan i orzeczenie to nadal obowiązuje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po trzecie, ingerencja instytucji unijnych w kwestie aborcji nie ma również uzasadnienia w Karcie praw podstawowych, gdzie w art. 51 ust. 2 czytamy: „Niniejsza Karta nie ustanawia nowych kompetencji ani zadań Unii, ani też nie zmienia kompetencji i zadań określonych w Traktatach”.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podsumowując: wszelkie ingerencje Parlamentu Europejskiego w rzeczonej materii mają w sposób oczywisty charakter pozaprawny.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Temat tej debaty nie leży w kompetencjach Parlamentu Europejskiego. Dlaczego? Dlatego, że kwestie światopoglądowe należą do kompetencji krajowych. Panie Przewodniczący, temat tej dyskusji byłby fałszywy – i przed tym ostrzegam. Bo jeśli mamy mówić o prawach kobiet w Polsce, to powinniście Państwo powiedzieć o tym, że to w Polsce różnica między płacami kobiet i mężczyzn jest najniższa wśród państw OECD, że to Polska jest drugim krajem OECD z najwyższym wskaźnikiem kobiet inwestorów, że czwarte miejsce wśród krajów OECD zajmuje Polska pod względem równego traktowania kobiet w miejscach pracy. I wreszcie, że badania Agencji Praw Podstawowych pokazują, że to Polska jest krajem o najniższej skali przemocy fizycznej i seksualnej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szanowni Państwo! Parlament Europejski powinien zajmować się dziś tymi problemami, które stoją przed zjednoczoną Europą: kryzysem bezpieczeństwa, kryzysem gospodarczym, rozpadającą się na naszych oczach Europą.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zapraszam Państwa do pięknej Polski, gdzie żyją Polki, które się kształcą, edukują, pracują, zakładają rodziny. Zobaczcie, jak Polska wygląda naprawdę. Pochylcie się nad tym. Nie chcemy rozmawiać o aborcji, gdyż jest to kompetencja państwa członkowskiego.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-0000" speaker_id="124992" name="Malin Björk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Det är klart att vi ska prata om kvinnors rättigheter. Vi ska prata om löneskillnader och beslutsfattande, men vi ska också prata om kvinnors rätt till sina kroppar. Det handlar om mänskliga rättigheter, och i det här huset pratar vi ofta om mänskliga rättigheter. Det ska vi göra, men vi ska också prata om kvinnors mänskliga rättigheter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Polen har redan blivit dömt för sin repressiva abortpolitik, och idag tycker jag att det är viktigt att vi uppmärksammar att det här rör sig om ännu grymmare lagstiftning. Jag tycker att det är viktigt att den debatteras och att kollegorna får veta vad det faktiskt handlar om. Vi kan inte ha ett jämställt Europa om inte kvinnor får bestämma över sina kroppar. Det ska upp i kammaren och det ska debatteras.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich lasse über den Antrag abstimmen. Der Antrag lautet, die Erklärung der Kommission zu Frauenrechten in Polen als vierten Punkt von der Tagesordnung abzusetzen.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament lehnt den Antrag ab.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Bitte sehr, Sie wollen sich zur Geschäftsordnung melden?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Chciałem zapytać, dlaczego nie udzielił Pan mi głosu, ponieważ chciałem dowiedzieć się, jaki jest prawdziwy sens tego głosowania, które przed chwilą odbywaliśmy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Temat jest sformułowany niezwykle enigmatycznie. Koledzy występujący za uchyleniem tego punktu przypuszczali, że chodzi o sprawy prawa do życia. Z tego, co mówiła pani poseł Björk, wynika tak również. A myśmy niedawno dyskutowali na temat demokracji konstytucyjnej w Polsce i chcę, żebyśmy wszyscy mieli świadomość, że polski Trybunał Konstytucyjny 28 maja 1997 r. sformułował orzeczenie obowiązujące po dziś dzień, stwierdzające jasno, że fundamentem demokratycznego państwa prawa jest prawo do życia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ja bym chciał się dowiedzieć, jakie jest stanowisko Parlamentu Europejskiego: czy wy chcecie znieść demokrację w konstytucyjnej Polsce, czy tak naprawdę mówić o Trybunale Konstytucyjnym, bo ja do tej pory nie wiem, co ma być przedmiotem tej debaty, i pan przewodniczący właściwie uniemożliwił mi uzyskanie informacji na temat tego, o co chodzi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Jurek, zunächst einmal stelle ich fest, dass Ihre Wortmeldung keine Wortmeldung zur Geschäftsordnung war, keineswegs. Sie haben hier eine politische Kommentierung abgegeben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zweitens: Der Antrag war eindeutig und ist übrigens von Ihrem Fraktionskollegen Legutko ziemlich präzise und umfassend formuliert worden, nämlich den Punkt von der Tagesordnung abzusetzen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich kann Ihnen aber sagen, warum ich Ihnen das Wort nicht gegeben habe. Bei Anträgen zur Tagesordnung wird der Antrag gestellt, das hat Herr Kollege Legutko gemacht. Dann gibt es einen Redner oder eine Rednerin dafür, das war Frau Wiśniewska, und einen Redner oder eine Rednerin dagegen, das war Frau Björk. Danach wird abgestimmt. Das ist das ganz übliche und übrigens in der Geschäftsordnung so vorgesehene Verfahren. Eine Aussprache über diese Anträge gibt es nicht. Deshalb hatte ich Ihnen das Wort nicht gegeben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Frau Fotyga, Sie haben sich zur Geschäftsordnung gemeldet. Bitte begründen Sie, auf welchen Artikel der Geschäftsordnung Sie sich beziehen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-029-0000" speaker_id="28353" name="Anna Elżbieta Fotyga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to enquire about the equal treatment of Member States within the EU, because in virtually every EU Member State there is a popular movement requesting consideration of certain legislative measures. For example, in Finland, one such request with 60 000 signatures, on issues relating to the right to abortion, was also deliberated upon in the parliament, yet we did not discuss that issue. Why is this one so? The current legislative measures are popular, societal initiatives, not governmental ones. Why are we considering it during this session?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Fotyga, ich werde den Text im Protokoll nochmal nachlesen und nachforschen, wo Sie sich auf die Geschäftsordnung bezogen haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mittwoch:</p>
      <p sl="en">Die GUE-Fraktion beantragt, eine Erklärung der Kommission zur Lage in Ungarn, und zwar zur Kampagne zum Referendum und zu Aspekten des europäischen internationalen Asylrechts, als fünften Punkt am Nachmittag nach der Debatte über die Frauenrechte in Polen auf die Tagesordnung zu setzen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine Vergiat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. – Monsieur le Président, hier, un référendum a eu lieu en Hongrie pour demander aux Hongrois s'ils voulaient que l'Union européenne puisse rendre obligatoire l'installation de quotas de réfugiés dans le pays. Les Hongrois ont voté – dont acte –, mais pas en nombre suffisant pour que le résultat de ce référendum puisse être validé. C'est une victoire pour ceux qui ont appelé au boycott. Ce qui nous inquiète et ce sur quoi nous voulons un débat, ce sont les conditions de cette campagne, au regard des règles européennes et internationales en matière de droits de l'homme et, notamment, de la convention de Genève.</p>
      <p sl="en">J'ai entre les mains les affiches de la campagne officielle intitulée «Tudta?» («Le saviez-vous?»). Les affirmations proposées sont consternantes en ce qu'elles manipulent des amalgames, notamment entre terrorisme et immigration. Je vais prendre un exemple: «Bruxelles veut installer l'équivalent d'une ville d'immigrés illégaux en Hongrie». Le quota en Hongrie, si celui-ci avait été accepté, c'est 1 294 personnes. Vraiment une toute petite ville, pour ne pas dire un village. C'est 0,01 % de la population hongroise, pas de quoi bouleverser les valeurs de la Hongrie, me semble-t-il.</p>
      <p sl="en">De tels mensonges sont-ils dignes des valeurs de l'Union européenne? Il me semble que le Parlement européen devrait, au moins, en débattre et avoir l'avis de la Commission, tout comme sur l'évolution des législations en matière d'immigration et d'asile.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'est pourquoi nous voulons un débat sur ce sujet, Monsieur le Président, et nous demandons que le Parlement européen se prononce par scrutin public.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, je crois en effet que la question qui a été soulevée dans le cadre du référendum hongrois est une question de portée européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les réactions observées au sein du corps citoyen hongrois sont des réactions que l'on observe ailleurs en Europe. Je pense donc qu'il est tout à fait indiqué que nous prenions un instant pour réfléchir à ce qui s'est passé en Hongrie, mais selon une perspective véritablement européenne. Cela ne doit pas être un festival de finger pointing – je ne trouve pas la bonne expression pour cela en français –, mais bien un exercice de réflexion collective sur la façon dont nous prenons en charge le défi des migrations et des réfugiés. Selon moi, il sortira assez clairement du débat qu'il n'y a qu'ensemble que nous pouvons y remédier ou, je dirais plutôt, y faire face.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-0000" speaker_id="96768" name="Enrique Guerrero Salom" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, mi Grupo no quiere que se debata en este Pleno, pero quiere que se discuta en la Comisión de Libertades Civiles, Justicia y Asuntos de Interior y se debata en el Pleno más adelante. ¿Por qué razón? A nosotros nos preocupa la situación en Hungría —este Parlamento ha debatido sobre ello varias veces, porque las políticas del Gobierno húngaro, del Gobierno de Orban, continuamente se sitúan al margen, cuando no fuera de los valores fundamentales de la Unión—. Y, por tanto, ese debate lo hemos tenido. Pero ese debate ha sido siempre aprovechado por el señor Orban para plantear un conflicto inexistente entre el Parlamento Europeo y Hungría.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ayer quedó demostrado que el conflicto existe entre el Gobierno de Orban y sus ciudadanos. Y sus ciudadanos dejaron en minoría al Gobierno de Orban de una manera clara. Rechazaron su tentación populista. No oscurezcamos su derrota. Pongamos el foco sobre su derrota. Llevemos la cuestión a la Comisión LIBE. Preparemos el debate y traigámosla de nuevo al Pleno.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-0000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine Vergiat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">J'ai demandé un scrutin public.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Vergiat, Sie haben Recht. Das ist mir hier oben nicht richtig übermittelt worden. Sie hatten eine namentliche Abstimmung beantragt. Ich bitte um Entschuldigung. Der Fehler liegt also bei mir. Ich eröffne daher die Abstimmung erneut, diesmal eine namentliche Abstimmung.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament lehnt den Antrag ab.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Donnerstag: Keine Änderungen.</p>
      <a text="(Der Arbeitsplan ist somit angenommen.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. The future of ACP-EU relations beyond 2020 (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="1911" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Norbert Neuser im Namen des Entwicklungsausschusses über die Zukunft der Beziehungen zwischen den AKP-Staaten und der EU nach 2020 (2016/2053(INI)) (A8-0263/2016).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="96844" name="Norbert Neuser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Seit 2000 gilt das Cotonou-Abkommen zwischen den 28 EU— Mitgliedstaaten und den Staaten Afrikas, der Karibik und des Pazifik. Dieses Abkommen ist weltweit einmalig. Es ist das Ergebnis einer engen Zusammenarbeit unserer Länder in Europa mit 78 Ländern – überwiegend Entwicklungsländern –, das sich auf das HYPERLINK "http://www.bpb.de/nachschlagen/lexika/lexikon-der-wirtschaft/20027/lome-abkommen" Lomé-Abkommen I und II aus den Siebzigerjahren bezieht. Das Cotonou-Abkommen läuft in wenigen Jahren aus. Deshalb ist es gut, jetzt früh genug die Weichen zu stellen, was über 2020 hinaus geschehen soll.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das Europäische Parlament ist gut aufgestellt. Wir legen diesen Bericht heute vor und damit unsere Position zu den AKP-Beziehungen dar. Dem wird die Kommission in wenigen Wochen oder Monaten folgen; dann ist der Rat gefordert. Die Verhandlungen, bei denen die Kommission mit vertreten war, haben ergeben, dass wir als Parlamentarier ungefähr auf der Linie der Kommission liegen. Deswegen wäre es gut, wenn wir im Parlament eine breite Mehrheit zustande bekommen, weil es in den Mitgliedstaaten, beim Europäischen Rat, auch in einigen Ländern Widerstand gegen eine Fortführung dieses Abkommens gibt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Warum glaube ich, dass dieses Abkommen fortgeführt werden soll? Es gibt einen rechtlichen Rahmen, den wir ohne dieses Abkommen nach 2020 nicht mehr hätten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen auch sehen, dass wir uns insgesamt – als Europäer und auch als Parlamentarier – besser aufstellen. Die Akzeptanz unter den Parlamentariern könnte besser sein, das Engagement der Mitgliedstaaten ebenfalls. Ich verweise darauf, dass sich seit dem Jahr 2013 die Mitgliedstaaten, die jeweils die Ratspräsidentschaft innehatten, geweigert haben, die Paritätische Parlamentarische Versammlung AKP-EU zu beherbergen. Das waren Irland, Griechenland und die Niederlande, und ich hoffe, dass sich vielleicht im nächsten Jahr Malta, wenn es die Ratspräsidentschaft hat, sich anders verhalten wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Bedeutung des AKP-Abkommens ist, in drei Säulen zusammengefasst, einmal die entwicklungspolitische Zusammenarbeit, die politische Dimension und die Zusammenarbeit im wirtschaftlichen und im handelspolitischen Bereich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei der Diskussion um die Fortführung wurde oft dargelegt, dass wir von europäischer Seite zu wenig Menschenrechtsverletzungen mit unseren afrikanischen, karibischen und pazifischen Partnern diskutieren. Das liegt aber auch an uns, weil das Cotonou-Abkommen bisher in den Artikeln 8 und 96 durchaus diese Möglichkeit sieht, und wir sollten dies auch in Zukunft, wenn das Abkommen verlängert wird, stärker berücksichtigen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben neue Herausforderungen nach 2020 in einem Abkommen anzugehen. Ich nenne den Klimawandel, die Migration, die neuen SDGs und die Bekämpfung des Terrorismus – globale Themen, die wir im Rahmen der EU-AKP gut lösen können und wo wir uns gemeinsam mit unseren Partnern auf Lösungen festlegen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Was brauchen wir in der Zukunft? Wir brauchen eine bessere regionale Orientierung, weil nicht alle Themen, die die kleinen Inselstaaten oder die großen Länder wie Nigeria und Südafrika haben, alle berühren, und deswegen, denke ich, brauchen wir neue regionale Strukturen unter einem gemeinsamen Dach, und durch die Paritätische Parlamentarische Versammlung AKP-EU parlamentarisch abgefedert.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neven Mimica" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to thank the Committee on Development and the rapporteur, Mr Neuser, for the report on the future of ACP—EU relations beyond 2020. I also thank the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on International Trade and the Committee on Budgets for their opinions.</p>
      <p sl="en">This report is an important milestone. The Cotonou Agreement binds us with almost 80 countries in the world. We have a unique opportunity ahead of us. Let us put the EU global strategy into practice and let us use a future partnership as a vehicle for implementing the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development jointly.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am pleased to express support for this report. Let me point out some of the features I find most important. We are aiming for a partnership that is flexible enough to cope with a radically, and rapidly, changing international environment. We should aim to address effectively common challenges and take advantage of economic opportunities to deliver peace and prosperity for our people, both in the European Union and in the ACP countries. We need a partnership that reflects and reinforces EU interests, objectives and means, as well as those of our ACP partners. This new partnership should keep what has worked, but we should also use the opportunity to improve, or create new ways of working, where weaknesses have been shown. Our main concern should be to keep the essential elements as global safeguards, such as respect for human rights, democracy and the rule of law, as well as good governance. This is clearly fundamental.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should also maintain and reinforce our regular political dialogue with our partner countries. International commitments, such as the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development or the Paris climate agreement, should be central references in a future partnership. Enhancing dialogue with ACP countries in order to forge global alliances in multilateral settings offers a new perspective for a future partnership. An excellent case in point was the final round of negotiations during COP 21 in Paris. The fight to eradicate poverty and combat inequalities is at the heart of our policies and we know that efforts should be maintained.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also expect strong commitment on the part of the ACP countries. Any future framework that links the ACP to the EU should learn from the positive aspects of Cotonou, including its legally binding nature. The world around us is evolving and so are the roles of organisations and institutions. The partnership should recognise this and give due consideration to all levels, both continental and regional. It should equally reflect on how to involve national parliaments and other actors at local level, as well as non-state actors, in our project. The impact of the private sector should also be fostered since it has proven to be an essential motor for development. The report encourages engagement with additional countries as well as our current ACP partners. For the sake of geographical and political coherence, this certainly merits consideration.</p>
      <p sl="en">While I trust that many honourable Members share most of these opinions, I look forward now to hearing your comments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="125997" name="Javier Couso Permuy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Asuntos Exteriores. – Señora Presidenta, como sabemos, los Acuerdos de Asociación han tenido numerosos impactos negativos en las economías de los países ACP, por lo que es necesario una nueva asociación, justa, entre iguales, que respete la soberanía de los países, que busque la satisfacción de las necesidades básicas y el respeto de los derechos humanos. La nueva asociación deberá promover el desarrollo de las capacidades productivas de los países, proteger la agricultura tradicional y luchar contra el acaparamiento de tierras.</p>
      <p sl="en">Apoyamos la decisión de las Naciones Unidas de crear un instrumento jurídico a fin de que las empresas respeten los derechos humanos, para acabar con la explotación laboral, la esclavitud moderna, el flujo ilícito de capitales y la financiación del terrorismo o de los conflictos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es importante subrayar la universalidad de los derechos humanos consagrados en el Derecho internacional —incluyendo el Derecho internacional de los migrantes y refugiados—, que deben ser respetados, así como la Convención de Ginebra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quisiera señalar, finalmente, la importancia de acabar con la injerencia extranjera en los asuntos internos, así como el fin de las políticas neocoloniales y el desmantelamiento de todas las bases militares extranjeras.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="124953" name="Jude Kirton-Darling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on International Trade">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, our economic and political relations with the African, Caribbean and Pacific countries have never been more important, and this report sets out three key principles for our future relations with those countries beyond 2020 and the current Cotonou Agreement. Firstly, the sustainable development goals must be at the heart of our future partnership. Secondly, any post-Cotonou agreement must remain legally binding and enforceable. And thirdly, we must strengthen the involvement of civil society and improve monitoring structures.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our trade policy and economic partnership agreements (EPAs) are central to this strategy. These regional instruments should support the overall framework agreement. However, there is a real danger here. A new framework agreement will only come once Cotonou expires after 2020, and yet we are already voting on the content of those EPAs, now and in the coming months, and the agreements so far put before this House have been a long way away from the principles contained in this report.</p>
      <p sl="en">I therefore urge colleagues not only to support Norbert Neuser’s excellent report but also to follow through when considering the ratification of future EPAs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-0000" speaker_id="96991" name="Eider Gardiazabal Rubial" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Presupuestos. – Señora Presidenta, señor Comisario, desde la Comisión de Presupuestos consideramos que la coincidencia en el tiempo de la finalización del actual marco financiero (2014-2020) y el Acuerdo de Cotonú nos brinda una oportunidad perfecta para que, por fin, tal y como viene reclamando hace tiempo este Parlamento, el Fondo Europeo de Desarrollo pueda ser incluido en los presupuestos europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y para ello consideramos fundamental que la Comisión empiece a trabajar desde ya en una hoja de ruta y la pueda presentar antes del próximo marco financiero. Eso creemos que le daría mayor legitimidad y eficacia al Fondo y, sobre todo, nos permitiría coordinar y mejorar la coherencia de las políticas de la Unión y de los instrumentos existentes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero recordar que la lucha contra la pobreza es esencial para afrontar las causas de la migración y de los desplazamientos forzosos y que, por lo tanto, esta tiene que seguir siendo uno de los objetivos globales de la Unión. Y con esto quiero decir que los nuevos instrumentos que ha planteado la Comisión, como el plan de inversiones para África o el fondo fiduciario, no pueden en ningún caso comprometer la política de cooperación al desarrollo, ni tampoco utilizar fondos para fines distintos a los que ya hemos tratado.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="96931" name="Maurice Ponga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe PPE. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, je souhaitais tout d'abord remercier notre collègue, Norbert Neuser, pour le travail réalisé et pour l'excellente collaboration sur ce dossier.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce rapport est important car il énonce nos priorités sur l'avenir de nos relations avec les pays ACP et permettra, je l'espère, d'orienter la Commission européenne dans ses propositions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je suis convaincu que nous devons nous servir de l'acquis de Cotonou et l'améliorer afin de répondre aux nouveaux défis mondiaux que sont notamment la migration ou bien le changement climatique. Nous ne pouvons pas repartir de zéro. Il faut avancer et faire progresser ce qui existe déjà.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ainsi, il faut garder un texte juridiquement contraignant qui s'adresse à l'ensemble du groupe ACP, même si la dimension régionale doit être mieux prise en compte. Il me semble important d'inscrire notre partenariat après 2020 dans le cadre des nouveaux objectifs de développement durable et d'insister pour que les droits de l'homme et la bonne gouvernance soient les pierres angulaires de notre partenariat avec les pays ACP.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si nous appelons à une budgétisation du Fonds européen de développement dans notre rapport, celle-ci doit être soumise à deux conditions préalables. Tout d'abord, le maintien des enveloppes existantes et, deuxièmement, la création d'un instrument permettant de financer les dépenses sécuritaires liées au développement. En effet, je partage l'idée qu'il ne peut y avoir de développement sans paix et que la sécurité est une condition préalable du développement. Il nous faut donc un outil qui permette de répondre à ces problématiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">À cet égard, je suis heureux que le rapport soutienne l'idée de sortir les pays et territoires d'outre-mer du Fonds européen de développement et propose la création d'un instrument financier spécifique à ces derniers. C'est là une étape nouvelle qui doit conduire, dès 2020, à mieux réaffirmer l'appartenance européenne de nos pays et territoires d'outre-mer et à promouvoir leur rôle d'ambassadeurs de l'Union européenne en défendant nos valeurs dans les pays en développement voisins.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="96768" name="Enrique Guerrero Salom" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señora Presidenta, señor Comisario, en primer lugar quería agradecer al señor Neuser el informe que nos ha preparado, que creo que es un informe muy completo que va a permitir una hoja de ruta para que el Parlamento participe en la renovación del Acuerdo de Cotonú.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este es un Acuerdo que nos ha permitido tener un diálogo político con un buen número de países de distintos continentes y que ha reforzado la acción exterior de la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es también un Acuerdo que nos ha permitido tomar parte en la prevención de conflictos y en trabajar por la paz una vez que estos conflictos han desembocado. También nos ha permitido participar en la protección de los derechos humanos, en proveer buena gobernanza, en hacer avanzar procesos democráticos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tengo que señalar, no obstante, que han sido muy discutibles los resultados en lo que se refiere a los Acuerdos de Asociación Económica, que sin duda deben ser revisados. Pero los tiempos están cambiando y los tiempos ya han cambiado, y la situación ahora de esos países y de la Unión Europea no es la misma situación que cuando se abordó por primera vez el Acuerdo de Cotonú.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ahora son tiempos para trabajar entre iguales; son tiempos de respeto mutuo; son tiempos de reequilibrio para equilibrar nuestras relaciones; y son tiempos, por tanto, de abrirnos a un nuevo horizonte para los próximos veinte años, a través de una colaboración más que de una acción unidireccional.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="96663" name="Morten Messerschmidt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">for ECR-Gruppen. – Fru formand! Der er nogen, der foregøgler, at man kan skabe vækst ved at lave indkomstomfordeling. Det har de sidste 50 års verdenshistorie vist ikke kan lade sig gøre. Det, der skaber vækst og fremgang og heldigvis også politiske rettigheder som demokrati og frihed, det er frihandel. Det, at nationer og aktører kan handle frit og uhindret, når de skal udveksle varer og andre gode sager, det skaber vækst! Og det er det, vi har brug for i forhold til de partnerskabslande, som vi taler om i dag.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meget er sket, siden de første aftaler blev indgået, men det er også på tide, at vi ser indad i forhold til mange af de udfordringer af mere dogmatisk karakter, som vi i Den Europæiske Union præsenterer. Jeg kan ikke lade være med at tænke på hele det støttehalløj, der findes inden for landbrugssektoren, som er af ekstrem protektionistisk karakter og forhindrer, at eksempelvis landbruget i mange af de partnerlande, vi taler med, kan agere netop frit i forhold til europæiske producenter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi har også brug for i højere grad at vurdere de programmer, vi sætter i søen. Da jeg skulle forberede mig til i dag, kiggede jeg tilbage og undersøgte, hvornår vi egentlig senest har fået særberetninger fra Revisionsretten, der gennemgår de støtteprogrammer, som AVS-landene indgår i. Og vi skal altså mere end ti år tilbage for at finde en gennemgående beretning om alle de støtteprogrammer, som vi har sat i søen. Det er ikke godt nok! Slet ikke, når man ser på den kritik, der blev fremsat dengang. Der er således i den grad behov for, at vi får gennemgået alle sagerne endnu engang.</p>
      <p sl="en">Overordnet er der dog mange gode betragtninger fra hr. Neuser, og vi kan støtte betænkningen, men der skal virkelig mere arbejde til, hvis det her skal virke.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="2128" name="Paavo Väyrynen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ALDE-ryhmän puolesta. – Arvoisa puhemies, ALDE-ryhmä on tyytyväinen kehitysvaliokunnassa laadittuun mietintöön Afrikan, Karibian ja Tyynenmeren alueen maiden ja Euroopan unionin suhteiden tulevaisuudesta. Cotonoun sopimuksen vanhentuessa vuonna 2020 haluamme tilalle uuden yhteistyösopimuksen, jonka keskiössä ovat kaikkia maailman valtioita koskeva Agenda 2030 ja kestävän kehityksen tavoitteiden saavuttaminen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cotonoun sopimuksen tavoitteena on ollut köyhyyden vähentäminen Afrikan, Karibian ja Tyynenmeren alueen maissa sekä näiden maiden tukeminen niiden integroitumisessa maailmantalouteen. Edellä mainittujen tavoitteiden saavuttamisessa ei valitettavasti ole edistytty riittävästi. Seuraavan sopimuksen tulee mahdollistaa yhteistyön syventäminen ja tehostaminen jäsenmaiden tahdon mukaisesti, jotta voimme edistää myönteistä kehitystä paitsi talouden, myös rauhan ja turvallisuuden, ihmisoikeuksien, oikeusvaltion, muuttoliikkeen, ilmastonmuutoksen ja laajemminkin ympäristön suojelun saralla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Paljon on tapahtunut vuoden 2000 jälkeen, jolloin Cotonoun sopimus allekirjoitettiin. Kumppanuuden rakenne tulee mukauttaa vastaamaan uusiin haasteisiin ja sovittaa se yhteen alueellisten sopimusten ja järjestöjen kanssa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kumppanuuden potentiaali on huomattava. Yhdessä me muodostamme merkittävän ryhmittymän, jolla on yhteinen toimielinkehys ja suuri budjetti, Euroopan kehitysrahasto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="125035" name="Lola Sánchez Caldentey" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señora Presidenta, lamento profundamente que este informe sea una oportunidad perdida para marcar una diferencia en la relación entre la Unión Europea y los países del África subsahariana, el Caribe y el Pacífico, es decir, los países más pobres del mundo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deberíamos fomentar una salida al círculo de la pobreza en el que la Unión Europea es, con frecuencia, parte del problema, y no de la solución.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me parece inaceptable que en este informe no se ponga en el centro la solución de la deuda, que mantiene a tantos Estados en una constante situación de subordinación frente a sus acreedores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tampoco intenta acabar con los flujos ilícitos de capital o con el fraude fiscal, que vacían de recursos domésticos sus economías. Estos países están sometidos a un expolio constante, pues grandes cantidades de capital generados en ellos vuelven a Europa o a paraísos fiscales, y eso se llama robar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todo esto tiene un solo nombre: neocolonialismo financiero.</p>
      <p sl="en">Basar la ayuda al desarrollo en relaciones comerciales asimétricas aumenta la desigualdad y la pobreza, condenando a estos países a un estado de perpetuo sometimiento y dependencia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se supone que los objetivos de desarrollo sostenible deben estar en el centro del nuevo acuerdo y, sin embargo, solo son un elemento ornamental.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los pilares fundamentales de las relaciones ACP-UE deben ser la lucha contra la pobreza y la desigualdad a través del desarrollo endógeno, respetando el espacio propio para que los Estados implementen las políticas que más convienen a sus ciudadanos, y no a las empresas europeas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todos tenemos nuestras contradicciones, pero hay algunas líneas rojas y algunos principios irrenunciables, y por eso no apoyaré con mi voto este informe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="124848" name="Maria Heubuch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Herr Kommissar, Norbert Neuser! Herzlichen Dank an Dich für Deine Arbeit, für einen Bericht, der sehr detailliert ausführt, in welcher Form die Zusammenarbeit zwischen EU und AKP-Ländern gestaltet werden kann. Ich meine aber, dass sich der Berichterstatter und der Entwicklungsausschuss zu früh auf eine bestimmte Position festlegen, und daher haben wir Grünen auch dagegen gestimmt. Die Arbeit im Ausschuss war so gut wie beendet, bevor die Ergebnisse der Evaluierung des Cotonou-Abkommens bekannt wurden. Auch wurde nicht abgewartet, bis mögliche Szenarien und Kooperationsformen auch im Detail durchdekliniert waren. Und ohne diese wichtige Grundlage wollen wir Grünen uns nicht vorschnell festlegen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uns ist es wichtig, evidenzbasiert Entscheidungen zu treffen für ein wirklich tragfähiges künftiges Abkommen. Ja, die Europäische Union blickt zurück auf eine lange Tradition der Zusammenarbeit mit den AKP-Ländern, und das war eine sehr wichtige Zusammenarbeit. Doch die Diskussion jetzt zur Zukunft in unserer Beziehung zu AKP findet ja schließlich nicht im luftleeren Raum statt! Wir haben die Überarbeitung des Europäischen Konsenses vor uns. Wir haben im Juni von der Hohen Vertreterin der Europäischen Union die globale Strategie der EU vorgestellt bekommen. Wir haben die SDGs. Sie haben selbst, Herr Kommissar, vom Klimaschutzabkommen geredet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also: Vieles ist im Umbruch, und wir sollten doch dies nutzen, hier auch ergebnisoffen an alle Möglichkeiten heranzugehen, uns mit allen Möglichkeiten auseinanderzusetzen, auch zu schauen, was in der Zusammenarbeit nicht so gut geklappt hat. Es gilt schließlich auch, schwierige Fragen zu beantworten: die Fragen zur Finanzierung, der rechtlichen Verbindlichkeit oder der künftigen Struktur der Partnerschaft, auch wie wir die regionale Zusammenarbeit im Detail ausbauen können. Doppelstrukturen müssen abgebaut werden. Ich bin überzeugt: Wie auch immer wir uns für die Zukunft entscheiden, wir müssen nicht bei Null anfangen, denn wir können auf eine gute Zusammenarbeit aufbauen und haben jetzt die Chance, hier etwas Neues voranzubringen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, innanzitutto voglio complimentarmi con il collega Neuser per l'ottimo lavoro fatto nella sua relazione, una relazione su cui abbiamo votato a favore in sede di commissione per lo sviluppo e con cui condividiamo la premura nel tracciare e dotare il Parlamento europeo di una posizione sul futuro dell'accordo di Cotonou dopo il 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Riconosciamo che troppo spesso il Parlamento europeo è arrivato in ritardo nel far conoscere la propria posizione su temi e argomenti che mettono insieme commercio, diritti umani e sviluppo. Anche da parte nostra si è espressa la volontà di poter rendere efficace ed adeguare la partnership ACP-UE in base alle attuali e future sfide che si presenteranno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Anche se siamo a favore dell'impostazione voluta dal collega Neuser, dobbiamo sempre ricordare che, nei quattro anni che ci separano dal 2020, il mutamento delle condizioni potrebbe portare a un superamento delle posizioni della relazione. Quindi, partendo dal presupposto che l'attuale situazione è quella di non aver saputo incidere sulle gravissime problematiche causate dagli interessi diretti e indiretti dei vari Stati e delle multinazionali europee e non nei paesi ACP, necessitiamo di un solido quadro legale con strumenti in grado di affrontare adeguatamente le gravissime problematiche dei settori per cui l'accordo con i paesi ACP era stato pensato per rappresentare una valida soluzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dovremmo essere tanto lungimiranti da prevedere e pensare alla nuova partnership come sarti in grado di realizzare un vestito su misura per il raggiungimento degli obiettivi dell'agenda delle Nazioni Unite del 2030.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="125028" name="Olaf Stuger" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ENF-Fractie. – September was de maand van de verspilling. September was een recordmaand, want in september is er 6,6 miljard aan verspilling geconstateerd. 5,7 Miljard aan havens, dokken en golfbrekers. Allemaal in het water gevallen. 780 Miljoen verdween in Moldavië en 129 miljoen is in rook opgegaan in de Palestijnse gebieden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, op datzelfde moment in september is de Nederlandse regering bezig met het vrijmaken van 50 miljoen euro voor mantelzorg aan chronisch zieken en ook volgend jaar in Nederland zal de zorgpremie met 10 euro stijgen. Nederland haalt de broekriem aan en in Brussel blijft verspilling troef.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, ik zie het zo: een moeder spaart elke euro en legt dat bij elkaar om het schoolreisje van haar dochter te betalen, terwijl op hetzelfde moment twee straten verder vader 300 euro in een gokmachine werpt. Dat kan niet. Dat is buitensporig. Voorzitter, dat is schandalig!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="125072" name="Ελευθέριος Συναδινός (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, οι συμφωνίες εταιρικής σχέσης μεταξύ της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και της Ομάδας των κρατών της Αφρικής, Καραϊβικής και Ειρηνικού πρέπει να επικεντρωθούν σε τρία βασικά ζητήματα. Το πρώτο είναι η οικονομική εταιρική σχέση με πρωταρχικό σκοπό την προώθηση των συμφερόντων των κρατών μελών της Ένωσης, αλλά και τη δημιουργία βιώσιμης ανάπτυξης στις χώρες αυτές ως βασικός παράγοντας αναχαίτισης της λαθρομετανάστευσης. Δεύτερον, δημιουργία προϋποθέσεων ώστε, ειδικά για τις αφρικανικές χώρες, κάθε εγκληματική τρομοκρατική ενέργεια και παραβίαση των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων και του κράτους δικαίου να συνιστά αυτόματα εφαρμογή μέτρων και κυρώσεων κατά των χωρών αυτών. Τρίτον και κυριότερο, με κάθε εγγραφή στον προϋπολογισμό κονδυλίων του Ευρωπαϊκού Ταμείου Ανάπτυξης θα πρέπει να οριοθετούνται σαφείς εγγυήσεις, νομικές ρήτρες και υλοποιήσιμοι στόχοι που θα συνδέονται άμεσα με τη συνέχεια ή τη διακοπή της χρηματοδότησης των χωρών αυτών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="124903" name="Bogdan Brunon Wenta" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Chcę pogratulować panu Norbertowi Neuserowi tego trudnego sprawozdania o przyszłych stosunkach AKP–Unia Europejska.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jak pokazują doświadczenia ostatnich lat, dzięki umowie z Kotonu dotychczasowa współpraca na linii AKP–Unia Europejska przynosi pozytywne rezultaty. Jednak ich wymiar nadal nie jest jeszcze zadowalający. Zauważalna jest konieczność dalszej kooperacji, a nawet jej wzmocnienie, zwłaszcza w aspekcie gospodarczym. W dalszym ciągu bowiem 80 % krajów wchodzących w skład AKP należy do państw najsłabiej rozwiniętych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Powyższe oraz aktualna sytuacja ekonomiczna wskazują, że potrzebna jest zmiana formuły w relacjach AKP–Unia Europejska. Zaangażowanie UE powinno coraz częściej polegać na wypracowaniu relacji, które będą w większym stopniu partnerskie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kluczową rolę w dalszym rozwoju odgrywać powinny umowy gospodarcze i inwestycje, co również przyczyni się do większego upodmiotowienia państw AKP. Handel jest jednym z trzech głównych filarów umowy z Kotonu, wpływającym na wzrost inwestycji, ograniczenie bezrobocia i oczywiście walkę z ubóstwem. Dlatego też jego wzmocnienie jest niezbędne dla dalszego wzrostu i rozwoju gospodarczego tych krajów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tymczasem import UE tylko z krajów Afryki Zachodniej zmalał z ponad 38 mld w roku 2013 do nieco ponad 27 mld w roku 2015. Jednocześnie UE jest nadal głównym partnerem handlowym krajów AKP z ponad 5 % poziomem importu i eksportu w skali całej UE.</p>
      <p sl="en">Równocześnie dbanie o dalszy zrównoważony rozwój i walka z ubóstwem muszą następować w połączeniu z postępem na rzecz rozwoju demokracji i poszanowaniem praw człowieka.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="124801" name="Cécile Kashetu Kyenge" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il quadro di cooperazione UE-ACP ha fortemente contribuito, nel corso degli ultimi quarant'anni, a rafforzare i legami tra i popoli e i parlamenti dei rispettivi paesi. In prossimità della scadenza dell'accordo di Cotonou, la nostra cooperazione va datata e calibrata alle nuove sfide del Millennio.</p>
      <p sl="en">È necessaria quindi una nuova struttura che conservi le parti dell'acquis UE-ACP e che ne preservi gli elementi essenziali. I diritti umani, l'uguaglianza di genere, i principi democratici e lo Stato di diritto devono costituire la base di valori di questo nuovo accordo, unitamente alla buona governance. Il dialogo politico deve restare un pilastro giuridico centrale. Gli articoli 8 e 96 devono trovare maggior attenzione anche al fine di preservare crisi e conflitti, come ha sottolineato l'on. Neuser. Chiedo inoltre il rafforzamento della dimensione parlamentare, ma anche il coinvolgimento della società civile.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Dobiegająca końca umowa o partnerstwie między Unią a grupą krajów Afryki, Karaibów i Pacyfiku nie przyniosła oczekiwanych rezultatów, gdyby porównać ją z innymi partnerstwami Unii. Osiągnięcia m.in. w dziedzinie zwalczania biedy, budowy państwa prawa czy integracji z gospodarką światową to niestety wciąż za mało, by na tym etapie bardzo dobrze ocenić spuściznę tego porozumienia. Szczególnie martwi mnie fakt, że dialog w kwestii promowania praw człowieka jest mało zaawansowany i występują w nim znaczne różnice interpretacyjne pomiędzy niektórymi krajami, co prowadzi do sporów i narastającej nieufności ze strony państw AKP. Narzucanie unijnych rozwiązań, groźby związane ze wstrzymaniem wsparcia finansowego często interpretowane są przez naszych partnerów jako przejaw paternalizmu, a nawet neokolonializmu. Niestety nie pomaga to w budowaniu realnego partnerstwa, wręcz przeciwnie, umacnia relację darczyńca-beneficjent, od której Unia musi zacząć odchodzić, by móc budować partnerstwo równych podmiotów oparte na wspólnych celach: odpowiedzialności, równych prawach i dzieleniu kosztów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wyrażam głęboką nadzieję, że podczas planowania kierunków i zasad współpracy uwzględnimy różnice interesów i weźmiemy pod uwagę zmiany, jakie zaszły w światowej gospodarce, w polityce oraz wewnątrz obu grup. Poddajmy dotychczasowe dokonania szczegółowej analizie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="840" name="Charles Goerens" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, les relations UE-ACP sont loin d'être démodées. Bien au contraire, le partenariat UE-ACP a toujours pu évoluer dans des contextes changeants, comme le confirment d'ailleurs nombre d'évaluations. Des progrès importants ont pu être réalisés dans les domaines de la santé, de la promotion et de la coopération régionale en Afrique, sans parler des infrastructures. Sur le plan de la coopération politique, le bilan est un peu plus mitigé. En effet, cette dimension reste encore largement inutilisée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je persiste à croire que le Cycle de Doha, par exemple, qui ambitionnait de combiner le commerce et le développement dans l'intérêt de tous, et plus particulièrement des plus faibles, a échoué faute de pouvoir s'entendre sur une ligne commune entre l'Union et les 79 États ACP. De mon point de vue, les deux parties auraient intérêt à s'entendre sur un pacte stratégique qui pourrait peser de tout son poids à l'Assemblée des Nations unies et dans le cadre des grandes conférences multilatérales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais il faut s'interroger avant tout sur la façon de valoriser ces potentialités. Or, il y a lieu de constater que, malheureusement, nos responsables politiques – les États membres – ne s'impliquent que faiblement dans cette coopération. Puisque nous ne cessons de proclamer à longueur de journée que le réveil de l'Afrique est imminent, nous serions en droit d'attendre une action politique plus offensive, plus robuste, plus déterminée et plus efficace. Oui, nous formons avec les ACP, et plus particulièrement avec nos voisins d'Afrique subsaharienne, une communauté de destin dans des domaines aussi divers que le climat, l'énergie et la sécurité, notamment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mon dernier point est une mise en garde pour ceux qui seraient tentés de faire éclater la relation UE-ACP dans ses composantes régionales. Et je ne voudrais pas terminer sans avoir remercié Norbert Neuser d'avoir ouvert le débat avec un rapport qui n'est pas la fin d'un processus, mais n'en est que le début.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, as relações entre a União Europeia e os países ACP devem assentar, desde logo, no reconhecimento de uma dívida histórica por reparar de centenas de anos de colonialismo, saque, de opressão e exploração; no reconhecimento e combate à natureza profundamente assimétrica das interdependências Norte-Sul que os últimos anos não mitigaram.</p>
      <p sl="en">O objetivo da integração progressiva dos países ACP na economia mundial não pode ignorar que essa integração não deve ser, mas está a ser, uma integração subordinada, dependente e periférica, assente em relações injustas entre partes desiguais.</p>
      <p sl="en">A liberalização e a desregulação do comércio de que os chamados Acordos de Parceria Económica são um instrumento servem os interesses das potências e dos grupos económicos do norte, mas não as necessidades de desenvolvimento sustentável dos países e das comunidades do sul, bem pelo contrário.</p>
      <p sl="en">A relação com os países ACP deve ser respeitadora da sua soberania, das suas legítimas opções e aspirações, não um biombo para lhes impor modelos de organização política e económica ou o alinhamento geoestratégico com as prioridades e opções da União Europeia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-0000" speaker_id="124993" name="Bodil Valero" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! Jag har haft möjlighet att delta i AVS-delegationen sedan 2014 när jag kom in här i parlamentet, och jag vill poängtera att jag tycker att den här politiska dialogen mellan våra länder är mycket värdefull, och att samarbetet är positivt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Men med det sagt menar jag inte att vi borde haft så bråttom, som vi har haft här i parlamentet, att komma med ett betänkande om detta just nu. Precis som min kollega Maria tidigare har tagit upp, menar jag att vi måste titta på och studera frågan mycket, mycket noggrannare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det är ju så att vi vid sidan av AVS-arbetet har många andra parallella strukturer, många som också omfattar i princip samma regioner, och då måste vi fråga oss om vi arbetar på rätt sätt. Att ha de här parallella strukturerna uppfattas också som väldigt rörigt av aktörer utanför, men vi måste vid en eventuell förändring också se till att det som är bra i den nuvarande strukturen och samarbetet inte försvinner. Jag tänker i synnerhet på de möjligheter vi har att tillsammans med flera regioner tala om frågor som omfattar oss alla, men inte bara just de här regionerna utan också andra delar av världen. Klimatpåverkan är en sådan fråga som vi måste diskutera väldigt brett, bland annat i det här samarbetet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="124941" name="Raymond Finch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would first like to say how shameful it is that there appear to be more spectators in the gallery than there are Members in the Chamber. Is it any wonder that the peoples of Europe do not listen to you, when you cannot even be bothered to listen to yourselves?</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU-ACP partnership is based upon near—colonialism. The EU taxpayer will pay EUR 30 billion for the EDF in 2014-2020 in order to ensure that the poorer nations are in its debt and therefore subject to the rapacious greed of big business. This is against all that your European Union is supposed to stand for, and we see the results in the economic partnership agreements, in the fisheries agreements and in the common agricultural policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">If the EU really wants to help the third world, then it should enable those nations to build their own economies and ensure free trade, not just for raw materials in the age-old manner of the colonialists, but also for finished products and goods. As long as we keep pouring in aid for no good outcome, we encourage the cycle of third—world government dependency and keep the poorest the poorest. Democracy, independence and freedom come only when peoples have a safe, solid, sustainable economy. We need to break the cycle of dependency, and giving corrupt governments more and more taxpayers’ money merely encourages more of the same results.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-0000" speaker_id="124755" name="Jean-Luc Schaffhauser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, la notion même de communauté de développement entraîne celle de frontières et de régulation du marché intérieur. C'est le Zollverein, c'est l'Europe communautaire qui, à l'origine, se protégeait comme toute zone économique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le rapport de ma collègue de Sarnez soulignait d'ailleurs, et à juste titre, le besoin d'un marché intérieur africain. Je souligne qu'il doit être protégé. C'est cette protection que vous refusez. Mais pouvons-nous donner des leçons de développement avec l'échec du développement chez nous et notre approche d'un marché sans frontières, d'une concurrence libre et non faussée, démarche qui nous a conduits où nous sommes, à savoir, au bord du précipice économique européen?</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette démarche, cette approche idéologique du marché, qui détruit les emplois chez nous, accroît les disparités Nord-Sud chez nous, la Commission veut cependant l'imposer à l'Afrique et aux autres continents. Cela ne marche pas. On veut encore aller plus de l'avant jusqu'à l'implosion de l'Europe et de l'Afrique. Non contente de détruire le développement Nord-Sud de l'Europe, la Commission veut aussi détruire le développement Nord-Sud du prochain de l'Europe, celui de l'Afrique et des pays du Sud de l'Europe. Chers collègues, nous devons dire "non" à ces accords. Les pays en développement nous regardent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les accords de Lomé osaient le protectionnisme pour le développement. Les accords de Cotonou ouvraient déjà cette folle idée du renard libre dans le poulailler libre pour obtenir le développement. Des pays refusent. C'est le chantage à l'ouverture de nos frontières, c'est le néocolonialisme. Honte à la Commission, honte à nous, si nous acceptons ces accords.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je tiens tout d'abord à féliciter le rapporteur, M. Neuser, qui a travaillé dans un esprit de compromis, ce qui a permis d'aboutir à un texte équilibré et ambitieux. Ce rapport représente une contribution importante du Parlement qui, je l'espère, sera prise en considération dans la communication que nous attendons sur l'avenir des relations ACP-UE après 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">En tant que rapporteur permanent pour la cohérence des politiques au service du développement (CPD), je me réjouis de voir que ce concept a été mis en avant dans ce rapport. La CPD a beaucoup à apporter, non seulement dans la révision de l'accord de Cotonou mais également dans la mise en œuvre des objectifs de développement durable. C'est pour cette raison que j'ai tenu à ce que le rapport appelle à nouveau à la mise en place de corapporteurs permanents sur la CPD au sein de l'Assemblée paritaire ACP-UE.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est vrai que le partenariat ACP-UE n'a pas rempli tous ses objectifs et qu'il a déçu sur certains aspects, mais je suis convaincu que nous pouvons améliorer ces points faibles tout en conservant la structure actuelle, qui est un outil unique dans les relations extérieures de l'Union. Son caractère juridiquement contraignant contribue grandement à son efficacité.</p>
      <p sl="en">Selon moi, il faut que la réforme du partenariat prenne en considération nos autres outils de politique étrangère, notamment les différentes feuilles de route qui vont aboutir à la stratégie globale de l'Union. Je regrette que cette stratégie ne mentionne pas spécifiquement le partenariat ACP-UE. S'il y a un point sur lequel la réforme de l'accord de Cotonou doit concentrer tous ses efforts, c'est celui du renforcement du dialogue politique. De nombreux pays africains sont actuellement confrontés à de graves crises politiques et électorales – le dernier en date étant le Gabon – et, notamment, à la question de la limite des mandats présidentiels: c'est ici que le dialogue politique prend tout son sens. Il doit pouvoir être utilisé par les deux parties pour prévenir ces crises et agir en amont.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it really is time to renew our relations with the African, Caribbean and Pacific states, not only because the current Cotonou Agreement expires in 2020 but also because pressing challenges need solutions that we can only achieve jointly with our partner countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am strongly in favour of European Parliament support for a new cooperation structure keeping the unity of the European Union states with their 79 partner countries, under one umbrella, while at the same time permitting closer regional cooperation. Climate change is one of the issues that the EU and ACP countries have to tackle as soon as possible. Another is addressing poverty and the fragility of states, as the root causes of migration, in a sustainable way. This forum is the best place to listen to each other’s needs and find common solutions to global problems.</p>
      <p sl="en">Last but not least, allow me warmly to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Neuser.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="124831" name="Isabella Adinolfi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'Accordo di partenariato di Cotonou tra l'Unione europea e i membri del gruppo degli Stati dell'Africa, dei Caraibi e del Pacifico è stato firmato nel 2000.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo visto, in questi sedici anni trascorsi, gli Stati coinvolti nel partenariato e gli stakeholder lottare per rafforzare i tre pilastri complementari dell'accordo – la dimensione politica ed economica, la cooperazione commerciale e la cooperazione allo sviluppo – al fine di debellare la povertà, promuovendo gli Stati ACP nell'economa mondiale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi ci complimentiamo per i risultati raggiunti finora. Lamentiamo però che il Fondo europeo di sviluppo sia uno strumento finanziario al di fuori del bilancio generale dell'Unione e chiediamo vivamente che il Parlamento europeo possa ricoprire in futuro un ruolo più forte nelle decisioni post-Cotonou.</p>
      <p sl="en">In alcuni paesi dell'Africa c'è una crescente tensione dovuta a ragioni di carattere politico. L'aumento dell'insicurezza alimentare e nutrizionale, della siccità e dell'immigrazione figura tra le problematiche che il futuro trattato dovrà affrontare. Spero, inoltre, che l'integrazione giovanile sarà considerata uno dei punti di primaria importanza da risolvere nei prossimi accordi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-0000" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael Gahler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Ich finde, es ist jetzt die richtige Zeit, dass wir über die Zeit nach Cotonou debattieren und diesen Bericht auf der Tagesordnung haben. Herzlichen Dank an den Kollegen Neuser, er hat sich damit sehr viel Mühe gemacht und auch die Fraktionen sehr gut in diesen Bericht eingebunden. Ich denke, das Abkommen sollte Anlass sein, dass wir über die Zukunft im Bereich der besseren Zusammenarbeit reden. Denn die Ziele, die wir uns eigentlich auch schon vor Cotonou in den vier HYPERLINK "https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lom%C3%A9-Abkommen" Lomé-Abkommen gesetzt haben, nämlich die Lebensumstände der Menschen im AKP-Bereich zu verbessern, diese Ziele haben wir leider in weiten Teilen nicht erreicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben es zum Beispiel nicht geschafft, dass der afrikanische Kontinent wirklich Teil der Weltwirtschaft geworden ist in der Form, dass dort die Menschen vor Ort davon profitieren. Wir haben es nicht geschafft, dass es bessere Regierungsführung, better governance, in weiten Teilen des AKP-Bereichs gibt, sondern wir erleben bis in die heutigen Tage – es ist eben Gabun genannt worden, ich selber war in den Sommerferien zur Wahlbeobachtung in Sambia –, dass es dort politische Umstände gibt, bei denen man feststellen muss, dass schon bei Wahlen selbst der Anfang von Illegitimität dadurch zustande kommt, dass eben die Umstände unfair sind, und dass daher auch die Menschen von Anfang an nicht das Vertrauen in ihre Regierenden bekommen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Da, glaube ich, müssen wir ansetzen: ohne gute Regierungsführung keine dauerhafte Entwicklung. Da müssen wir auch bisherige Instrumente hinterfragen. Ich nenne da mal diese generelle Budgethilfe, die war über viele Jahre lang ein beliebtes Instrument. Ich glaube, da müssen wir andere Wege finden, um dafür zu sorgen, dass die Mittel tatsächlich dort ankommen, wo sie auch eingesetzt werden sollten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-065-0000" speaker_id="118858" name="Marlene Mizzi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sinjura President, dan hu rapport importanti għax jindirizza r-relazzjoni bejn il-pajjiżi tal-ACP u l-Unjoni Ewropea u jirrikonoxxi l-fatt li l-koperazzjoni bejn il-pajjiżi tal-ACP u l-Unjoni hi kisba valida u importanti, u li ġiet imsaħħa matul is-snin.</p>
      <p sl="en">L-Economic Partnership Agreements - l-EPAs- huma għodda ta’ żvilupp biex ikabbru l-kummerċ bejn iż-żewġ blokki. L-EPAs servew sew biex jgħinu lill-pajjiżi tal-ACP jgħaġġlu l-iżvilupp tal-ekonomiji tagħhom u jidħlu fis-suq globali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hu importanti li l-EPAs jintużaw biex jiġu indirizzati iżda sfidi ġodda, bħall-ambjent, tibdil fil-klima, terroriżmu, u l-migrazzjoni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Għad hemm ħafna xi jsir biex nindirizzaw żvilupp akbar fil-pajjizi ACP. Biex isir hekk irid ikun hemm tisħiħ tad-djalogu politiku u nimxu lejn qafas uniku ta' ftehimiet reġjonali li jkunu mfassla għall-bżonnijiet partikolari ta' dak ir-reġjun. Mhux każ li kull qies hu tajjeb għal kulħadd, għax kull reġjun għandu l-bżonnijiet u l-isfidi tiegħu. Hekk biss nistgħu nindirizzaw l-isfidi u l-bżonnijiet komuni tal-pajjiżi ACP u tal-Ewropa.</p>
      <p sl="en">U prosit lir-Rapporteur Norber Neuser.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="124715" name="György Hölvényi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, first of all let me thank my colleague Mr Neuser for his good work. We have recognised that ACP-EU cooperation is a unique achievement. It has intensified the ties between ACP and EU countries for the last four decades. I would like to highlight two elements that would improve the situation of the peoples of the partner countries: first, placing the 2030 agenda and the sustainable development goals at the centre of the new agreements; and, second, placing the human—rights aspect at the centre of European action.</p>
      <p sl="en">Migration and displacement will dominate the ACP-EU agenda for the future. A new agreement must address this expanding challenge. To increase political oversight, we need a strong parliamentary dimension in the new cooperation agreement. We must guarantee that European development partnerships are concluded only with regimes respecting human dignity. Where governments cannot be our partners, we must bring on board local communities that are ready to cooperate with us. Faith-based communities and their organisations represent the real local power in very many places. They often manage development programmes that are already functioning well. Their efficiency on the ground is remarkable.</p>
      <p sl="en">My strongest message today is that we must engage better with local communities and faith-based organisations in coordinated – and I underline again coordinated – dialogue. Let me draw attention to the importance of local small and medium-sized enterprises: they are key to the improvement of communities and the extension of social cohesion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lastly, the situation is quite clear: let us have cooperation with local powers and international actors to address the humanitarian situation which can no longer be overlooked in many ACP countries.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, le cadre UE-ACP représente un partenariat unique et privilégié entre l'Europe et ses partenaires d'Afrique, des Caraïbes et du Pacifique. Seize ans plus tard, l'heure est au bilan. Les particularités parfois trop divergentes entre les différentes régions ont mené à une sous-exploitation des institutions de Cotonou. Pourtant, celles-ci offrent une opportunité unique de dialogue, d'échange et de coopération entre les régions du monde qui ont tant de défis en commun. Il sera donc essentiel, à mon sens, de revoir le cadre de coopération en tenant davantage compte des spécificités régionales de chaque partie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il me semble que nous pouvons travailler autour de quatre priorités. La première de celles-ci est que le futur cadre devra mettre au cœur de ses priorités les objectifs de développement durable, mais aussi et surtout la cohérence des politiques en faveur du développement afin de s'assurer que les politiques commerciales, migratoires, sécuritaires et environnementales soient cohérentes et compatibles avec les objectifs de développement.</p>
      <p sl="en">La deuxième priorité concerne le dialogue politique. À l'heure où les tensions touchent une grande partie de l'Afrique, celui-ci reste un pilier fondamental qui a été trop peu utilisé jusqu'à présent. Ce pilier devra être renforcé et doté d'outils adéquats afin de le rendre plus efficace et plus pertinent.</p>
      <p sl="en">La troisième priorité a trait au pilier économique. À ce propos, l'Union européenne devrait s'engager à soutenir davantage les pays ACP dans la mise en œuvre des accords de partenariat économique (APE) quand les pays ont décidé d'en conclure et à s'assurer que ces pays aient d'abord renforcé leurs capacités institutionnelles et leur capacité de diversification économique et qu'ils aient procédé à une réforme de leurs politiques fiscales avant de se lancer dans une libéralisation commerciale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, l'implication de la société civile doit être garantie dans tous les domaines de coopération, tant dans le développement que dans la coopération commerciale, à tous les niveaux du dialogue et avec de nouveaux outils plus performants. La société civile doit continuer à être reconnue comme un acteur officiel de la coopération entre l'Union et les pays ACP.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="125006" name="Francesc Gambús" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, el 80 % de los países menos desarrollados del mundo, y los más olvidados, se encuentran en lo que aquí conocemos como países ACP. Y ahora que tanto se parlotea de los fracasos de la Unión Europea, y ahora que tanto se habla de la necesidad de trabajar en las causas de las migraciones, debemos, cuando menos, mostrar la tranquilidad de que ya hace tiempo que los europeos entendimos lo que había que hacer y nos pusimos manos a la obra.</p>
      <p sl="en">No empezamos ayer. Cabe recordar aquí los acuerdos de Lomé y el que hoy nos ocupa, el Acuerdo de Cotonú, que sigue siendo un instrumento válido, mucho más concreto en objetivos de cooperación para el desarrollo que la estrategia global de la Unión o la Agenda 2030 de las Naciones Unidas, por ejemplo, tanto en la promoción de la integración regional como en las acciones contra el cambio climático, uno de los asuntos sobre los que hemos llegado a una posición común.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, también es cierto que, a fecha de hoy, tenemos cuestiones pendientes, retos que superar, nuevos paradigmas en las relaciones de la Unión con los países ACP o las relaciones de estos mismos países con otros actores globales, como China.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creemos que, en esencia, sigue siendo válido el modelo de colaboración basada tanto en la dimensión política como en las estrategias de desarrollo y en la cooperación económica y comercial. Precisamente, la coincidencia en el tiempo de la expiración del Acuerdo de Cotonú y del marco financiero plurianual de la Unión nos da una oportunidad única para conseguir integrar el Fondo Europeo de Desarrollo en el presupuesto general y mejorar así en transparencia, eficiencia y rendición de cuentas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sabemos que el diálogo político no ha logrado introducir mejoras en lo tocante a los derechos humanos y la democracia en los países que no comparten los valores de la Unión: otro reto por superar. Desde esta casa debemos velar por consolidar y mejorar en el futuro el trabajo hecho estos veinte años. Quedan más de tres años, hay margen. Es por todo ello que apoyaré el informe del señor Neuser, que me parece apropiado, bien trabajado y que aprovecho para agradecer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-0000" speaker_id="23693" name="Alojz Peterle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Govorimo o odnosih Evropske zveze z največjo skupino držav na svetu. Čaka nas izredno veliko pomembnega dela, ki ga brexit, če do njega pride, finančno ne bo okrepil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dosedanji odnosi in sodelovanje med AKP in Evropsko zvezo so bili in ostajajo usmerjeni v krepitev univerzalnih vrednot in ciljev, kot so uveljavljanje človekovih pravic, demokracije in trajnostnega razvoja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sporazum smo sklenili v Coutonouju leta 2000 in ga dvakrat revidirali. Razvoj je v letih po zadnji reviziji pokazal, tako je pokazala tudi moja izkušnja na terenu z vodenjem dveh Evropskih misij za opazovanje volitev v podporo demokracije v Nigeriji in Keniji, da je potrebno izhodišča, ki jih delimo z našimi AKP partnerji konkretizirati z bolj specifičnimi regionalnimi strategijami in regionalnimi sporazumi, ki bodo bolj upoštevali spremenjene politične, gospodarske in varnostne razmere.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po drugi strani se zelo strinjam s poudarkom poročila, da naj sodelovanje poteka na področjih skupnega interesa, kjer bi bilo mogoče pričakovati vzajemno korist, ne le z ekonomskega vidika, temveč tudi in predvsem v zvezi z mirom in varnostjo, s človekovimi pravicami, načeli pravne države, dobrim upravljanjem, demokracijo, migracijami, okoljem in tako naprej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mir je vrednota, ki po mojem mnenju ostaja prva razvojna prioriteta. Ne moremo se uspešno lotiti revščine, če ni zagotovljen mir. Zato se mi zdi smiselno, da AKP in Evropska zveza delata skupaj kot celota, pri tej in drugih podpornih vrednotah.</p>
      <p sl="en">V tem smislu predlagam, da v bodoče še več energije posvetimo medkulturnemu dialogu, ki je še vedno podcenjena možnost za dodano vrednost v polariziranih družbah, ki potrebujejo za trajnejši razvoj višjo raven notranjega sožitja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolegu Neuserju in poročevalcem v senci sem hvaležen za dobro opravljeno delo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="26837" name="Λευτέρης Χριστοφόρου (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">PPE). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, πιστεύω ότι αν πράγματι θεωρούμε ότι η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση δεν πρέπει να είναι εσωστρεφής, αλλά να απλώνει το χέρι της για να βοηθήσει - με κοινωνικό πρόσωπο, με κοινωνικό χαρακτήρα και με μια ευφάνταστη αναπτυξιακή πολιτική - και άλλες χώρες εκτός Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, τότε θα πρέπει να στηρίξουμε συμφωνίες όπως είναι η συμφωνία Κοτονού, η συμφωνία με τις χώρες της Καραϊβικής, της Αφρικής και του Ειρηνικού, εκεί όπου η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση πραγματικά συνεισφέρει, και οικονομικά, και με άλλους τρόπους …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή λόγω έλλειψης αγγλικής διερμηνείας, ο οποίος στη συνέχεια ξαναπαίρνει τον λόγο)"/>
      <p sl="en">Έλεγα, κύριε Πρόεδρε, ότι αν θεωρήσουμε ότι η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση δεν μπορεί να είναι ένα κλειστό κλαμπ χωρών που ασχολούνται μόνο με την ανάπτυξη της ίδιας της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, αλλά ότι, αντιθέτως, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση έχει ευθύνη αλλά και ρόλο να διαδραματίσει και πέραν των ορίων της, τότε θα πρέπει να θεωρήσουμε επίσης ότι η συμφωνία που επιτεύχθηκε μεταξύ των χωρών της Καραϊβικής, του Ειρηνικού και της Αφρικής και των κρατών μελών της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης αποτελεί το επιστέγασμα μιας σύγχρονης Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης που ανταποκρίνεται στα καλέσματα ολόκληρης της ανθρωπότητας και που βρίσκεται παντού όπου υπάρχει πρόβλημα. Πιστεύω ότι αν κάποιος μελετήσει αυτήν τη συμφωνία, στα δεκαέξι χρόνια της ύπαρξής της, θα αντιληφθεί ότι, όσα προβλήματα και αν υπάρχουν, όσες δυσκολίες και όσα κωλύματα και αν προκύπτουν, ότι πρόκειται για μια πολύ χρήσιμη συμφωνία, χρήσιμη γιατί προσφέρει πραγματικά σε αυτές τις χώρες και συμβάλλει τόσο στη βιώσιμη ανάπτυξη, όσο στην εξέλιξη και την ένταξή τους στην παγκόσμια οικονομία.</p>
      <p sl="en">Συμφωνώ όμως - και ως σκιώδης εισηγητής στη γνωμοδότηση της Επιτροπής Προϋπολογισμού στήριξα με όλες μου τις δυνάμεις αυτήν την άποψη - ότι η συγκυρία της αναθεώρησης του πολυετούς δημοσιονομικού πλαισίου το 2020 και της λήξης της συμφωνίας μας προσφέρει μια σημαντική ευκαιρία για να εντάξουμε τον προϋπολογισμό του Ευρωπαϊκού Ταμείου Ανάπτυξης στον προϋπολογισμό της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, ούτως ώστε να υπάρχει αποτελεσματικότερη διαχείριση με διαφάνεια και με όλους εκείνους τους όρους που απαιτούνται. Επιθυμώ δε, κύριε Πρόεδρε, να τονίσω κάτι τελευταίο, ότι είναι πράγματι πολύ σημαντικό να υπάρχει αποτελεσματικός έλεγχος και διαφάνεια εκεί όπου πηγαίνουν τα χρήματα της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και ότι πρέπει σε αυτές τις χώρες να εφαρμόζονται οι αρχές της δημοκρατίας, των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων και του κράτους δικαίου.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="124890" name="Adam Szejnfeld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Za nami aż 40 lat współpracy, a przed nami tylko 4 lata na to, aby przygotować nowe warunki, nowe umowy, nowe zasady realizowania współpracy między państwami członkowskimi Unii Europejskiej a 78 państwami AKP.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trzeba więc wyciągać wnioski z przeszłości, a te wnioski to to, że nie wszystkie cele w sposób optymalny udało nam się osiągnąć. By więc przyszłe lata współpracy – nie ma co ukrywać – także pojęcia pomocy nie poszły na marne, trzeba podejmować działania, które będą bardziej skuteczne. Nie ulega żadnej wątpliwości, że między innymi trzeba postawić na zwiększenie inwestycji, a nie tylko na handel i zwykłe pomocnictwo. Zasadę ryby trzeba zamienić i zastąpić zasadą wędki.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niestety żyjemy w czasach, które są groźne dla tego rodzaju umów, bowiem żyjemy w czasach, w których wzbierają siły przeciwne handlowym umowom międzynarodowym, a to jest jeden z bardzo ważnych elementów tego porozumienia. To jest proces, który jest groźny dla krajów rozwijających się, i też musimy brać to pod uwagę, chcąc tym państwom pomagać.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'accordo di Cotonou rappresenta una valida piattaforma di cooperazione tra l'Unione europea e i paesi ACP. Lo è per il considerevole numero di paesi che ne prendono parte, ma anche per i preziosi legami instaurati tra i rispettivi popoli. I risultati conseguiti in materia di eliminazione della povertà e di integrazione dei paesi ACP nell'economia mondiale sono tuttavia ancora scarsi, troppo scarsi. L'Agenda 2030 e gli Obiettivi di sviluppo sostenibile dovranno segnare la strada maestra in vista di una più stretta cooperazione che tenga in considerazione le sfide intanto sopravvenute.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'esigenza di dover garantire, nel periodo post 2020, una maggiore rilevanza al tema dei diritti umani e al rafforzamento del dialogo politico è, per esempio, un tema che non può essere sottovalutato. Così come è di fondamentale importanza istituire, all'interno di un quadro comune giuridicamente vincolante, validi meccanismi di monitoraggio volti a salvaguardare la concreta attuazione dell'accordo. Il nuovo accordo di cooperazione dovrà riflettere un progetto politico ambizioso e fare della buona governance un caposaldo, lasciando alle spalle la deleteria mentalità donatore-beneficiario.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η συμφωνία του Κοτονού αποτελεί μια συμφωνία εταιρικής σχέσης ανάμεσα στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και τις χώρες της Αφρικής, Καραϊβικής και του Ειρηνικού, η οποία, όπως κάθε συμφωνία οικονομικής εταιρικής σχέσης, παρουσιάζεται ως δήθεν ευκαιρία για την προώθηση της περιφερειακής ολοκλήρωσης, του εμπορίου και της ανάπτυξης, ενώ στην πραγματικότητα το μόνο που προωθεί είναι τα συμφέροντα των μεγάλων εταιρειών σε βάρος των μικρών επιχειρήσεων, αλλά και των λαών των συμβαλλομένων μερών. Παράλληλα, ο αγροτικός, ο περιβαλλοντικός και ο κοινωνικός τομέας πλήττονται ανεπανόρθωτα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ως παράδειγμα, αναφέρω τη συμφωνία Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης-Μεσημβρινής Αφρικής, μια συμφωνία που αφήνει τη φέτα και τις ελιές Καλαμών, δύο προϊόντα Ονομασίας Προέλευσης σημαντικά για την Ελλάδα, εκτός λίστας προστασίας της Ένωσης, την στιγμή που η παραγωγή πορτοκαλιών και λεμονιών στην Ελλάδα αναμένεται να πληγεί από την εν λόγω συμφωνία, αφού καταργούνται με αυτήν οι δασμολογικοί φραγμοί για το εμπόριο μεταξύ Αφρικής και Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Εκτιμώ επομένως ότι το μόνο που πετυχαίνουν αυτές τις συμφωνίες είναι να πλήξουν τις εθνικές παραγωγές και να αυξήσουν τις κοινωνικές ανισότητες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, poštovani gospodine povjereniče, uopće ne mogu zamisliti da EU nakon 2020. nema sporazum sa zemljama AKP-a. Sporazum iz Cotonua iz 2000. je, naravno, papir koji je pomalo zastario i koji danas traži nove vizije, nove prijedloge i nove odnose.</p>
      <p sl="en">Međutim, objektivno, treba nam globalni okvir jer s tim državama rješavamo ključne probleme ovog planeta. Poslije ćemo razgovarati o siromaštvu i kako ga iskorijeniti. Većina siromašnih ljudi živi upravo u zemljama AKP-a, da ne govorimo o problemu migracija o kojem stalno pričamo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naravno da sam sklon onome, kako se kaže: „Dajmo nekome udicu, a ne ribu”. Pomozimo zemljama AKP-a da razviju vlastito gospodarstvo na principima održivog razvoja i na taj način razriješimo krizu s kojom se suočavamo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the partnership between the EU and ACP countries is an important vehicle for sustainable development and I would like to thank my colleagues who truly understand this.</p>
      <p sl="en">We all know that the future belongs to young people and that is why it is important for me to highlight the participation and empowerment of children and young people when we talk about the future of ACP-EU relations and sustainability. Article 26 of the Cotonou Agreement stipulates that our cooperation must support youth, releasing their potential. I would like to see such a commitment strengthened post 2020, with ambitious new initiatives and monitoring structures. We need to share best practice and empower civil society networks like the ACP Young Professionals Network, with whom I have had the great pleasure of working.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neven Mimica" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am thankful for this fruitful debate and interesting exchange. The comments I have heard demonstrate that we all agree that the European Union and its partner countries should engage in a relationship of equals. The donor—recipient mentality is over. The European Union has much to gain from building a strong alliance for the future.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me reiterate support for the report presented today. Its vision of the future makes me confident about the next steps in the process. The Commission and the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy have been preparing a joint communication for November, proposing broad elements and building blocks for a future policy framework with the ACP countries. It will be accompanied by an impact assessment of options for a Cotonou successor framework. This report and subsequent discussion in Parliament and the Council, as well as with the ACP leaders, will feed into the preparation of the recommendation to Council, with draft negotiating directives, in the course of 2017.</p>
      <p sl="en">Much is still to be decided, but I believe we are moving together in the right direction and for the benefit of all. I look forward to continuing our strong and fruitful cooperation as we go forward.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="96844" name="Norbert Neuser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar! Danke auch nochmal für das klare Wort: Donor mentality is over, und von dem Geist muss auch das neue Fortsetzungsprogramm nach Cotonou ausgehen. Ich will auch den Schattenberichterstattern danken, weil die Zusammenarbeit sehr fruchtbar war und auch dem DEVE-Sekretariat, insbesondere Jesper Haglund und seinem Team, das mit hoher Kompetenz mitgeholfen hat, einen guten Bericht auf den Weg zu bringen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Ausschüsse AFET, INTA und BUDG stehen hinter diesen Bericht, und es ist wichtig, dass wir diese drei wichtigen Ausschüsse ebenfalls mit eingebunden haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben bisher nicht diskutiert, wie sich die AKP-Staaten zu einem Nachfolgeabkommen stellen, und ich denke, das sind die Signale von unseren Partnern aus den AKP-Ländern: Sie wollen diese gewachsenen Beziehungen weiter aufrechterhalten. Es ist ein ganz wichtiges Argument zu wissen, was die Partner wollen und in welchem Rahmen die Partner ihre Arbeit mit uns, der EU, über 2020 hinaus weiter fortsetzen wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sprachen von neuen Herausforderungen. Ich nehme nur ein Beispiel: die Bekämpfung der Fluchtursachen. Wo haben wir die Möglichkeit, den Dialog über Fluchtursachen zu führen, wenn nicht bei den AKP. Wir haben dort als Mitglieder Sudan, Südsudan, Äthiopien, Eritrea, Nigeria, Niger, Tschad, Somalia – Beispiele, die klarmachen, wie wichtig die Zusammenarbeit ist und dass wir dort auch den politischen Dialog führen und auch zu Ergebnissen kommen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und ein Letztes: Hätten die USA, Russland oder China ein solches Vertragswerk mit 78 Ländern – über Jahrzehnte gewachsen –, sie würden sich die Finger danach lecken und würden alles tun, damit dieser Vertrag fortgesetzt wird!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votul va avea loc marți, 4 octombrie 2016.</p>
      <p sl="en">Declaraţii scrise (articolul 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0500" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Unia Europejska, chcąc działać na rzecz zrównoważonego rozwoju, a także promowania demokracji na świecie, musi zastanowić, się, w jaki sposób ułożyć relacje z krajami AKP nie tylko na kilka najbliższych lat, ale także po roku 2020. Otóż regulująca owe relacje do tej pory umowa z Kotonu okazała się niewystarczającym narzędziem w tym zakresie. Uważam, że przyszłe partnerstwo, jeśli ma być skuteczne, musi zerwać z mentalnością darczyńca–biorca, przede wszystkim uwzględniając realne potrzeby państw AKP. W związku z tym musi ono w większym stopniu niż dotychczas opierać się na zaangażowaniu parlamentów krajowych, władz lokalnych, społeczeństwa obywatelskiego i sektora prywatnego z krajów AKP. Dobrym krokiem w tym kierunku były obszerne konsultacje społeczne, jakie przeprowadziła Komisja Europejska z obywatelami oraz różnymi organizacjami społecznymi z całego świata. Uważam także, iż w celu uniknięcia dublowania pewnych zadań przez UE należy pamiętać o umowach o partnerstwie ekonomicznym, które jako istotne forum współpracy regionalnej powinny pozostać kamieniem węgielnym przyszłego partnerstwa.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Access to education for Syrian children in Lebanon (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este dezbaterea privind Declarația Comisiei referitoare la accesul la educație al copiilor sirieni din Liban (2016/2913(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me start by underlining our 100% commitment to the goal of education for all Syrian refugees, in line with our pledge at the Syria Donors Conference in London.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is absolutely essential that we do not lose a generation of displaced Syrian children. First and foremost, this is important for the well—being of the children themselves. It is also crucial for regional stability, for the eventual recovery of Syria from this crisis as well as – let’s face it – in our own interest over the long term. Where there are needs, we are responding and we are ready, if necessary, to do more. Our neighbours in the region need to know that we stand by them as they work towards a better future.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the outcomes of the London Conference was a joint commitment to provide access to quality education for all refugee and vulnerable children in host communities. We will make every effort to empower young Syrians by investing in their future. Education is, and has always been, a key priority of the EU response to the crisis in Syria. So far we have made a substantial contribution to education in Lebanon, with EUR 180 million allocated to this sector since the beginning of the crisis. We have stepped up this approach both through the EU Trust Fund in response to the Syria crisis as well as the compact we have been negotiating with the Lebanese and Jordanian authorities. This aims to turn the challenges posed by the huge influx of Syrian refugees into an opportunity both for refugees and host communities. In Lebanon the focus has been on education, where we hope that reforms will have an impact across the entire public education sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">EUR 42.5 million has already been allocated to the so-called Reaching All Children with Education Strategy, the abbreviation for which is RACE, which I think is a good one. Called the RACE Programme, it was designed by the Lebanese Ministry of Education. A substantial part of this has gone towards the enrolment of Syrian children in formal and non-formal education, the supply of educational material and transport. I am pleased to say that this coming school year is already well funded and we will be able to cover school fees for over 168 000 Syrian children in formal education.</p>
      <p sl="en">I must stress, however, that money alone will not solve the problem of access to education. There are still serious legal, administrative and technical barriers. This includes the lack of residency status, the distance between where refugees live and the schools that service them but also, unfortunately, harassment and discrimination, which has been documented in last summer’s Human Rights Watch report.</p>
      <p sl="en">The problem of residency status is a serious one and has a clear impact on freedom of movement of refugees and leads to exploitation, including child labour. This is why we have placed this at the core of the EU-Lebanon compact. In exchange for the considerable financial support being offered by the European Union, Lebanon has agreed to provide an appropriate and safe environment for refugees.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are working closely with various UN agencies and international NGOs in this respect and it should be noted that when we see or hear of the commendable work being done by UNICEF, UNHCR and others, that behind this effort there is a strong European Union contribution which should also be acknowledged.</p>
      <p sl="en">Although not directly linked with the subject we are dealing with today, I should also mention the humanitarian initiative launched by my colleagues Mogherini and Stylianides over the past few days. The tragedy of Aleppo cannot continue and we call on all parties concerned to ensure that the desperately needed aid can be delivered.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thank you for your attention and I await a very fruitful discussion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="95074" name="Jeroen Lenaers" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de PPE-Fractie. – We zijn anderhalve week geleden met de Commissie burgerlijke vrijheden op delegatiebezoek geweest in Libanon en we hebben daar ter plekke kunnen constateren dat de EU-steun aan het land echt cruciaal is. Steun om Libanon te helpen om te gaan met de meer dan een miljoen vluchtelingen uit Syrië die hun toevlucht hebben gezocht in het kleine buurland. 489 000 Kinderen tussen de 3 en de 18 jaar uit Syrië zitten in Libanon. Het is mede ónze verantwoordelijkheid om ervoor te zorgen dat ze ook naar school kunnen gaan. Het is heel terecht wat de commissaris zei: niet alleen Syrische kinderen maar hou ook als alstublieft oog voor andere kwetsbare kinderen, zoals die van de lokale Libanese bevolking, maar ook die de Palestijnse vluchtelingen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Met betrekking tot Syrische vluchtelingen: veel van die kinderen hebben vanwege de omstandigheden delen of soms hele schooljaren gemist en dat vereist een op maat gemaakte aanpak om ervoor te zorgen dat deze kinderen niet uiteindelijk het kind van de rekening worden. Zo'n aanpak kost geld en we hebben daar ter plekke gezien dat de steun vanuit de Europese Unie zeer gewaardeerd wordt en ook werkt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Het gaat echter om meer dan alleen om geld en ik ben heel blij dat de commissaris de opmerking maakte over de verblijfspapieren. Steeds meer Syrische vluchtelingen in Libanon hebben moeite om hun verblijfspapieren te vernieuwen. Op dit moment beschikt ongeveer 70 % van de mensen niet over de juiste papieren en dat heeft ook gevolgen voor de kinderen. Sommige ouders zijn bang om hun kinderen naar school te brengen, omdat ze bang zijn gecontroleerd te worden op die papieren. Dus vraag ik de Europese Commissie ook: blijf daarover overleggen met de Libanese regering - heel scherp - opdat we op die manier echt proberen die kinderen naar school te krijgen. Het Europese hulpbudget aan Libanon werkt. Het is tastbaar. Mensen merken het in hun eigen dagelijkse leven, dus laten we ervoor zorgen dat we dat doorzetten, dat we dat mogelijk verruimen, want zolang er nog steeds honderdduizend Syrische kinderen in Libanon niet naar school gaan, zit ons werk er nog niet op.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-0000" speaker_id="96844" name="Norbert Neuser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir müssen darauf achten, dass die Verpflichtungen, die bei der Geberkonferenz für Syrien eingegangen wurden, auch umgesetzt werden. Herr Kommissar, Sie haben gesagt: Es geht um das Wohl der Kinder, es geht um den Aufbau eines Syriens nach dem Bürgerkrieg. Es geht aber auch darum, weitere Ursachen für die Flucht aus den Lagern nach Europa zu vermeiden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir waren vor einem Jahr in den Lagern in der Türkei. Uns wurde gesagt: Wir junge Familien verlassen die Türkei, weil wir hier keine Gelegenheit haben, dass unsere Kinder in Erziehung, in die Schule integriert werden können. Dieses Beispiel macht klar, dass wir hier ungeheuer viel tun müssen. Wir haben 250 000 von 500 000 Kindern, die keinen Zugang zur Schule haben, und deswegen müssen wir alles tun, um den Libanon zu unterstützen, damit den syrischen Kindern ein Zugang zur Bildung gewährt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die S&amp;D-Fraktion hat mit ihrer EDUCA-Kampagne genau dies auch vor und will deswegen, dass der Haushalt auch dementsprechend vergrößert wird. Wir sind in naher Zukunft dabei, uns im Rahmen einer fact finding mission im Libanon speziell auch die Situation im Bildungssystem anzusehen. Jedes Kind, das dort im Libanon die Möglichkeit hat, in die Schule zu gehen, um damit später für sich selbst, für sein Wohl, aber auch für die syrische Gemeinschaft wieder sein Land mit aufzubauen, ist sehr wichtig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank, und ich hoffe, dass wir insbesondere gegenüber den Gebern soviel Druck machen können, dass das notwendige Geld fürs kommende Schuljahr auch schnell bereitgestellt wird.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Szanowni Państwo! W ostatnich dniach byłem w kolejnych dwóch krajach Bliskiego Wschodu: w Libanie i Jordanii. Odwiedzałem tam obozy uchodźców, podobnie jak parę miesięcy temu, kiedy byłem w Iraku. Jednak, co chciałem podkreślić, sytuacja dzieci i młodzieży syryjskiej w Libanie jest szczególnie trudna. Mój kolega z PPE mówił też o uchodźcach z Palestyny, ale oni mają na przykład własny samorząd, mają własne siły porządkowe i jest to wspólnota, która funkcjonuje w Libanie od kilkudziesięciu lat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stopień skolaryzacji dzieci palestyńskich jest dużo większy niż dzieci i młodzieży syryjskiej. Oczywiście my na tej sali możemy się różnić w wielu kwestiach, gdy chodzi o imigrantów, napływ imigrantów do Europy, ich rozdzielenie. Myślę jednak, że się nie różnimy w kwestii, że musimy, że warto i trzeba inwestować właśnie w uchodźców, którzy tam mieszkają, a także w ich edukację. Im bardziej wyedukowane będą dzieci uchodźców, tym prawdopodobnie mniejsze będą szanse, że wejdą one na drogę terroryzmu, który, chociaż bywa, że jest także on oczywiście pokusą ludzi wykształconych, występuje bardzo często wśród ludzi niewykształconych.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-0000" speaker_id="125038" name="Maite Pagazaurtundúa Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor Presidente, muchísimas gracias a todos los miembros de la Comisión presentes. Algunos vinimos del Líbano hace muy pocos días y pudimos ver, por una parte, que las autoridades libanesas contemplaban como una carga muy, muy difícil de sobrellevar la situación de los refugiados en su país —a los que, por cierto, porque no están obligadas, prácticamente no les dan papeles legales—. De hecho, cada vez más, en la sociedad libanesa se habla de mandarlos a Siria; y hablan de lugares seguros, cosa que sabemos que no existe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y efectivamente, ACNUR y Unicef trabajan de forma extraordinaria, y usted habla de 168 000 escolarizados en este curso escolar, pero es que son más de 250 000 los que no están escolarizados, y no podemos conformarnos con menos de que todos tengan oportunidades de escolarización.</p>
      <p sl="en">En este caso, la eficacia no es algo que tenemos que perseguir, sino que tenemos que conseguir. Porque seis años de escolarización perdida es la vida, prácticamente, de una criatura, y estamos hablando de los de primaria, de los de secundaria. Y solo un puñado muy pequeño, un puñado de jóvenes con escolarización suficiente han podido acceder a la universidad, de todos los refugiados sirios que están en edad y que tienen estudios, porque los sirios tenían la tasa de graduación más alta de toda la región.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y estamos hablando de gente como usted y como yo que hace seis años empezaron a perder oportunidades, y que además saben que sus padres, sus primos, sus hermanos mayores tuvieron oportunidades de escolarización antes de la maldita guerra que les asola.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por tanto, Comisario, no podemos hacer menos que conseguir que la escolarización sea del cien por cien y alcance al cien por cien. No podemos quedarnos con esos 168 000 y felicitarnos por ello.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-0000" speaker_id="125035" name="Lola Sánchez Caldentey" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor Presidente, la respuesta internacional a la guerra en Siria ha sido y sigue siendo nefasta. Parece que nadie tenga verdadero interés en acabar con esta masacre. Y las peores consecuencias caen siempre sobre los más vulnerables: los niños.</p>
      <p sl="en">El Líbano, que puede darnos lecciones en el cumplimiento de la legalidad internacional respecto a refugiados, otorga el derecho a la escolarización de niños y niñas sirias. Sin embargo, el apoyo de la Comisión Europea y los Estados miembros a la educación de los refugiados es todavía muy deficiente y secundario.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y no es por falta de recursos, sino una cuestión de prioridades. Porque sí que tenemos siete mil millones de euros para darle a Turquía para que haga el trabajo sucio, pero no somos capaces de garantizar un derecho humano, como es la educación pública y de calidad a todos y cada uno de los refugiados, apoyando económicamente, como se merece, al Líbano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay dos formas de dar respuesta a esta crisis migratoria que tanto miedo les da a algunos de ustedes. Una, con vallas y fronteras externas, y, otra, buscando un futuro digno y seguro en las zonas de conflicto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si no garantizamos un futuro a los niños que sufren la guerra, estaremos pavimentando el camino al odio, al miedo y, por tanto, a los fascismos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="124993" name="Bodil Valero" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Herr talman! Jag vill börja med att påminna om det väldigt stora ansvar som Libanon har tagit för de syriska flyktingarna ända sedan kriget startade. Jag skulle ha varit stolt om Europas länder hade tagit samma ansvar, om vi också hade gett flyktingarna uppehållstillstånd och arbetstillstånd, gett barnen skolgång etc, etc.</p>
      <p sl="en">När 163 000 flyktingar kom till Sverige förra året kollapsade våra mottagningssystem. Boende, skolor och hälsovård räckte inte till. Vi är ändå ett av de länder som tog emot; det gör inte alla. Jag har full förståelse för att Libanon har samma problem, men deras problem är så mycket större. Jag förstår också om Libanon tycker att vi ska ta ett större ansvar.</p>
      <p sl="en">För att slippa ta emot i Europa talar vi ju om att vi ska hjälpa till på plats, och det är där pengarna kommer in i det hela. Trots att vi har utlovat mycket pengar, stora resurser, är inte alla de resurserna på plats. Enligt den studie som kommissionären hänvisade till hade bara 23 procent, tror jag, nått fram.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi vill ju också samtidigt att när flyktingarna kommer till Libanon ska Libanon ge uppehållstillstånd och arbetstillstånd, de ska ge barnen skolgång etc, och vi vill hjälpa till. Men vi ska titta på vad vi gör själva. Vi gör faktiskt inte samma sak själva. Vi borde också ställa krav på oss själva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kommissionären tog också upp problemet med att man blir av med sitt uppehållstillstånd. När man är utan uppehållstillstånd blir man papperslös, och när man är papperslös vågar man inte låta sina barn gå i skolan för man är rädd att myndigheterna då hittar en; man kan söka föräldrarna genom att man vet var barnen är. Det här är ett problem som vi har inte bara i Libanon, utan också i länder här i Europa. Det är svårt att vara papperslös oavsett var i världen man lever. Men det viktiga som det här handlar om är att se till att vi inte får de här förlorade generationerna, kanske, av flyktingbarn, som kommissionären pratade om. Att inte få gå i skola, som kan vara den enda fasta punkten i tillvaron, leder också på sikt till stora hälsoproblem för de barnen, och det måste vi till varje pris undvika.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="96674" name="Anna Maria Corazza Bildt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, today we cannot stay silent and turn our back on the bloodshed in Aleppo. Children are being slaughtered, injured and starved. They are trapped and traumatised. More than 100 kids have been killed in Aleppo last week by the Syrian army and Russian air strikes. More than 100 000 children are under siege. We have to strongly condemn the indiscriminate bombing of families and hospitals and the use of illegal weapons. The United Nations Secretary calls it war crimes. So what can we do?</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU should call for an immediate ceasefire, and I welcome the new humanitarian initiative for Aleppo to ensure access to emergency aid, safe passage for rescue workers and the evacuation of the sick and the wounded. The EU must also relaunch negotiations. There is no military solution. The EU should unite in confronting Russia with its responsibility as a member of the United Nations Security Council. For Russia to be a partner for peace, they must respect humanitarian law and go back to the negotiating table, and those responsible must be held accountable.</p>
      <p sl="en">All Member States should increase resettlement for thousands of kids, especially unaccompanied minors, and education. Going back to school gives children a sense of normality, a chance for self-sufficiency, and hope for the future. Education empowers children, it helps prevent violence, early marriage, forced labour and radicalisation and recruitment. With the Intergroup of human rights in the European Parliament that I co-chair, we stand united with the children of Syria. We fully support the ECHO/UNICEF Emergency Lessons campaign to provide education for children in conflict, and the No Lost Generation initiative to recruit Syrian teachers for Syrian children. We fully support the UNICEF campaign Education Cannot Wait as five years is a lifetime. We urge the EU and the Member States to increase efficient funding for education for Syrian children. Let us raise our voices and invest in children. End violence against the children of Syria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-092-0000" speaker_id="96768" name="Enrique Guerrero Salom" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, nadie sufre más en la situaciones de guerra que los niños. Son víctimas de bombardeos, son víctimas de desplazamientos, pierden su acceso a la educación; a veces pierden el contacto con sus propias familias.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cuando una guerra dura seis años, o más, como es el caso de Siria, lo que está en riesgo es todo el ciclo vital de esos niños perdidos en distintos sitios, muchos de ellos en campos de refugiados.</p>
      <p sl="en">El Líbano, en cierta medida, es un ejemplo. Asume un número de refugiados que, si fuéramos siquiera la décima parte de generosos, no tendríamos en estos momentos ningún problema en la Unión Europea. Por tanto, no podemos culpabilizar al Líbano, pero es verdad que el Líbano tiene que resolver problemas como los que se refieren a la residencia legal, al permiso de trabajo y a la escolarización efectiva de 250 000 niños que todavía no acceden a sus aulas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nada proporciona más oportunidades a la vida futura de los niños que la paz y la educación. Y nada proporciona más estabilidad a las sociedades que la educación para la paz. Por tanto: hagamos el esfuerzo que nos corresponde para proveer de estabilidad, de paz —acabando con este conflicto— y de educación a esos niños para que tengan una vida futura en reconstrucción.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Liban tak jak Jordania to są właśnie te miejsca, gdzie naprawdę są uchodźcy, ludzie, którzy uciekli przed wojną i w sąsiednim kraju czekają na jej zakończenie. Oni naprawdę przede wszystkim potrzebują domu, czyli pokoju, bo pokój to jest dom. Wszyscy zastanówmy się, co zrobiliśmy, żeby ta niepotrzebna wojna się skończyła, ale póki trwa, to im trzeba pomagać tam na miejscu.</p>
      <p sl="en">I Polska jest krajem, który nie tylko mówi, ale najzwyczajniej po prostu pomaga. My dwa miesiące temu zwiększyliśmy nakłady na pomoc dla uchodźców w Libanie, na utrzymanie szkół, przekazywane organizacjom pozarządowym, które tam na miejscu ludziom pomagają, ale przede wszystkim ci ludzie muszą wrócić do domów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ja z dużym niepokojem słucham tych opinii na tej sali, marzymy: skończy się wojna, karanie, ściganie winnych i tak dalej. Ilu ludzi dożyje tej bezwarunkowej kapitulacji? Ta wojna naprawdę trwa już o wiele lat za długo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-0000" speaker_id="135491" name="María Teresa Giménez Barbat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, estimados compañeros, el conflicto en Siria está produciendo una generación perdida de millones de niños que nunca han estado en clase o que solo tienen recuerdos de tal experiencia.</p>
      <p sl="en">En Líbano, el Gobierno, junto a varias organizaciones y gracias a programas como No Lost Generation, de Unicef, financiado por la Unión Europea, hace un trabajo activo para permitir a los menores tener acceso a la educación pública, a la salud, a la nutrición y a los servicios higiénicos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lamentablemente, la mayoría de los niños siguen quedándose sin posibilidad de escolarizarse. En Líbano, las cifras dicen que 150 000 niños sirios no van a la escuela, y se calcula que antes del fin de año el número llegará a los 400 000.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estamos enfrentados a un desafío que no es únicamente humanitario. Podemos y debemos seguir financiando estos programas para que se garantice una educación básica a toda una generación que un día volverá a su país y será responsable de su reconstrucción.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero ¿pensamos de verdad que eso pueda bastar? Debemos tener coraje político. En primer lugar, nuestra diplomacia tiene que luchar por una solución pacífica a la guerra de Siria, empezando por la prohibición de la venta de armas; en segundo lugar, es inútil y vergonzoso firmar acuerdos con terceros países para que se encarguen ellos de los refugiados que llegan a nuestras fronteras.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si no conseguimos alcanzar este esfuerzo político, que sí es sostenible si lo repartimos entre todos los Estados miembros, servirá de poco lo humanitario.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-0000" speaker_id="125997" name="Javier Couso Permuy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, a las niñas y a los niños sirios no los llevó un viento huracanado al Líbano. Huyeron por una guerra de desestabilización que muchos países de la Unión Europea —y, sobre todo, nuestros queridos aliados— financian y en la que entrenan e impulsan a grupos extremistas que practican el terrorismo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Siria tenía un sistema educativo sólido: casi el 100 % de los niños escolarizados en primaria; el 70 % en secundaria. El Líbano muestra las vergüenzas de la Unión Europea. Un país de solo 4,6 millones acoge a 2 millones de refugiados sirios. Un país con un equilibrio precario que hace un esfuerzo admirable para escolarizar al 60 % de las niñas y de los niños sirios de seis a once años.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ya que no cumplimos con los refugiados —lo cual nos avergüenza—, hay que apoyar más este esfuerzo. Pero, sobre todo, hay que impulsar la paz entre el Gobierno legítimo y la oposición no terrorista, porque esa es la única solución para que las niñas y los niños sirios puedan volver a estudiar a su país.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="124702" name="Jaromír Štětina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, Jordánsko a Libanon se k uprchlické krizi postavily lidsky a zodpovědně. Tyto dvě země přijaly celkem více než čtyři miliony uprchlíků, což je více než třetina, opakuji třetina jejich celkové populace. Libanon hostí více než jeden milion syrských uprchlíků. V Libanonu žije 417 000 syrských uprchlických dětí ve věku tři až čtrnáct let. Odhaduje se, že téměř polovina z nich nemá přístup k žádné formě vzdělání.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mezi léty 2012 až 2015 Evropská komise poskytla 269 milionů pro humanitární pomoc v Libanonu v souvislosti se syrskou krizí. V roce 2016 Evropská komise plánuje alokovat 87 milionů dodatečných prostředků na humanitární asistenci. Oceňuji tuto snahu Evropské unie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vzdělání je budoucnost, znamená naději. Matky dětí, které neměly šanci dostat se do Libanonu, si však každodenně kladou jinou otázku. Bude moje dítě zítra naživu? Přežije další útok ruských a asadovských vojsk?</p>
      <p sl="en">Připomínám, dámy a pánové, že tuto sobotu byla v Alepu již potřetí bombardována traumatologická nemocnice, kde jsou i dětští pacienti. Jordánsko a Libanon si zaslouží nejen naše uznání, ale také pokračující finanční podporu v rámci regionálního fondu Evropské unie a evropské humanitární pomoci. Nejmenší, co můžeme udělat, je usnadnit práci těm, kteří zachraňují životy místo nás. Zastavme vraždění syrských dětí asadovsko- ruskou aliancí. Dejme syrským dětem vzdělání. To je nejlepší zbraň proti válce.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-0000" speaker_id="96911" name="Tanja Fajon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Prejšnji teden sem se vrnila iz Libanona, kjer si štiri milijone Libanoncev deli državo s skoraj poldrugim milijonom beguncev.</p>
      <p sl="en">Med begunci v Libanonu je danes še vedno četrtina Palestincev, ki so že drugo ali tretjo generacijo brez državljanstva. Ostali so večinoma iz Sirije. Več kot polovica vseh je otrok, med njimi tretjina šoloobveznih, a jih v šolo hodi le 30 odstotkov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dovoljenja za prebivanja so predraga, vse več beguncev nima … (Govorka je nadaljevala v angleščini, ker ni bilo tolmačenja.)</p>
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I hear there is no interpretation. I will make it short in English. I just wanted to say that last week I came from Lebanon, and it was very shocking. A third of children are not going to school, and the reason is, for the most part, that they do not have residency permits.</p>
      <p sl="en">Residency permits cost USD 200 per year, and 90% of refugees today do not simply manage to get them. So their parents are extremely afraid to send their kids to school, not to mention that private schools are impossible to reach. The situation is very critical, economically and politically, because of the war in Syria. What is very worrying is the new policy of the Lebanese Government, which is urging us to recognise some parts of the country as safe, and send refugees back. I think this is completely unacceptable.</p>
      <p sl="en">I completely agree with my colleague: we have to ensure that the money gets there. But it is not only money that is crucial. It is extremely crucial that we create efficient policies on the ground so that – in a highly corrupt environment – money gets to where it is needed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-0000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, when we listen to the public debate about refugees and asylum seekers in Europe, it would be easy to think that Europe is facing the main crisis, and it also sounds as if the deal or the statement with Turkey – as the unofficial and intransparent deal is now called – is the main solution.</p>
      <p sl="en">This picture could not be more false, and it only distracts from the urgent need for the EU Member States to do their homework and ensure that our borders are protected and that they develop a common EU position to engage actively with the goal of facilitating a negotiated end to the horrifying war in Syria. As long as Assad’s and Russian planes are bombing residents and homes, people will not return.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let there be no confusion: it is the Lebanese who have taken extraordinary numbers of people in need. It is the half a million Syrian children who live in an absolute crisis: half of them not enrolled in schools, and girls being particularly vulnerable. I have no illusions about the short- or long-term impact of a lost generation on these people themselves and also on us. We must connect the dots and realise that our fates are intertwined. If we prefer sheltering the region over opening our doors, we must invest in safe, sufficient and accessible education for kids in Lebanon. We cannot afford for Lebanon to destabilise, and it would cause more suffering for children.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. – Chciałbym zapytać koleżankę, czy nie zauważa tego, że interwencja rosyjska, która odgrywa rolę bardzo destrukcyjną w Syrii, trwa jednak o wiele krócej niż ta wojna. My naprawdę nie myślimy o tym, jak tę wojnę kontynuować, tylko jak najszybciej doprowadzić tam do pokoju, gdyż jest to jedyny ratunek dla tych dzieci i jedyna szansa na powrót do domu dla tych setek tysięcy uchodźców, którzy znajdują się w Jordanii i w Libanie, i jedyna szansa, żeby zniknął pretekst do kontynuowania fali imigracyjnej do Europy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – I heard only a statement from my respected colleague. However, let me reiterate that, indeed, the Russians are playing a destructive, unacceptable role in bombing innocent people in Syria, and it is high time that the EU stopped allowing this to happen. It is in the vacuum that the EU and the international community have left that the destructive forces that are killing people have taken too much space. I think that we should be very focused on what we have to do ourselves, which is on the one hand to allow for a humane and functioning asylum policy – and that goes for all EU Member States – and on the other hand to invest in a common position and a more ambitious diplomatic approach to a negotiated peace in Syria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef Weidenholzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Der Zugang zur formalen Bildung ist einer der wichtigsten Aspekte der Flüchtlingskrise, und wir haben das viel zu lange vernachlässigt. Ich freue mich über diese Debatte und über die Fortschritte, die es offensichtlich gibt. Die Lage ist in der Tat erschütternd. Bei einem meiner Besuche in dem Lager hat mich ein junger, 14- oder 15-jähriger Mann begleitet, hat mir die Situation erklärt, und ich fragte ihn dann, wo er Englisch gelernt hätte. Seine Antwort war: Ich habe ein Wörterbuch gefunden und lerne es auswendig. Diese Antwort des jungen Mannes werde ich nie vergessen! Und ich frage Sie: Ist es nicht ein Skandal, dass dieser Mann keine Chance hatte, in eine Schule zu gehen? Und was wird aus ihm in ein, zwei, drei Jahren werden, wenn ihm der Zugang zur Bildung weiterhin versagt bleibt?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, education is a fundamental human right and essential for the exercise of all other human rights. That is why the Committee on Culture and Education has put forward the proposal of education corridors. I am very proud that my group, the Socialists and Democrats, have launched the EDUCA campaign, calling for more international funding to be focused on the education of refugee children and young people, and mobilising universities in Europe and in conflict zones to act on this.</p>
      <p sl="en">A whole generation of refugee children, especially girls and young women, face a bleak future without education. This is also important for all the welcoming countries who will benefit from the economic contribution of educated newcomers. It is a moral humanitarian duty for the European Union, as one of the main welcoming regions and a key player in the international scene, to guarantee that these young people have the opportunity for a brighter future.</p>
      <p sl="en">Education initiatives, including informal education, must support refugee children’s mental health after they have gone through traumatic experiences. It is vital for present and future conflict resolution and peace-building in the region.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, five years after the start of the conflict in Syria, more than 250 000 children – approximately half of the nearly 500 000 school—age Syrian children registered in Lebanon – are out of school. This is totally unacceptable. The high number of refugee children out of school is an immediate crisis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Education is a fundamental right under international law. All children in Lebanon – including Syrian refugees – have a legal right to free and compulsory primary education and access to secondary education without discrimination. Education is also crucial for protecting children in situations of displacement, which can sometimes last for an entire childhood.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite these efforts, too many Syrian children are still out of school. I believe Lebanon needs more international financial support to respond to the educational needs of Syrian refugees, including expanding and rehabilitating public schools, investing in quality education, fully including children with disabilities, training and hiring more teachers and subsidising school transportation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-0000" speaker_id="124864" name="Michela Giuffrida" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, circa un milione di persone ha urgente bisogno di assistenza umanitaria in Libano e la metà di questi sono bambini. Il Libano è un paese che sta affrontando con enormi sforzi la crisi umanitaria che l'ha investito – e lo sta facendo forse con maggiore coraggio dell'Europa che, in proporzione, come tutti sappiamo, accoglie molti meno rifugiati – e molti di questi sforzi riguardano proprio i minori. In Libano i bambini siriani possono andare a scuola, però solo sulla carta, perché purtroppo Human Rights Watch ci descrive una situazione che è nella realtà molto difficile.</p>
      <p sl="en">Più della metà dei 500 000 bambini siriani non riesce infatti ad accedere all'istruzione e concedere un diritto non equivale sempre a garantirne l'esercizio. L'estrema povertà delle famiglie siriane e la difficoltà di accesso al mondo del lavoro e ad avere una residenza gravano tutte sul futuro di questi bambini che hanno già conosciuto il peggio che questo mondo poteva offrire loro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Libano – ma credo sia un dovere morale dell'Europa – deve garantire a questi bambini l'opportunità per combattere un giorno con la forza della cultura quel nemico così ignorante che oggi li ha costretti ad abbandonare le loro case e il loro paese.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="124861" name="Caterina Chinnici" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, recentemente ho avuto anch'io modo di partecipare, con la commissione per il controllo dei bilanci, a una missione in Libano e in Giordania, visitando proprio i campi profughi in cui vivono i rifugiati siriani.</p>
      <p sl="en">La situazione è drammatica e lo è più di quanto non si possa immaginare, soprattutto con riferimento alle condizioni dei minori, anche perché, se le stime sono corrette, saranno circa 250 000 i bambini che non avranno accesso all'istruzione e che si vedranno quindi negato un diritto fondamentale per la loro crescita e soprattutto per un futuro dignitoso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tante, forse troppe, le volte in cui in quest'Aula abbiamo discusso della crisi migratoria e delle sue terribili conseguenze, soprattutto per i minori. Occorre ormai porre la situazione dei minori concretamente al top dell'agenda politica della cooperazione dell'Unione europea. Solo in questo modo potremo dare una reale speranza ai bambini ed evitare il fenomeno della lost generation cui rischiano di andare incontro le giovani generazioni di siriani. In questo senso auspico che sia rinnovato il supporto ai programmi educativi per i bambini siriani in Libano.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-0000" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Úr! Európának és a menekülteknek azonos az érdeke, hogy a menekültek visszatérhessenek szülőhazájukba, amint a kiváltó okok mérséklődnek vagy megszűnnek. Tehát a kiváltó okokat kell megszüntetnünk és ott kell segítenünk, ahol a baj van, nem idehoznunk azt. Ennek érdekében pedig létfontosságú, hogy a menekülésre kényszerített emberek a hazájukhoz közeli táborokban megfelelő életkörülmények között élhessenek.</p>
      <p sl="en">És ennek az egyik legfontosabb eleme az oktatás. Az oktatás biztosítása elengedhetetlen nemcsak a gyermek egészséges fejlődése miatt, de saját közösségük jövője szempontjából is. Nem eshet ki egész generáció az oktatásból, már csak a radikalizáció elkerülése végett is. Ezért is nagyon fontos, hogy a szír gyermekek részesülhessenek oktatásban Libanonban. És örvendek, hogy Magyarország is támogatja direkt a libanoni, jordániai, iraki menekülttáborokban az oktatás biztosítását konkrét felajánlásokkal, vagy kórházak építését.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, è un'emergenza senza fine quella dei profughi siriani in Libano. Secondo un rapporto di Human Rights Watch sulla condizione dei bambini siriani rifugiati in Libano, i minori a cui è stato negato l'accesso all'istruzione sarebbero 250 000. Solo il 3% dei ragazzini nell'ultimo anno ha frequentato una scuola pubblica libanese.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gli sforzi del governo libanese per assicurare un minimo di istruzione ai minori siriani sono però insufficienti. Le scuole pubbliche rifiutano i bambini disabili per mancanza di risorse e molte famiglie con il permesso di soggiorno scaduto non possono mandare i figli a scuola per paura di essere arrestate. L'accesso all'istruzione è fondamentale per aiutare e dare un futuro a questa nuova generazione, ma anche per superare i segni di tanta violenza. È fondamentale il supporto economico internazionale a progetti per l'espansione del programma di istruzione, ma sono anche necessarie azioni politiche concrete per favorire l'accoglienza. Il rischio è che altrimenti anche le speranze dei giovani siriani intrappolati dalla guerra in Libano resteranno vane.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, ο Λίβανος είναι μια μικρή χώρα 4,5 εκατομμυρίων κατοίκων που φιλοξενεί σήμερα πάνω από ένα εκατομμύριο πρόσφυγες, από τους οποίους οι μισοί είναι παιδιά. Από τα παιδιά αυτά, 250.000 δεν έχουν πρόσβαση στην εκπαίδευση. Πρέπει λοιπόν να ενισχυθούν οι προσπάθειες παροχής βοήθειας στο Λίβανο, αλλά και στην Ιορδανία, και να επικεντρωθούν οι συναφείς δράσεις στο μείζον ζήτημα της εκπαίδευσης, η έλλειψη της οποίας υπονομεύει το μέλλον αυτών των παιδιών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Στην Ελλάδα, κύριε Επίτροπε, η κατάσταση με το προσφυγικό έχει φτάσει στο απροχώρητο. Επιπλέον, δεν είναι δυνατόν να επιφορτιστεί το ελληνικό εκπαιδευτικό σύστημα που έχει διαλυθεί από την τρόικα και με την εκπαίδευση χιλιάδων παιδιών προσφύγων. Για τον λόγο αυτό, κύριε Hahn, η εκπαίδευση των παιδιών των προσφύγων στην Ελλάδα πρέπει να παρέχεται αποκλειστικά μέσα στα κέντρα φιλοξενίας, με αποκλειστική χρηματοδότηση της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Αντί λοιπόν η Ένωση να δίνει 6 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ στην Τουρκία, εκεί όπου τα παιδιά των προσφύγων καταλήγουν να δουλεύουν στις βιοτεχνίες κλωστοϋφαντουργίας, είναι καλύτερο να δώσει τα χρήματα αυτά σε δομές φιλοξενίας στο Λίβανο, στην Ιορδανία και στην Ελλάδα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, ova me rasprava podsjetila na 90-e godine u Hrvatskoj, na vrijeme rata na Balkanu kada su mnoge osobe raseljene, kada je mnogo izbjeglica došlo u Istru, regiju u kojoj sam tada politički djelovao, kada smo s mnogo mladih ljudi, osnovnoškolaca i srednjoškolaca, imali ozbiljnih problema kako nastaviti njihov obrazovni ciklus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Netko je tada izgubio koji mjesec, možda je netko izgubio i godinu dana, ali ovdje govorimo o tome da djeca gube više godina. I to je zaista tragično. Prisjećajući se tih dana i znajući za probleme u jednoj organiziranoj zemlji kao što je Hrvatska – sa sto problema, ali organiziranoj zemlji – mogu zamisliti kako to može izgledati u Libanonu ili Jordanu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pozivam vas, gospodine povjereniče, da uložite dodatne napore, neovisno o tome što ste jako angažirani, da pomognemo tim državama jer one zaslužuju našu podršku.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, όταν παρατηρούνται μεγάλες μετακινήσεις μεταναστευτικής φύσεως, τα μεγάλα και αθώα θύματα αυτών των εξελίξεων είναι τα παιδιά που υποφέρουν τα πάνδεινα, όπως είναι η έλλειψη εκπαίδευσης. Κάτι τέτοιο συμβαίνει και με τους πρόσφυγες της Συρίας στο Λίβανο. Κάτι τέτοιο συμβαίνει όμως, σε ακόμη χειρότερη μορφή, και στην Ευρώπη και συγκεκριμένα στην Ελλάδα, η οποία έχει καταστραφεί από τα μέτρα του μνημονίου και άρα αδυνατεί να απορροφήσει αυτά τα εκατομμύρια των παράνομων μεταναστών που παραμένουν στο έδαφός της. Μεταξύ αυτών των παράνομων μεταναστών υπάρχουν πολλά παιδιά. Το εκπαιδευτικό σύστημα δεν μπορεί να τα απορροφήσει αλλά οι ανίκανες και άτεγκτες ελληνικές κυβερνήσεις, αντί να ζητήσουν από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση βοήθεια για αυτά τα παιδιά, προσπαθούν να τα βάλουν δια της βίας μέσα στα σχολεία τα ελληνικά. Τι εννοώ όταν λέω δια της βίας; Εννοώ ότι, όταν διαμαρτύρονται οι γονείς τους διότι κινδυνεύουν τα παιδιά και από ασθένειες, η κυβέρνηση στέλνει τις μονάδες αποκατάστασης της τάξεως για να χτυπήσουν τους Έλληνες. Αυτό είναι το πρόβλημα που πρέπει να αντιμετωπίσει η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση κατά τη γνώμη μου κι όχι τόσο πολύ το πρόβλημα του Λιβάνου.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="96917" name="Silvia Costa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, prima di tutto vorrei esprimere il mio sdegno per il genocidio di bambini che sta avvenendo in Siria, dove non si rispettano nemmeno gli ospedali e le vittime innocenti. Per quanto riguarda il diritto all'educazione dei bambini in Libano – ricordo che il Libano sta ospitando più profughi dell'Europa intera – devo dire che tempo fa noi abbiamo lanciato la campagna Educa, e sono felice che la Commissione l'abbia raccolta, e siamo arrivati a 52 milioni di EUR in più per superare quel misero 2 % degli aiuti umanitari che attualmente andavano per l'educazione dei bambini in queste situazioni di profughi o di displacement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Credo che sia importante anche ricordare che, se noi vogliamo evitare una lost generation, dobbiamo fare più sforzi – come chiedo anche alla Commissione– perché tutti i paesi membri ai quali abbiamo mandato una richiesta ufficiale come commissione per la cultura e l'istruzione del Parlamento europeo facciano propria la proposta dei corridoi educativi, ovvero di aprire le università europee e dell'area euromediterranea a ragazzi e studenti che rischiano di perdere l'intero ciclo di studi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="124804" name="Elly Schlein" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, fanno bene i colleghi a ricordare la strage in atto ad Aleppo, una strage di bambini, e fanno bene anche a ricordare gli sforzi che sta facendo il Libano, che ospita da solo un numero di rifugiati maggiore rispetto a quelli che abbiamo accolto in Europa l'anno scorso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il rapporto di Human Rights Watch, del luglio di quest'anno, dice che più della metà dei quasi 500 000 bambini siriani registrati in Libano sono però fuori dal sistema scolastico. Alcuni sono stati fuori sin dal loro arrivo cinque anni fa. Nonostante gli sforzi del governo libanese e dei donatori, la mancanza di risorse e i requisiti restrittivi sulla residenza limitano le possibilità di accedere all'istruzione e li consegnano alla piaga del lavoro minorile.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'educazione è un diritto e deve essere considerata prioritaria in questi contesti, poiché assicura una garanzia di protezione e un senso di normalità ai bambini, proprio nel momento in cui sono più vulnerabili. Rinviare le attività educative a quando l'emergenza e la crisi saranno finite vuol dire rischiare di non tornare a scuola mai più, condannandoli spesso a un futuro di povertà.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Commissario Stylianides aveva affermato l'intenzione di fare dell'UE il primo donatore internazionale a raggiungere il 4 % di spesa in aiuti umanitari per l'istruzione in situazioni di emergenza. Ecco, a partire dal supporto al Libano, dobbiamo fare di più.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is good to see and to hear that there is, across all parties, a common understanding that we have to be extremely focused and committed to guaranteeing education for every child. It is also important to take care that those who are not yet in school have the opportunity to attend school. It is impossible, and I think there is a moral obligation, not to lose any generation, not to lose any child and to give everybody an opportunity to be educated.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think we are all impatient and we are all concerned because still, I agree, not every child is going to school. There are a lot of reasons for that and we should not underestimate that many families push, urge, force their children to work, to contribute to the family’s financial support and income. There are also reasons, as it was already said by some colleagues, because of the lack of having a residency status. This is why one of the key areas we have addressed in our negotiations with the Lebanese Government concerning an EU compact agreement is that this has to be resolved in order to guarantee, including from a legal perspective, the possibility to enrol in schools.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is also some progress, I have to admit. There is now a decision by the Lebanese Government to apply the new Lebanese curriculum. There were some discussions in the past whether it should be the Syrian or the Lebanese curriculum, but there is now a decision, and I think it is a good decision to apply the Lebanese curriculum which allows also that Lebanese teachers can teach Syrian kids. There should also be an opportunity for Syrian teachers who are refugees to get a work permit to teach Syrian kids, and this is also something we have addressed in our negotiations concerning the compact.</p>
      <p sl="en">There was also an issue about the money. May I say that in 2016, as far as the expected number of school children being de facto in school is concerned, this is being financed. There is an overall budget of EUR 191 million. Out of that, EUR 190 million is provided by the European Union and its Member States, with more than 60% of this budget being provided by the European Union. Primarily the financing is provided via UNICEF, but we are also trying to find an agreement with the Lebanese Government directly. This also depends a little bit on the very complicated political situation inside Lebanon. As there is no president elected, with all the consequences of that, it is difficult to have an agreement with the Lebanese Government, and therefore we have decided, in order not to waste time and resources, to channel most of the money via UNICEF.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is one element I would like to highlight, and I think this is something we should not forget. Of course it is important to provide elementary and secondary school education, but it is equally important to offer afterwards children in the region vocational education. Therefore, also the aim of this new compact is to support the Lebanese economy to offer jobs, to offer economic business opportunities and to give young people the opportunity to get an apprenticeship, as an example.</p>
      <p sl="en">So while this is about investment in young people, it is not only an investment in their basic education, but equally important is to have an investment further on in specific training and education to become a skilled member of the workforce. I think this is something which should be our joint focus in the future, of course still taking care about the elementary and secondary school education. Once again, I think we should be determined to provide this additional education not only in Lebanon but also, of course, in Jordan, in Turkey. Wherever Syrian refugee children are, we have to support them and their parents.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Declarații scrise (articolul 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-0000" speaker_id="124883" name="Krystyna Łybacka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Naszym priorytetowym celem w kontekście pomocy dla dzieci-uchodźców, oprócz zapewnienia im bezpieczeństwa i dostępu do żywności i opieki medycznej, powinien być powszechny dostęp do bezpłatnej edukacji. Edukacja dzieci to najlepsza inwestycja w przyszłość. To jest inwestycja długotrwała i jedyna, dzięki której możemy wychować nowe pokolenia w duchu pokoju, tolerancji i zrozumienia międzykulturowego. Edukacja dzieci-uchodźców to także dla nich szansa na powrót do normalności i częściowej stabilizacji, jaką cieszyły się przed wojną. Szkoła daje pewne poczucie bezpieczeństwa i może pomóc w poradzeniu sobie z trudnymi doświadczeniami. Dzięki edukacji młodzi ludzie nabywają także wiedzę i umiejętności, które pomogą im odnaleźć się w nowej sytuacji i pozwolą na dalszy rozwój. Pomimo niekwestionowanej wartości dodanej, jaką jest edukacja dla życia przyszłych pokoleń migrantów, pozostaje ona jedną z najbardziej niedofinansowanych sfer działań pomocowych. Nie możemy na to pozwolić! Dziękuję Komisji za zaproponowanie nowego pakietu pomocy humanitarnej na projekty edukacyjne dla dzieci z rejonów objętych kryzysem. Liczę na jego szybkie i efektywne wdrożenie. Każde dziecko zasługuje na szansę na lepsze życie, które może mu zapewnić właśnie edukacja.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Global goals and EU commitments on nutrition and food security in the world (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-120-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este dezbaterea privind întrebarea cu solicitare de răspuns oral referitoare la obiectivele globale și angajamentele UE în materie de nutriție și securitate alimentară în lume, adresată Comisiei de dl Enrique Guerrero Salom, în numele Comisiei pentru dezvoltare (O-000099/2016 - B8-0717/2016) (2016/2705(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-0000" speaker_id="96768" name="Enrique Guerrero Salom" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, intervengo para presentar esta pregunta oral que la Comisión de Desarrollo tiene interés en debatir con la Comisión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">En septiembre del año pasado, los líderes mundiales, alentados y acompañados por la sociedad civil, incluidas numerosas organizaciones no gubernamentales, acordaron la Agenda para el Desarrollo Sostenible 2030.</p>
      <p sl="en">En los distintos puntos, concretamente en el segundo, se hacía referencia, se subrayaba que la lucha contra el hambre y la desnutrición sigue siendo todavía hoy, ya en pleno siglo XXI, una cuestión central. Trabajar para acabar con el hambre, lograr la seguridad alimentaria, proporcionar mejor nutrición, proveer de medios para la agricultura sostenible son, en el mundo actual, objetivos aún por conseguir.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión de Desarrollo, que presenta esta pregunta para debate, quiere destacar que una parte de nuestra contribución al desarrollo ha servido, sin duda, para disminuir el número de personas que sufren de desnutrición en el mundo, pero está muy lejos de haber alcanzado los objetivos de erradicarla de nuestra realidad. De hecho, la proporción de personas desnutridas en las regiones en desarrollo se ha reducido a casi la mitad desde 1990, pero aun así 785 millones de personas no reciben suficientes alimentos y tampoco obtienen los nutrientes necesarios.</p>
      <p sl="en">La desnutrición crónica afecta a 160 millones de niños, es la causa de casi la mitad de las muertes entre menores de cinco años, uno de cada seis está por debajo del peso para sus edades. La nutrición inadecuada durante los primeros 1 000 días de vida tendrá consecuencias negativas en las capacidades físicas e intelectuales de un niño durante toda su vida.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es por esto que, en 2012, la Asamblea Mundial de la Salud estableció el objetivo de lograr en 2025 una reducción del 40 % en el número de niños con retraso en su crecimiento. Instamos a la Comisión a que aumente los esfuerzos para combatir la malnutrición y por ello necesitamos intervenciones específicas en esos primeros 1 000 días de vida.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me gustaría recordar que la Unión Europea se comprometió en la Cumbre de Londres de 2012 a reducir el retraso en el crecimiento de al menos siete millones de niños para 2025 y de contribuir a esta causa con 3 500 millones de euros hasta 2020. Esperábamos que este año en Río de Janeiro haríamos un balance de los progresos y renovaríamos nuestros compromisos. No ha sido posible. Sin embargo, actuar es hoy más urgente que nunca, porque las intervenciones de desarrollo contra la desnutrición reciben solo el 0,57 % de toda la ayuda oficial al desarrollo. Necesitamos multiplicar por 70 veces la inversión para cumplir nuestros objetivos.</p>
      <p sl="en">En 2013 la Unión Europea comprometió 400 millones para iniciativas específicas. Llamamos a la Comisión a que incremente ese compromiso con otros 1 000 millones adicionales. Tenemos que poner en práctica estrategias, nosotros y todos nuestros socios, para apoyar el importante papel que desempeñan los agricultores a pequeña escala. Ellos producen el 70 % de los alimentos del mundo. Tenemos que apoyarles, utilizar su potencial, aumentar su rendimiento y productividad, preservar la variedad de semillas y el valor nutritivo de lo que producen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comisario, me gustaría escuchar qué piensa hacer la Comisión en este campo. Seguro que está de acuerdo con nosotros en que tenemos que hacer mucho más. También lo ha dicho el presidente del Banco Mundial, que incluso ha señalado o ha dicho que tenemos que señalar a los Gobiernos de los países que no están cumpliendo con sus objetivos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sabemos también qué es necesario hacer en seguridad alimentaria y le pedimos a la Comisión que nos diga qué pretende para los próximos años. Nos gustaría escuchar nuevas iniciativas y que pida a los Estados miembros que se comprometan en 2017 a una cumbre intergubernamental que revise los objetivos y que haga balance de las necesidades que tenemos por delante.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neven Mimica" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the Committee on Development and its Chair, Ms Linda McAvan, for putting nutrition high on the development agenda in line with our commitment to the UN 2030 Agenda and Sustainable Development Goals. The resolution on malnutrition proposed by the committee is, in our view, an important step forward. Since 2012, the Commission has emerged as a world leader in the nutrition arena. This leadership is backed by a robust policy framework addressing both stunting and wasting. Over the last three years, we have observed a trend pointing towards the decrease of stunting. Our first progress report on the European Commission’s Nutrition Action Plan shows that we are well on track to reach the commitment of reducing the number of stunted children under the age of five by seven million by 2025.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our further actions on nutrition and food security should be guided by the approach that would seek to strike the right balance between our preferred nutrition-sensitive interventions that address the multiple nature of undernutrition and malnutrition causes, including food insecurity, health, sanitation, social safety nets and inequalities, and the needed nutrition—specific interventions. This balance is to be better assessed in the programming exercise with partner countries and other donors. This may also include a further look into our development instruments in 2017.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have taken due note of Parliament’s request to increase the Commission’s funding for nutrition-specific actions. In this context, the Commission has put forward the following approach: we should maximise the synergies and complementarities of our development and humanitarian responses to nutrition and food security needs, having in mind that humanitarian responses are, in principle, nutrition-specific.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will promote programming coordination with other donors, who can focus on nutrition-specific interventions, thus complementing the Commission’s focus on nutrition-sensitive issues. We shall also advocate at global level, especially through the Scaling Up Nutrition (SUN) movement, to increase investment in nutrition, including nutrition-specific investments by both donors and developing countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">The first results of this three-pronged approach are encouraging, notably in Rwanda, Ethiopia, Niger, Mali, Bangladesh, Laos and Guatemala. We support partner countries in developing and implementing their own true multi—sectoral nutrition action plans, which combine nutrition-specific and nutrition-sensitive interventions. This also allows donors to align their support to national priorities and coordinate the division of nutrition efforts.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has gained a strong record and evidence in supporting nutrition, mainly through the agriculture, education, water or health sectors. However, the Commission is exploring other areas, such as social safety nets, which have proved to be successful in improving nutrition – particularly in Mali. In this context, the Commission and the Club du Sahel are organising a major event on social protection for nutrition in Abuja in December. The objective will be to further increase investments and to reduce undernutrition faster, while putting women, children, and small farmers at the centre of nutrition actions.</p>
      <p sl="en">At the global level, the Commission will continue advocating further investment in nutrition, notably through the Scaling Up Nutrition movement. We should also explore with the SUN Movement the opportunity to organise a pledging event for nutrition in the coming years.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="124903" name="Bogdan Brunon Wenta" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy PPE. – Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Według danych Organizacji Narodów Zjednoczonych, o czym wspomniał już kolega Guerrero, aktualnie 795 mln ludzi (tzn. 1 na 10 osób) jest niedożywionych. Przewiduje się, że do 2050 r. liczba ta wzrośnie do 2 mld. W świetle stale powiększającej się liczby ludności i jednoczesnym wysokim procencie osób głodujących celowe i konieczne jest wsparcie szczególnie sektora rolniczego i poprawa jego wydajności.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sektor rolniczy to nie tylko dostawca żywności, ale uchodzi także za największego pracodawcę na świecie (dostarcza środków utrzymania ponad 40 % światowej populacji). Zwalczanie ubóstwa i likwidacja głodu, a także wspieranie tej gałęzi gospodarki powinny być celem nadrzędnym Unii Europejskiej, czyli realizacji drugiego punktu celów zrównoważonego rozwoju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głód niesie za sobą szczególnie negatywne konsekwencje dla dzieci, a skutki odczuwalne są nie tylko w skali jednostki, ale i całych społeczeństw, powodując zahamowanie rozwoju osobistego i dalsze negatywne skutki społeczne. Szacunki na rok 2016 wskazują, że w samej tylko Etiopii liczba osób, które będą dotknięte problemem głodu, wzrośnie z 10 do 18 mln, a już teraz jest to około 6 mln dzieci.</p>
      <p sl="en">Działania mające na celu rozwiązanie wskazanych problemów oznaczają także pomoc w walce z innymi zagrożeniami, począwszy od społecznych po migracyjne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mam nadzieję, że w świetle powyższego odpowiedzą Państwo na pytania Komisji Rozwoju i wskażą dalszy kierunek działań na rzecz poprawy omawianej sytuacji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-0000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, le rapporteur spécial des Nations unies sur le droit à l'alimentation, M. Olivier De Schutter, avait souligné le rôle essentiel de l'agriculture en termes de développement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est clair que, dans nos politiques, nous devons être cohérents sur ce point et essayer de faire en sorte que, partout dans le monde, l'agriculture soit source d'autosuffisance alimentaire. Or, aujourd'hui, par nos politiques, nous tournons le dos à cette autosuffisance alimentaire. Dans les accords de partenariat économique que nous signons avec l'Afrique, finalement, nous faisons dépendre les pays africains du business européen, ce qui contrarie leur développement agricole normal. De même, au niveau européen, notre politique agricole commune est peut-être la seule, parmi les grands acteurs de production agricole au monde, qui découple les aides. Ainsi, les aides de la PAC – qui représentent 40 % du budget européen – sont complètement découplées de la réalité économique de l'agriculture.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est donc clair qu'il faut recoupler les aides à la réalité économique. Nous devons veiller à faire preuve de cohérence dans nos divers accords internationaux et faire en sorte que l'agriculture se développe partout dans le monde, surtout dans les zones où les gens ont faim. Je rappelle, en effet, que 70 % des personnes qui souffrent de malnutrition dans le monde sont des paysans des zones rurales.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-0000" speaker_id="25704" name="Ελένη Θεοχάρους" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας ECR. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η εξάλειψη της πείνας και του υποσιτισμού είναι μια μεγαλεπήβολη δέσμευση της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Πρόθεσή μας πρέπει να είναι η επίτευξη της αειφόρου ανάπτυξης εντός του στόχου ΙΙ, αλλά και των συναφών στόχων, οι οποίοι αποσκοπούν στην εξάλειψη τόσο της πείνας όσο και του υποσιτισμού, μέχρι το 2030. Ωστόσο, η σημερινή κατάσταση αποδεικνύει ότι οι μέχρι τώρα πολιτικές μας είναι αναποτελεσματικές και λανθασμένες και διαφωνώ με τα ενθαρρυντικά αποτελέσματα και στοιχεία που αναφέρθηκαν.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι νέοι στόχοι μπορούν να επιτευχθούν κυρίως με την αύξηση της παραγωγικότητας των μικρών καλλιεργειών και ιδιοκτησιών και με τη δημιουργία βιώσιμων συστημάτων γεωργίας και παραγωγής τροφίμων, ικανών να τροφοδοτήσουν ένα συνολικό πληθυσμό που αναμένεται να αγγίξει τα 8,5 δισεκατομμύρια ανθρώπους. Είναι επομένως ιδιαίτερα σημαντικό να πραγματοποιηθούν συντονισμένες δράσεις μεταξύ της παγκόσμιας κοινότητας και των εθνικών και τοπικών αρχών, των μη κυβερνητικών οργανώσεων και του ιδιωτικού τομέα, καθώς και μεταξύ χορηγών για την αντιμετώπιση των λιμών και όλων των μορφών υποσιτισμού, μέσω μιας αυξημένης παραγωγής και μιας πιο αποτελεσματικής διαδικασίας ανάπτυξης της παραγωγικής διατροφικής αλυσίδας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Στη βάση αυτή επίσης, θα πρέπει να λάβει και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση υπόψη ότι απαιτούνται μεγαλύτερη συνοχή και συντονισμός μεταξύ όλων των οργάνων και των φορέων της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και των κρατών μελών. Τα κράτη μέλη πρέπει να εντείνουν, σύμφωνα με τις δεσμεύσεις τους, τις προσπάθειές τους για την παγκόσμια επισιτιστική ασφάλεια και να δώσουν προτεραιότητα στη βιώσιμη γεωργία και στην τοπική παραγωγή τροφίμων, καθώς και στην στήριξη των μικρών καλλιεργητών και των γυναικών αγροτισσών ως παραγωγών τροφίμων. Ταυτοχρόνως, η διεθνής κοινότητα και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση οφείλουν να συνεργαστούν με όλες τις χώρες για να στηρίξουν τη χάραξη και την εφαρμογή ενός ολοκληρωμένου πλαισίου με συγκεκριμένα, εφικτά και ισχυρά εθνικά και υπερεθνικά μέτρα επισιτισμού, στη βάση των στόχων για την αειφόρο ανάπτυξη, προκειμένου να μειωθεί η υπανάπτυξη και ο υποσιτισμός.</p>
      <p sl="en">Όσον αφορά την παραγωγή, θα πρέπει να γίνεται προσεκτική και επιστημονική επιλογή των καλλιεργειών, με εκπαίδευση των αγροτών και με προσαρμογή στις τοπικές κλιματολογικές και εδαφολογικές συνθήκες, αλλά και στις ανάγκες των ντόπιων πληθυσμών. Τέλος, η ανθρωπιστική βοήθεια πρέπει να είναι στοχευμένη, να μην γίνεται αντικείμενο εκμετάλλευσης από διεφθαρμένους φορείς, να αποφεύγεται η σπατάλη και να συμπληρώνεται με στρατηγικές της Επιτροπής που θα συνδέουν την ανθρωπιστική και αναπτυξιακή βοήθεια. Ταυτόχρονα, η Επιτροπή θα πρέπει να αυξήσει τις επενδύσεις ως προς τις ειδικές παρεμβάσεις που σχετίζονται με τη διατροφή, με δεδομένο μάλιστα το σημερινό τεράστιο χάσμα χρηματοδότησης. Τέλος, θέλω να θυμίσω, κύριε Επίτροπε, ότι τεράστιοι ευρωπαϊκοί πληθυσμοί σήμερα λιμοκτονούν.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ALDE. – Gospodine predsjedniče, pogledajmo u kakvom svijetu živimo. S jedne strane u ovom Parlamentu raspravljamo kako zaštititi vrhunske poljoprivredne proizvode EU-a. I ja sudjelujem u toj raspravi i to podržavam. Ali, s druge strane imamo akutnu glad.</p>
      <p sl="en">U Parlamentu često pričamo o činjenici da se hrana u europskim restoranima, supermarketima, trgovinama napretek baca, a s druge strane, dame i gospodo, imamo akutnu glad, koja je prisutna uglavnom i prvenstveno u Africi, ali ne samo na tom kontinentu. Imamo situaciju u kojoj danas stotine milijuna ljudi živi na rubu gladi, na rubu egzistencije. Nažalost, ogromna broj njih, milijuni, su djeca.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ono što je paradoks u cijeloj ovoj priči je to da su često ljudi koji žive uz zemlju, kraj zemlje, na zemlji, oni koji su gladni. Govorim ponovno o Africi. Japan je dao dobar primjer i u nekim afričkim državama krenuo u edukaciju i učenje kako uzgajati rižu. Znam da naša Komisija također radi na edukaciji stanovništva u Africi, kako da sami proizvode hranu, jer uvijek sam bio uvjeren da onome tko je gladan treba pomoći, ali prvenstveno tako da mu daš udicu da može uloviti ribu, a ne da mu daš ribu.</p>
      <p sl="en">I u tom kontekstu, uvjeren sam da i naša politika mora ići u tom pravcu. Pomoći i s ribom, dakle konkretnom pomoći u hrani, ali prvenstveno pomoći u edukaciji i načinu proizvodnje hrane u zemljama u razvoju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127-0000" speaker_id="125035" name="Lola Sánchez Caldentey" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor Presidente, 800 millones de personas en el mundo pasan hambre. Más de tres millones de niños mueren cada año por malnutrición.</p>
      <p sl="en">El hambre en el mundo no es un problema de abastecimiento, sino de pobreza, de ausencia de democracia y de acceso desigual a la tierra y al agua, especialmente para las mujeres. Pero nuestras políticas comerciales y de desarrollo solamente profundizan en este camino, y entonces quiero centrarme en un aspecto concreto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sociedad civil y expertos se han hecho eco de la grave amenaza que supondrían las fusiones previstas entre grandes multinacionales de la alimentación, que acabarían controlando la mayoría de suministros agrícolas del mundo. Implicaría un mayor aumento de precios, la privatización de las investigaciones e índices, por tanto, más altos de pobreza y de hambre. El control corporativo de la alimentación ya está expulsando a los pequeños productores, que producen, en el caso de África, hasta el 80 % de los alimentos que se consumen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desde las instituciones europeas debemos regular un derecho tan elemental como la alimentación, para que no quede en manos de tres gigantes multinacionales que solo persiguen el negocio y la especulación, y no acabar con el hambre. No nos fiemos de ellos, Señorías.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-0000" speaker_id="124848" name="Maria Heubuch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar! Wir alle wissen es und haben es jetzt mehrfach gehört, dass trotz all unserer Bemühungen nach wie vor mehr als 800 Millionen Menschen unterernährt sind und hungern. Weitere Menschen haben richtige Mangelernährung, das heißt, Mineralstoffe, wie zum Beispiel Eisen, Jod und Zink sind in ihrer Nahrung nicht ausreichend vorhanden, was wirklich zu großen Gesundheitsproblemen führt – insbesondere bei Kindern. Und es sterben mehr Kinder an den Folgen von Hunger als an Aids, Malaria und Tuberkulose zusammen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trotz dieser katastrophalen Situationen gibt es zu wenig entwicklungspolitische Intervention, ist der Finanzbedarf nur zu einem Bruchteil gedeckt. Die Zusage der Kommission, hier 3,5 Mrd. EUR in Ernährung zu investieren, kann ich an der Stelle wirklich nur begrüßen. Aber wir wissen auch, dass das nicht ausreicht, um das Nachhaltigkeitsziel 2, den Hunger bis 2030 zu beenden, zu erreichen. Daher fordert das Parlament eine weitere Milliarde. Doch es zählt nicht nur das Geld, es zählt nicht nur wie viel Geld kommt, es zählt auch, wie es ausgegeben wird – entscheidend sind die Maßnahmen, die wir mit diesem Geld in die Hand nehmen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Denn es reicht nicht nur, ausreichend Kalorien zur Verfügung zu stellen, sondern wir brauchen eine vielfältige, gesunde Nahrung, und das bedeutet am Ende: Wir müssen die Nahrung dort produzieren, wo sie auch gebraucht wird. 60 Prozent der Bäuerinnen, Bauern und Fischer dieser Welt müssen hungern. Und 20 weitere Prozent der Hungernden sind Landarbeiter. Daher ist eigentlich das Groteske an dieser Situation –etwas, was mich wirklich sehr bewegt –, dass die Menschen, die eigentlich Nahrung produzieren selbst nicht ausreichend ernährt sind. Sie brauchen Zugang zu Wasser, Land, Werkzeugen, zu angepasstem Saatgut. Und das muss Vorrang haben, Vorrang vor den industriellen Interessen in diesen Regionen. Ich möchte noch einmal darauf hinweisen, dass die Menschen, die in diesen Regionen, wo Nahrungsmittel produziert werden, leben, auch heute Abend wieder hungernd ins Bett gehen müssen – und das mus als Skandal von uns wahrgenommen werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-0000" speaker_id="124941" name="Raymond Finch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Commission may well promote itself as a champion in the field of enhancing nutrition and food security. However, it is clear that tens of millions of taxpayers’ money will again be misused and channelled to the wrong projects with no tracking or real control whatsoever. Besides that, there is the danger that the EU is influencing the political agenda in the governments concerned, causing more instability.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, there is another point that I would like to make. On the one hand, the EU promotes itself as a champion of development, providing poor countries with aid and assistance to deal with food security and food shortages. But, on the other hand, the EU is undermining food security in many parts of the world. Taxpayers in the EU are forced to bear the cost of EU fisheries agreements, which are essentially a tool to allow a few big fishing companies to plunder the waters of poor African coastal nations.</p>
      <p sl="en">People of poor coastal communities rely on fish as an affordable source of protein. Fish is their main source of food and they need it to survive, but we are stealing it from them. The plundering of these fish stocks has led to serious protein deficiencies within these communities. It is threatening food security and causing malnutrition. We can only hope that when we leave the EU, which we will do shortly, we can then promote true food security and sustainability.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, βρισκόμαστε μπροστά σε ένα σημαντικό πρόβλημα που αναμένεται, δυστυχώς, να επιδεινωθεί τα επόμενα χρόνια. Μεγάλο ποσοστό του παγκόσμιου πληθυσμού υποσιτίζεται την ίδια ώρα που μεγάλες ποσότητες τροφίμων, κυρίως στις κοινωνίες της Δύσης, καταλήγουν κάθε χρόνο στα σκουπίδια. Κοινωνικές αδικίες υπήρχαν, υπάρχουν και θα συνεχίσουν να υπάρχουν και στο μέλλον. Οφείλουμε όμως, από τη θέση στην οποία βρισκόμαστε, να καταβάλουμε τις μέγιστες δυνατές προσπάθειες, ώστε να τις αμβλύνουμε τόσο εντός της Ένωσης, όσο και διεθνώς.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η παγκόσμια αγορά τροφίμων - με μεγάλο μερίδιο ευθύνης της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, των κυβερνήσεων των κρατών μελών, αλλά κυρίως της μορφής της παγκόσμιας οικονομίας - δεν αποσκοπεί στην ικανοποίηση των διατροφικών αναγκών παγκοσμίως, αλλά στην επίτευξη του μέγιστου δυνατού κέρδους. Όμως οι άνθρωποι δεν είναι αριθμοί και ισολογισμοί. Η έλλειψη τροφίμων δημιουργεί και άλλα, ανυπολόγιστα προβλήματα που δεν απασχολούν καθόλου τις πολυεθνικές εταιρείες.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πρότασή μας είναι η θέσπιση ενός ορισμένου ποσοστού αυτάρκειας για την Ένωση. Συγκεκριμένο ποσοστό τροφίμων πρέπει να παράγεται αναγκαστικά εντός της Ένωσης, πράγμα που θα ωφελήσει τους Ευρωπαίους παραγωγούς ενώ ταυτόχρονα η παραγωγή τρίτων χωρών θα κατευθύνεται στο εσωτερικό τους, προς όφελος των λαών τους.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="124890" name="Adam Szejnfeld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! W dzisiejszej Europie, szczególnie w jej zachodniej części rozwija się i umacnia się ruch antyglobalizmu. Chcę powiedzieć o tym przy tym temacie, ponieważ jest to niezwykle ważne. Globalizm dzisiaj to jest globalizm demokracji. Globalizm dzisiaj to globalizm praworządności, globalizm równości. Globalizm nowoczesny w XXI w. to jest globalizm edukacji. To jest globalizm społeczeństwa obywatelskiego. W końcu w dzisiejszych czasach globalizm to upowszechnianie dobrobytu na świecie. Ci wszyscy, którzy występują w Europie przeciwko globalizacji, tak de facto – ja rozumiem, że bez świadomości – opowiadają się za upowszechnianiem biedy, za utrzymywaniem biedy. Świat, w którym państwa zamykałyby się tylko w swoich granicach, w którym wspólnoty działałyby tylko w ramach swoich umów, i nie przejmowały się innymi państwami, innymi narodami, to by był świat zdominowany przez biedę. Ten proces globalizacji, który obecnie obserwujemy i który się w sposób pozytywny rozwija, służy ideałom, o których tutaj dzisiaj mówimy. I mam nadzieję, że ci, którzy mają wpływ na życie publiczne w Europie i na całym świecie, to rozumieją. Będziemy poprzez globalizację działać na rzecz zmniejszenia biedy na świecie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I strongly support this report, which underlines the importance of the development of social safety nets. I would like to underline the importance of achieving sustainable development goal 2, which aims to end hunger and malnutrition by 2030, notably by increasing the productivity of smallholders’ farms, and achieving sustainable and climate resilient agriculture and food systems.</p>
      <p sl="en">Currently 159 million children are stunted and 50 million are affected by wasting. Malnutrition has a tremendous impact on their development and health and fuels the cycle of poverty. The level of investment remains inadequate. The Commission Nutrition Action Plan pledged to reduce stunting by 7 million children by 2025 and should honour its commitments, ensuring it addresses all forms of under-nutrition while also filling the huge current funding gap for nutrition—specific interventions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="28389" name="Zbigniew Kuźmiuk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Zabierając głos w tej debacie, chcę przypomnieć, że według danych FAO sprzed zaledwie kilku lat produkcja żywności na świecie powinna wzrosnąć do roku 2030 przynajmniej o 75 %, a to oznacza, że rolnictwo i produkcja żywności powinny być pod szczególną ochroną poszczególnych państw i ich związków takich jak Unia Europejska, która przecież od blisko 50 lat finansuje wspólną politykę rolną. Delegacja polska w grupie EKR, w imieniu której przemawiam, chce oczywiście wesprzeć większość zapisów przygotowywanej rezolucji Parlamentu Europejskiego dotyczącej żywienia i bezpieczeństwa żywnościowego, w tym szczególnie wspieranie małych producentów rolnych, zwalczanie zjawiska zawłaszczania ziemi w krajach rozwijających się czy też sprzeciw wobec tzw. prywatyzacji nasion, co wprost zagraża suwerenności żywnościowej poszczególnych państw. Przy tej okazji chciałbym jednak przypomnieć, że reformy wspólnej polityki rolnej realizowanej przez samą Unię Europejską bardzo często mają na celu ograniczenie produkcji rolnej w Europie. Przy użyciu ogromnych sum idących w miliardy euro finansowane są programy zmniejszania produkcji, na przykład cukru czy ostatnio mleka, co jest przecież sprzeczne z zapewnieniem bezpieczeństwa żywnościowego zarówno w Europie, jak i na świecie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the EU has committed to reducing the number of chronically undernourished children by at least seven million by 2025 with a nutrition action plan. Indeed, progress in hunger reduction has been substantial in spite of the difficult global environment.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proportion of undernourished people in the developing world has dropped from 18 % in the 1990s to 10 % in 2014. However, the path towards the total eradication of hunger will be a long one. If we continue at this tempo, many children, women and those living in poverty will pay the price. That is why more consecrated action is required from us. We need to step up and tackle rising unemployment by creating the conditions for growth. Volatile commodity prices, economic recessions and, primarily, political instability and wars.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nutrition is an investment for our collective future. Here is where the EU has a crucial role, so let’s play it!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="125023" name="Anja Hazekamp" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Over twee weken is het Wereldvoedseldag, maar op 8 augustus hadden we al meer van de aarde gebruikt dan zij ons kan bieden. Voorzitter, in mijn jeugd bestond er nog geen Earth Overshoot Day, maar tegenwoordig groeit er een generatie op die neemt wat ze wil, ook als dat ten koste van anderen gaat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vandaag hebben één miljard mensen overgewicht en bijna één miljard mensen gaan met honger naar bed. Niet omdat er te weinig voedsel is, maar door ons eigen consumptiepatroon en ons eigen landbouwbeleid. We kunnen iedereen voeden als we stoppen met het verspillen van eten. We kunnen iedereen voeden als Brussel niet langer intensivering en overproductie stimuleert. We kunnen iedereen voeden als we kinderen appels geven in plaats van schoolmelk.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, morgen is het Werelddierendag en de Partij voor de Dieren vraagt u om ook eens stil te staan bij de 7 miljard dieren in onze vee-industrie, want we kunnen honger bestrijden en deze dieren een lange lijdensweg besparen door te stoppen met het verspillen van voedsel aan veevoer. Voorts ben ik van mening dat de Europese landbouwsubsidies moeten worden afgeschaft.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-0000" speaker_id="124942" name="Molly Scott Cato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, ending hunger by 2030 is not about increasing production of commodities for global markets; rather we need to put nutrition, health and food security at the core of agricultural policy. We need a fundamental shift towards agro-ecology so that countries can feed themselves with a diversity of crops while addressing climate and poverty challenges. Support to family farmers and smallholders is key.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EuroLat Assembly, of which I am a member, is debating a resolution on food security, recommending measures such as food reserves which governments can use to mitigate short term price fluctuations. In the EU, the Commission has a role in reducing volatility by ensuring that robust position limits are put in place to curb food speculation, as citizens rightly expect from the MiFID 2 Agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">The right to food also depends on access to land, yet inconsistencies in EU sectoral policies are inhibiting this. Current policies towards biofuels and many liberalising trade and investment agreements are jeopardising food security, contributing directly or indirectly to land grabbing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il nostro obiettivo dichiarato e conclamato è quello di porre fine alla fame e alla malnutrizione nel mondo entro il 2030. Domani ce lo ricorderà probabilmente il Segretario generale delle Nazioni Unite Ban Ki-moon con la sua presenza qui a Strasburgo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Purtroppo, però, l'obiettivo dichiarato sembra davvero fuori portata. Signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, convenite con me che oggi ci troviamo in netto ritardo rispetto a questo obiettivo? Non credete che, continuando con questo passo, non ce la potremo mai fare a raggiungerlo? È assurdo che ancora oggi si debba assistere al puntuale e quotidiano sfruttamento di persone e suoli da parte di interessi privati per il proprio esclusivo tornaconto, senza alcun riguardo per la vita altrui. Vanno aumentati i nostri sforzi sulle tematiche legate all'alimentazione e alla sicurezza alimentare globale. Dobbiamo seriamente impegnarci per rilanciare e sostenere i piccoli produttori agricoli e la produzione alimentare locale, per sviluppare politiche agricole che siano efficaci e resilienti, per assicurare l'accesso alla terra e arrestare una volta per tutte il land grabbing.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se vogliamo provare a raggiungere l'obiettivo, la strada è quella di garantire la sovranità alimentare a coloro che ne dovrebbero essere i principali beneficiari, ossia le popolazioni locali. Per tutto questo, con tali obiettivi saldi in mente, oggi invitiamo la Commissione e l'intera Unione europea a prendere nuovamente in esame la questione e a interrogarsi sull'efficacia delle proprie azioni, per prendere in considerazione un intervento diverso, basato sulla trasparenza e sulla tutela delle popolazioni locali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="124991" name="Jytte Guteland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Vi lever i en paradoxernas tid. Det har påtalats här i kväll, men det är sjukt hur det ser ut. Å ena sidan har vi det här parlamentet som kan tala om hur vi ska minska matsvinnet. Å andra sidan har vi nära 800 miljoner människor som lider av att få för lite mat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi lever i en tid när vi med blixtens hastighet kan få reda på att människor riskerar svält – jag tänker på El Niño i våras. Samtidigt tar det månader innan omvärlden samlas för att kunna stödja och hjälpa de utsatta. Jag ser fortfarande framför mig de hungrande barnen och de trötta blickarna från barnen som inte orkar leka längre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jag stöder nu uppmaningarna till kommissionen att tydligare ta en ledarroll när det gäller en tryggad livsmedelssäkerhet – där är samordning och långsiktighet en nyckel – och vill också att kommissionen svarar på vad man gör för de El Niño-drabbade områdena.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139-0000" speaker_id="132366" name="Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, maailman väestömäärän on ennustettu kasvavan vuoteen 2050 mennessä 9,5 miljardiin. Niinpä ruuan saamisen turvaaminen kaikille maailman ihmisille onkin oltava ykkösprioriteetti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mielestäni on ensisijaisen tärkeää, että ravinnon laatua korostetaan enemmän kuin pelkkiä tyhjiä kaloreita. Tällä hetkellä ruokaa tuotetaan määrällisesti paljon, mutta esimerkiksi nykyisistä pääviljoista, kuten maissista, vehnästä ja riisistä, saatavat kalorit eivät pidä sisällään tarpeeksi välttämättömiä hivenaineita. Maailman köyhimmät kansalaiset ovat usein riippuvaisia juuri siitä pääviljasta, jota kyseisessä maassa tuotetaan. Siksi onkin tärkeää, että tulevaisuudessa kehitystä ohjataan siihen suuntaan, että tämä päävilja olisi aikaisempaa useammin ravintopitoinen kaura, ohra, ruis, hirssi ja durra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tällä hetkellä jopa kaksi miljardia ihmistä kärsii raudan puutteesta ja viidennes maapallon väestöstä elää sinkin puutteessa. On esitetty arvioita, joiden mukaan noin 170 miljoonaa lasta kärsii ravinteiden puutteesta ja siitä johtuvasta kasvun hidastumisesta, joten viljelykasvien ravintopitoisuuden tärkeyttä ei voida korostaa liikaa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kasvisruokaan liittyviä innovaatioita tulisikin edistää entistä enemmän. Suomessa kehitetty nyhtökaura ja härkäpapuvalmiste ovat esimerkkejä tulevaisuuden kestävistä ratkaisuista.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="124818" name="Klaus Buchner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Der Hunger in den ärmsten Staaten entsteht ganz wesentlich auch durch unsere Handelspolitik. Wir drängen die afrikanischen Staaten in Handelsabkommen, die uns erlauben, ihre Küsten leer zu fischen. Wir verlangen den unbeschränkten Zugang zu ihren Märkten, wo wir unsere hochsubventionierten landwirtschaftlichen Produkte absetzen. In vielen Bereichen können die einheimischen Bauern, die nicht subventioniert werden, mit unseren Preisen einfach nicht mehr mithalten. Wir drängen sie dazu, für den Export zu arbeiten, Kakao, Kaffee, Obst, Südfrüchte, Blumen anzubauen. Das Problem dabei ist nur, dass den Handel nach Europa, nach USA meistens eine einzige, manchmal zwei Handelsfirmen machen, die die Preise drücken, die den Bauern so wenig geben, dass sie davon nicht leben und nicht sterben können. Wir produzieren den Hunger. So ist unsere Handelspolitik, die Handelspolitik der EU, schlimmer als das, was früher, vor 100 Jahren, in der Kolonialpolitik passiert ist.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="96891" name="Paolo De Castro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, l'instabilità dei mercati delle materie prime agricole, la crescita demografica e il cambiamento delle diete a livello globale, i vincoli ambientali alla produzione di cibo e le conseguenze del cambiamento climatico sono tutti elementi che compongono uno scenario di nuova scarsità. In questo scenario l'agricoltura è chiamata a ricoprire un ruolo di primissimo piano nella sempre più pressante sfida globale dell'accesso al cibo, non solo da una prospettiva produttiva, ma anche per la capacità di generare occupazione e stabilità nelle aree più marginalizzate del pianeta. Un ruolo riconosciuto dalle stesse Nazioni Unite che pongono il tema della sicurezza alimentare al centro degli Obiettivi di sviluppo sostenibile dell'Agenda 2030.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signor Commissario, la questione è globale e come tale va affrontata. Occorre quindi una vera Global Food Policy e l'Europa deve assumere un ruolo di protagonismo che finora ha purtroppo solo annunciato, un protagonismo nella definizione di misure di sviluppo inclusive e innovative che garantiscano coesione sociale e territoriale, coinvolgendo i gruppi fin qui considerati più vulnerabili nei processi decisionali e di governance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, ανάμεσα στους στόχους και τις δεσμεύσεις της Ένωσης για την επισιτιστική ασφάλεια στον πλανήτη βρίσκουμε την εξάλειψη της πείνας και της κακής διατροφής μέχρι το 2030, μέσω της αύξησης της παραγωγικότητας των μικρών εκμεταλλεύσεων και της επίτευξης βιώσιμων στην κλιματική αλλαγή επισιτιστικών συστημάτων. Στο πλαίσιο του στόχου αυτού περιλαμβάνεται και η μείωση του αριθμού των καχεκτικών ατόμων κατά 7 εκατομμύρια παγκοσμίως έως το 2025, με την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση να έχει δεσμευτεί ότι θα διαθέσει 3,5 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ την περίοδο 2014-2020 για τον σκοπό αυτό. Το 2014 βεβαίως διατέθηκε για τις παρεμβάσεις που είχαν στόχο την εξάλειψη του παγκόσμιου υποσιτισμού μόνο το 0,57% της συνολικής επίσημης αναπτυξιακής βοήθειας. Δεδομένου ότι 159 εκατομμύρια παιδιά είναι καχεκτικά και 50 εκατομμύρια πάσχουν από ατροφία, καθίσταται σαφές ότι θα πρέπει να αναληφθεί άμεσα δράση από την Ένωση υπέρ της επισιτιστικής ασφάλειας, καθώς και ότι θα πρέπει να χρησιμοποιηθεί το σύνολο της επίσημης αναπτυξιακής βοήθειας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Επιπλέον, η επισιτιστική ασφάλεια στον πλανήτη σχετίζεται με τη χρήση ασφαλούς τροφής, κάτι που σημαίνει ότι θα πρέπει να χτυπηθούν τα μεταλλαγμένα και να ενισχυθεί η βιολογική καλλιέργεια και η βιολογική κτηνοτροφία. Πώς όμως μπορεί να γίνει αυτό, κύριε Επίτροπε, όταν στην Ελλάδα την τελευταία πενταετία οι εκτροφείς βιολογικής κτηνοτροφίας δεν έχουν πάρει τις ενισχύσεις που δικαιούνται από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση; Το ίδιο ισχύει, κύριε Επίτροπε, και για τους κτηνοτρόφους που στηρίζουν τη διατήρηση των απειλούμενων φυλών αγροτικών ζώων. Επίσης περιμένουν ακόμη τις επιδοτήσεις. Τι πρόκειται λοιπόν να γίνει, κύριε Επίτροπε; Τι θα κάνετε προκειμένου οι Έλληνες κτηνοτρόφοι να πληρωθούν τις επιδοτήσεις τους;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, ahogy itt több képviselő – köztük legutóbb De Castro kolléga is – említette, egy globális élelmiszerpolitikára van szükség. És amennyiben a glóbuszt, a Föld egészét úgy értelmezzük, hogy annak Európa is része, akkor bizony azt kell mondjam, hogy idehaza, az európai kontinensen is bőven van tennivaló. Valószínűleg a sokak által szóvá tett különböző botladozásoknak az az oka, hogy hazai terepen, azaz az Európai Unión belül kevés tapasztalatot szereztünk, márpedig itt is nagyon súlyos problémák vannak. Elnök úr, elmondanám, hogy Európa keleti felén – köztük a saját hazámban, Magyarországon – a lakosság 2%-a effektív alultáplált és éhezik. Ezeknek a döntő többsége persze gyermek, mindennek a tetejébe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ha ezeknek az élelmezésével is foglalkoznánk, akkor lehet, hogy sokkal könnyebben tudnánk érvényesülni a nemzetközi porondon. De nemcsak erről van szó, hanem arról is, hogy mindaddig, amíg az Európai Unióban nem lesz egységes adópolitika az élelmiszerek tekintetében, addig az lesz, hogy Magyarországon 27% az ÁFA az élelmiszereken, máshol meg nulla.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-0000" speaker_id="124804" name="Elly Schlein" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, oggi circa 800 milioni di persone, la maggior parte in zone rurali, soffrono ancora la fame e più di 2 miliardi sono malnutrite. Con i nuovi Obiettivi di sviluppo sostenibile ci siamo impegnati non solo a porre fine alla fame cronica, ma anche a lavorare per una maggiore sicurezza alimentare e a combattere la malnutrizione perché, una volta soddisfatto il bisogno di cibo, è alla qualità e alla varietà della dieta che bisogna guardare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per farlo la FAO ci dice che avremmo bisogno di 267 miliardi di dollari l'anno per investimenti. Si tratterebbe solo dello 0,3 % del PIL mondiale per diversificare le culture, investire seriamente nelle popolazioni rurali, in particolare sui piccoli produttori agricoli, e promuovere un'agricoltura sostenibile. Se non vogliamo che i nuovi SDG rimangano sulla carta, servono più risorse – questo stiamo chiedendo – e serve anche un framework europeo per l'implementazione degli SDG.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il coordinamento tra Commissione e Stati membri su questo è essenziale, perché sono obiettivi universali, e chiedo al Commissario quando avremo finalmente questo framework europeo sull'implementazione dei nuovi Obiettivi di sviluppo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-145-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to focus specifically on women and girls, who suffer more nutritional deficiencies than men for reasons such as women’s reproductive biology, low social status, poverty and lack of education. Although malnutrition’s effects on this group have been recognised for decades, there has been little measurable progress in addressing the specific nutritional problems of women and adolescent girls. Addressing women’s malnutrition has a range of positive effects because healthy women can fulfil their multiple roles more effectively, thereby helping to advance their country’s socio-economic development. Secondly, more consideration should be given to the power of civil society and people—to—people initiatives in making real differences in their communities, such as the World Vision Gicumbi Child Nutrition Centre that I recently visited in Rwanda.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I want to emphasise the role that education and intercultural dialogue plays as a key tool in development, emphasising and transforming mindsets and addressing key causes of under—nutrition. Fighting against malnutrition requires access to education.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">V tej dvorani velikokrat govorimo o človekovih pravicah in zagotovo je pravica do hrane, do kvalitetne, zdrave hrane osnovna človekova pravica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato zelo podpiram vse programe, ki jih izvaja Evropska unija, tako v obliki humanitarne pomoči kakor tudi v obliki razvojen pomoči.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mislim, da je prišel čas, da pri razvojni pomoči resnično osredotočimo to razvojno pomoč Evropske unije v to, da v deželah, kjer je največje pomanjkanje hrane, se pravi v Afriki največ, pomagamo razviti malo kmetijstvo, kmetijstvo, ki je na neki način osnova za to, da bodo ljudje prvič, prišli do hrane, drugič, da bodo tudi razvili delovna mesta. Izobrazba, izmenjava izkušenj, in tu mislim, da lahko Evropa zelo veliko naredi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kajti, če bomo uspešni na tem problemu, na problemu prehranske varnosti, bomo delno rešili tudi velik problem migracij, s katerim se bomo v svetovnem formatu soočili tudi v prihodnje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'obiettivo di sviluppo sostenibile dell'agenda ONU mira a porre fine alla fame nel mondo entro il 2030 attraverso un aumento della produttività dei piccoli coltivatori e l'incentivo dell'agricoltura sostenibile. Tuttavia, occorre prendere atto del fatto che limitarsi a garantire una maggiore produzione e una più grande disponibilità di prodotti alimentari non è sufficiente a risolvere il problema.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gli ultimi dati disponibili ci dicono che oltre 159 milioni di bambini nel mondo soffrono di ritardo nella crescita. Alla luce di ciò, occorre implementare l'attuazione delle politiche europee elaborate dal piano di azione della Commissione sulla nutrizione. La sicurezza alimentare e nutrizionale necessita di una costante attenzione a livello strategico, oltre che di sostegno agli investimenti, specie nelle aree rurali. L'elaborazione e la programmazione delle politiche devono tener conto dei legami tra nutrizione, salute e creazione di occupazione, crescita e produzione sostenibile. Occorre che l'Unione europea lavori strategicamente per determinare le condizioni per contrastare lo spreco alimentare e per favorire lo sviluppo di un'agricoltura sostenibile e di qualità, con particolare riferimento al sostegno delle piccole e piccolissime aziende agricole.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a persistência da fome, a persistência de milhões de casos de subnutrição crónica no mundo, numa altura em que o desenvolvimento científico e tecnológico atinge níveis que poderiam facilmente permitir erradicar este fenómeno é um dos mais vivos libelos acusatórios que pesa sobre o sistema capitalista largamente dominante à escala mundial.</p>
      <p sl="en">As razões da fome são políticas, antes de mais. Não por acaso assistimos a um recrudescer do fenómeno mesmo em países normalmente incluídos no lote de países ditos “desenvolvidos”. Olhemos, por exemplo, aos efeitos devastadores dos programas da União Europeia e do FMI. O livre comércio que arruína a pequena agricultura, a agricultura familiar e a soberania alimentar de nações inteiras, a usurpação de terras, o monopólio das transnacionais do agronegócio sobre sementes e outros fatores de produção, o desmantelamento de infraestruturas e serviços públicos e o ataque às funções sociais dos estados estão entre as causas incontornáveis da fome, e um genuíno esforço de combate à fome deve, obrigatoriamente, ter em conta a necessidade de combater as suas causas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this is a very important topic, and again I think it shows the genuine commitment of the European Union to helping all peoples in the world. It is a commitment that is genuine and sincere and to which we give a lot of support and for which we get very little credit, not to mention publicity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nevertheless, it is work that needs to be done, because when millions and millions of people around the world – especially children – are dying of malnutrition on the one hand, and then in our own first-world many of them are suffering from obesity, there is a reconciliation there that needs to be done, which will not be easy.</p>
      <p sl="en">One area that I would like to see much more emphasis placed on is the whole area of research and development – especially research. With climate change, some places are getting warmer and drier while other places are getting wetter and colder. Crops need to adjust, and I think we need to do a lot more research in that regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Neven Mimica" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, if we want to achieve the sustainable development goals we must pursue our efforts to eradicate undernutrition. The Commission spent almost EUR 500 million per year on nutrition interventions, representing 3.1% of its development aid in 2014.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union is also addressing undernutrition through its humanitarian assistance. We had EUR 700 million spent between 2011 and 2015. But we all must do more.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will continue keeping our development policy focus on nutrition and food security issues, as well as advocating further investment in nutrition by other donors and partner countries. We will explore with a strong movement the possible Pledging Conference on Nutrition. We will continue also to explore other interventions, such as the social safety nets, as well as reflecting on the balance between nutrition-sensitive and nutrition-specific interventions. We will continue to coordinate with donors who focus on nutrition-specific interventions, as well as maximising the synergies and complementarities of our development and humanitarian responses.</p>
      <p sl="en">This development humanitarian collaboration has been further confirmed by the Commission’s response to the food crisis generated by El Niño climate change phenomenon. The Commission allocated an additional EUR 543 million this year, almost equally shared between humanitarian and development interventions. This is coherent with the resilience approach, which aims at meeting the more immediate needs of populations in food crisis while addressing the root causes of partner countries’ fragility and vulnerability.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am confident that the proposed resolution on nutrition of the European Parliament, the Nutrition Action Plan of the Commission and the Council conclusions on nutrition can help the European Union improve nutrition and make undernutrition history, as foreseen in sustainable development goals agenda by 2030.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Otrzymałem jeden projekt rezolucji złożony zgodnie z art. 128 ust. 5 Regulaminu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się w środę 5 października 2016 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0500" speaker_id="124766" name="Petras Auštrevičius" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Hunger and malnutrition are the epicentre of one of the biggest issues we have to fight today. One in six children are underweight for their age and even though since 1990 the amount of people being effected by malnutrition has halved, there are still millions of people not receiving enough food and water. The percentage of development assistance dedicated to malnutrition should be increased and coupled with long-term goals for prevention of hunger. More specifically, we should pay more attention to small farmers, who at this moment produce around 70% of the world’s food. Increasing their potential yield and diversifying the seeds being grown gives the surrounding area not only short-term assistance but also the tools to combat malnutrition in the long run. In addition, toddlers and new-born babies are severely affected by malnutrition; this is impacted by the fact that breastfeeding is still not fully recognised as an acceptable and culturally—decent practice in many places. The EP report tackles this issue by calling on the EU for a worldwide campaign highlighting the importance of breastfeeding and its necessity for a growing baby.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0000" speaker_id="124887" name="Karol Karski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Bezpieczeństwo żywnościowe, oprócz bezpieczeństwa energetycznego i bezpieczeństwa obronnego, jest najważniejszym z globalnych wyzwań współczesnego świata. Związane jest to przede wszystkim ze stale rosnącą liczbą ludności, oczekuje się, że do 2030 r. wzrośnie ona aż do 8,5 mld., a ponadto według prognoz FAO (Światowej Organizacji do spraw Wyżywienia i Rolnictwa) do 2050 r. zapotrzebowanie na żywność wzrośnie o 70 %. Wyżywienie ludności stanie się głównym problemem świata i z tego powodu obserwujemy nasilony wzrost zawłaszczania ziemi w krajach rozwijających się i nie tylko. Wzywam Komisję do podjęcia konkretnych środków w celu przeciwdziałania zawłaszczaniu gruntów rolnych oraz do opracowania planu działania na rzecz zwalczania masowego wykupu gruntów i zapewnienia skutecznego wdrożenia wytycznych FAO w zakresie własności.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0500" speaker_id="33989" name="Daciana Octavia Sârbu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – De decenii vorbim despre malnutriție și despre foamete, însă, în ciuda ajutorului de dezvoltare alocat statelor subsahariene, malnutriția și foametea încă există. Din păcate, chiar dacă planul de acțiune al Comisiei pentru nutriție s-a angajat să reducă numărul cazurilor de retard de creștere în rândul copiilor cu 7 milioane până în 2025, dintr-un angajament total de 3,5 miliarde doar 400 de milioane sunt alocate măsurilor specifice nutriției. În 2012, Adunarea Mondială a Sănătății a aprobat un set de șase obiective globale în materie de nutriție pentru 2025, inclusiv obiectivul de a reduce cu 40 % numărul de cazuri de retard de creștere în rândul copiilor cu vârsta sub cinci ani. Totuși, investițiile în nutriție sunt în continuare insuficiente. Comisia Europeană ar trebui să mărească ajutorul pentru nutriție și să sprijine dezvoltarea sectorului agricol în țările care se confruntă cu foamete.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Amendment of the agenda : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Tackling illegal logging, deforestation and forest degradation (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-158-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest debata nad pytaniem wymagającym odpowiedzi ustnej skierowanym do Komisji przez Lindę McAvan w imieniu Komisji Rozwoju, Giovanniego La Vię w imieniu Komisji Ochrony Środowiska Naturalnego, Zdrowia Publicznego i Bezpieczeństwa Żywności, Bernda Lange w imieniu Komisji Handlu Międzynarodowego, Czesława Adama Siekierskiego w imieniu Komisji Rolnictwa i Rozwoju Wsi oraz Jerzego Buzka w imieniu Komisji Przemysłu, Badań Naukowych i Energii w sprawie przeciwdziałania nielegalnemu wyrębowi, wylesianiu i degradacji lasów – program działań UE (O-000112/2016 - B8-0720/2016) (2016/2824(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-0000" speaker_id="2128" name="Paavo Väyrynen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in 2003 the European Union took action against illegal logging and trade in illegally—logged tree timber by adopting the FLEGT Action Plan, the central element of which is the system of voluntary partnership agreements signed between the EU and timber—producing countries in Africa, Asia and Latin America.</p>
      <p sl="en">In 2015, the European Court of Auditors issued a special report identifying gaps in FLEGT implementation and enforcement. The Court found that EU support to timber—producing countries was not sufficiently effective and targeted and called for an appropriate work plan with clear objectives, milestones and a dedicated budget. The Court also found that monitoring and reporting on progress had been inadequate, in particular due to the lack of an accountability framework.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has recently issued an evaluation of the FLEGT Action Plan, 12 years after its entry into force. Given this context, five committees asked the Commission to answer the following questions. First, how will the Commission concretely respond to the European Court of Auditors recommendations in its Special Report No 13/2015? Will additional resources be mobilised to respond to implementation challenges and will specific monitoring and evaluation mechanisms be developed to strengthen implementation of the EU Action Plan on Forest Law Enforcement, Governance and Trade? What is the Commission strategy to revive the political momentum for FLEGT in voluntary partnership agreement countries and to accelerate the governance reforms that are necessary for the issuance of FLEGT licences? Thirdly, how is the Commission ensuring coherence and synergies between climate mitigation policies and FLEGT, especially on governance aspects?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="1403" name="David Martin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am speaking on behalf of Bernd Lange, who cannot be here this evening. Illegal logging and trade in illegal timber has a devastating impact on the world’s forests, threatening the survival of various wildlife species and contributing to climate change. Regrettably, we have not managed to reverse global deforestation, even though illegal timber imports to the EU have declined. This signals the urgent need to step up our efforts. The Committee on International Trade is a lead committee for FLEGT, the voluntary partnership agreements that are signed under the FLEGT Regulation between the EU and timber-producing countries, and that should address the supply side of the problem.</p>
      <p sl="en">I note with satisfaction that Indonesia will be the first country to start issuing FLEGT licenses this autumn, and the whole process has contributed to strengthened forest governance through an inclusive multi-stakeholder approach. Today, over 90% of Indonesia’s timber exports are from independently—audited factories and forests, compared to just 20% in 2002. It is an important milestone, especially as one third by value of the EU’s tropical timber imports come from Indonesia.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to hear from the Commission how they are going to step up and accelerate the process in other Voluntary Partnership Agreement countries (VPAs). Could the Commission indicate which VPA countries, in addition to Indonesia, are closest to signing FLEGT licenses, and – as we have just heard, this is especially relevant in light of the Court of Auditors recommendation – notably that resources should be allocated to where they are likely to have the greatest impact in tackling illegal logging and related trade? In cases where implementation of the VPA requirements appears less feasible, would the Commission agree to propose measures supporting forest governance without necessarily signing a VPA?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karmenu Vella" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have to start by saying and reconfirming that the EU is strongly committed to the fight against illegal logging and the associated trade. The FLEGT Action Plan has built an effective global coalition against it, tackling both the supply and demand sides through trade measures, through development cooperation and through broad stakeholder engagement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our action plan tackles some of the real drivers of deforestation and forest degradation. But deforestation continues and its consequences are potentially catastrophic at many levels – for the local communities that depend on forests, for the ecosystems that they support and at the global level as we deplete one of the most effective carbon sinks that we have.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must continue this fight both through our own actions and in the new global dynamic of the 2030 Agenda and the Paris Agreement. The honourable Members are right to raise their concerns, and I welcome the interest of the Parliament in the follow-up to the European Court of Auditors report. FLEGT has been the subject of two reviews in the past two years. EU support to timber production countries under FLEGT was reviewed by the European Court of Auditors, while the overall performance of the action plan was also independently evaluated.</p>
      <p sl="en">A basic finding is that FLEGT remains highly relevant and that the work carried out so far under the action plan is delivering significant results. Forest governance has improved, particularly in targeted countries, while demand for illegal timber in the EU has been reduced. The design of FLEGT has also been found to be future proof.</p>
      <p sl="en">That being said, things have changed since the inception of the action plan. Imports of tropical timber in the EU have fallen, whilst China has become the world’s largest market and global political attention has shifted to other drivers of deforestation such as the competition for land and to other drivers of climate change. The evaluation stressed that such changes may have an impact on the relevance of the action plan if not sufficiently addressed. That is why the Commission has been considering opportunities to scale up efforts to combat deforestation through FLEGT but also through other instruments such as REDD+ and the EU timber regulation.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have now commissioned a study to consider the feasibility of a comprehensive EU action plan on deforestation. The review of the Court and of the independent evaluation have highlighted important implementation challenges and areas for improvement in the way the FLEGT Action Plan has been managed, particularly in relation to the support to the countries concerned, and have recommended adjustments.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are working to address these findings to a multiannual work plan with clear objectives, targets, timeframes and budget. This will redefine priorities geographically and thematically and will ensure more effective monitoring of progress, achievements and impact. FLEGT is our flagship priority under the Global Public Goods and Challenges Programme of the European Development Cooperation Instrument, but we should remember that the action plan is a joint initiative. It must draw on the combined strengths and capacities of the EU and of its Member States. According to the evaluation, stronger commitment and more active support by more Member States is needed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the honourable Members also asked about voluntary partnership agreements (VPAs). As mentioned by Paavo Väyrynen, VPAs are a central FLEGT element, and the Commission has invested intensely in their negotiation and implementation through political dialogue, through stakeholder engagement and through capacity building.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our colleague David Martin also mentioned Indonesia and yes, soon we will be launching Indonesia’s FLEGT licensing, and hopefully Ghana will follow soon after, hopefully next year. These efforts are yielding good results in those countries where there is willingness to implement the necessary reforms. The difficulty of putting in place these reforms should not be underestimated. There are often strong vested interests, benefiting from the status quo.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will, of course, continue to make all possible efforts to maintain political momentum in VPAs and address the challenges with our partner countries.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-0000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">v imenu skupine PPE. – Najlepša hvala najprej kolegoma za postavitev tega zelo pomembnega vprašanja in seveda tudi vam, komisar Vella, za odgovore, ki ste nam jih podali na začetku te točke.</p>
      <p sl="en">Evropska unija se zaveda pomena ekosistema gozda, zato se že vse od devetdesetih let ukvarja s problemom nezakonitega krčenja, trgovine s tem lesom in, kot ste dejali, se tudi skozi teh, sedaj že 25 let, stvari bistveno spreminjajo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ne vem, Kitajska se pojavlja sedaj kot največji kupec, v vmesnem času je tudi Evropska unija namenila in to, kar je pregledalo tudi Evropsko sodišče, kar 300 milijonov evrov sredstev v to, da se to gospodarjenje z gozdovi po svetu izboljša in da se tudi na osnovi teh ugotovitev, pa tudi skupnih priporočil izboljša gospodarjenje z gozdovi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poleg velike biotske raznovrstnosti, ki je eden od ključnih problemov ob okoljski škodi, je zagotovo tudi velik problem tega področja, področje korupcije in pa pravzaprav nedelovanje držav od koder prihajamo. Zato je na neki način tudi manjše razočaranje to, da imamo podpisanih le nekaj, se pravi sporazum z Indonezijo in pa nekaj sporazumov z afriškimi državami.</p>
      <p sl="en">Želim vam v tem delu veliko uspeha, kajti, kot sem že dejal tudi sam, zelo podpiram, da se ta problematika reši. Ti problemi, hočemo ali nočemo, slejkoprej pridejo tudi na naše domove.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naj samo povem lastno izkušnjo iz Slovenije izpred dobrih dveh let, ko smo pozimi leta 2004 po velikem žledu imeli veliko škodo, se pravi klimatske spremembe, povzročajo različne pojave, veliko škodo, ko je skoraj polovica slovenskega gozda bilo kovanega v led in kot posledica, dve leti po tistem, čutimo pa tudi po zelo vročem letu velike posledice s podlubniki, ki uničujejo sedaj smrekov gozd.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tako, da problem, o katerem govorimo, na prvi pogled zgleda, da je zelo daleč od nas, posledice pa zelo hitro čutimo tudi na lastnih tleh. Zato podpiram ta prizadevanja, v tej smeri, kot ste jih omenili, tu pri tej točki.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-0000" speaker_id="124787" name="Renata Briano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo S&amp;D. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ringrazio il Commissario Vella per gli impegni e le risposte. Ci sono paesi in cui il tasso di disboscamento illegale raggiunge il 90 %, implicando forme di corruzione in tutta la filiera di abbattimento, trasporto e vendita. Gli obiettivi posti nell'Action Plan sono ancora ostacolati da una moltitudine di fattori, tra cui la resistenza al cambiamento del settore forestale, il ritardo nell'applicazione del regolamento europeo, l'importanza di altri mercati come Cina e India, nonché il boom delle materie prime agricole la cui produzione occupa superficie forestale.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'agricoltura estensiva gioca un ruolo chiave nel processo di deforestazione, se pensiamo che dal 2000 circa la metà della foresta tropicale è stata convertita in terreno agricolo o per piantagioni monocultura, spesso contro il volere delle popolazioni autoctone, come è il caso dell'olio di palma in Indonesia, in Liberia e in Ecuador. Si stima che oggi l'80 % della deforestazione globale è causato dall'agricoltura e con l'importazione di prodotti come olio di palma, manzo, cuoio, soia, gomma, cacao e legname anche l'Unione europea è attore di questo problema.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non si possono sottostimare inoltre i danni ambientali legati alla deforestazione. In aggiunta alla gravissima perdita di biodiversità, la deforestazione è una delle principali cause di dissesto idrogeologico e provoca alluvioni e frane. Bisogna quindi che l'UE dimostri e continui a dimostrare un forte impegno politico per l'efficace attuazione dei Voluntary Partnership Agreement, per rafforzarne l'impatto, per assicurare l'attuazione efficace del regolamento sul legname e per adottare ulteriori misure per sostenere la tutela e il recupero degli ecosistemi forestali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ECR. – Poštovani predsjedniče, pitanje nezakonite sječe, deforestacije i degradacije šuma od posebnog je značaja za moju domovinu Hrvatsku jer je gotovo polovica njezina teritorija prekrivena šumama. Posljednjih je nekoliko godina sve izraženije djelovanje tzv. „šumske mafije“ koja godišnje ukrade na tisuće kubika drvne mase, bilo da je riječ o drvu za ogrjev ili skupim hrastovim i bukovim trupcima kojima nezakonito opskrbljuju drvno-prerađivačku industriju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Problem je posebno izražen u privatnim šumama čiji vlasnici ne žive na svom posjedu i gdje nisu sređeni imovinsko-pravni odnosi, no ne zaobilazi ni državne šume. Lopovi su dobro organizirani i umreženi, državni šumari ne mogu učinkovito patrolirati i sprječavati krađe na tolikom prostoru, a policija lopovima teško ulazi u trag.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ako doista želimo zaštititi šume, država mora učinkovitije upravljati onima u svom vlasništvu, a vlasnike privatnih šuma trebamo poticati na osnivanje udruga privatnih šumoposjednika i uvođenje sustava zajedničkog nadzora koji bi uključivao stalnu razmjenu informacija s državnim šumarijama i policijom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za zemlje poput Hrvatske drvo je u svakom smislu strateški resurs i ne smijemo dozvoliti da ga bilo tko nezakonito prisvaja te svojim razbojništvom ugrožava budućnost naših šuma, njihovog ekosustava i budućnost naše djece.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-0000" speaker_id="124862" name="Ulrike Müller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ALDE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Ich begrüße die Aussprache hier im Plenum über den FLEGT-Aktionsplan ganz besonders. Ein weltweit nachhaltiger Einschlag und Handel von Holz ist die Grundlage für eine funktionierende Holzwirtschaft. Mir persönlich ist es besonders wichtig, sorgsam mit unserer Ressource umzugehen und unsere Märkte zu schützen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der illegale Holzeinschlag beschäftigt uns schon lange. Hier ein paar Fakten: Es werden ungefähr 20 bis 40 % der globalen Holzproduktion illegal geschlagen. Der wirtschaftliche Schaden beträgt durch entgangene Einnahmen im Bereich des Staates, der Kommunen, der Industrie, aber auch der privaten Waldbesitzer etwa 15 Milliarden Dollar. Weltweit wird dadurch der Holzpreis ungefähr um 10 % gedrückt. Ungefähr 16 % der Holzimporte in die Europäische Union stammen aus illegalem Holzeinschlag, und die Weltbank spricht sogar von organisiertem Verbrechen, das mit schärferen Gesetzen bekämpft werden muss. Wir können also hier nicht weiter zusehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Heute bewerten wir den Aktionsplan FLEGT. Mit ihm sollten die Probleme angegangen und gelöst werden. Kernstück des Aktionsplans sind bilaterale Abkommen zwischen Europa und den Holz exportierenden Ländern. Trotz aller Bemühungen, hier verantwortungsvolle Rechtsstaatlichkeit zu schaffen, werden weiter Regenwälder gerodet und Artenvielfalt zerstört. Unsere Vorsorgemaßnahmen haben bisher kaum Erfolg. Wir brauchen Aktionen gegen die Hintermänner des Handels. Greifen wir also die wichtigsten Punkte vom Rechnungshof auf! Ich fordere Sie hier dazu auf, bitte auch eine klare Strategie zu beschreiten, kohärente Arbeitspläne, Prioritäten, Zeitpläne und Etappenziele zu erklären und aus diesem zahnlosen Tiger endlich ein Regelwerk zu schaffen, das europaweit in allen Staaten gleich umgesetzt wird.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-0000" speaker_id="125049" name="Maria Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor Presidente, yo creo que la Unión Europea podría hacer muchísimo más para desincentivar la tala ilegal en el mundo. Podría empezar, por ejemplo, por desincentivar el monocultivo del eucalipto o de otras especies de crecimiento rápido y promover en su lugar en la producción de maderas de calidad. Esto contribuiría muchísimo a mantener la biodiversidad, a mantener también el medio ambiente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me parece que otro aspecto importantísimo que podría tener en cuenta la Unión Europea para desincentivar la tala ilegal sería no aplicar solo medidas voluntarias, sino poner fin al comercio ilegal controlando las importaciones y también a los importadores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Promover una política forestal en Europa que incentive la ordenación de los bosques, que evite la deforestación de tierras agrarias y potencie la producción de madera de calidad sería una magnífica contribución a este proyecto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Heidi Hautala" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is of the utmost importance that the Commission really comes up with a comprehensive EU action plan on deforestation and forest degradation. We have lots of reasons and obligations as to why we need this. First of all, we have the UN Sustainable Development Goals and the Paris climate agreement, which both require effective action on illegal logging and deforestation. Besides, illegal logging is a major problem in illicit capital flows from developing countries. Indeed, FLEGT has had many successes, but the global context has changed a lot since its introduction in 2003.</p>
      <p sl="en">So now we really need new measures and we need to look at innovative ways of shedding light on the supply chains. It is a very important task for us to make sure that consumers in the end—user countries, like those in the European Union, have full access to information on the origin of the timber. I believe that FLEGT could actually inspire many other sectors and products. The approach is really innovative, with the voluntary partnership agreements.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the things that I have noticed is that the evaluation has come to the conclusion that there are limitations in terms of lack of data on illegal logging and trade and on governance achievements. Here I believe some new instruments could be introduced. We could see how customs information could be used to shed light on which companies are importing what to the EU Member States. I also firmly believe that we could look in the countries of origin at how we can support the countries to put in place proper systems of forest inventory. I am proud to say that Finland, my country, has been very active in helping countries like Vietnam and Tanzania in this field.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-0000" speaker_id="106202" name="Julia Reid" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, illegal logging is symptomatic of wider governance problems, such as weak and unclear laws, corruption, big business behaving badly and poor local people with few incentives to behave well – all brought about by scientific theories which have been preached with the certainty of religious fervour. This, with the assertion that the rule of law means the same everywhere, is not a pretty picture, and it applies to much in the developing world – especially in the issue of industrial scale illegal logging and deforestation, which is threatening the survival of some of the world’s most endangered animal species.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is a stupid response to rush to criminalise in ways which further incentivise bad behaviour, based on questionable science, and to reinforce this with due diligence bureaucracy which adds to costs, thus further incentivising the very activity that we want to stop. If you raise the price of something, you encourage new market entrants, including illegal ones. What is needed is to ask the Commission whether it has done a robust behavioural economic analysis of the incentive system in the global logging market. This is, of course, not the kind of question asked by or of the European institutions. Instead, we have the usual cliché buzzwords: ‘political momentum’, ‘coherence’, ‘synergies’, ‘climate’, ‘mitigation’. Thank goodness my country is leaving.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169-0000" speaker_id="125684" name="Philippe Loiseau" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, le rapport spécial n° 13/2015 de la Cour des comptes européenne décrit l'échec du programme européen de soutien aux pays producteurs de bois dans la lutte contre l'abattage illégal. Ce fléau met en péril le patrimoine forestier mondial, mais aussi des populations indigènes qui tirent leur subsistance de cette forêt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les raisons de ces abattages illégaux sont diverses. Tout d'abord, en Indonésie, une grande quantité d'arbres sont coupés pour laisser place à des plantations qui produiront du papier ou de l'huile de palme, détruisant ainsi la biodiversité. En Amérique du Sud, l'abattage illégal sert à l'exportation de ce bois au profit d'organisations parfois liées aux autorités corrompues qui, bien sûr, veulent s'enrichir en répondant à la demande de bois sur les marchés internationaux. On poursuit les bûcherons alors qu'ils sont victimes d'un système qui les exploite et, bien entendu, les décideurs ne sont jamais arrêtés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Outre la corruption, la lutte contre l'abattage illégal n'est pas toujours la priorité du gouvernement du pays en question. L'extension des productions d'huile de palme ou de champs de soja pour soutenir l'agriculture intensive fait partie du problème.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, le dernier problème est celui de la traçabilité des produits sur le marché. Par exemple, 80 à 90 % du bois exporté du Pérou vers la Chine et d'autres marchés asiatiques est illégal, ce qui correspond à une perte d'environ 86 millions d'euros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour finir, je pense que développer et durcir l'impératif de traçabilité serait une bonne solution. Au vu de la complexité du problème, savoir d'où vient le bois et connaître la société d'abattage apparaît évidemment comme une solution crédible et tout à fait envisageable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-170-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η σημασία της υπάρξεως δασών σε παγκόσμια κλίμακα είναι μεγάλη, όχι μόνο διότι αυτά συμβάλλουν στον περιορισμό των αερίων του θερμοκηπίου και κυρίως του διοξειδίου του άνθρακος, περιορίζοντας κατ’ αυτό τον τρόπο τις κλιματικές μεταβολές, αλλά και διότι αποτελούν σημαντική πηγή πλούτου για τις χώρες που τα διαθέτουν. Συνεπώς, η προστασία των δασών από παράνομη υλοτομία και αποψίλωση πρέπει να αντιμετωπιστεί από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση ως ένα θέμα πρώτης προτεραιότητας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πρέπει η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση να εκπονήσει μία σχετική πολιτική και να συνεργαστεί όχι μόνο με τα κράτη μέλη της Ενώσεως, αλλά και με τα κράτη εκείνα τα οποία παράγουν μεγάλες ποσότητες ξύλου, ούτως ώστε να περιοριστεί η παράνομη υλοτομία καθώς επίσης και το εμπόριο των αγαθών των οποίων η παραγωγή συνεπάγεται την αποψίλωση των δασών. Παράλληλα, πρέπει να χρηματοδοτήσει κατάλληλα αυτή την προσπάθεια και να συνάψει και τις απαραίτητες εμπορικές συμφωνίες, ούτως ώστε να υπάρξει δυνατότητα επιτυχίας του προγράμματος.</p>
      <p sl="en">Τέλος, το θέμα του περιορισμού τόσο της παράνομης υλοτομίας, όσο και των καταστροφών των δασών οι οποίες προκαλούνται είτε από πυρκαγιές, είτε από εμπρησμούς, είτε από συμπτωματικά γεγονότα, πρέπει επίσης να αντιμετωπιστεί στο πλαίσιο της Ευρωπαϊκής Ενώσεως.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-0000" speaker_id="96882" name="Elisabeth Köstinger" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar! Ich möchte doch noch einmal darauf hinweisen und halte es für wichtig herauszustreichen, dass die heutige Debatte kein Fingerzeig auf unsere europäischen Waldbesitzer ist, die bereits seit Generationen mit nachhaltiger Waldbewirtschaftung unseren grünen Schatz pflegen. Es geht heute vielmehr darum, alle Kräfte zu bündeln, damit der Handel mit illegalem Holz endlich gestoppt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Weltweit wird alle zwei Sekunden eine Waldfläche in der Größe eines Fußballfeldes illegal gerodet, und zuverlässige Daten von illegaler Waldholzung in Drittstaaten sind nach wie vor sehr schwer zugänglich. Schätzungen zufolge wird aber in der Europäischen Union jährlich illegales Holz im Wert von 1,2 Mrd. EUR verkauft. Der wirtschaftliche Schaden für die Holzerzeugerländer ist demnach auch enorm. Jährlich entgehen ihnen Einnahmen in Höhe von 10 bis 15 Mrd. EUR, und dieses Geld, vor allem auch in Hinblick auf die immens großen Herausforderungen, insbesondere in den Staaten – vor auf dem afrikanischen Kontinent, ist hier wirklich von ganz besonderer Bedeutung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Geschätzte Kolleginnen und Kollegen, wir haben hier eine Verantwortung für die nachfolgenden Generationen zu tragen, denn neben dem wirtschaftlichen Schaden ist illegaler Holzeinschlag auch ein massiver Eingriff in unser weltweites Ökosystem. FLEGT ist die Antwort der Europäischen Union auf das globale Problem. Das Konzept ist innovativ und absolut richtig. Der Sonderbericht des Rechnungshofs zeigt allerdings massive Umsetzungsdefizite auf. Hier gibt es großen Erklärungsbedarf: Welche Konzepte hat hier die Kommission? Wie können wir aber vor allem auch die Partnerstaaten zu Reformen animieren? Wie können wir ihnen auch unterstützend zur Seite stehen? Und gibt es hier wirklich auch eine nach vorne weisende Strategie?</p>
      <p sl="en">Als Berichterstatterin der freiwilligen Partnerschaftsabkommen mit Indonesien, Liberia und Zentralafrika möchte ich die Kommission auch um einen Fortschrittsbericht zur Umsetzung dieser Abkommen bitten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-0000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, em março de 2015 abordei em plenário a questão da desflorestação ilegal de florestas tropicais, o conflito com a agricultura, o papel da corrupção e a perda de diversidade. Hoje, foco-me no plano de ação desenhado pela Comissão Europeia, pois a sua implementação carece de clarificação, de objetivos e de prioridades.</p>
      <p sl="en">É difícil entender algumas das opções. Por exemplo, ao abrigo deste plano foi estabelecido um acordo de parceria voluntária com a Libéria, que incluía apoios no valor de 12 milhões de euros, mas este país exporta apenas 5 milhões de euros em madeira para o nosso território. A Costa do Marfim, que exporta para a Europa um valor 30 vezes superior, foi deixada de fora. Caso tivesse sido incluída garantiria a adequação ambiental e social dessa madeira.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para além de ser um problema ambiental grave constitui uma competição desleal com as nossas regiões produtoras que estão a fazer um esforço de certificação, como é o caso dos Açores, ilhas portuguesas de que sou de origem e que estão no centro do Atlântico.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedniče, lako ćemo se složiti oko stanja u Latinskoj Americi i znamo da je pretjerana proizvodnja palminog ulja u raznim državama prouzročila veliku sječu šuma, da je neplanska loša poljoprivreda također napravila veliku štetu za naš planet. Ali, ja želim govoriti o Europi, želim govoriti o nama, želim govoriti o problemima s kojima se suočavamo u zemljama članicama Europske unije u kojima također postoji ilegalna sječa šuma, krađa šuma, krađa drva i gdje postoji krađa resursa ljudi koji žive okruženi šumama.</p>
      <p sl="en">Konkretan primjer je Gorski kotar u Hrvatskoj. Promašena politika koju država vodi već 25 godina, zbog koje mladi odlazi iz Gorskog kotara jer ne vide svoju perspektivu i svoju budućnost, a okruženi su kvadratnim kilometrima šuma prve klase. Loša državna politika koja ne vodi brigu o lokalnom zajednici i na taj način ne omogućava da fantastični resursi koje Gorski kotar ima budu iskorišteni u korist razvoja građana tog jednog malog, ali predivnog dijela Hrvatske. Mislim da i o takvim temama trebamo govoriti, gospodine povjereniče.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-0000" speaker_id="125051" name="Josu Juaristi Abaunz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, los compromisos y medidas recogidos en el Plan de Acción siguen siendo relevantes, pero su eficacia será menor si no es reforzado, como reconoce la Comisión. Y será ineficaz si la Unión Europea no garantiza su total implementación, como por ejemplo, la del Reglamento relativo a la comercialización de la madera.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay que detener la circulación de madera extraída ilegalmente, que viola la normativa sobre protección de bosques y los derechos de las poblaciones nativas. Necesitamos medidas adicionales, como las que ha mencionado mi colega Lidia Senra, para proteger la biodiversidad, los bosques y los pueblos del bosque.</p>
      <p sl="en">En 2015 los Estados miembros reconocieron la necesidad de una acción urgente cuando se comprometieron con los objetivos de desarrollo sostenible y el Acuerdo de París sobre el cambio climático. Creo que es hora de cumplir dichos compromisos y de cerrar las brechas del Plan de Acción.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-0000" speaker_id="124903" name="Bogdan Brunon Wenta" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Problem nielegalnego wykorzystania zasobów leśnych i zagrożeń, jakie niosą ze sobą takie działania, dotyczy aspektów nie tylko środowiskowych, ale także ekonomicznych i społecznych. Niewłaściwe użytkowanie lasów wywołuje znaczne szkody nie tylko dla środowiska naturalnego. Oprócz wylesiania, utraty bioróżnorodności i zwiększonej emisji gazów cieplarnianych nielegalny wyrąb przyczynia się do konfliktu wśród rdzennych i lokalnych społeczności, łamania praw człowieka i korupcji. Dochody z tych działań używane są często do finansowania konfliktów zbrojnych, przyczyniają się do zwiększenia poziomu ubóstwa. W Afryce największe straty w sektorze leśnym zanotowano w ostatnich latach w Nigerii, Tanzanii, Zimbabwe, Demokratycznej Republice Konga. Władze niektórych z tych krajów stosują tak zwane kontrolowane wypalania obszarów leśnych w celu pozyskania tych ziem pod uprawy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przeciwdziałanie negatywnym tendencjom, w tym nielegalnej wycince drewna, wymaga ścisłej współpracy z krajami rozwijającymi się, gdzie duże znaczenie dla gospodarki ma użytkowanie drewna i handel nim. Niezbędne jest wsparcie w zakresie wymiany dobrych praktyk i odpowiednie reformy polityki leśnej. Dlatego plan działania FLEGT mający na celu zwiększenie zdolności krajów rozwijających się do kontroli nielegalnego użytkowania lasów – przy jednoczesnym ograniczaniu handlu wyrobami z nielegalnego drewna pomiędzy tymi krajami a Unią Europejską – jest dobrą postawą. Jednak należy przeznaczyć dodatkowe środki, aby sprostać wyzwaniom związanym z jego wdrażaniem oraz monitorowaniem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-0000" speaker_id="112744" name="Tonino Picula" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, gospodine povjereniče, ilegalna sječa i trgovina nezakonito posječenom drvnom sirovinom godišnje generira ekonomski gubitak od 7 milijardi eura. Još je značajniji iznimno nepovoljan utjecaj na biološku raznolikost i razinu ispuštanja stakleničkih plinova, a to posljedično utječe na živote ljudi koji ovise o šumama, narušava tržište i, svakako, potiče korupciju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Akcijski plan Europske unije za provedbu zakonodavstva, upravljanje i trgovinu u području šumarstva (FLEGT), iako je u teoriji dobro zamišljen, u praksi je zakazao. Zbog toga je potrebno što prije oživiti tu političku inicijativu i iskoristiti njezin potencijal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Osim toga, vrijeme je da se potakne zanimanje za stanje šuma u Europskoj uniji. Prekomjerna, nelegalna sječa i trgovina nezakonito posječenim drvom nije problem samo trećih zemalja s kojima sklapamo FLEGT sporazume jer se sve to na dnevnoj bazi događa i u našim zemljama članicama. U Hrvatskoj se uništavaju putevi i ceste koji su građeni desetljećima, a nelegalno posječeno drvo se uglavnom odvozi u susjedne zemlje i bez kontrole stavlja na tržište.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zbog toga još jednom pozivam na pojačanu aktivnost i koordinaciju kada je u pitanju očuvanje europskih šuma. Šume su puno značajnije nego što nam se čine; one su pluća Europe, izvor energije, čuvar klime i bioraznolikosti te ih trebamo poštovati sukladno njihovoj izuzetnoj važnosti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-0000" speaker_id="125193" name="Eleonora Forenza" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, in tempi di cambiamenti climatici le foreste diventano l'unico alleato per la salvaguardia della vita e del benessere di milioni di esseri umani. Inoltre, esse rappresentano il più importante serbatoio di biodiversità e un elemento costitutivo per le comunità indigene e i contadini in tutto il mondo.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europa rimane la prima destinazione per il commercio illegale di legname e per questo è fondamentale nei prossimi anni che vi sia un impegno reale di tutta l'Unione per far sì che il FLEGT non resti un impegno volontario nell'ambito degli accordi commerciali. Sono necessari impegni cogenti in grado di regolare l'attività di governi e multinazionali e al tempo stesso di bloccare il sistema di corruttele. È fondamentale che la riforma del FLEGT vieti esplicitamente il commercio di legname proveniente da zone di conflitto, prevedendo un sistema di sanzioni fino alla revoca delle licenze di importazione e alla sospensione degli accordi di libero scambio o delle tariffe preferenziali per le multinazionali e gli Stati che violino l'embargo.</p>
      <p sl="en">In ultimo consideriamo inadeguato il sistema di monitoraggio volontario degli investimenti nel settore forestale da parte delle multinazionali dell'agricoltura e del settore finanziario. Sono invece necessari una regolamentazione efficace e meccanismi di due diligence in grado di limitare le attività illegali e fornire una speranza ai polmoni verdi del pianeta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-0000" speaker_id="125006" name="Francesc Gambús" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, señor Comisario, en primer lugar creo que es importante señalar que el informe del Tribunal de Cuentas Europeo es bastante devastador en sus observaciones. En resumidas cuentas nos dice que la intención política es buena e innovadora, pero que este Plan de Acción —que por sí no tendría que ser malo— no llega implementado por un buen plan de trabajo, o si llega, lo hace tarde y mal. Parece un buen resumen también de la percepción de los males que afectan a la Unión: bien pensada, pero vamos tarde y mal. Debemos actuar con una visión global, porque la deforestación es un problema grave tanto ambiental como humano, pero debemos actuar bien.</p>
      <p sl="en">En 2015 se calcula que hubo cien mil muertes en Indonesia atribuidas a los incendios forestales. Indonesia, que en 2014 superó a Brasil en el dudoso honor de ser el país con mayor deforestación anual del mundo. Indonesia, que recibió diez millones de euros destinados a la lucha por la aplicación de las leyes, la gobernanza y el comercio forestales en 2004; y, desde entonces, la Unión Europea no ha programado ningún otro proyecto de ayuda al desarrollo para el Gobierno de este país en el sector forestal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, no debemos ser pesimistas, sino —como dice el propio informe— verlo como una oportunidad para mejorar el enfoque que se le da actualmente, para tener resultados más tangibles, que también los hemos tenido.</p>
      <p sl="en">El mismo fondo ha tenido buenos resultados, por ejemplo en Camerún, donde ha conseguido que la sociedad civil participara en la gobernanza forestal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Debemos insistir en la necesidad de reconocer el valor ambiental pero también social y económico de los bosques. Debemos recordar el valor añadido que suponen para las poblaciones rurales, también las actividades que como el pastoreo ayudan a prevenir peligros como los incendios forestales, así como a mantener un bosque limpio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello quisiera poner en valor el informe Köstinger de este Parlamento sobre una nueva estrategia de la UE en favor de los bosques y del sector forestal en la que pedíamos un plan de acción sobre deforestación y degradación con el fin de abordar los objetivos fijados en la Comunicación respecto a la protección y mejora de los bosques mediante su gestión sostenible, así como el apoyo a los mecanismos que fomentan el desarrollo mundial de la silvicultura con miras a una explotación más sostenible de los bosques.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-0000" speaker_id="124699" name="Miroslav Poche" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the EU Action Plan on Forest Law Enforcement, Governance and Trade (FLEGT) and its implementation have fundamentally helped to increase awareness of the devastating impact of illegal logging. The commitments and measures contained remain highly relevant today and should be further strengthened. Governments have recently committed themselves to the Sustainable Development Goals and the Paris Agreement. If the European Union wants to remain a credible global partner and a global force in combating climate change, we have to take concrete actions, cooperate with international partners, and increase the coherence of EU policies to effectively push for ending deforestation and the connected violations of human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tackling deforestation and illegal logging can be successful only if indigenous peoples’ land rights are respected. The EU Action Plan needs strong governance reforms, coherence with other environmental policies and additional resources. We should express our firm position on some particular points of the problem, which I believe are essential to achieving the concrete picture of what the European Union plans to undertake.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-0000" speaker_id="124689" name="Νεοκλής Συλικιώτης (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">GUE/NGL). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, κύριε Επίτροπε, είναι σημαντικό να στηριχτούν οι χώρες παραγωγής ξυλείας και να κινητοποιηθούν πόροι για την ανάπτυξη μηχανισμών, ώστε να ενισχυθεί το σχέδιο δράσης της Ένωσης για την εφαρμογή της δασικής νομοθεσίας. Κάθε μας ενέργεια όμως πρέπει να σέβεται και να προωθεί τους στόχους που έχουμε θέσει για το κλίμα και την προστασία του περιβάλλοντος. Είναι αναγκαίο να ληφθούν άμεσα μέτρα για την πρόληψη και αποτροπή της παράνομης υλοτομίας, της αυθαίρετης αποψίλωσης, αλλά και της σκόπιμης καταστροφής και πυρπόλησης των δασών που πραγματοποιούνται με σκοπό την οικοπεδοποίηση δασικών εκτάσεων, κάτι που ζούμε πολύ έντονα στη Νότια Ευρώπη, και την εξυπηρέτηση μεγάλων ιδιωτικών συμφερόντων.</p>
      <p sl="en">Είναι επίσης σημαντικό να προωθηθεί η αναδάσωση. Η προστασία του περιβάλλοντος αποτελεί βασική προϋπόθεση για την αναβάθμιση της ποιότητας ζωής του ανθρώπου. Έχουμε λοιπόν χρέος να προστατεύσουμε τα δάση από κάθε μορφή παράνομης αποψίλωσης και καταστροφής και να αναπτύξουμε μια δασική νομοθεσία με γνώμονα τα συμφέροντα της κοινωνίας και των ανθρώπων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já bych chtěl ve své jedné minutě podpořit všechny svoje kolegy, kteří zde vystupovali, protože skutečně podle mého soudu nezákonně vytěžené dřevo ohrožuje plíce světa. A v tomto smyslu bych chtěl především podpořit východiska, která jsou stanovena v akčním plánu. Na druhou stranu mám opravdu pocit, že zaostáváme v jeho provedení i právě na tom mezinárodním poli, protože tento akční plán by měl být podle mého názoru přímo provázán se zahraniční politikou Evropské unie. My bychom měli i ty státy, které skutečně nedodržují závazky, které třeba i byly smluvně sjednány s naší Unií, jaksi být schopni efektivně podpořit právě na mezinárodním poli. Já jsem byl v Singapuru před několika lety a byl jsem opravdu zděšen z toho, jak kouř z Indonésie dopadá dokonce do tohoto státu a právě pochází z vypalovaných lesů a týká se palmového oleje. Já myslím, že bychom na tyto skutečnosti neměli rezignovat a měli bychom podpořit naši politiku i právě v této zahraniční oblasti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-183-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, per effetto della posizione di rilievo, ma non dominante, che l'Unione europea detiene nel mercato mondiale dei prodotti del legno, qualsiasi provvedimento risulterà inefficace se non condiviso con i grandi player del settore, come ad esempio Stati Uniti, Giappone e Cina.</p>
      <p sl="en">Penso che la Commissione debba dare impulso politico al piano d'azione dell'Unione europea per l'applicazione delle normative, la governance e il commercio nel settore forestale, portando a compimento la creazione di un sistema di rilascio di licenze su base volontaria, volto a garantire l'import del solo legname tagliato legalmente. Affinché un tale sistema possa funzionare correttamente, i paesi partner FLEGT dovrebbero provvedere a istituire sistemi e strutture affidabili per una corretta identificazione e certificazione del legame del legname tagliato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Relativamente all'aspetto finanziario, la Commissione dovrebbe integrare le iniziative previste dal programma FLEGT nei principali programmi europei di cooperazione allo sviluppo, al fine di poter attuare programmi di assistenza tecnica e di sviluppo di capacità nei paesi partner produttori di legname.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-184-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η παράνομη υλοτομία και η αποψίλωση των δασών δημιουργούν σοβαρές επιπτώσεις στο περιβάλλον, καθώς μειώνουν τη βιοποικιλότητα και συμβάλλουν αρνητικά στην αλλαγή του κλίματος. Για την αντιμετώπιση των περιβαλλοντικών καταστροφών που προκαλούνται από την παράνομη υλοτομία και την αποψίλωση, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση από το 2003 έχει υιοθετήσει ένα σχέδιο δράσης για την επιβολή της δασικής νομοθεσίας, τη διακυβέρνηση και το εμπόριο, με στόχο την ενθάρρυνση μιας βιώσιμης διαχείρισης των δασών. Αυτό το σχέδιο δράσης δεν έχει φέρει ακόμη τα επιθυμητά αποτελέσματα. Σύμφωνα με το Ελεγκτικό Συνέδριο της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, τα 300 εκατομμύρια ευρώ που κατανεμήθηκαν σε 35 χώρες στο πλαίσιο του σχεδίου είχαν πενιχρά αποτελέσματα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Επομένως, η Επιτροπή θα πρέπει να λάβει άμεσα μέτρα για την καταπολέμηση της παράνομης υλοτομίας και της αποψίλωσης. Ταυτόχρονα, κύριε Vella, θα πρέπει η Ένωση να ενισχύσει οικονομικά την Ελλάδα για την αποκατάσταση των ζημιών που υπέστησαν οι παραγωγοί και το φυτικό και ζωικό τους κεφάλαιο από τις πρόσφατες πυρκαγιές στη Χίο, την Εύβοια, αλλά και την Κέρκυρα. Το ίδιο βεβαίως πρέπει να ισχύσει και για την Κύπρο, η οποία επίσης φέτος υπέφερε από πυρκαγιές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this is a most interesting discussion and a serious issue for the world generally. I would hope, particularly now that we have 195 countries signed up to COP 21, that this is an issue that should be easier to tackle globally – especially now as we go to Morocco and try to implement the agreement that was signed in Paris in December. That should certainly help.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also of interest is that in my own constituency there is an innovative company called Treemetrics who log, map and monitor what is happening in forests through satellite imagery. That might be useful, especially in tracking illegal logging, etc., and is something that might be worth looking at. I was very encouraged, though, to hear that progress has been made, for instance, in Indonesia. In the space of 14 years, there was a 70% reduction in illegal logging due to bilateral arrangements and discussions. I think, as the Commissioner pointed out, that Ghana and other countries will hopefully follow in due course.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-187-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, az illegális fakitermelés és erdőirtás óriás problémát jelent több európai uniós tagállamban. Ezen a téren is tapasztaljuk a jól ismert jelenséget: miközben vannak a kérdés kezelésére alkalmas jogszabályaink, a mindennapok valósága az, hogy korrupcióval átitatott rendszerek épültek ki az ellenőrizhetetlen fakitermelési tevékenység ipari méretekben való folytatására. Egész erdőket tüntetnek el, az állami hatóságok sok esetben szemet hunynak, a helyi erdőtulajdonosok pedig tehetetlenek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nyílt titokként keringenek olyan információk, hogy fakitermelő vállalkozások illegálisan kitermelt fát vásárolnak meg, feldolgozzák, értékesítik, nem törődve a környezetvédelmi és egyéb szempontokkal. A jogszabályok áthágásának mintha nem lenne következménye, a polgárok pedig elvárják, hogy a törvény mindenkire vonatkozzon: még azokra a cégekre is, amelyek több millió köbméter fát dolgoznak fel és több száz munkahelyet biztosítanak.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karmenu Vella" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank all the Members for their statements, comments and suggestions, to which I have listened very carefully. I have to say that I agree with many points that have been raised. I will also communicate these to my colleagues, Neven Mimica, Miguel Arias and Cecilia, with whom I work very closely on deforestation issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">It has already been mentioned that progress is being made even with some timber producers, and in a few weeks’ time we will see the launching of FLEGT licensing in Indonesia. I think this is a major step and one we hope will be followed by Ghana next year. At the moment we are discussing VPAs with some 15 other countries. So there should be no doubting the Commission’s commitment to making FLEGT work.</p>
      <p sl="en">There were also some interesting points which were made like, for example, Mr Tomašić, who mentioned the joint surveillance between Member States, and the fact that we still have illegal timber coming into Europe, and I have to stress again the responsibility of the Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is also the fact of the link between deforestation and the agricultural sector, especially the fact that we have to find monoculture and so on, and the socio-economic impact as well.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think many of you also spoke about inadequate implementation and I have to say yes, the Commission acknowledges that the absence of an implementation plan to guide strategic management and monitoring has rendered implementation of FLEGT, and VPAs in particular, largely demand-driven. That is why the Commission is working towards the development of a multiannual plan to guide activity planning by setting clear targets, indicators, monitoring deadlines and associated budgetary resources.</p>
      <p sl="en">Many of the honourable Members also mentioned the corruption problem. I totally agree with what they said, and that is why we took a number of precautions, especially in VPAs. The scheme developed for VPAs has several layers of safeguards and independence. Firstly, compliance with legal requirements is checked by private certification companies. Secondly, a specific role is provided for civil society to check that audited enterprises and forest operators comply with legal requirements. Thirdly, there is an overall systems audit, or periodical evaluation, that is foreseen and that will be carried out at least on an annual basis to check that the system is working properly overall.</p>
      <p sl="en">There were several mentions of dealing with SDGs and climate change, and many of the action plan’s areas of action contribute to addressing several goals of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, including SDG 8, SDG 12 and SDG 13, which is climate change, SDG 15 which is life on land and SDG 16, which is peaceful and inclusive societies.</p>
      <p sl="en">What the Commission intends to do: as indicated in the 7th Environmental Action Plan, the Commission remains committed to developing policy proposals to address the deforestation challenge, and to this end the Commission is in the process of considering the feasibility of measures to achieve this objective, also as a follow-up to the study on the impact of EU consumption on deforestation.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will continue to ensure adequate resources for the implementation of the action plan, through the development and cooperation instrument, including support for the engagement of civil society, private sector and public administrations. When we talk about resources, as Notis Marias mentioned, we have not only to monitor and talk about input but, more importantly, I think we need to monitor the output as well.</p>
      <p sl="en">As the Court’s report found, the fundamentals of the FLEGT Action Plan are right. It is making an important contribution to mitigating climate change and to improving governance by clarifying tenure rights but, I agree, still more needs to be done. The Commission is also acting to address the important recommendations of the Court to ensure that the action plan is fit for purpose in a world where the pressures on forests are increasing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0500" speaker_id="95281" name="Viorica Dăncilă" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Pădurile ocupă suprafețe semnificative ale planetei și sunt ecosisteme importante atât pentru om, cât și din punct de vedere ecologic. Pentru atingerea obiectivelor Strategiei 2020 în ceea ce privește pădurile, consider că este necesară consolidarea strategiei pentru păduri și sectorul forestier prin: lupta împotriva despăduririlor și a degradării pădurilor, promovarea gestionării durabile a pădurilor ca mijloc de protecție a biodiversității, lupta împotriva deșertificării și de reacție la schimbările climatice, asigurându-se totodată că ecosistemele forestiere oferă bunuri și servicii, contribuind la dezvoltarea durabilă și la eradicarea sărăciei. Este nevoie de un angajament ferm, coerență și de sprijin politic din partea tuturor părților implicate în cadrul Planului de acțiune FLEGT, astfel încât politicile de dezvoltare și în materie de schimbări climatice să plaseze pădurile și sectorul forestier în centrul demersului către o economie ecologică și să pună în valoare avantajele pe care le pot oferi pădurile în mod durabil, asigurând totodată protecția acestora și combaterea despăduririlor ilegale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0750" speaker_id="124749" name="Marijana Petir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – U provedbi sporazuma iz Pariza kojeg ćemo potvrditi ovih dana, nužno je da svaka država svijeta preuzme odgovornost i da svoj doprinos ostvarivanju zadanih ciljeva. EU u provedbi svoje energetske i klimatske politike mora tražiti i od drugih da slijedeći njezin primjer doprinose očuvanju svojih šuma. Upravo na tom tragu smatram kako održivo korištenje šuma kakvo poznajemo u Europi mora biti ujedno i uvjet za trgovinu s trećim državama kada se radi o uvozu drva i drvne građe. FLEGT dozvola predstavlja dobrovoljan okvir unutar kojeg je moguće postići željene ciljeve. Smatram pozitivnim istaknuti primjer Indonezije koja je od 2002. do danas podigla udio certificirane sječe s 20 % na 90 % te na taj način pokazuje predanost očuvanju i održivom korištenju svojih šuma. To je za nas važno zbog toga što EU uvozi gotovo trećinu svojih potreba za tropskim drvom upravo iz Indonezije. Smatram potrebnim, a kako to također naglašava Revizorski sud u svom izvješću, konkretizirati akcije kroz mehanizme praćenja i ocjenjivanja uspješnosti provedbe Akcijskog plana EU-a za provedbu zakonodavstva, upravljanje i trgovinu u području šumarstva. Postojeći način dobrovoljnog certificiranja potrebno je dodatno ojačati kako bi i druge zemlje postigle zaštitu svojih šuma barem do razine njihovog održivog korištenja.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-193-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca gli interventi di un minuto su questioni di rilevanza politica in base all'articolo 163 del regolamento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194-0000" speaker_id="39726" name="László Tőkés" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, hatvan éve annak, hogy 1956 októberében a magyar nép példátlan egységben lázadt fel a kommunista diktatúra és az országát megszálló szovjet bolsevik uralom ellen. Az 1956-os magyar forradalom és szabadságharc 1968-ban a prágai tavasszal, majd a ’80-as években a lengyel Szolidaritás szabadságmozgalmával folytatódott. 1989 sorsfordító esztendejében közép- és kelet-európai népeink közös küzdelme vezetett el a szovjet kommunizmus bukásához, a rendszerváltozás pedig a megosztott Európa újraegyesüléséhez. Az Európai Közösség egyik legfőbb alapértéke a szabadság. Méltó, hogy közös történelmünk egyik legkiemelkedőbb eseményeként emlékezzünk meg a magyar ’56-ról és azokról, akik életüket áldozták a szabadságért. Az ő példájukat követve kell folytatnunk harcunkat minden elnyomó hatalom és totalitárius rezsim ellen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-195-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, entro il 2020 l'Italia, per essere al passo con l'Europa, dovrà garantire una crescita inclusiva, creando ben 2,8 milioni di nuovi posti di lavoro, e sottrarre circa 2,2 milioni di persone a condizioni di povertà o deprivazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Purtroppo sono ancora otto le regioni italiane lontane dal raggiungere il traguardo nazionale fissato per il 2020 e tra le regioni con maggiori difficoltà figurano tutte quelle del Mezzogiorno, con un gap da recuperare che va dall'8,4 % dell'Abruzzo al 23,9 % della Campania e al 24,9 % della Calabria. Va ha messo in campo un grande piano d'azione, un piano che preveda riforme e investimenti nell'edilizia sociale, nelle infrastrutture fisiche e digitali e nelle infrastrutture educative.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il governo italiano, specie nell'ultimo periodo, sta facendo molto per migliorare le condizioni del paese in chiave di sviluppo e di creazione di nuovi posti di lavoro, ma risulta chiaro che per raggiungere i traguardi precisati dalla strategia Europa 2020 serve anche il contributo dell'Europa. Occorre una politica economica più flessibile ed espansiva per permettere al nostro paese di superare le difficoltà e raggiungere i target prefissati.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-196-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Неразумната и сбъркана обща политика по съсредоточаването на нелегални имигранти в центрове в населените места създаде изключително много затруднения, заплаха за обществения ред и сигурност, заплаха за сигурността и здравето на гражданите около тези центрове. Навсякъде около Овча купел, Враждебна, Харманли гражданите протестират срещу тези центрове и настояват те да бъдат закрити.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ще ви прочета накратко декларация, приета от общото събрание на населението в град Харманли вчера, в която се изисква регистрационно-приемателният център в град Харманли да бъде премахнат от града. Изисква се незабавно прекратяване на обществената поръчка за разширяването на този център и за изграждането на нови центрове в населените места. Изисква се полицейска проверка за нелегално пребиваване на мигранти на външни адреси. Изисква се действие по линия на Европейския съюз за сключване на реадмисия с Афганистан. Изисква се незабавна промяна на законите, така че нелегалните мигранти да бъдат отблъснати.</p>
      <p sl="en">Уважаеми г-н Председател, уважаеми колеги, нуждаем се от нова политика по отношение на миграцията и убежището. Няма да допуснем родината ни да бъде превърната в лагер за нелегални мигранти.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-0000" speaker_id="28116" name="Marian Harkin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, there was always a contradiction at the heart of the argument that said ‘we will control our borders while keeping access to the single market’. Those lies were laid bare by Theresa May last weekend. There were no weasel words from Mrs May. She laid it on the line when she said: ‘we will decide for ourselves how we control immigration and we will be free to pass our own laws’. The most important word there is ‘ourselves’. There is no attempt at negotiation; no soft Brexit. She is setting the parameters.</p>
      <p sl="en">This has the potential to be catastrophic for Ireland in so many ways, but particularly for some of our indigenous industries, particularly the agri-food sector. By comparison, 7% of German exports go to the UK, 17% of Irish exports go to the UK. The British will be hard-nosed in their negotiations. We in Ireland must move swiftly and sure-footedly to protect our interests. We are entering a critical time. As we say in Ireland: ‘we are playing senior hurling now’.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198-0000" speaker_id="96907" name="Τάκης Χατζηγεωργίου (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">GUE/NGL). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, έληξε πρόσφατα η τριμερής συνάντηση στη Νέα Υόρκη μεταξύ των ηγετών των δύο κοινοτήτων στην Κύπρο. Επειδή δεν γνωρίζουμε αν θα βρεθούμε μπροστά σε μια μεγάλη επιτυχία της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, αν επιτευχθεί λύση, ή αν θα καταρρεύσει αυτό το πράγμα, με όλους τους κινδύνους που κάτι τέτοιο συνεπάγεται, λαμβάνοντας υπόψη και το τι τρέχει στη γύρω περιοχή, θα ήθελα να καταθέσω μερικές σκέψεις για την ανάγκη επίλυσης του Κυπριακού και τις παραμέτρους του. Ζητούμε λοιπόν αποχώρηση των τουρκικών κατοχικών στρατευμάτων στη λύση και κατάργηση του αναχρονιστικού συστήματος των εγγυήσεων του 1960, καθώς και οποιωνδήποτε μονομερών επεμβατικών δικαιωμάτων. Το κόμμα μου απορρίπτει κάθε Νατοϊκή λύση στο θέμα της ασφάλειας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεύτερον, ζητούμε συνέχεια της Κυπριακής Δημοκρατίας και μετεξέλιξή της σε Δικοινοτική Διζωνική Ομοσπονδία. Ζητούμε απρόσκοπτη εφαρμογή των βασικών ελευθεριών και των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων για όλους τους Κύπριους πολίτες. Δεν αποδεχόμαστε μόνιμες αποκλίσεις από το κοινοτικό κεκτημένο. Απαιτούμε τον τερματισμό του εποικισμού και τον σεβασμό της πληθυσμιακής αναλογίας 4 προς 1. Ζητούμε ουσιαστικές εδαφικές αναπροσαρμογές, όπως την ένταξη, μεταξύ άλλων, της Αμμοχώστου και της Μόρφου υπό Ελληνοκυπριακή Διοίκηση. Θεωρούμε αναγκαία την σύντμηση στο ελάχιστο των χρονοδιαγραμμάτων τόσο της επιστροφής εδαφών, όσο και της αποχώρησης των κατοχικών στρατευμάτων και ζητούμε, τέλος, ισχυρό ψήφισμα του Συμβουλίου Ασφαλείας και άλλες συναφείς δεσμεύσεις όλων των εμπλεκομένων για διασφάλιση της εφαρμογής και πιστής τήρησης της συνολικής διευθέτησης.</p>
      <p sl="en">Θέλω να κλείσω, αν μου επιτρέπετε, με μια αναφορά στον Şener Elcil, ο οποίος βραβεύθηκε μόλις προχθές με το Βραβείο του Ευρωπαίου Πολίτη και, παρά την προστασία που θα έπρεπε να του δώσει αυτή η βράβευση, αντιμετωπίζει απειλές. Νομίζω ότι το Κοινοβούλιο πρέπει να έχει ανοιχτά τα μάτια του στο θέμα αυτό.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-199-0000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard Batten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Theresa May has outlined her great repeal bill, but nothing will happen for six months until Article 50 is triggered in March next year. Two years of negotiations will then follow to arrive at the elusive deal supposedly required before the UK can leave the EU, and we won’t actually leave until April 2019. By then, we will have had another two-and-a-half years of uncontrolled EU immigration and not a single EU law will have been repealed.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is a much simpler solution. Forget Article 50. Repeal the European Communities Act and return supremacy to our parliament. Introduce emergency legislation on immigration and border controls. Offer the EU a choice: continued mutual tariff-free access to the single market, or trade under WTO terms. The choice is theirs. Existing EU directives would continue to apply until amended or repealed by parliament. That is the way to make Brexit mean Brexit now.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, l'Union européenne s'est construite contre la volonté des peuples. Elle le paie très cher aujourd'hui. Après le peuple britannique, qui a voté le Brexit, c'est au tour du peuple hongrois de lui donner une leçon de démocratie directe.</p>
      <p sl="en">98 % des Hongrois qui ont participé au référendum du 2 octobre ont en effet voté contre l'accueil de 1 300 migrants que l'Union voulait imposer à la Hongrie. Même si seulement 40 % des électeurs inscrits se sont déplacés, c'est un score sans appel. La conséquence est claire: le plan européen de relocalisation de 160 000 migrants ne sera pas exécuté. C'est une victoire éclatante des peuples sur la folle politique d'immigration programmée par Bruxelles.</p>
      <p sl="en">60 ans après sa révolte contre l'Union soviétique, la Hongrie s'est révoltée contre l'Union européenne. L'âme européenne est toujours vivante, la résistance à la destruction des identités nationales s'organise. Demain, la France donnera le coup de grâce à l'Union en se prononçant par référendum pour le Frexit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-0000" speaker_id="124879" name="Janusz Korwin-Mikke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Bardzo przepraszam, ale będę mówił na bardzo podobny temat – nie tyle może o Węgrzech, co o Parlamencie Europejskim, ponieważ zdumiewa mnie, że w tym Parlamencie co chwila słyszę słowa o demokracji, natomiast gdy na Węgrzech demokratycznie coś się robi, bo rzeczywiście większość – dziewięćdziesiąt osiem procent głosujących jest prawdą – a zatem ten procent jest znacznie większy niż procent chcących głosować na panią Clintonową w Ameryce, to wtedy Unia chce robić dyskusję na temat tego, że jest zaniepokojona sytuacją na Węgrzech.</p>
      <p sl="en">Otóż chciałem zwrócić uwagę, że jeżeli ktoś jest demokratą – ja a nie jestem demokratą – ale jeżeli Państwo jesteście demokratami, to musicie przyjąć do wiadomości, że większość Węgrów sobie czegoś życzy. I cieszę się tylko, że Unia Europejska nie ma jeszcze armii, bo gdyby Unia Europejska miała armię, to z całą pewnością już by niosła pomoc narodowi węgierskiemu, tak jak armia sowiecka, o czym pamięta pan Tőkés, niosła tę pomoc w roku 1956.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-0000" speaker_id="102886" name="Ildikó Gáll-Pelcz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Úr! Mi magyarok mindig népszavazáson döntünk a jövőnket érintő legfontosabb ügyekről, így volt ez tegnap is. Egyértelműen a magyarok eldöntötték, kivel szeretnének együtt élni és kivel nem szeretnének együtt élni. Ez a népszavazás tisztázta a magyarok álláspontját. A kötelező betelepítési kvótacsomag jelentős gazdasági, kulturális és biztonsági kockázattal jár, ezért nem tudjuk azt vállalni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Köszönöm mindenkinek, aki elment szavazni. Aki otthon maradt, az pedig a többiekre bízta ezt a döntést. Azt gondolom, hogy ez a döntés most a jövőnkről szól, gyermekeinkről szól. Tisztelettel kérem a demokratikus Európai Uniót, ahogy a Brexit esetén tette, tartsa tiszteletben a magyar polgároknak az ezirányú döntését. 3 millió 300 ezren döntöttek úgy, hogy nemet mondanak erre a kötelező kvótacsomagra. 10 emberből 9 döntött úgy, hogy nemet mond.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sokan azt szeretnék, hogyha elbagatellizálnánk ezt a 3 millió 300 ezer embert, de ez sokkal több, mint ahányan igennel szavaztak az EU-hoz való csatlakozásra. Sőt, sokkal több, mint amennyi szavazatot 2014-ben kaptunk, amikor megerősítettek bennünket a kormányzásban – pontosan 1 millióval több. 10%-kal több, magasabb a részvétel, mint az EU-ról szóló szavazáson volt. Köszönöm, Elnök úr. Kérem, tartsák tiszteletben a döntésünket.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Priekšsēdētāj! Godātie kolēģi, godātie Komisijas pārstāvji! Me miyvars Saqartvelo — tulkojot no gruzīnu valodas, tas nozīmē “es mīlu Gruziju”. Es domāju un esmu pārliecināts, ka vairākums deputātu, kas ir Eiropas Parlamenta deputāti, varētu teikt to pašu. Tad man ir pretjautājums — kāpēc mēs, Eiropas Savienība, piemānām Gruziju? Kāpēc mēs, Eiropas Parlaments, nezinām, kas notiek Padomē, un Eiropas Savienības Padome dotajā brīdī ir bremzējošais faktors, kas reāli uz doto brīdi neļauj ieviest bezvīzu režīmu starp Gruziju un Eiropas Savienību. Man ir kauns, kolēģi, jo esošajā situācijā, kad plosās krīze Eiropas Savienībā, mums nav īpaši daudz draugu, bet Gruzija ir viens no sabiedrotajiem un draugiem. Es aicinu Eiropas Parlamentu aktīvi iesaistīties šajā procesā un ieviest bezvīzu režīmu ar Gruziju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-204-0000" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Po powrocie po raz pierwszy przemawiając, chciałam podziękować za troskę, jaką Parlament Europejski otacza Polskę w ostatnim roku przez wprowadzenie debat na temat praworządności i praw kobiet. Szkoda tylko, że nie oferowano podobnej pomocy za czasów poprzednich rządów, kiedy zniszczono wiele dziedzin życia, prowokując wielomilionową emigrację moich rodaków – najczęściej młodych, wykształconych i przedsiębiorczych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Łatwo jest niszczyć, trudniej odbudowywać, co stara się robić obecny rząd. Rozmiar zniszczenia i głębię destrukcji w jednym tylko – moralnym – aspekcie można było zobaczyć w Polsce dzisiaj, kiedy organizowano czarny poniedziałek. Były marsze i strajki ubranych na czarno zwolenników cywilizacji śmierci, którzy zamiast opłakiwać miliony zabitych w majestacie prawa nienarodzonych dzieci, w całkowitym bezwstydzie walczą nadal o barbarzyńskie prawo do zabijania poczętych dzieci w łonach matek.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-205-0000" speaker_id="125091" name="Σοφία Σακοράφα (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">GUE/NGL). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, πριν από ακριβώς ένα χρόνο, κατ’ επιταγή των Ευρωπαίων πολιτών, εκδώσαμε το ψήφισμα για το δικαίωμα στο νερό. Απαιτούσαμε τότε, επί λέξει, από την Επιτροπή να μην προωθήσει με κανένα τρόπο την ιδιωτικοποίηση των επιχειρήσεων ύδρευσης στο πλαίσιο προγραμμάτων οικονομικής προσαρμογής ή οποιασδήποτε άλλης ενωσιακής διαδικασίας και να εξαιρέσει μόνιμα τις υπηρεσίες ύδρευσης από τους κανόνες της εσωτερικής αγοράς και από οποιαδήποτε εμπορική συμφωνία, καθώς και να τις παρέχει σε προσιτές τιμές. Χθες, το Κουαρτέτο, σε συνεργασία με την πρόθυμη και υπάκουη ελληνική κυβέρνηση, ενέταξε στο Υπερταμείο Ιδιωτικοποιήσεων το νερό και την αποχέτευση της Ελλάδας για 99 ολόκληρα χρόνια. Ευτυχώς, ο Έλληνας Υπουργός Οικονομικών, Ευκλείδης Τσακαλώτος, δήλωσε ότι, όσο είναι αυτός υπουργός, δεν πρόκειται να πουληθούν. Απ’ ό,τι φαίνεται, το μόνο που μας μένει για να υπερασπιστούμε τόσο την αξιοπρέπεια και τον λόγο ύπαρξης του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου, όσο και τη βαρύτητα των ψηφισμάτων μας, είναι να υποχρεώσουμε ή το Κουαρτέτο να χρίσει τον κύριο Τσακαλώτο μόνιμο Υπουργό Οικονομικών για τα επόμενα 99 χρόνια ή την Επιτροπή να συμμορφώνεται με τα ψηφίσματά μας. Δυστυχώς, κύριε Πρόεδρε, και τα δύο φαντάζουν το ίδιο εξωπραγματικά.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-206-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε πρόεδρε, οι δηλώσεις Erdoğan με τις οποίες αμφισβητεί τη Συνθήκη της Λωζάνης είναι ιδιαίτερα επικίνδυνες, όπως είναι και αυτές του τουρκικού ρεπουμπλικανικού κόμματος που εγείρουν ανύπαρκτα ζητήματα κυριαρχίας για 16 ελληνικά νησιά και θέτουν ζήτημα γκρίζων ζωνών και συνόρων, διαιωνίζοντας έτσι την διαχρονική προκλητικότητα που εκφράζεται με τις συνεχείς παραβιάσεις του ελληνικού θαλάσσιου και εναέριου χώρου, με τις διαρκείς προκλήσεις κατά της Κύπρου, με την αμφισβήτηση της Αποκλειστικής Οικονομικής Ζώνης. Αποκαλύπτεται το τι σημαίνει συμμαχία Ελλάδας-Τουρκίας στο πλαίσιο του ΝΑΤΟ και τι είναι τα λεγόμενα «ευρωπαϊκά σύνορα», όταν η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και το ΝΑΤΟ ενθαρρύνουν την τουρκική επιθετικότητα στο όνομα της συμφωνίας Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης-Τουρκίας και της διχοτομικής λύσης που προωθείται στο Κυπριακό.</p>
      <p sl="en">Το ότι από Επίτροπο της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης εγείρεται επίσης το ανύπαρκτο ζήτημα των Τσάμηδων φανερώνει το πόσο επικίνδυνη είναι η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και όσοι τη στηρίζουν, όπως είναι η κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ–ΑΝΕΛ, αφού η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση αμφισβητεί σύνορα και αποκαθιστά πρώην συνεργάτες των Ναζί. Οφείλουν οι λαοί με την πάλη τους να είναι σε επαγρύπνηση ενάντια σε όλες τις δυνάμεις που, είτε εφησυχάζουν, είτε καλλιεργούν το εθνικιστικό μίσος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-207-0000" speaker_id="124988" name="Deirdre Clune" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, yesterday the British Prime Minister announced her intention formally to trigger Article 50 by the end of March 2017. Politically, socially and economically, Brexit has enormous consequences for the island of Ireland. It is said that Ireland is the country that will be most affected by Brexit. We export 50% of our beef, 60% of cheese and 85% of our agricultural products to the UK. But the most important issue I want to comment on tonight is the peace process.</p>
      <p sl="en">A lot of time, effort and energy has been invested, with the help of the European Union, in ensuring that there is peace on the island of Ireland. Communities live together side by side, there are no divisions, there is free movement of people across the border. We have agencies such as Tourism Ireland and InterTrade Ireland working on an all-Ireland basis, promoting the island of Ireland and activities on the island of Ireland.</p>
      <p sl="en">We do not want to see that border reinstated. We want to ensure that the implications of such a border are recognised: that there could be a negative influence on the peace process, which has been supported by the European Union. I would ask this House, and everybody here, to bear in mind the peace process and the border in Ireland. We do not want to see that border reinstated, and it behoves everybody to pay due attention to that issue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-208-0000" speaker_id="124723" name="Péter Niedermüller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, a tegnapi magyarországi népszavazáson a választópolgároknak mindössze 40%-a vett részt, illetve szavazott érvényesen. A többi, közel 5 millió állampolgár bojkottálta ezt a szégyenletes színjátékot, vagy pedig kisebb részük érvénytelenül szavazott. Ez azt jelenti, hogy az Orbán által kikényszerített népszavazás érvénytelen és eredménytelen volt. A népszavazás megmutatta: Orbán szélsőjobboldali gyűlöletpolitikájának ma Magyarországon nincs semmiféle többsége. Orbán vereséget szenvedett, a demokratikus Magyarország győzött, és ezen a tényen semmiféle hazug kormányzati propaganda sem tud változtatni. A magyarok többsége az Európai Unió szellemét, értékeit választotta.</p>
      <p sl="en">A magyar demokraták megérdemlik, hogy az Európai Unió támogassa őket, hiszen ez a népszavazás Európáról, a közös európai értékekről, Európa jövőjéről is szólt. Ebből az eredményből az Európai Unió bátorságot meríthet, hogy ne engedjen a zsarolóknak, és következetesen, az eddigieknél sokkal bátrabban szálljon szembe a szélsőjobboldali populizmussal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-209-0000" speaker_id="124891" name="Zdzisław Krasnodębski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Ja trochę zmienię temat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Otóż przed paroma dniami odbyły się uroczystości upamiętniające siedemdziesiątą piątą rocznicę masakry w Babim Jarze pod Kijowem, gdzie zamordowano od stu do stu pięćdziesięciu tysięcy osób, w tym co najmniej trzydzieści cztery tysiące Żydów. Oprócz Żydów, głównych ofiar zbrodni, w tym miejscu zabijano także Polaków, Romów, partyzantów, żołnierzy sowieckich oraz przedstawicieli ukraińskiej elity, a także członków organizacji ukraińskich nacjonalistów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pouczająca jest późniejsza historia Babiego Jaru – historia prób zafałszowania przeszłości. Dziś także nie jesteśmy wolni od takich skłonności. Pamiętając o zawiłościach historii, z szacunku dla ofiar, powinniśmy jasno mówić kto, jakie państwo, jaki naród w to państwo zorganizowany, był sprawcą tej zbrodni. Powinniśmy pamiętać, jaka to ideologia, jakie dążenia motywowały tę zbrodnię.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie powinniśmy się godzić na eugenikę w żadnej postaci. Dzisiejsza neostalinowska maniera obrzucania wszystkich konkurentów politycznych po prawej stronie mianem faszystów to także znak braku szacunku dla ofiar i dążenie do zakłamania przeszłości.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-210-0000" speaker_id="124987" name="Liadh Ní Riada" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, ba mhaith liom tacú leis an méid atá ráite ag na Feisirí ó Éirinn maidir le Brexit, ach táim anseo chun labhairt faoin gclár LEADER tráthnóna mar go bhfuil sé práinneach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Is léir go bhfuil fadhbanna ollmhóra ceangailte leis an bpróiseas nua; is clár iontach é LEADER agus tugann sé spreagadh agus tacaíocht d’fhorbairt eacnamaíochta inár mbailte beaga agus pobail tuaithe. Tá go leor fianaise ann trí na blianta gur oibrigh sé go maith mar chlár agus gur cruthaíodh neart postanna dá bharr. Ní thuigim mar sin cén fáth go bhfuil an méid sin ciorruithe déanta insan gclár féin. Ní thuigim cén fáth gur aistríodh na rialacha agus go bhfuil sé anois faoi smacht na bpolaiteoirí seachas an pobal. Níl sé trédhearcach agus níl sé féarálta agus níl aon soiléiriú ann maidir leis an bpróiseas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tá an t-am anois ann don gCoimisiún ceisteanna a ardú faoin slí ina bhfuil an clár seo ag feidhmiú. Is iad ár bpobal atá ag fulaingt gan an maoiniú, agus is measa atá an scéal seo ag éirí. Ba mhaith liom go dtabharfaí aird ar an gceist thábhachtach seo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-211-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, politica de coeziune este un mecanism conceput la nivelul Uniunii Europene în vederea înlăturării disparităților sociale dintre statele membre, astfel încât fiecare cetățean european să se simtă la el acasă, indiferent dacă se află în estul sau vestul Europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Astăzi în Europa, criza economică, gestionarea ineficientă a crizei imigranților au contribuit la creșterea populismului cu efecte grave asupra viitorului politicii de coeziune. Multe voci, în special din statele vestice, vin să conteste eficiența acestei politici, apreciindu-se că nu există modalități clare de exprimare a avantajelor de care ar urma să beneficieze și cetățenii din statele net donatoare în urma acestor investiții. Atrag însă atenția că statele care sunt azi net donatoare au beneficiat de-a lungul timpului de resurse financiare consistente de la Uniunea Europeană. Subliniez totodată că acești bani se reîntorc în bună măsură în aceste state, deoarece aproape toate investițiile realizate în țările din est sunt efectuate de firme cu tehnică sau materiale care provin din vestul Europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-212-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, since October 2015 Nnamdi Kanu, a British-Nigerian citizen and leader of the indigenous people of Biafra, has been unlawfully imprisoned by Nigeria’s Department of State Services, despite the fact that all criminal charges against him were dropped and a court order has been issued for him to be released on bail. Chapter 4, Section 39, of the Nigerian Constitution says that ‘every person shall be entitled to freedom of expression, including freedom to hold opinions and to receive and impart ideas and information without interference’. I therefore call upon the President of Nigeria, Muhammadu Buhari, to uphold his country’s constitution and to ensure Nnamdi Kanu’s immediate and safe release, as well as that of his co-defendants, Benjamin Madubugwu and David Nwauwisiare.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Nigerian Government must guarantee the freedom of expression of all Nigerian citizens, including their right to protest without intimidation, and must end the violence towards those who identify as Biafran. I call, too, on my colleagues here in the European Parliament to do much more to promote human rights in Nigeria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213-0000" speaker_id="124984" name="Lynn Boylan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, while many are speaking tonight on Brexit, I would like to raise another issue relating to Britain. Between 2002 and 2010 it is known that the British Metropolitan Police sent undercover police to infiltrate democratic campaign groups in Ireland, the six counties, Scotland and Germany. Some of these undercover police incited violent actions at protests. Others testified under their aliases, leading to over 50 convictions being overturned in England and Wales.</p>
      <p sl="en">More disturbing is the fact that some sexually exploited female activists and even fathered children. Despite Scotland, the North of Ireland and Germany rightly demanding answers from the British Metropolitan Police, Irish Justice Minister Frances Fitzgerald is refusing to demand how many undercover police operated in Ireland, which organisations were targeted and who authorised their presence in Ireland.</p>
      <p sl="en">Brexit will not excuse Theresa May from explaining what British undercover police were doing in Ireland. Their victims demand answers and Minister Fitzgerald should join her counterparts in demanding those answers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-214-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, szeretném felhívni az Európai Parlament tagjainak figyelmét, hogy Romániában az állam továbbra is üldözi a közösségek szimbólumhasználatát. Legutóbb az Egyesült Államok bukaresti nagykövete is megtapasztalhatta ezt, amikor olyan fotó jelent meg róla a médiában, amelyen helyi önkormányzati vezetők társaságában egy székely zászlót tartott. A román médiában ez a gesztus elég volt arra, hogy botrány törjön ki, még a Külügyminisztérium is közleményben tiltakozott a gesztus ellen, a létező érzékenységek ismeretének fontosságát hangsúlyozva. Persze nem minden közösségi szimbólum okoz ekkora felzúdulást Romániában, sok tájegységnek megvan a saját zászlaja, amelyet szabadon használhat. Csupán a többségében magyarok által lakott Székelyföld zászlója ellen tiltakoznak a román hatóságok.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ez pedig diszkrimináció, még akkor is, ha minden létező érzékenységre tekintettel vagyunk. Sőt, Romániában a bíróság úgy döntött, hogy a Székelyföld megnevezést nem lehet turisztikai desztinációként sem használni, azaz nem lehet megnevezni egy térséget azon a néven, amelyen azt a lakói nevezik több száz éve. Kérem, döntsék el, hogy sérti-e az európai érzékenységet ez a jelenség.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-215-0000" speaker_id="103488" name="Sergio Gutiérrez Prieto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, hace unos días, Draghi, el presidente del Banco Central Europeo, recomendó a los Estados miembros incrementar los salarios como una medida más para la recuperación. Lo dijo por razones económicas y tenía razón.</p>
      <p sl="en">El 80 % de las exportaciones en Europa se producen entre Estados miembros; por lo tanto, los salarios son una medida fundamental para fortalecer la demanda interna y para impulsar el crecimiento económico. Pero, además, hay razones sociales más que evidentes, porque solo los salarios dignos producen un trabajo decente, y solo los trabajos y los salarios decentes producirán la posibilidad de mantener el Estado del bienestar.</p>
      <p sl="en">¿Cómo podemos hacer que las palabras de Draghi se conviertan más en un hecho que en una recomendación? Desde la Unión Europea tenemos dos mecanismos: el primero, el Semestre Europeo. Tenemos que introducir esa recomendación en el marco de los programas nacionales de reformas. Tenemos que animar a los Estados miembros a que lo hagan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y segundo, el Grupo Socialista apuesta por un marco europeo de salarios mínimos; no por un salario mínimo europeo, imposible hoy dadas las divergencias, sino por un marco en el que se establezca una horquilla y en el que animemos, obliguemos a los Estados miembros a establecer un mínimo para evitar ese fenómeno del que hoy tanto nos avergonzamos en Europa, denominado la pobreza laboral, es decir, trabajadores que, aun dedicando horas de la semana a trabajar, no son capaces de llegar a fin de mes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Acabemos con la pobreza laboral con el único mecanismo real que tenemos: los trabajos dignos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-216-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, bhí sé de phribhléid agamsa a bheith mar ionadaí ar son na Parlaiminte i bPáras i mí na Nollag, nuair a d’éirigh linn COP 21 – an comhréiteach domhanda stairiúil sin – a bhaint amach. Dar ndóigh thug an Coimisiún, go háirithe an Coimisinéir Arias Cañete, an-cheannasaíocht insna cainteanna sin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Anois, caithfimid é a chur i bhfeidhm. Arís, tá moladh ag dul go dtí Uachtaránacht na Slóvaice mar gur éirigh leo tacaíocht a fháil ó na hAirí chun glacaint leis an gcomhréiteach sin. Anois tá an sprioc de 55% a bhí riachtanach bainte amach againn agus is féidir linn dul chun cinn maith agus éifeachtach a dhéanamh i Marrakech an mhí seo chugainn. Agus beidh mé féin ann arís, buíochas le Dia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ach ina dhiaidh sin, beidh orainn sa Pharlaimint agus san Eoraip ár spriocanna féin a bhaint amach agus caithfimid é sin a dhéanamh gan cur isteach ar iomaíochas an Aontais, jabanna, fás, geilleagar agus mar sin de. Ach is féidir linn é a dhéanamh má chuirimid agus oibrímid le chéile. Tá súil agam go n-éireoidh linn é sin a dhéanamh.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-217-0000" speaker_id="124722" name="Csaba Molnár" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr! Orbán Viktor magyar miniszterelnök Európa-ellenes álnépszavazása tegnap érvénytelen lett. Ezzel a miniszterelnök politikája megbukott, Orbán hatalmas vereséget szenvedett el. Jó hír ez Európának, és hatalmas győzelem ez Magyarországnak és a magyar embereknek. Egyrészt jó hír Európának, hiszen ezek után a magyar miniszterelnök nem tud abban a pózban tetszelegni, hogy ő az európai kisemberek véleményét képviseli a brüsszeli politikai elittel szemben, hiszen láthatóan már saját országában, saját hazájában is kisebbségbe került. Másrészt hatalmas győzelem ez a magyar embereknek, mert vereséget szenvedett a gyűlölet, vereséget szenvedett az a gyűlöletkampány, amelyre a magyar kormány a magyar adófizetők pénzéből többet költött, mint amire a brit kilépést megelőző népszavazáson Nagy-Britanniában költöttek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bárhol Európában ennek a következménye a miniszterelnök lemondása lenne. Orbán persze nem fog lemondani, hiszen nem engedi hiúsága, hatalomvágya és üzleti érdekei. De egy dolog biztos! A bukása már közelebb került! Egyre közelebb vagyunk ahhoz, hogy oda juttassuk Orbán Viktort, ahova ő, és a hozzá hasonló szélsőséges kalandorok valók: a történelem szemétdombjára.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-218-0000" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, yesterday the British Prime Minister announced that the negotiations for the UK to leave the EU would start at the end of March 2017. The lack of any commitment to the importance of the EU single market was shocking. The British Government is about to start negotiations and it cannot commit to making the EU single market a key factor in any negotiations. The single market is pivotal to the UK’s current market access for goods and services. Throw that away and you put British jobs and the UK economy at risk. Only today, we saw the fall in the value of the pound. Hundreds of thousands of British jobs rely on our accessing the EU single market. Why is it important? It is important because the single market allows us to create one set of rules that cover 20 different countries, covering 500 million citizens, allowing certainty for business and security and quality for consumers. It is no coincidence that here in this Parliament, since the single market – or internal market – committee was created in 2004, it has had only had UK chairs in Phillip Whitehead, Arlene McCarthy, Malcolm Harbour and currently Vicky Ford. The EU single market matters to the UK and the UK should recognise this. The UK Government should recognise this before it irrevocably damages the British economy and destroys British jobs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-219-0000" speaker_id="129256" name="Emilian Pavel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule Președinte, Uniunea Europeană este și rămâne indispensabilă pentru noi toți. Această construcție are în fața sa un viitor de câștigat pentru cetățenii săi, iar eu cred că o va face. Din păcate, însă, politicieni precum Nigel Farage, Viktor Orban, Marine Le Pen sau alții și alții au și ei nevoie de Uniunea Europeană pentru a arunca orice problemă națională în cârca altora. Ce nu spun ei este faptul că Uniunea Europeană există prin voința statelor membre. Că Parlamentul European este ales direct de cetățeni și că, da, Comisia Europeană nu este un templu al tehnocraților, ci o instituție eminamente politică, formată în urma deciziilor luate împreună de aceleași state membre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dacă Uniunea Europeană are o față, ea nu este una ascunsă, așa cum sugerează unii. Fața Uniunii Europene sunt toate statele membre, reduse în curând, cu sprijinul populismului și demagogiei, la un număr de douăzeci și șapte. Dar responsabile toate pentru ce face și pentru cum funcționează Uniunea Europeană. Acest adevăr trebuie comunicat oamenilor cât mai des posibil.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-220-0000" speaker_id="124932" name="Josep-Maria Terricabras" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor Presidente, la amenaza de suspensión de fondos europeos para España y Portugal es una cuestión importante. Los compromisos, desde luego, hay que cumplirlos, pero algún otro país más poderoso no los ha cumplido con anterioridad y no ha ocurrido nada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me parece que en un momento tan delicado de la Unión Europea en que los ciudadanos sienten poco afecto por la Unión y, sobre todo, por los poderes centrales de la Unión, sería realmente muy grave que se produjera esta suspensión de fondos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Además, hay que reconocer y aceptar que España y Portugal han pasado por un periodo cruel de crisis y de austeridad, y ellos no pueden pagar, como nadie ha pagado hasta ahora, los platos rotos de esta situación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-221-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Con questo si conclude il punto.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. Agenda for next sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
