<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20170202.EN" lang="en" date="2017-02-02" place="Brussels" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Democracy and justice in Romania (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-006-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la discussione sulla dichiarazione della Commissione sulla democrazia e la giustizia in Romania.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-007-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Frans Timmermans" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">First Vice-President of the Commission. – Mr President, fate has dictated that for the last 28 years, in some way or form, I have been a close follower of developments in Romania, and if you see the progress made over that period of time, you can only be astonished by the force of the Romanian people’s will to become a fully fledged European, democratic, open nation. This development was reflected in the recent report on the cooperation and verification mechanism (CVM) which the Commission published last week, where we had an overview of the progress of the CVM over the past decade.</p>
      <p sl="en">It was not a linear development: sometimes, elements went fast; sometimes they went a bit more slowly, but still the development was spectacular. We could say that Romania is now in the final leg of this long, long marathon, heading to a situation where development towards the strengthening of the rule of law is irreversible, and that is the criterion the Commission now applies.</p>
      <p sl="en">It should be irreversible and, in this context, what we have seen over the last couple of days is worrying. The emergency ordinance and the draft legislation pertaining to the fight against corruption cannot be interpreted as anything other than a step back from the progress we have seen in the last decade, and I would urgently call upon the Romanian Government to reconsider what they have done, both with the emergency ordinance and with the draft legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Like any European nation, the Romanian nation deserves politicians and governments who support the fight against corruption, who want to rid their societies completely of corruption. And the efforts made in Romania – I must underline this – have been phenomenal, with really very good progress. So, why would you, in the final metres of a marathon, turn back and go in the other direction?</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to call upon the Government not to go down that road. And we have seen the protests in Romania. We have seen the very clear worries expressed by the Romanian judiciary on this. Let them finish their job so that we can then come to the conclusion that developments are irreversible.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has a direct interest in all of this because the legislation, if it is adopted, could also affect the disbursement of European funds in Romania, so we have to be very careful that we assess that. We will analyse the draft legislation and look into these matters, but today, for me, the most important thing is to make this political point to the Romanian Government: do not turn your back on this development. Do not go the other way. Continue. Hold this course, however painful it might sometimes be, because you do it in the service of your population. All Romanians deserve a country freed of corruption. And look at what has been achieved! Do not ever forget that.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me end by referring to someone whom I regard as one of the biggest, most important Romanians of the 20th century. Sadly he has been dead for quite some time, but for me he reflects the European spirit of that great nation. It is Paul Celan. He was a Romanian who spoke German. He was a Jew, who lived in exile in Paris. He was thus a true European, not by choice but by fate because first the Nazi persecution then the Communist oppression prevented him from staying in his native land. But he remained a European, living in Paris, writing his poetry in German even in the 1940s, and believing in this European dream of European brotherhood. And he was a true son of the Romanian nation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Romania needs to take its place amid the European nations without being seen as in any way different. To achieve its dream it also needs to rid itself of corruption. It is almost there: the development is almost irreversible. So please, I say to the Romanian Government: do not take any steps in the other direction.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-008-0000" speaker_id="125027" name="Esteban González Pons" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, al igual que acaba de expresar el vicepresidente Timmermans, nos preocupan las decisiones que está tomando el Gobierno rumano. A los 29 días de ocupar el cargo, sus prioridades son debilitar la lucha contra la corrupción y rebajar las penas de prisión a los corruptos. El fiscal general, el Consejo General de la Magistratura y hasta el presidente de la República han pedido corregir estos dos excesos y el Gobierno rumano no les escucha. Los ciudadanos están manifestándose en las calles de todo el país y el Gobierno rumano también los ignora.</p>
      <p sl="en">Que nadie se confunda. El problema no es si nos gustan o no las leyes que aprueba el Gobierno de un Estado miembro. El problema es si estas leyes debilitan la calidad de la democracia, la calidad de la justicia, la calidad del Estado de Derecho. Y eso es lo que estamos debatiendo esta mañana. Nada más, pero nada menos. Debatimos con pleno respeto a la soberanía política institucional de Rumanía pero, al mismo tiempo, con plena responsabilidad. Porque este Parlamento representa también a los veinte millones de rumanos. La voz de los rumanos tiene el mismo derecho a ser escuchada en el Parlamento de Estrasburgo o en el Parlamento de Bruselas que en el Parlamento de Bucarest.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señorías, en días como hoy conviene recordar que pertenecer a la Unión Europea no es solo recibir fondos y compartir fronteras. Es asumir una serie de principios y valores y, sobre todo, el compromiso de mantenerlos en el futuro. Es asumir que en Europa, en Europa, nadie está por encima de la ley y velar por que la justicia sea exactamente igual para todos. Es asumir que los delitos nunca quedan impunes y que es obligatorio perseguirlos y llevarlos ante los tribunales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un gobierno puede tener mayoría parlamentaria, pero eso no significa que no esté equivocado, eso no significa que pueda hacer cualquier cosa. En el Estado de Derecho la fuerza de la ley tiene límites en los valores constitucionales que justifican nuestra convivencia. En el Estado de Derecho la ley no puede ser injusta. En el Estado de Derecho la ley no puede ser un caballo de Troya contra la democracia. No se puede gobernar para que haya ciudadanos de primera y de segunda ni ciudadanos que tengan que cumplir la ley y otros que puedan vivir al margen de la ley. La acción del nuevo Gobierno de Rumanía —como ha dicho el señor Timmermans— está tirando por tierra años y años de lucha contra la corrupción, fomentando la impunidad. Y las conductas abusivas pueden hacer retroceder a Rumanía.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta es una alerta que se enciende en el Parlamento Europeo. El Gobierno de Rumanía aún está a tiempo de rectificar, y le pedimos formalmente desde el Parlamento Europeo que rectifique. Las cosas en democracia no pueden hacerse de cualquier manera y cuando uno se equivoca tiene que saber rectificar. Ningún gobierno del mundo está por encima de la ley. Las leyes son del pueblo y cuando el gobierno actúa contra el pueblo pierde el título que le permite llamarse un gobierno democrático. Gobernar a favor de la corrupción es gobernar en contra de la democracia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-009-0000" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef Weidenholzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Für die S&amp;D-Fraktion ist die heutige Debatte der Beginn einer sorgfältigen und konstruktiven Auseinandersetzung mit den Vorgängen in Rumänien. Rechtsstaatlichkeit und der Grundsatz der Gewaltenteilung sind für uns unverrückbare Prinzipien; sie haben universelle Bedeutung und müssen für alle Mitgliedstaaten gelten. Wo immer diese Grundsätze verletzt werden, müssen wir dagegen auftreten. Wir nehmen diese Debatte sehr ernst, und die Situation verträgt kein parteipolitisches Hickhack; deshalb muss auf diese Debatte eine detaillierte Erörterung im LIBE-Ausschuss folgen, und dazu gehört auch eine Informationsreise nach Rumänien.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir dürfen uns nicht von einer tagespolitischen Oberflächlichkeit verführen lassen: Wir müssen in die Tiefe. Alle Fakten müssen auf den Tisch, und alle Akteure müssen auf den Prüfstand. Die Geißel Korruption kann man nur ausrotten, wenn die Analyse schonungslos angelegt wird. Wir müssen über die Rolle der Institutionen reden und darüber, inwieweit sie ihren Verpflichtungen nachkommen, über das Strafvollzugssystem und darüber, wie Korruptionsverbrechen geahndet werden, über den Grundsatz der Verhältnismäßigkeit und die Bedeutung der Prävention und auch über die Rolle der Geheimdienste bei der Korruptionsbekämpfung. Unserer Meinung nach haben sie da nichts verloren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es geht vor allem darum, die Unabhängigkeit der Justiz, der Strafverfolgung und der Gerichtsbarkeit zu stärken. Diese Fragen werden wir im LIBE-Ausschuss nachdrücklich, schonungslos und mit dem politischen Willen, nicht tagespolitisches Kleingeld zu wechseln, führen. Es geht darum, die Situation in Rumänien zu verbessern und das zu machen, was der Herr Vizepräsident gerade gesagt hat, nämlich auch noch die letzten Meter erfolgreich zu bestreiten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-010-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului ECR. – Domnule președinte, acum două nopți, guvernul socialist din România a modificat, prin ordonanță de urgență, Codul penal și Codul de procedură penală. Modificările aduse Codului de penal și de procedură penală au fost publicate în jurul orei unu noaptea în Monitorul Oficial.</p>
      <p sl="en">Știți care sunt titlurile din presa românească? Acest guvern este numit guvern de hoți, mafia instalată la guvern, grup de crimă organizată, guvern de bandiți. Sigur, pentru că au acționat noaptea, pe neașteptate, fără să anunțe pe nimeni, fără să fie pe ordinea de zi și au modificat Codul penal și de procedură penală ca să se scape pe ei, ca să scape, în primul rând, președintele Partidului Socialist din România, domnul Dragnea, care mai are o condamnare de doi ani de zile pentru fraudă electorală și care risca încă una acum, dar a scăpat de dosar pentru că, prin aceste ordonanțe - asta era urgența: ordonanțe de urgență - Dragnea, președintele Partidului Socialist din România, nu mai poate fi judecat în al doilea dosar pentru că și-a abrogat această infracțiune, nu mai există. Deci să modifici abuzul în serviciu, abuzul de putere care există în toate țările din lumea asta, în urma căruia scapă foarte mulți politicieni, foarte mulți din administrație, foarte mulți din Partidul Socialist și ALDE care sunt împreună la guvernare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Știți că este lumea în stradă? Acum o săptămână erau o sută de mii de oameni în București, duminică, tocmai ca să prevină adoptarea peste noapte, ca bandiții să adopte apoi aceste ordonanțe de urgență. Și aseară au fost pe stradă, în București, circa două sute de mii de oameni și alți două sute de mii de oameni, cel puțin, în toată țara, aproape jumătate de milion de oameni au ieșit în stradă și vor ieși în fiecare zi în stradă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Singurul lucru pe care Parlamentul poate să-l facă și trebuie să-l facă, și Comisia, este să ceară ca, până pe 9 februarie, când intră în vigoare modificările la Codul penal să ceară acestui guvern să revoce tot prin ordonanță de urgență acea ordonanță de urgență care a modificat Codul penal. Atât, nicio misiune. Ce să verificați în misiune? După ce s-a întâmplat și când nimic nu se mai poate întoarce? Acum duceți-vă, mâine, în misiune, dacă vreți! Duceți-vă lângă oameni, fiți lângă poporul român, lângă poporul român și nu lângă hoți!</p>
      <p sl="en">Și aș mai spune ceva: tocmai s-a anunțat ieri că vineri urmează o nouă lovitură: vor să desființeze Direcția Națională Anticorupție, vor să nu mai fie anchetați.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deci, duceți-vă în România, dar mâine, nu după 9 februarie când intră în vigoare modificările la Codul penal, dacă chiar sunteți corecți și alături de România și de români!</p>
      <p sl="en">(Vorbitorul a acceptat să răspundă unei întrebări adresate în conformitate cu procedura „cartonașului albastru” (articolul 162 alineatul (8) din Regulamentul de procedură)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-011-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Ioan Mircea Paşcu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card question. – Madam, as you surely know, last night the anti-corruption prosecutors were ordered to initiate penal investigations against the officials and civil servants who dared to draw up draft legislation perceived as a curtailment of their absolute power. Is that not a perfect example of anti-corruption being abused?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-012-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Răspuns la o întrebare adresată în conformitate cu procedura „cartonașului albastru”. – Mulțumesc foarte mult pentru întrebare, domnule Pașcu. Exact aceasta trebuie să se întâmple: hoții trebuie anchetați. În România, hoții trebuie anchetați și au fost anchetați, că de aceea am intrat în Uniunea Europeană cu lupta anticorupție, cu stegulețul roșu, pe care tot socialiștii l-au lăsat. Nu este normal să îi ancheteze? Ca să nu mai spun că, tot prin acea ordonanță de urgență, dată noaptea, nu modifici Codul penal noaptea, la miez de noapte, decât dacă ești hoț.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prin acea ordonanță, au modificat Codul penal ca să se scape și pe ei de ceea ce făceau în noaptea aceea. Au scos favorizarea infractorului, de exemplu. Exact ceea ce au făcut, pentru că sunt peste două mii de dosare din care scapă infractorii. Infractorii trebuie investigați, sigur că da.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-013-0000" speaker_id="96825" name="Norica Nicolai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului ALDE. – Domnule președinte, nimeni nu poate pune în discuție vocația europeană a poporului român. Cum nimeni nu poate pune în discuție opțiunea politică exprimată în decembrie, care a dus la guvernare un guvern PSD-ALDE. De fapt, astăzi la București, domnule comisar, asistăm, sub un pretext care ține de administrarea justiției, la o încercare de răsturnare a unei puteri politice legitim alese. Pentru că această ordonanță, domnule comisar, este realizată în acord cu prevederile Constituției României, care obligă, atunci când Curtea Constituțională declară ca neconstituționale texte de lege, acestea în 45 de zile să fie puse în acord cu legea respectivă. În paranteză, fie spus, un ministru al justiției din guvernul precedent spunea că în România drepturile omului sunt un lux. Da, domnule președinte, sunt un lux pentru că această Curte Constituțională a consacrat faptul că se fac abuzuri cu privire la dreptul de apărare, faptul că sunt interceptări fără mandat de la judecător, că abuzul în serviciu este o incriminare prea largă, că dreptul cetățeanului la garanțiile procesuale nu este respectat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Statul român este motivat să lupte împotriva corupției și a dovedit-o, dar bătălia corupției nu înseamnă în niciun caz justiție selectivă, justiție abuzivă. Justiția trebuie să fie egală pentru toți și, de aceea, salut faptul că vom avea o investigare foarte clară a ceea ce se întâmplă în România și nu o manipulare emoțională.</p>
      <p sl="en">Înțeleg, domnule președinte, că România este un partener credibil și un membru credibil al Uniunii Europene. Nu aș vrea, pentru poporul român, să punem în discuție astăzi această credibilitate sub un pretext pur politic. Inclusiv DNA, principala instituție care se revendică astăzi ca apărător al corupției, a fost înființată prin ordonanță de urgență. Nu putem, domnule președinte, în numele unei bătălii care este corectă, care este legitimă, cu mijloace neoneste să schimbăm o putere politică.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-014-0000" speaker_id="124810" name="Barbara Spinelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo GUE/NGL. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, decine di migliaia di cittadini rumeni scendono in piazza da giorni per protestare contro due decreti legge predisposti dal premier che depenalizzano reati di corruzione sotto una certa soglia di danni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono solidale con la loro battaglia e con la reazione del presidente Iohannis, che ha parlato dei decreti come di un giorno di lutto. Venendo dall'Italia, so cosa intenda quando parla di lutto. In Italia sono stati molteplici i tentativi di depenalizzare la corruzione e perfino la complicità con la mafia negli anni di Berlusconi. Posso assicurarvi che la corruzione ne è uscita rafforzata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trovo soprattutto inquietante il modo in cui i decreti d'urgenza sono stati approvati: di nascosto, di notte, senza prima consultare Parlamento e Corte costituzionale. È un modo di procedere frequente in Europa: il potere esecutivo viene sempre più accentrato e le forze politiche che vincono le elezioni si comportano come se tale vittoria permettesse di abolire i meccanismi di check and balance su cui si fondano le democrazie costituzionali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le proteste dei cittadini e della stampa, in Romania, ci ricordano che anche loro – associazioni e stampa – sono poteri chiamati a frenare il potere centrale, specie in tempi di crisi economica e sociale. Dice il governo rumeno che la depenalizzazione è necessaria per evitare le carceri sovraffollate, denunciate dalla Corte europea dei diritti dell'uomo. È una scusa che non sta in piedi. L'argomento è stato usato anche in Italia. Decreti simili sono adottati per evitare il carcere a qualche decina di politici corrotti. È tutto qui. Cosa che i cittadini, le ONG, i giudici costituzionali, lo stesso presidente, in Romania denunciano, a mio modesto parere, giustamente.</p>
      <p sl="en">(L'oratrice accetta di rispondere a una domanda "cartellino blu" (articolo 162,</p>
      <p sl="en">paragrafo 8, del regolamento))</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-015-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonaşului albastru”. – Stimată colegă, ați vorbit de două ordonanțe: cunoașteți situația reală în România? Știți că nu este vorba de două ordonanțe? Știți că ordonanța de grațiere este trimisă în Parlament sub formă de lege?</p>
      <p sl="en">Și a doua întrebare: dacă președintele țării dumneavoastră ar incita populația mergând la un miting neautorizat - el este mediator, nu incitator- și ar refuza să desecretizeze niște documente legate de cercetările în echipă mixtă SRI și justiție, ați considera imixtiune în justiție? Pentru că experții noștri judiciari, asociațiile profesionale, consideră imixtiune în justiție.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-016-0000" speaker_id="124810" name="Barbara Spinelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Risposta a una domanda "cartellino blu". – Non entro nei dettagli, so che si tratta di due decreti e vi invito soltanto a non parlare di interferenza della giustizia perché anche questo è un linguaggio che conosco, che abbiamo tutti sentito in Italia. Quando la corruzione politica si espande, i responsabili della corruzione dicono in genere che c'è un'interferenza della giustizia. Io vi invito a soltanto a fare attenzione.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-017-0000" speaker_id="96815" name="Judith Sargentini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de Verts/ALE-Fractie. – De massale demonstraties in Boekarest gisteravond en de dagen daarvoor laten zien dat de Roemenen hun democratie heel serieus nemen. Vanochtend las ik dat de minister van Handel zijn positie wil opgeven omdat hij deze voorstellen niet voor zijn rekening wil nemen. Ook dit debat zie ik als een ondersteuning voor het pleidooi om de zaken te herbekijken. Het moet een gevoel van urgentie overbrengen bij de Roemeense regering want corruptie is de rot in het systeem. Het laat het vertrouwen in de rechtsstaat wegebben en ook het vertrouwen tussen jou en de buren. Als dat gebeurt dan ben je heel erg ver van huis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissaris Timmermans zei terecht: Roemenië is op de goede weg, de laatste meters. Waarom gebeurt dit nu? Ik waardeer uw heel heldere uitspraken. Ik stel voor samen op te trekken want we hebben gezien met Hongarije en Polen wat er gebeurt als we niet op tijd zijn.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-018-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Roberta Metsola" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is important that we are having this debate. We must speak out against corruption everywhere, and today we are here because we hear the people of Romania and we stand with them. The EU institutions, and this Parliament in particular, cannot remain silent on political corruption if we are to remain relevant to the people we represent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me be clear. This is not about the Romanian nation or the Romanian people: this is about the corrupt few who are working to circumvent the law. Romania’s efforts to join the European Union, 10 years ago, were pushed by those who wanted a different way, who believed in Europe and its value system, and who looked to Europe as a way to ensure that a crooked establishment never again gripped the reins of power. Europe cannot and should not abandon those who are reaffirming these ideas in the streets of Bucharest and Timișoara.</p>
      <p sl="en">And this is an issue that goes beyond Romania. I come from Malta, where our Government has the dubious honour of having the only sitting EU Minister, and now the EU Energy Council Chair, whose secret financial set-ups were exposed by the Panama Papers. So, as you can imagine, Vice-President Timmermans, the fight against corruption is top of people’s concerns, at home too.</p>
      <p sl="en">Strong anti-corruption policies must be a hallmark of our European Union. This is about standing up for our founding principles. People across the Union look to the EU institutions for leadership and direction in the fight against corruption. They cannot be met with silence, indifference or excuses. So my message here today: Români, suntem cu voi!</p>
      <p sl="en">(Vorbitorul a acceptat să răspundă unei întrebări adresate în conformitate cu procedura „cartonașului albastru” (articolul 162 alineatul (8) din Regulamentul de procedură)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-020-0000" speaker_id="40224" name="Andi Cristea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonaşului albastru”. – Stimată colegă, vă respect foarte mult și întrebarea mea pentru dumneavoastră este dacă credeți că sunteți informată și documentată necesar și corect cu privire la ce se întâmplă în România sau dacă dumneavoastră ați preluat, fără o analiză, practic, explicațiile și argumentele colegilor români din delegația dumneavoastră?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-021-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Roberta Metsola" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – Listening to the people in this room today and looking at all the young people protesting on the streets of Romania, knowing many Romanian people, who have spoken to me – and even, yes, looking at the message that was just sent by the highest authorities in Romania to all the email addresses of those working in this Parliament – yes, I know what is happening in Romania, and I am more convinced than ever of what I have just said.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-022-0000" speaker_id="39711" name="Victor Boştinaru" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule prim-vicepreședinte al Comisiei Europene, dincolo de discursul cu tente tragic-comice al colegei mele, Macovei, în jurul modificărilor la Codul penal adoptate de guvern, este clar că strada în România încearcă să anuleze alegerile din 11 decembrie. În ultimii ani, abuzurile, încălcările legii, accentuarea caracterului abuziv și represiv al statului s-au accentuat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comisia a tăcut la greva magistraților, deși avea informații despre această situație. A tăcut atunci când a luat cunoștință despre protocoale secrete între DNA și SRI, deși ar fi trebuit să investigheze. Acest lucru trebuie să îl facă Comisia LIBE în România și aici, la Parlament.</p>
      <p sl="en">Această țară, profund loială, România, merită să se întoarcă la democrație, la constituție și la separarea puterilor în stat. În acest moment dramatic pentru țara mea, țara nu ar accepta, națiunea mea nu ar accepta ca strada să răstoarne un guvern și consecințele ar fi incalculabile; și reamintesc Comisiei Europene, în 2012, complicitatea Comisiei sau voluptatea cu care s-au îmbrățișat tezele lui Băsescu a dus la anularea referendumului din 2012. Ar fi tragic și inacceptabil ca acest lucru să se întâmple încă o dată.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-023-0000" speaker_id="124805" name="Mircea Diaconu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, ca discuția să fie completă trebuia să aveți aici și un infractor din România. Și acela sunt eu. Am fost anchetat în timp ce eram senator și ministrul culturii. Am fost anchetat doi ani de zile. La fiecare vizită la Procuratura Generală era anunțată presa, era firesc să fie anunțată presa, se încerca, firește, distrugerea mea publică. După doi ani de zile, procurorul care mă ancheta a zis următorul lucru: „Domnule Diaconu, nu am găsit niciun prejudiciu, dar vă trimit în judecată.” Cred că a și zâmbit cinic, ca un fel de victorie personală, și m-a trimis în judecată cerând doi ani și jumătate închisoare pentru mine, cu executare. Am fost achitat, bineînțeles, după alți doi ani de zile. Nu vreau să vorbesc despre anii mei de chin și de cât am pierdut și cât, probabil, am îmbătrânit în timpul acesta. Nu aceasta este problema. Problema este că în România este, într-adevăr, o enormă problemă, dar nu unde o discutați, unde o vedeți, unii dintre dumneavoastră, ci în faptul că, de o vreme încoace, votul popular este modificat, furat, aruncat la coș pur și simplu prin alte metode decât cele democratice. Nu intru în amănunte, nu este timp.</p>
      <p sl="en">Domnule comisar, cu tot respectul, am tot respectul pentru dumneavoastră, fără discuție, nu sunt de acord deloc cu dumneavoastră decât într-un singur punct și anume în acel al admirației pentru Paul Celan. Și eu gândesc la fel. Problema este alta: lăsați, după părerea mea și după rugămintea mea, lăsați România să-și găsească calea, singură, are toate instituțiile la îndemână, există justiție și este funcțională, există Curte Constituțională care va tranșa în scurt timp acest diferend de opinii. Este democrație în România. În clipa în care lumea iese afară în stradă nu se întâmplă nimic și pot să-și spună păsul, este justiție în România în clipa în care va fi tranșat acest diferend în justiție.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-024-0000" speaker_id="38420" name="Cristian-Silviu Buşoi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, 300 000 de români au ieșit în stradă doar aseară în București și în alte orașe din România și Europa să protesteze împotriva unor măsuri de politică penală care oferă unor politicieni o apărare împotriva justiției. Dar, înainte de orice, trebuie să spunem că nu este o problemă a României și nu trebuie să fie afectată imaginea României. Sutele de mii de români care protestează pașnic, sancționând politica penală interesată a guvernului, arată că societatea românească a luat-o înaintea unor politicieni. Majoritatea românilor, președintele Klaus Iohannis, societatea civilă, instituțiile din sistemul judiciar luptă cu toate armele legale și constituționale să oprească acest abuz al guvernului. Nu strada încearcă să răstoarne un guvern legitim, ci politicienii de la guvernare, liderii partidului de guvernământ consideră că, dacă au câștigat alegerile, politicienii primesc nu responsabilitatea de a guverna conform legii, ci privilegiul de a fi peste legea care guvernează țara, punând sub semnul întrebării funcționarea statului de drept.</p>
      <p sl="en">Partidul Social Democrat în jurul căruia se constituie acest guvern a făcut o campanie electorală agresivă pentru măsuri populiste, acțiuni sociale centrate pe promisiuni de creștere a veniturilor fără fundamentare bugetară și nu a vorbit niciun moment despre aceste modificări ale legilor penale care se află în centrul preocupărilor acestui guvern de la începutul mandatului.</p>
      <p sl="en">Solicităm Comisiei Europene și Parlamentului European să sprijine eforturile cetățenilor români, să sprijine eforturile președintelui României, eforturile instituțiilor sistemului judiciar și să facă toate demersurile legale și posibile pentru a determina și convinge guvernul României să retragă și să anuleze de urgență aceste modificări la Codul penal și Codul de procedură penală. Ce se întâmplă în România nu este o luptă a românilor contra românilor, este o luptă a societății românești cu o parte a liderilor politici care nu înțeleg că într-o țară a Uniunii Europene legea nu poate fi modificată după bunul lor plac.</p>
      <p sl="en">(Vorbitorul nu a acceptat să răspundă unei întrebări adresate de Doru-Claudian Frunzulică în conformitate cu procedura „cartonașului albastru” (articolul 162 alineatul (8) din Regulamentul de procedură), motivând că este vorba de o stratagemă a colegilor socialiști de a lua cât mai mult cuvântul pentru a apăra un proiect greșit).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-025-0000" speaker_id="96932" name="Birgit Sippel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Was wurde eigentlich in Rumänien beschlossen? Erstens: Bis zu einer Schadenshöhe von maximal 45 000 EUR soll künftig Amtsmissbrauch nicht mehr zu einer Haftstrafe führen. Vielmehr muss der Betrag erstattet werden, und zusätzlich wird ein Bußgeld fällig. Kritisiert wird, dass es zur Ermittlung zunächst einen Beschwerdeführer braucht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zweitens: Es gibt einen Straferlass bei minderschweren Straftaten, für Schwerstkranke und Mütter mit kleinen Kindern. Angesichts der Zustände in rumänischen Gefängnissen ist dies gerade für Letztere sicher eine gute Entscheidung. Um diese Zustände insgesamt nachhaltig zu verbessern, braucht es natürlich ganz andere Maßnahmen. Und sicher kann man auch diskutieren, warum ein Eilverfahren beschlossen wurde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bin sehr dankbar, dass dieser Vorgang auf Antrag der Sozialdemokraten heute nicht nur mal so nebenbei angesprochen wird, sondern kritische Fragen im zuständigen Ausschuss sowie im Rahmen einer sogenannten Mission konkret weiterverfolgt werden können.</p>
      <a text="(Die Rednerin lehnt es ab, eine Frage von Herrn Rübig nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel 162 Absatz 8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-026-0000" speaker_id="95281" name="Viorica Dăncilă" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, Curtea Constituțională a constatat că unele prevederi ale Codului penal nu erau constituționale. Drept urmare, guvernul PSD-ALDE a dat o ordonanță de urgență pentru a reglementa acest lucru. Același lucru a fost folosit anterior de guvernul Cioloș și de guvernul Boc. Guvernul președintelui Iohannis, guvernul Cioloș, a operat o sută cincizeci și unu de modificări, realizate în secret fără nicio consultare publică. De ce, domnule comisar, nu ați spus și atunci că România a făcut un pas înapoi?</p>
      <p sl="en">Mai mult, o serie de modificări efectuate de guvernul Cioloș au încălcat fundamental drepturile omului, de pildă, procurorul a primit dreptul de a schimba decizia judecătorului, deși justiția se înfăptuiește de către judecător. Aceste modificări constituționale nu au făcut obiectul niciunui scandal public, nu au fost sancționate și nu s-a atras atenția nici de către Comisie, iar acum este o acțiune mascată de a dărâma guvernul legitim al României și de a nu ține cont de votul românilor din 11 decembrie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Doamnă Macovei, ați lipit o etichetă nedreaptă și neadevărată României. Așa ați pledat și la referendum și la MCV. De aceea nu vă votează românii și nu sunt de acord cu opiniile dumneavoastră. Da, fiți cu noi, cei care nu vor încălca cel mai democratic mod de exprimare, votul românilor!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-028-0000" speaker_id="96838" name="Cristian Dan Preda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, în România strada nu cere schimbarea guvernului cum au spus doamnă Dăncilă și domnul Bostinaru, ci retragerea ordonanțelor. Este nevoie de o asemenea decizie, în caz contrar fondurile europene vor fi pierdute. Comisarul Timmermans a spus-o foarte clar. Dar nu doar banii sunt în joc, ci și onoarea țării. A arătat-o chiar un ministru din guvernul socialist care tocmai a demisionat. „Nu pot accepta impostura sau minciuna” a spus acest ministru din partidul socialiștilor români.</p>
      <p sl="en">Îi invit, de aceea, pe socialiștii europeni să reflecteze la acest gest, solidaritatea lor cu corupții care se autoamnistiază este inacceptabilă. Le sugerez să nu uite că românii l-au răsturnat în 1989 pe Ceaușescu și sunt convins că ei sunt în stare să îl pună la locul lui și pe Dragnea, iar locul lui nu e în fruntea Parlamentului României, este în altă parte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-029-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, mă adresez în primul rând colegilor mei europarlamentari din partidele de dreapta și vreau să vă spun încă o dată că românii prin cultură, istorie, tradiții sunt clar un popor european și care au o vocație europeană. Vreau să îi întreb: de ce nu ne aplecăm mai mult spre dialog, spre cooperare, spre parteneriat? De ce de fiecare dată ne adresăm organismelor internaționale, așa numitei „Înalte Porți”? De ce nu încercăm să colaborăm mai mult noi între noi, românii? Pentru că numai împreună noi am putea, în final, să realizăm o Românie mai puternică, mai respectată, o Românie care să joace un rol mai important în Uniunea Europeană. De ce de fiecare dată nu reușim să colaborăm și de ce de fiecare dată ne împărțim în două sau mai multe tabere? De ce există o fractură în societatea românească? De ce nu dăm dovadă de acele valori europene pe care le invocăm mereu? Există o singură soluție: colaborare între români pentru mersul înainte al României.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-030-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, από χθές παρακολουθώ στην αίθουσα τις αντεγκλήσεις των συναδέλφων από τη Ρουμανία και αυτό αποδεικνύει ότι σίγουρα η κατάσταση είναι ιδιαίτερα οξυμένη σε αυτή τη χώρα. Η τήρηση του κράτους δικαίου αποτελεί θεμέλιο λίθο κάθε κράτους μέλους της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Από τη συζήτηση προκύπτει ότι υπάρχει σύμφωνη γνώμη όλων ότι θα πρέπει να παρακολουθήσουμε την κατάσταση της Ρουμανίας εκ του σύνεγγυς. Στηρίζουμε τον αγώνα του ρουμανικού λαού που κινητοποιείται μαζικά για το χτύπημα της διαφθοράς, της διαφθοράς η οποία βέβαια δεν είναι χαρακτηριστικό μόνο της Ρουμανίας αλλά και άλλων κρατών μελών της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Η διαφθορά δεν χτυπιέται βεβαίως ούτε με την αποποινικοποίηση των παραβάσεων που έχουν σχέση με υπεξαίρεση χρημάτων κάτω από 200 000 EUR, ούτε με την αποφυλάκιση διεφθαρμένων πολιτικών, ούτε βέβαια με το να βγούνε από τις φυλακές οι εγκληματίες με το επιχείρημα ότι, δήθεν, υπάρχει συνωστισμός στις φυλακές. Είναι σίγουρο ότι πρέπει να υπάρξει ανάκληση της νομοθεσίας αυτής, η οποία πέρασε εκτάκτως.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-031-0000" speaker_id="124742" name="António Marinho e Pinto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, Caros Colegas, este debate chama-nos a atenção para um dos problemas mais graves de hoje na União Europeia: a promiscuidade entre a instância política e a instância judicial, entre o poder político e o poder judicial.</p>
      <p sl="en">O Estado de Direito democrático só será democrático se for de Direito e só será de Direito se for democrático. Isto implica separação de poderes, implica que a investigação judicial não se faça de acordo com a oportunidade política, significa que a política não se aproveite das investigações judiciais.</p>
      <p sl="en">A política não pode ser judicializada, assim como a justiça não pode ser politizada. O Estado de Direito é um estado que é balizado nas suas atuações concretas pelo Direito e quem diz o Direito são os tribunais, não os serviços secretos ou outras instituições quaisquer de natureza política ou administrativa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não se pode utilizar a investigação criminal para fins políticos, assim como não se pode fazer investigação criminal com fins políticos. Não se pode manipular o poder judicial, nem se pode manipular o poder político.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-032-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, Romániában az igazságszolgáltatási rendszer az elmúlt években sem működött hibátlanul. A jogállamiság mindig is ingatag lábakon állt, számtalan konkrét példát hozhatunk. Elég, ha arra gondolunk, hogy jelenleg is zajlik az ország ’89 utáni legnagyobb titkosszolgálati botránya, mely röviden arról szól, hogy úgy tűnik, a belügyi szolgálat közvetlenül befolyásolta az ügyészségek és a bíróságok munkáját, politikai harcokra és leszámolásokra használták az igazságszolgáltatást. A helyzet tehát eddig sem volt olyan jó, mint ahogy sokan külföldről látni vélték. Elég, ha csak a kisebbségi kérdésre gondolunk. Ám a mostani módosítások évtizedes visszalépést jelentenek. A kormánypártok szándéka egyértelmű: megmenteni az eljárás alatt álló politikai, gazdasági elitet az igazságszolgáltatás karmai közül.</p>
      <p sl="en">A polgárok pedig pontosan észlelik ezt, ám a választások után két hónappal tehetetlenek, még azok is óriásit csalódtak, akik a baloldalra szavaztak. Románia forrong, dühös emberek vannak az utcákon, ez a düh pedig érthető. A megoldás pedig nem egy olyan igazságszolgáltatás, amely megbosszulja ezeket a támadásokat és még több politikus ellen indít eljárást, hanem egy méltányos, a jogállamiságot tiszteletben tartó és a társadalom, nem pedig egyes csoportok érdekeit szolgáló rendszer. Olyan rendszer, amilyen még nem volt Romániában.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-033-0000" speaker_id="124793" name="Claudia Țapardel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, ce se întâmplă în această plenară astăzi este o gravă dezinformare. Vă voi spune că sunteți dezinformat. Sunt convinsă că nu ați citit modificările care s-au operat la Codul penal și la Codul de procedură penală și nici legea care a fost trimisă în Parlament, legea grațierii. Pentru că dacă ați fi citit aceste documente și această legislație, ați fi înțeles foarte clar că sunt niște solicitări care vin de la Curtea Constituțională a României, precum și niște solicitări care vin de la președintele CEDO privind situația din închisorile din România.</p>
      <p sl="en">Așa că vă voi ruga ca, înainte să avem o dezbatere în plenară și să vă grăbiți să arătați România cu degetul, să facem o analiză în cadrul Comisiei LIBE și, de asemenea, vă invit în România să discutați cu autoritățile statului, cu toate instituțiile și să înțelegeți situația reală din România.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este păcat că ajungem în Parlamentul European să dezinformăm așa de grav despre situația din România. Situația din România este gravă, dar se referă la drepturi, libertăți, la democrație și la respectarea justiției și a drepturilor cetățeanului când se află în fața instanței. Așa că vă aștept în România.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-034-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, dincolo de orice declarații care se fac astăzi aici există o realitate care nu poate fi ignorată: peste 400 de mii de oameni au fost aseară în stradă în peste 50 de orașe din țară, iar aceștia au nevoie de un răspuns, iar acest răspuns este unul singur, și anume abrogarea ordonanței de urgență prin care s-a modificat, la ceas de seară, Codul penal și de procedură penală și, dacă se dorește, discutarea acestora în Parlamentul României, acolo unde este locul. În caz contrar, se va pune în pericol atât parcursul european al României, dar, în mod cert, și viața de zi cu zi a românilor, ceea ce desigur nu ne dorim.</p>
      <p sl="en">România s-a angajat în mod ferm pe un parcurs european, iar prezența masivă a acestora demonstrează nevoia de a păstra aceste angajamente, dincolo de orice alte interese.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-035-0000" speaker_id="40224" name="Andi Cristea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, îl salut pe domnul prim-vicepreședinte Timmermans și vreau să îi supun atenției următorul exemplu: domnia sa este membru al Parlamentului din România. Domnia sa este reales și domnia sa își angajează staff-ul pe care l-a avut în mandatul anterior ca să lucreze cu el în continuare. Mă refer la asistenți, mă refer la consilieri. Ei bine, domnia sa trebuie să știe că este acuzat și se face vinovat de conflict de interese pentru că, în trecut, a avut o relație comercială cu angajații lui și acest lucru mie, personal, mi se pare ridicol și aș dori să îl întreb care este opinia domniei sale cu privire la acest lucru.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-036-0000" speaker_id="124802" name="Siegfried Mureşan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, stimați colegi, după cum a fost deja spus, în România, aseară, mai mult de 400 de mii de oameni au protestat împotriva acestei ordonanțe de urgență adoptate de guvernul României prin care se fac modificări la Codul penal. Aceste modificări dezincriminează abuzul în serviciu. Această ordonanță va duce la eliberarea mai multor politicieni condamnați și la oprirea multor anchete în desfășurare. Este cea mai mare lovitură dată justiției din România în ultimii douăzeci și șapte de ani de la căderea comunismului.</p>
      <p sl="en">Domnule vicepreședinte Timmermans, ați întrebat de ce face guvernul asemenea lucruri? Răspunsul este simplu: fiindcă de pe urma acestei ordonanțe vor beneficia politicieni corupți, inclusiv președintele Parlamentului României, social-democratul Liviu Dragnea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce este de făcut acum? Solicit tuturor partenerilor internaționali, inclusiv Comisiei Europene, să exercite presiune asupra guvernului României pentru ca aceste modificări adoptate să nu intre în vigoare la termenul stabilit peste zece zile. Este important ca Europa să fie alături de cetățenii României în lupta împotriva politicienilor corupți. Aceasta așteaptă cetățenii României de la Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-037-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, stimate domnule prim-vicepreședinte vreau mai întâi să declar că vă apreciez foarte mult și întotdeauna am fost impresionată de inteligența și diplomația dumneavoastră, dar trebuie să spun că m-ați dezamăgit. Dacă dumneavoastră corelați ce se întâmplă în România cu acordarea fondurilor europene, nu pot să mă gândesc decât că acum, când s-au încheiat cei 10 ani cu MCV-ul, a fost un mecanism special pentru a discrimina douăzeci de milioane de români.</p>
      <p sl="en">Domnule prim-vicepreședinte, spuneați de suveranitate în discursul dumneavoastră, în același timp cereți guvernului: ori avem suveranitate parlament - guvern, rezultat în urma alegerilor, ori dumneavoastră impuneți.</p>
      <p sl="en">Apoi spuneați să lăsați să își facă treaba. Haideți să lăsăm guvernul să și facă treaba, justiția să funcționeze. Am pledat întotdeauna pentru condamnarea hoților, dar nu pentru încălcarea drepturilor omului, corecție care se încearcă acum prin această ordonanță. Vă mulțumesc și aș vrea punctual să îmi răspundeți.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-038-0000" speaker_id="94282" name="Jean-Paul Denanot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, effectivement, vu de cet hémicycle, il est difficile de savoir ce qui se passe exactement. C’est la raison pour laquelle je me réjouis que nous ayons accepté qu’il y ait un débat en commission des libertés publiques, de la justice et des affaires intérieures qui soit plus documenté que celui d’aujourd’hui et qu’effectivement, une délégation puisse se rendre en Roumanie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce que je peux dire, c’est que je connais la Roumanie depuis longtemps puisque je suis un des premiers Français à s’être rendu en Roumanie après la chute de Ceausescu. Je me dis que la Roumanie est encore une jeune démocratie, qu’elle a fait beaucoup de progrès mais qu’il faut vraiment y conforter la démocratie et l’état de droit. Je crois qu’aujourd’hui, il faut faire en sorte que cet état de droit puisse effectivement avoir ses prérogatives et fonctionner en Roumanie.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est dans ce sens, me semble-t-il, qu’il faut que nous poussions la Roumanie. Il faut que l’état de droit soit respecté et que la démocratie soit respectée. Je crois que c’est le fond du problème et c’est vers cela que nous devons nous diriger.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-040-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Frans Timmermans" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">First Vice-President of the Commission. – Mr President, I was inspired by what Mr Frunzulică said earlier, that we should not be turning this into a party-political confrontation between government and opposition. Sadly, that happened here in this House today, which, in a sense, is normal in a political chamber – that is what you get – but on this issue I am a bit saddened by that.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would say to your PPE colleagues that they should hold onto the passion with which they spoke today when we are discussing nations where one of your parties is in power. Hold on to that and be exactly the same: you would really help all of us. But for me this has nothing to do with party political issues and, frankly, it is preposterous and rather insulting to suggest that I would be an agent to topple a government led by the party I belong to. That is nonsensical. I am looking at a situation as it is. On these issues, the Commission – as we have shown over the last year and certainly since the Juncker Commission came into being – is colour blind. This is not party political.</p>
      <p sl="en">The issue at hand is very straightforward. We have cooperated with Romania in the last 10 years in the cooperation and verification mechanism (CVM). I have cooperated personally with various governments, of differing compositions, and all these governments have cooperated with me personally – with the Commission – in a constructive way, albeit, of course, blaming the opposition or saying to us that we are more critical of them when they are in power than we are of the opposition. In that sense, regardless of the political colour in Romania, the criticism is always the same.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I accept that criticism. Yes, we are critical and sometimes that hurts if you are in government or in parliament. I understand that, but that is simply our role. That is the role of the Commission, that is the role we have been given in the Treaty and that is the role that also emanates from the CVM.</p>
      <p sl="en">The point I was trying to make this morning is this: Romania is in the final stretch of this long, long marathon, leading to a situation where we can all say the development is now irreversible. Romania is not at risk of going back to what the situation was in the past. We are almost there. That is what the last CVM report stipulated very clearly, and in our perception the emergency ordinance and the draft legislation seem to indicate another direction – backwards – and I think this needs to be discussed.</p>
      <p sl="en">We signalled it in the CVM report last week. This needs to be discussed because it would not speed up the process. It would slow down the process or even stop the process of where we want to go, namely to the point where we, the Commission, can also say that the development is irreversible. That is where we want to get to. So that is why I call upon the authorities in Romania carefully to look into what they are doing.</p>
      <p sl="en">I find it very difficult to understand what emergency would warrant an emergency ordinance on this subject. I find it difficult to understand why lowering the standards on fighting corruption is in the interest of the Romanian nation. I find it difficult to understand but, of course, this is not interference in internal affairs. The Parliament of Romania is sovereign in its decisions, and it also has to face the consequences of those decisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">If we in the Commission believe those consequences might not be positive, I think it is our duty – even if it is uncomfortable to some – to signal that. That is what we are doing – nothing more, nothing less.</p>
      <p sl="en">I say to everyone in this House that you will not help the situation by turning this into a party-political confrontation, by making this a theoretical battle about principles. It is about facts and actions. Let us try to find a cooperative way, as we have done in the past, to come out of this situation. Let us pause for a moment to reflect whether this is the right course to take, given also the reactions in the judiciary in Romania and from the Romanian public.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am encouraged by the fact that so many people attach such great importance to the fight against corruption. Hold on to that: it is a great, great asset. I also see that there is overwhelming support in the Romanian population for the involvement of the European Union in this joint progress towards an irreversible situation. This is strongly supported by the Romanian population. Nobody is saying that the EU should stay out of it. Use this as a strength.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will end with a quote from the famous Romanian sculptor, Brâncuși, who said: ‘Theories are patterns without value. What counts is action.’ Let us take action to make sure that this process, towards an irreversible, strong rule of law where corruption is controlled and rooted out, happens soon in Romania and that we do nothing that would indicate a different direction.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-041-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-041-0500" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – Il provvedimento adottato dal governo romeno, che alleggerisce le pene per un complesso di reati minori e per casi particolari, ha destato non poche perplessità. Si tratta di un provvedimento che va in controtendenza rispetto al percorso compiuto fin qui dalla Romania nella lotta alla corruzione. Il recente rapporto MCV, infatti, mette in evidenza il fatto che le autorità dello Stato romeno hanno ottenuto risultati buoni e molto buoni, che ci sono progressi notevoli ottenuti dalle istituzioni romene nella lotta alla corruzione e contro la criminalità in genere. Gli ultimi provvedimenti del governo stanno generando malcontento e forti critiche tra i cittadini.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europa deve fare il possibile perché la Romania riprenda il cammino delle riforme e perché continui il processo di lotta alla corruzione che da lungo tempo lo Stato stava portando avanti. Passi indietro non sono consentiti su questo terreno, né alla Romania né ad altri paesi dell'UE.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Third countries whose nationals are subject to or exempt from a visa requirement: Georgia (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-043-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la relazione di Mariya Gabriel, a nome della commissione per le libertà civili, la giustizia e gli affari interni, sulla proposta di regolamento del Parlamento europeo e del Consiglio che modifica il regolamento (CE) n. 539/2001 del Consiglio che adotta l'elenco dei paesi terzi i cui cittadini devono essere in possesso del visto all'atto dell'attraversamento delle frontiere esterne e l'elenco dei paesi terzi i cui cittadini sono esenti da tale obbligo (Georgia) (COM(2016)0142 - C8-0113/2016 - 2016/0075(COD)) (A8-0260/2016).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-044-0000" speaker_id="96848" name="Мария Габриел" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">докладчик. – Г-н Председател, скъпи колеги, изминахме дълъг път преди днешното финално гласуване за отпадане на визите за грузинските граждани. Това е признание за постигнатото от грузинските власти и граждани. Днес е исторически ден не само за Грузия, но и за Европейския съюз. Въвеждането на безвизов режим за Грузия бележи нов етап в отношенията ни със страната.</p>
      <p sl="en">Благодаря на всички колеги за силната подкрепа в процеса на работа по това ключово досие. Пътят до днес не беше лек. Но усилията си заслужаваха в името на грузинските и европейските граждани. През септември компетентната комисия LIBE прие с голямо мнозинство доклада ми. Така получих мандат за водене на преговори от името на Европейския парламент. Междувременно Съветът/държавите членки обвързаха влизането в сила на визовата либерализация за Грузия с укрепването на механизма за суспендиране на безвизовия режим. Това отложи стартирането на междуинституционалните преговори. То стана възможно след постигане на споразумение по механизма за суспендиране през декември миналата година.</p>
      <p sl="en">Силата на Европейския парламент е, че сме последователни в действията си. Винаги сме отстоявали една позиция: при изпълнени всички критерии, визовият режим се либерализира. Радвам се, че Съветът подкрепи многократно заявявания ни ангажимент за постигане и на бързи резултати в процеса на либерализиране на визовия режим за Грузия. Едновременното влизане в сила на механизма за суспендиране и визовата либерализация за Грузия бележи крайния успех на тези усилия.</p>
      <p sl="en">Премахването на изискването за визи за Грузия е силен сигнал към гражданите. Тук специално искам да им благодаря за последователността, търпението и силата на демократичните им убеждения. Грузия не само изпълни всички изисквания, поставени от Европейския съюз, но и надгради над тях. По този начин и общата визова политика на Европейския съюз се доказва като ефективен инструмент за външна политика в диалога с нашите партньори. Грузия постигна значителен напредък при провеждането на широкообхватни и комплексни реформи. Това доближи страната още повече до европейските ценности и демократични стандарти.</p>
      <p sl="en">Грузия е стратегически важен партньор на Европейския съюз в рамките на европейската политика на съседство и по-специално на Източното партньорство. Нещо повече – страната играе ключова роля и в усилията на Европейския съюз за укрепване на общоевропейската сигурност. Европа трябва да бъде обградена от приятели и партньори. Ето защо е важно да изпълним собствения си ангажимент към страната за премахване на изискванията за визи. Така ще гарантираме задълбочаване на отношенията ни в дух на взаимно доверие и диалог.</p>
      <p sl="en">Въвеждането на безвизов режим е от съществено значение и за грузинските, и за европейските граждани. Не бива да забравяме, че реалното доближаване на грузинците до нашите общоевропейски ценности е възможно само при условие че им бъде гарантирана свободата да пътуват безвизово. Само така можем да споделяме нашите култури, да насърчаваме икономическото и политическото сближаване, да затвърждаваме позицията на Съюза като важен фактор в региона.</p>
      <p sl="en">Не на последно място бих искала да призова Съвета сега и за започване на преговори без повече забавяне по визовата либерализация за Украйна. Нека отговорим на очакванията на нашите партньори. Те също са изпълнили критериите.</p>
      <p sl="en">В заключение бих искала да призова да подкрепим днес силно визовата либерализация за Грузия по време на гласуването. Така ще изпълним собствения си принцип за визова реципрочност. Вярвам, че днес Европейският парламент ще отправи силно положително послание към грузинските граждани. Разчитам на Вашата подкрепа.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-045-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me start by expressing our thanks to Ms Gabriel for the excellent job she has done. She was behind all these efforts in order to arrive where we are today. Georgia has been exemplary in fulfilling a demanding roadmap which allowed us to propose to you – and the Council of course – visa liberalisation for its citizens. I am therefore very pleased that Georgian citizens with biometric passports will soon be able to travel to the Schengen area without a visa for a short period of up to 90 days. It is a very important achievement indeed, and it has been a long process.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU-Georgia visa liberalisation dialogue, as you will remember, started in June 2012. The continuous monitoring and reporting carried out since then showed that Georgia has made the necessary progress. Georgia has undertaken all the necessary efforts to meet all of the benchmarks. Therefore, following the positive assessment of the progress report, the Commission proposed in March 2016 to lift the visa requirement for Georgian citizens holding a biometric passport. This will be done by amending the Visa Regulation. This proposal also took into account overall EU-Georgia relations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The hard work, really hard work, of the Georgian authorities over the past two years has paid off. The Commission will continue to monitor Georgia’s continuous compliance with the visa liberalisation criteria, in particular on fighting organised crime. Because, as I have said on other occasions, these reforms bring Georgia closer to European Union standards, facilitating cooperation with the European Union and bringing the country a step forward on its European path.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to remind you that visa-free travel for Georgia will enter into force at the same time as the revised suspension mechanism, even though they are two separate issues. In addition, the suspension mechanism applies to all visa-free countries horizontally, not just to Georgia. It will be an important tool to further enhance security for the European Union, but also a catalyst that will enable our visa liberalisation policy to expand.</p>
      <p sl="en">Visa liberalisation with Georgia is an essential contribution to strengthen cultural and economic ties between Georgian and EU citizens because, let’s not forget, visa-free travel is a tangible tool of European integration that directly concerns the citizens. I would like to share personal experience with you. When I first visited Tbilisi as European Commissioner, I was very impressed by the many European Union flags around the city – I would say more European flags in Georgia than in Brussels. I was touched, because in a period where we here in the European Union, in the Member States, take our Union for granted and where we see anti-European rhetoric develop, the citizens of Georgia remind us what a unique achievement of peace, stability and prosperity the European Union is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear Members of the European Parliament, let me conclude by calling on you to support the proposal on the table later during the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-047-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on Foreign Affairs">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, dear colleagues, dear Georgian friends, I would like to say some words about the process of adoption of the visa-free regime with Georgia. It was very ugly. The Council’s idea to connect the visa-free regime between the EU and Georgia and Ukraine with the visa suspension mechanism was, in my opinion, a bad idea. As a result, an unexpected delay occurred and nobody could say when this process would be finished. Some EU country leaders publicly declared that they were glad to see these Eastern European countries on the way of European integration, but at the same time behind closed doors they put their feet on the brakes and started to blackmail the European Parliament. In this way they tried to solve their internal political problems.</p>
      <p sl="en">Colleagues, in politics as in a business company, reputation of reliable partners is a very valuable thing, and the reputation of the EU in this case, in my opinion, was seriously damaged. I would like to apologise to our Georgian friends for this unpleasant experience. Nevertheless, dear colleagues, now in this Chamber among us is the Speaker of the Parliament of Georgia, the best friend of the European Parliament and Europe, his Excellency Irakli Kobakhidze. Dear Georgian friends, I hope that today’s decision will give impetus for the new achievements in cooperation between Georgia and the European Union. Fulfilling all the criteria for adopting the free visa regime was not an easy task but the Georgians have done a great job. It is a very important step on the path of the European integration of Georgia. It is a great achievement of the Georgian people, politicians, civil society, students and so on.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-048-0000" speaker_id="28397" name="Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, señor comisario. Felicito a la ponente Maríya Gabriel por su trabajo tan profesional y tan comprometido y, asimismo, al pueblo y a las autoridades georgianas. Tal y como ya he manifestado en reiteradas ocasiones, Georgia merecía desde hace mucho tiempo la exención del visado, ya que cumplía todas las exigencias recogidas en el artículo -1 del Reglamento n.º 539/2001. Nunca entendí la vinculación innecesaria de este expediente con otros en negociación. Desde mayo del pasado año hemos trabajado intensamente para mejorar el mecanismo de suspensión, de cuyo informe —como saben— soy ponente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Espero sinceramente que la aprobación definitiva del mecanismo, el corrigendo que realizaremos durante la próxima sesión plenaria, sirva para asegurar la entrada en vigor definitiva del acuerdo de exención de visados que hoy debatimos. Nadie entendería ninguna dilación que impidiera su firma el 1 de marzo, su publicación más allá del 9 de marzo y su entrada en vigor antes del final del mismo mes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello le pido a la Presidencia de turno la mayor diligencia posible para realizar todos los trámites pertinentes con el Consejo que supongan la aprobación definitiva de ambos expedientes, su firma y su publicación. Este Acuerdo profundizará y mejorará las relaciones recíprocas entre Georgia y la Unión Europea. Y como ya se ha demostrado en otros muchos casos, producirá efectos beneficiosos para ambas partes en ámbitos tan dispares como la seguridad, el turismo, la cultura o la defensa y, sobre todo, servirá para acercar mucho más a Georgia a Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-049-0000" speaker_id="96932" name="Birgit Sippel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Bereits im Dezember 2015 attestierte die Europäische Kommission: Georgien hat alle Kriterien des Aktionsplans zur Visaliberalisierung erfüllt. Voilà! Dass die Menschen in Georgien dennoch bis heute auf diese Visaliberalisierung warten, lag auch an den Mitgliedstaaten, die dann diese Visaerleichterung zusätzlich an einen sogenannten Aussetzungsmechanismus knüpften. Dank der Hartnäckigkeit und Kompromissbereitschaft des Europäischen Parlaments und insbesondere unseres Berichterstatters konnten wir diesen Mechanismus jetzt beschließen – zu klaren Bedingungen und gegen den Willen des Rates, inklusive eines Mechanismus demokratischer Kontrolle durch dieses Haus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Georgien hat lange genug auf die hart erkämpfte Visaerleichterung gewartet. Es wird Zeit, diese Reisefreiheit endlich in Kraft treten zu lassen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-050-0000" speaker_id="28353" name="Anna Elżbieta Fotyga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it was a long way for Georgians, regardless of their political option. It was a long way for many of us participating in the first Congress of Polish Solidarność, extending a friendly message to all nations suffering under Communist rule. I welcome this report, and I await quick decisions concerning Ukraine.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-051-0000" speaker_id="28208" name="Nathalie Griesbeck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ALDE. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, mes chers collègues, je me réjouis évidemment, comme mes collègues, de la finalisation de cet accord de libéralisation et je voudrais saluer l’excellent travail que nous avons réalisé avec Mariya Gabriel, notre très efficace rapporteure.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Géorgie a démontré, ces dernières années, une volonté très claire de rapprochement avec l’Union, une volonté politique mais surtout une volonté concrète, qui s’est traduite par un certain nombre de réponses à tous les critères qui avaient été exigés et imposés, comme cela a été rappelé à l’instant, et qu’elle a réalisé toutes les avancées nécessaires afin de pouvoir bénéficier de ce régime de libéralisation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si je salue ces avancées, il faut cependant insister sur le fait que ces nombreuses réformes mises en œuvre par la Géorgie ne doivent pas être, bien sûr, le fait d’un jour. Elles doivent être maintenues, consolidées et pérennes dans tous les domaines clés que sont l’indépendance et le pluralisme des médias, l’indépendance de la justice, le respect des droits des minorités ainsi que la lutte contre la criminalité organisée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cet accord marque une étape importante dans l’approfondissement des relations, mais aussi parce que la Géorgie est un acteur, un partenaire clé, un partenaire stratégique dans le cadre de la politique européenne de voisinage et plus particulièrement du partenariat oriental. Je pense notamment – et j’insiste - à la coopération dans le domaine des affaires intérieures et de la lutte contre la criminalité organisée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans ce contexte, dans notre contexte géopolitique extrêmement instable et pour certains citoyens, angoissant, il n’y a pas besoin de longs commentaires pour comprendre combien il est stratégique d’établir des relations privilégiées avec ces pays du sud du Caucase, pour en faire des partenaires et des amis, des amis aussi entre les citoyens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-052-0000" speaker_id="124993" name="Bodil Valero" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Herr talman! Jag vill också välkomna förslaget. Det här hade kunnat gå mycket fortare. Vi hade kunnat bevilja visumlättnader mycket tidigare. Jag kan inte heller riktigt förstå det som herr Díaz de Mera tog upp här tidigare: att vi skulle invänta, att vi måste koppla det här till den så kallade upphävandemekanismen. De har ju inte direkt med varandra att göra. De har kopplingar på ett visst sätt, men de är inte någonting som man absolut måste ta tillsammans.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det är ju så att Georgien sedan länge har uppfyllt alla kriterier för att få de här visumlättnaderna. Det som jag också välkomnar väldigt mycket är att det nu gäller att de georgiska medborgarna ska kunna få komma också till oss, och inte bara vi som ska få komma till dem utan visum, såsom det är idag. Så jag vill också lyckönska de georgiska medborgarna här idag, därför att jag tycker att det är på tiden att vi faktiskt tar det här steget nu.</p>
      <p sl="en">När det gäller visumlättnader generellt så är ju vår inställning att det är väldigt viktigt att den fria rörligheten omfattar inte bara oss i Europa, utan att vi utvidgar den också till andra länder. Ju lättare människor har att röra sig över gränserna, desto bättre, menar vi också.</p>
      <p sl="en">Egentligen så borde inga gränser få finnas i världen, men det är ju en utopi, så vi kan inte förvänta oss att det ska gå åt det hållet. Men jag vill verkligen välkomna det här förslaget idag, och hoppas att det kan träda i kraft så tidigt som möjligt och egentligen inte alls kopplat till den här upphävandemekanismen. Tack!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-053-0000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard Batten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, well, the Treaty of Rome is burning. And while it’s burning you’re fiddling, specifically fiddling with visa restriction rules. A lot of people were very upset in this Chamber yesterday and there were some very disgraceful scenes, and it was the people who would like Britain to remain in the EU getting upset with the people on this side who want it to leave. Now the truth is finally dawning on you here that Britain is going to leave and the European Union is going to lose one of its biggest net contributors.</p>
      <p sl="en">Perhaps it would be good for you to understand that the central issue on why we decided to leave was because of a loss of democracy and national sovereignty and control, and the biggest issue that brought that home to the British people was the issue of immigration, and specifically mass uncontrolled immigration, which is what we’ve had for many years, specifically from the European Union in great numbers since 1997. To give you an idea on those figures, last year the official figure is that we had 650 000 people come into the country, but there were 825 000 National Insurance numbers issued, so it’s out of control and nobody knows what the real figures are.</p>
      <p sl="en">To come onto the specifics of what we’re discussing here, this is a technical change, I understand, which would give Georgia visa-free access to the European Union for a period of 90 days, and as the rapporteur Ms Gabriel says, the EU remains a very attractive destination. Well, it’s true that back in the 18th century Dr Johnson said the most attractive thing about Scotland was the road to England. That’s still true, and in the 21st century equivalent the most attractive thing for many countries on the periphery of Europe is the road somewhere else, and one can hardly blame them.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now perhaps there is something that you should consider. The British people voted to leave the European Union for many reasons, and one of the biggest ones was mass immigration. You’re actually making the problem worse for the European Union because you are extending these visa arrangements to people, who can come, there are then very few or no checks, they can overstay their welcome, and once inside the Schengen area, they can move anywhere else that they like.</p>
      <p sl="en">You are going to lose Britain, and I wish you well when we’ve left. I don’t want to destroy the European Union; if that’s what you want, then good luck to you. But you’re going to destroy your own project because the next countries that are going want to leave are Germany, Holland, France and more. So in your own interest. I think you should wake up to what’s happening in the real world.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8).)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-054-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">zilās kartītes jautājums. – Godātais kolēģi! Paldies, ka akceptējāt manu zilās kartītes jautājumu! Man tiešām ir prieks, ka drīzumā jūs nesēdēsiet šajā plenārsēžu zālē, par cik jūs tik gribat pamest gan šo posteni, gan cīnāties par to, lai jūsu valsts pamestu Eiropas Savienību. Bet pasakiet, par kādiem migrācijas draudiem jūs tikko runājāt? Jūs zināt, cik cilvēku dzīvo Gruzijā? Jūs tiešām saskatāt, ka aptuveni trīsarpus miljonu cilvēku ir drauds Eiropas Savienībai, ja viņi brauks padzert alu Rīgā vai padzīvot viesnīcā Berlīnē? Paldies!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-055-0000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard Batten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – Well, there were two parts to your question. The first one was about Brexit, and I can tell you that we want to leave as quickly as possible. I am the UKIP Brexit spokesman, and I’m writing a plan which would get Britain out of the European Union a very much a great deal faster than Theresa May’s, and soon as it’s done I’ll be happy to send you a copy. The day that I leave here and Britain is restored as an independent country, I will be very, very happy, and pleased to make you happy as well.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second part of your question was about 3.7 million people in Georgia, I believe, and it’s not about the actual numbers in Georgia – we’ve had this from every country in the European Union. We were told that about 13 000 people would come from Poland. I think that the figure is at least 700 000 – it’s over a million, probably, and we in Britain have no problem with people going to other countries. It’s a matter of numbers and the degree. That is the problem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-056-0000" speaker_id="97513" name="Vicky Maeijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ENF-Fractie. – En weer krijgt een dubieus land van Brussel visumliberalisatie cadeau, deze keer Georgië. Terwijl Europa wordt geteisterd door georganiseerde misdaad uit het voormalige Sovjetland mogen straks miljoenen Georgiërs vrij door Europa reizen. Eerder waren het de asielprocedures die massaal door Georgische criminelen werden misbruikt om in Europese steden te komen roven, stelen, afpersen en mishandelen. Dat is straks niet meer nodig, want criminelen wordt het door visumvrijstelling namelijk supersimpel gemaakt om op rooftocht te gaan. Uit cijfers van 2016 bleek dat alleen al in Duitsland in één jaar tijd meer dan 8000 Georgische criminelen waren geregistreerd en het kan Brussel ondertussen allemaal niet schelen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nederland moet zelf beslissen wie er wel en wie er niet ons land binnenkomt. Het vrij verkeer van personen is ondertussen al verworden tot vrij verkeer van asielzoekers, terroristen en wapens. Mijn partij is voor veiligheid. De PVV is tegen meer Europese Unie en daarom is mijn fractie tegen de visumvrijstelling voor Georgië.</p>
      <a text="(De spreker gaat in op een &quot;blauwe kaart&quot;-vraag (artikel 162, lid 8, van het Reglement).)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-057-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card question. – Dear colleague, you come from a European country. Your country has important European values, and you are Europeans because of your traditions, culture, history and values. So is Georgia. They fulfilled all the benchmarks required in order to receive this, and they are also a European country, and we have to send them the message that they could become one day Members of the European Union. That’s why we have to implement, as soon as possible, this visa liberalisation for Georgian citizens. Don’t you agree that you and all the other MEPs, who come from European countries, have to support this – not to be against?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-058-0000" speaker_id="97513" name="Vicky Maeijer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">"blauwe kaart"-antwoord. – Uiteraard steun ik dat niet. Want vrijheid en veiligheid zijn de waarden die ik verdedig, die mijn partij verdedigt. Om die te kunnen verdedigen is wat wij nodig hebben absoluut niet méér Europese Unie, maar minder Europese Unie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-059-0000" speaker_id="124966" name="Steven Woolfe" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, when Ms Merkel made the monumental error of judgment by opening the doors of Germany to those from all countries without positive checks, we now have seen the consequences. The European Union, in its desire to continue to extend its influence – or, as some would say, its empire – is doing two things. The first of those is making the same mistakes by not making sure it checks those who are coming in. In the Library of Congress on Georgia, it says that borders with Turkey are porous and dangerous for terrorists. In June of last year, the Georgian newspaper Rezonansi reported that ISIS had established a special—purpose vehicle brigade of 600—700 terrorists to use Georgia as a transit corridor for ISIS. Please do not make the same mistakes, with your huge desire to have open borders between all countries of Europe, that Merkel made last year.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-060-0000" speaker_id="124896" name="Michał Boni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to give special thanks to Mariya Gabriel, the rapporteur. I would like to take this one minute and turn to Georgia’s citizens. Dear Georgians, today’s decision of the European Parliament is one of the last miles in your visa liberalisation marathon. You deserve it, and I am proud to be part of the decision by voting in favour. Liberalisation of the visa regime provides you with a lot of opportunities and advantages. Use it to the benefit of the development of your country. To meet the visa liberalisation benchmarks was a challenge to which you have risen. There will be more reform challenges from the Association Agenda to meet. I am convinced that the decision on visa liberalisation will yield even more energy and enthusiasm to deliver on those new challenges.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear Georgians, your country is not suspicious. You are a very proud, brave European nation. I am keeping my fingers crossed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-061-0000" speaker_id="28306" name="Ana Gomes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">O regime de isenção de vistos entra a Geórgia e a União Europeia é desejável e devido, já que a Geórgia há mais de um ano que tomou todas as medidas necessárias para corresponder aos padrões de exigência da União Europeia. E o seu povo e instituições estão empenhados na consolidação da democracia e imbuídos de um espírito pró-europeu, como eu pude constatar, como chefe da missão de observação do Parlamento Europeu às eleições na Geórgia, há uns meses.</p>
      <p sl="en">Torna-se mais importante ainda que este regime entre sem demora em vigor, face às mudanças tectónicas a ocorrer no contexto político internacional, com Trump, Presidente dos Estados Unidos, a servir a estratégia de Putin, visando destruir a União Europeia e a democracia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Precisamos, por isso, de reorganizar forças e de apoiar todos aqueles que, na Geórgia, se opõem à ocupação russa do seu território e trabalham pela intensificação das relações económicas e políticas com a União Europeia. A isenção de vistos facilitará o intercâmbio de pessoas a todos os níveis e dará às forças democráticas na Geórgia sinal claro de que queremos ajudá-los a consolidar a sua democracia e a sua autonomia.</p>
      <p sl="en">As minhas saudações ao Presidente do Parlamento da Geórgia e à sua delegação, que hoje estão aqui connosco, e à colega Maria Gabriel pelo seu empenho como relatora neste processo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-062-0000" speaker_id="28481" name="Sajjad Karim" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it amazes me how our Parliament can be the best of parliaments and the worst of parliaments in the same session, all at the same time. Whilst I rise and it gives me a huge amount of personal pleasure to be able to congratulate Georgia on such a tremendous achievement, let me also make it clear that the vast majority of this House stands absolutely united in rejecting the alternative facts and the bare racism that is demonstrated by a very small minority of people in this House, who speak about things that they do not understand. I apologise to colleagues for my anger that is coming through today, but may I echo the words of our Commissioner when he stands and says that Georgia made him proud. Let our Commissioner know that this House stands united behind him because we have all seen those same flags in Georgia. We have seen their commitment. We have seen how their sovereignty and territorial integrity remains compromised but yet they stand firm, through their people, on their European way. Let Europe stand firm with them. We owe it at least to them to stand united in the face of these alternative facts and this changing geopolitical situation that is emerging in the world today.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-063-0000" speaker_id="125214" name="Bronis Ropė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Klausimas, ar panaikinti Gruzijos piliečiams vizas, visų pirma yra ir klausimas, ar Europos Sąjunga nori turėti efektyvią išorės santykių politiką. Gruzija jau seniai siekė suartėjimo su Europos Sąjunga, dėl to atliko daug sunkių reformų, dėl to jie ir daug nukentėjo nuo savo ne itin draugiškos kaimynės. Ir visa tai vyko žinant, kad mainais už Gruzijos europėjimą siūlomi tokie apdovanojimai kaip bevizis režimas. Todėl panaikindami vizas Gruzijos piliečiams mes parodysime, jog Europos Sąjunga laikosi savo įsipareigojimų ir paskatinsime kitas mūsų kaimynes plėtoti gerą valdymą ir demokratiją, saugoti žmogaus teises ir laikytis rinkos ekonomikos principų. Visi žinome, jog reformos buvo sėkmingos. Gruzija yra demokratiška, stabili šalis, gerbianti žmogaus teises ir besilaikanti europinių vertybių.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-064-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, δεν θα έπρεπε καν να συζητούμε σοβαρά την προοπτική απελευθέρωσης βίζας για τους υπηκόους της Γεωργίας. Η συγκεκριμένη χώρα αντιμετωπίζει τεράστια προβλήματα διαφθοράς και έχουν εντοπιστεί πολλές φορές πλαστά διαβατήρια. Επιπλέον, αντιμετωπίζει εκτεταμένο και άριστα οργανωμένο έγκλημα, το οποίο και έχει ήδη εξάγει σε αρκετές χώρες της Ένωσης. Επίσης, το πολιτικό προσωπικό της χώρας θυμίζει άλλες εποχές και καταστάσεις, με πρώην προέδρους να γίνονται μέχρι και νομάρχες σε γειτονικές χώρες, μήπως και αποφεύγουν τη φυλακή με την υποστήριξη της Ευρωπαϊκής Ενώσεως βεβαίως. Όσον αφορά τα ανθρώπινα δικαιώματα, οι λαοί της Αμπχαζίας και της Νοτίου Οσετίας στους οποίους και αναφέρετε στην έκθεση σαν πληθυσμούς, λες και ομιλείτε περί προβάτων, έχουν βιώσει και συνεχίζουν να βιώνουν καθημερινά τις «προόδους» της Γεωργίας στον τομέα αυτό που μέχρι και εισβολή με τις ένοπλες δυνάμεις της πραγματοποίησε εναντίον αμάχων και αναγκάστηκε τελικά να αποσυρθεί όταν τα ρωσικά άρματα έφτασαν λίγα χιλιόμετρα έξω από την Τιφλίδα. Όλα αυτά συμβαίνουν με την υποστήριξη της Ενώσεως, που υπερασπίζεται το δικαίωμα στην αυτοδιάθεση των λαών πολύ επιλεκτικά.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-065-0000" speaker_id="124702" name="Jaromír Štětina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to openly declare my support for granting a visa-free regime to the Georgian people. I have met many Georgians, especially young Georgians, and I am happy to observe their enthusiasm and dedication to the idea of bringing their country closer to the EU. They feel that European roots are an essential part of their identity and I believe that the Georgian nation does indeed deserve to have a European future one day.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, in these difficult times, we need to pragmatic and look well at the reasons why we should support Georgia. One such reason is the increasingly tense security situation in the Black Sea region. Georgia is strategically important, not just as a transit country but also as the only pro-western littoral state along the eastern shores of the Black Sea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-066-0000" speaker_id="39711" name="Victor Boştinaru" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I very much welcome the visa—free regime for Georgia. We are today in a highly volatile political context, we need our strategic partners more than ever, and we need to prove to them that they can rely on us. Georgia has shown its strong commitments towards European values and integration, and it undertook reforms that were not easy. Despite the visa-free delays, Georgia’s citizens demonstrated once again in the recent parliamentary elections what they stand for, and it is high time to give them tangible signals – in fact, nothing more than what we promised, and what they have been waiting for for too long. According to the European Commission report, Georgia was already meeting the visa liberalisation Action Plan requirements in December 2015 and it is a pity that our Georgian partners had to wait until now to reach this important objective. Finally, considering that all necessary elements are in place, I hope also that the visa liberalisation process for Ukraine will be completed with no further delay.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-068-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, that the EU countries recently exercised caution in their visa liberalisation policy after an uncontrolled influx of more than a million refugees and migrants can be easily understandable. However, considering the hard geo-political choices Georgia has made about the country’s future and the far-reaching and difficult reforms it has implemented in the Justice and Home Affairs area, it is time for the EU to show that once its benchmarks are fulfilled, it can also deliver on its promises. I agree with the rapporteur that the visa waiver for Georgian citizens should prove an important tool for enhancing economic and cultural relations, and provide a stable framework for a dialogue on fundamental rights. Ultimately, in difficult political weather, it could also be one small step for Europe in securing democratic development in its turbulent neighbourhood.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-069-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'esenzione dal visto per i cittadini georgiani che viaggiano nell'Unione europea rappresenta uno strumento importante per rafforzare le relazioni economiche e culturali con questo importante paese, ma anche per intensificare il dialogo politico sui diritti umani e le libertà fondamentali.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Georgia è un partner strategico dell'Europa nel quadro della politica di vicinato e, in particolare, del partenariato orientale. L'accordo di associazione tra l'Unione europea e la Georgia firmato nel 2014 ha contribuito a portare le relazioni a un nuovo livello e ha rafforzato la cooperazione in molti settori. Utile potrà essere l'apporto del paese dell'ex Unione Sovietica nella lotta contro la criminalità organizzata, compresi terrorismo, corruzione e tratta di esseri umani.</p>
      <p sl="en">Negli ultimi due anni, la Georgia ha compiuto i progressi necessari e ha soddisfatto tutti i parametri di riferimento stabiliti nel piano d'azione sulla liberalizzazione dei visti. Pertanto, valuto positivamente la decisione di esentare dal visto i cittadini georgiani che viaggiano nell'Unione europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-070-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, την ώρα που η Ελλάδα και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση αντιμετωπίζουν τεράστιες προσφυγικές και μεταναστευτικές ροές η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, αποφασίζει να απαλλάξει από την υποχρέωση θεώρησης τους πολίτες της Γεωργίας που ταξιδεύουν στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση για σύντομο χρονικό διάστημα. Βεβαίως η απόφαση κατάργησης της βίζας οδηγεί τη Γεωργία ένα βήμα πιο κοντά στην ευρωπαϊκή της πορεία. Όμως, για να συμβεί αυτό, πρέπει να διασφαλιστεί ότι η Γεωργία σέβεται τα ανθρώπινα δικαιώματα, το κράτος δικαίου και τα δικαιώματα των μειονοτήτων. Δεν θα πρέπει να ξεχνούμε ότι στη Γεωργία υπάρχει ελληνική μειονότητα που επί εκατοντάδες χρόνια ζει και εργάζεται σε αυτή τη χώρα. Καλούμε λοιπόν τις αρμόδιες αρχές της Γεωργίας να σεβαστούν πλήρως τα δικαιώματα της ελληνικής μειονότητας και επιπλέον να μεριμνήσουν ούτως ώστε να παραδοθούν στους Έλληνες Πόντιους τα σπίτια τους, τα οποία, δυστυχώς, έχουν καταληφθεί παράνομα από τρίτους.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-071-0000" speaker_id="124766" name="Petras Auštrevičius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I think that today we have an excellent reason to congratulate both the European Union and Georgia. Let’s be frank: Georgia has made a great step forward towards Europeanisation. We have to admit that Georgia’s progress in many areas, such as the fight against corruption, the judiciary, better border control, and producing better passports for its own citizens, is self—evident. But of course Georgia has not completed everything and I wish Georgia all the best on its way.</p>
      <p sl="en">But, colleagues, let us again be frank. We have even better reason to congratulate the European Union, since today the European Union is building a partnership and not a wall, as unfortunately some countries are doing in today’s world. I am very hopeful that Ukraine will follow suit and that we will in a short time approve the decision on visa liberalisation for Ukraine.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-072-0000" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr, Georgia sikeresen teljesítette a számára meghatározott feltételeket, ezzel is demonstrálva elkötelezettségét az Unióval kialakítandó szorosabb kapcsolatok mellett. Ezzel a maga részéről mindent megtett a vízumkötelezettség eltörléséhez. A felfüggesztési mechanizmus a visszaélések elkerülésére megszületett, ezért most az Unión a sor az ígéreteinek betartására. Az Unió szavahihetősége a tét, ha a vízummentesség megadása tovább halogatódik, ez a térség felé rossz geopolitikai üzenetet közvetítene. Számunkra a kezdetektől fogva prioritást élvez, Magyarország számára is, hogy az Európai Unió Georgiát felvegye a vízummentes országok listájára. Személyes meggyőződésem is az, hogy a biometrikus útlevéllel rendelkező grúz állampolgárok már jó ideje vízummentesen kellene, hogy utazzanak.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ugyanúgy, ahogy az ukrán állampolgárok is. Hiszen Ukrajna – Georgiához hasonlóan – kiérdemelte a vízummentességet. Minden uniós feltételt teljesített, a kettős mérce nem indokolt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-073-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já podporuji zrušení krátkodobých víz pro Gruzii. Tato země je naším důležitým partnerem a také usiluje o přidružení do NATO. Gruzie splnila všechny podmínky, a jak tady řekl pan komisař, tak Evropská komise bude dál sledovat plnění podmínek pro to, aby trval bezvízový styk. My jsme přijali mechanismus pozastavení bezvízového styku, čili nemusí zde být obavy, že bychom v případě velkého nárůstu migrantů či velkého nárůstu žádostí o azyl nemohli bezvízový styk zastavit. Gruzie si prošla velmi složitým obdobím a myslím, že můžeme pogratulovat Gruzíncům, že dosáhli svých cílů, je to pro ně důležitý signál, že se vyplatí bojovat a pokračovat i nadále v reformách. Já bych si přála, abychom dosáhli stejného pokroku a stejného úspěchu v liberalizaci víz s Ukrajinou.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-075-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members of Parliament, let me start by expressing my thanks for this debate. I am really glad at the end of this session that there is a large consensus in this House on the need to keep the promises the European Union has made to the people of Georgia. The Georgian Government has indeed worked very hard to fulfil all the benchmarks of the Visa Liberalisation Action Plan, and I would like to commend and praise once again the government for its commitment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Should there be any problems after visa liberalisation, the revised suspension mechanism is there to deal with that. We will continue to monitor the situation. There is no need to delay this important file any further. Let us proceed with the voting on the report by Ms Gabriel, which will bring us one step closer to the conclusion of the whole procedure to grant visa-free travel for the citizens of this great country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-0000" speaker_id="96848" name="Мария Габриел" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">докладчик. – Г-н Председател, г-н Комисар, искам най-напред да благодаря на колегите за подкрепата и за ясните послания. Благодаря Ви, г-н Комисар, за постоянния диалог и доброто сътрудничество по нелеката работа по това досие. Искам да кажа само две неща. Одобрението днес за безвизово пътуване на грузинските граждани не е жест. То е признание, то е и предизвикателство. Признание за свършеното от грузинските власти, признание за отстояването на общите ни европейски демократични ценности и от грузинските граждани.</p>
      <p sl="en">Днешният вот е и предизвикателство. Предизвикателство да продължим да задълбочаваме партньорството си с Грузия, предизвикателство за нашите културни, икономически и политически връзки. Затова призовавам Съвета максимално бързо да финализира процедурата, за да може преди края на месец март да изпълним ангажимента си.</p>
      <p sl="en">Още веднъж, когато говорим за визи, нека винаги не забравяме, че говорим за гражданите. Дължим им го в името на нашите общи споделени ценности, в името на нашата обща сигурност, в името на нашето общо бъдеще. Сега трябва да преминем и към последния етап на процедурата.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-077-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mam poczucie, że wziąłem udział w historycznej debacie. Cieszę się, że ją prowadziłem. Pozdrawiam naszych gruzińskich przyjaciół na galeriach dla publiczności.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się w czwartek 2 lutego 2017 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-077-0001" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Gruzija je važan trgovinski partner EU-a, te ključni akter u pogledu sigurnosnih izazova u području Istočnog partnerstva. Upravo radi toga, potrebno je osnažiti načelo po kojem svaka zemlja koja je uspješno zadovoljila sva mjerila može ostvariti koristi liberalizacijom viznog režima, ali kriteriji koji su doveli do liberalizacije moraju se sustavno poštovati. Gruzija je postigla očite napretke u provedbi akcijskog plana za liberalizaciju viznog režima (VLAP), te uspjeh u pogledu dostizanja potrebnih mjerila. Takvo što donosi znatne prednosti i za gruzijske građane. Iako je Gruzija zemlja stabilne demokracije, koja je pokrenula konkretne mjere u borbi protiv organiziranog kriminala, uključujući trgovinu ljudima, terorizam i korupciju, potrebno je dodatno pojačati napore koji se ulažu u ostvarivanje napretka u području slobode medija, neovisnosti pravosuđa te pravednog provođenja izbora.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-077-0500" speaker_id="129073" name="Urmas Paet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjalikult. – Gruusia on juba mõnda aega valmis viisavabaduseks ELiga ning on hea, et Euroopa Parlament selle heaks kiitis. Viisavabadus aitab kaasa inimestevaheliste kontaktide loomisele ning ka majandussuhete edendamisele. Loodetavasti saame üsna pea edasi liikuda ka Ukrainale viisavabaduse kehtestamisega.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-078-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Az Európai Unió szomszédságpolitikájának fontos eleme a Keleti Partnerség, amely központi szerepet játszik az EU keleti határán húzódó térségek stabilitását és demokratizálását célzó törekvéseinkben. Figyelemmel arra is, hogy ez egyaránt szolgálja az érintett partnerek és az EU tagállamai érdekét, a Grúziával kötött társulási megállapodás végrehajtása, ennek keretében pedig a vízumliberalizációs akcióterv teljesítése érdekében végzett közel ötéves intenzív munka alapján Grúziát szomszédságpolitikánk egyik sikertörténeteként értékelhetjük. A vízummentes utazás lehetősége – amelyet egyébként a grúz fél már korábban egyoldalúan biztosított az uniós állampolgároknak – a lakossági kapcsolatok és üzleti lehetőségek új területeit nyithatja meg.</p>
      <p sl="en">Természetesen nem lehet szem elől téveszteni, hogy az Európai Unió a Grúziából kivándorolni szándékozók legkedveltebb célpontja, de a megelőző parlamenti viták és az előterjesztés alapján úgy vélem, a megállapodásban előirányzott monitoring és felfüggesztési mechanizmus kellő biztosítékot nyújt az esetleges visszaélésekkel szemben. Megjegyzem, hogy az EU szempontjából kedvező értékelés ugyanígy vonatkozik a grúz esettel gyakorlatilag párhuzamosan tárgyalt ukrán EU-vízumliberalizáció megítélésére, amelynek sikeres végrehajtása minkét partnerünk számára az európai értékekhez és demokratikus struktúrákhoz való kapcsolódás fontos állomását jelenti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-079-0000" speaker_id="96784" name="Janusz Zemke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Popieram wspólny wniosek Parlamentu Europejskiego i Rady w sprawie zwolnienia obywateli Gruzji z wymogu posiadania wiz wewnątrz Unii Europejskiej, jeżeli posiadają oni paszporty biometryczne. Pamiętajmy, że Gruzja uczyniła pierwszy krok, znosząc obowiązek wizowy dla obywateli wszystkich państw UE, w przypadku gdy ich pobyt na terytorium Gruzji nie przekracza 90 dni. Przyjęcie podobnych środków w stosunku do obywateli Gruzji będzie ważnym instrumentem zacieśniania kontaktów kulturalnych i gospodarczych z tym państwem. Gruzja jest kluczowym partnerem UE w ramach wspólnej polityki sąsiedztwa. Powinno nam zależeć na stopniowym zbliżaniu UE i Gruzji. To rozwiązanie będzie istotne zwłaszcza dla studentów, naukowców, nauczycieli i przedsiębiorców. Równocześnie jednak UE powinna monitorować sytuację w Gruzji, podkreślając znaczenie praworządności i niezawisłości sądownictwa w tym państwie.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Cross-border aspects of adoptions (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-081-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Tadeusza Zwiefkę w imieniu Komisji Prawnej zawierające zalecenia dla Komisji w sprawie transgranicznych aspektów adopcji (2015/2086(INL)) (A8-0370/2016).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-082-0000" speaker_id="28301" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">sprawozdawca. – Pani Komisarz! Koleżanki i Koledzy! Kiedy rozpoczynaliśmy pracę nad tym sprawozdaniem w Komisji Prawnej, zadawaliśmy sobie jedno zasadnicze pytanie: jaki tak naprawdę jest cel procedury adopcyjnej? Odpowiedź była prosta i jasna dla wszystkich: tym celem jest stworzenie dobrego, przyjaznego, kochającego środowiska dla właściwego rozwoju dziecka. Dobro dziecka jest podstawowym celem, dla którego przeprowadza się procedury adopcyjne. Zgoda co do tego stwierdzenia stanowiła bardzo dobry punkt wyjścia do dyskusji nad treścią sprawozdania, które finalnie podzieliłem na dwie części.</p>
      <p sl="en">W części pierwszej omawiamy różne aspekty procedur adopcyjnych. Wydaje się, że mimo ich ulepszania z każdym rokiem, wciąż występują poważne braki, wciąż są znaki zapytania, które wymagają odpowiedzi. Dlatego apeluję o stworzenie choćby minimalnych standardów, które pozwoliłyby we wszystkich państwach członkowskich Unii Europejskiej postępować według tych samych zasad. Jakie są te minimalne standardy? Przede wszystkim uszanowanie podmiotowości dziecka. Dziecko jest indywidualnym człowiekiem, nie stanowi niczyjej własności. Zatem w procedurze adopcyjnej w przypadkach, w których jest to już możliwe, należy wysłuchać dziecka przed podjęciem decyzji. Trudno sobie także wyobrazić, aby decyzje o adopcji były podejmowane bez wysłuchania rodziców biologicznych, jeśli oni żyją, bez ich zgody wręcz czy też przed wyczerpaniem linii proceduralnej, jeśli chodzi o pozbawienie biologicznych rodziców władzy rodzicielskiej. Takich kwestii jest wciąż bardzo dużo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mówiliśmy także o tym, jak funkcjonuje konwencja haska z 1993 r. o adopcji międzynarodowej. To jest ważny instrument, bardzo ważny dokument, ale reguluje on tylko te adopcje, które przeprowadzane są w aspekcie transgranicznym. Nie mówi natomiast o tym, jak powinniśmy sobie pomagać w przypadku adopcji krajowej. Poruszam także w moim sprawozdaniu zagadnienie szkoleń sędziów oraz pracowników ośrodków adopcyjnych, którzy zajmują się tą tematyką, tak by procedury były zbliżone, byśmy w podobny sposób podchodzili do kwestii dobra dziecka. Chcę bardzo wyraźnie zaznaczyć, że w całym sprawozdaniu nie ma ani jednego słowa o tym, by zmieniać prawo rodzinne materialne. Doskonale wiemy, że należy to do wyłącznych kompetencji państw członkowskich, i tak powinno pozostać. Natomiast tam gdzie jest to możliwe, powinniśmy wspólnie tworzyć takie procedury, które pozwolą zapewnić dobro dziecka w jeszcze bardziej odpowiedni sposób.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stąd w drugiej części mojego sprawozdania przedstawiam propozycję legislacyjną: zwracam się do Komisji Europejskiej o przygotowanie wniosku w sprawie rozporządzenia Rady dotyczącego uznawania adopcji krajowych. Adopcje krajowe, przeprowadzane według prawa krajowego, mają miejsce w sytuacjach, w których zarówno rodzice adopcyjni, jaki i adoptowane dziecko przebywają, mieszkają w tym samym kraju, są obywatelami tego samego państwa. Kiedy przemieszczają się do innego kraju, te procedury muszą być powtarzane. Stanowi to oczywiście kłopot finansowy i czasowy oraz powoduje niepewność prawną. Dlatego wprowadzenie automatycznego wzajemnego uznawania orzeczeń o adopcji krajowej pozwoliłoby tę sytuację zmienić i poprawić. Wnoszę także o przygotowanie wielojęzycznego poświadczenia o adopcji na wzór poświadczenia spadkowego, które przyjęliśmy dwa lata temu i które świetnie funkcjonuje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-083-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the protection and promotion of children’s rights is a real priority for the Commission. We must ensure that the rights of those who are in particularly difficult situations, such as the victims of abduction or children in migration, are fully respected and promoted. For instance the proposal for the recast of the Brussels IIA Regulation, which was adopted last year on 30 June, strengthens the rights of the child. It introduces a new obligation concerning the hearing of children and specific measures to enhance the efficiency of return proceedings in cases of parental abduction.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank Mr Zwiefka for his comprehensive report. I fully support the call on Member States to strengthen mutual trust and administrative cooperation between them on this important matter. Training for legal practitioners working in the field of cross-border adoption is essential in this respect. The Commission is ready to co-finance relevant projects proposed by interested Member States and stakeholders in line with the current financial framework. The Commission is aware that the lack of recognition of adoption orders between Member States may entail problems both for the parents and, especially, for the child, but we lack updated data on this. The Commission did a study on the subject back in 2009 which was discussed at a joint conference with the Council of Europe in the very same year. However, that study did not provide the Commission with data, as Member States either did not keep statistics or simply did not want to share them. We are aware that adoptive parents may encounter problems when they move to another Member State and that the adopted children’s civil status may be questioned.</p>
      <p sl="en">But let me be clear: this is a very sensitive area of law and, for any legislative proposal in the area of family law to be adopted, we need unanimity in the Council. You mentioned yourself that family law is a domain for the Member States. Any initiative on the recognition of adoption orders at EU level therefore needs to be very strongly evidence-based. For instance, how many cases of lack of recognition are we talking about? What are the key aspects invoked when recognition is challenged? How are Member States dealing with such cases?</p>
      <p sl="en">Currently, preliminary work and consultation regarding a possible initiative on the recognition of domestic adoptions are being carried out at international level in the context of the Hague Conference on Private International Law. Further developments within the Hague Conference can help clarify the depth and extent of the problem and the willingness of Member States to deal with it at international level, as well as any need for corresponding action at EU level. I am following this issue closely and will keep Parliament informed. In parallel, we will continue to support Member States on this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-084-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Συντάκτης της γνωμοδότησης της Επιτροπής Αναφορών. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, θέλω κατ’ αρχάς να ευχαριστήσω τον εισηγητή για τις απόψεις τις οποίες εξέφρασε. Το θέμα των διασυνοριακών πτυχών των υιοθεσιών έχει απασχολήσει πάρα πολλές φορές την Επιτροπή Αναφορών, όπου έχουμε συζητήσει το ζήτημα αυτό και το θεωρούμε πάρα πολύ σημαντικό. Το τελευταίο διάστημα, έχουν προκύψει σημαντικά ζητήματα σε σχέση με τις διασυνοριακές υιοθεσίες που απαιτούν διαφορετική αντιμετώπιση εκ μέρους της Ευρωπαϊκής Επιτροπής. Κατ’ αρχάς, πρέπει να εξασφαλίσουμε ότι όλες οι αποφάσεις υιοθεσίας θα εκδίδονται αποκλειστικά με γνώμονα το συμφέρον του παιδιού για ένα καλύτερο αύριο. Γι’ αυτό και είναι σημαντικό, αναλόγως της ηλικίας και της ωριμότητας του παιδιού, να λαμβάνεται πάντοτε υπόψη η γνώμη του ίδιου του παιδιού. Ταυτόχρονα, πρέπει να καταβάλλεται κάθε δυνατή προσπάθεια ώστε να μην χωρίζονται τα αδέλφια και να διατηρείται η ταυτότητα του ίδιου του παιδιού. Επιπλέον, είναι απαραίτητο να αναληφθεί ευρωπαϊκή νομοθετική δράση προκειμένου να διευκολυνθεί η διασυνοριακή αναγνώριση αποφάσεων υιοθεσίας και να σταματήσουν οι υπερβολικές γραφειοκρατικές διατυπώσεις μεταξύ των κρατών μελών. Τέλος, οι πολιτικές λιτότητας και περικοπών είναι βέβαιο ότι έχουν αρνητικές επιπτώσεις στις ίδιες τις κοινωνικές υπηρεσίες, οι οποίες παίζουν σημαντικό ρόλο και σε σχέση με το αντικείμενο αυτό.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-085-0000" speaker_id="96272" name="Pavel Svoboda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Pane předsedající, paní komisařko, problém přeshraničního uznávání osvojení je jedním z těch problémů, jejichž vyřešení přispívá ke zjednodušení života občanů EU. Mobilita evropských občanů je dnes faktem, který je třeba vzít na vědomí, a je potřeba vytvořit taková pravidla, která využívání svobody pohybu v rámci EU ulehčí, a nikoli ztíží.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pokud se dnes vyslovujeme pro uznání jednotlivých rozhodnutí o osvojení v rámci celé Unie, netvoříme Evropu shora, ale reagujeme na již existující realitu, na neustálé sílící osobní vazby mezi Evropany, na vznikající evropský démos. Mechanismus, který umožní přeshraniční uznávání rozhodnutí o osvojení, aniž by přitom zasahoval do pravidel jednotlivých států upravujících vznik osvojení, je opatřením, které od EU její občané očekávají. Děkuji tedy kolegům z JURI, ale především zpravodaji Tadeuszi Zwiefkovi, že tuto zprávu tak výborně zpracoval.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-086-0000" speaker_id="103845" name="Virginie Rozière" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, je voudrais d’abord remercier le rapporteur et l’ensemble des collègues pour l’excellent travail qui a été réalisé sur cette question.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madame la Commissaire, vous disiez qu’il faut fonder toute action sur des faits, mais notre Parlement est régulièrement saisi de situations de familles qui sont confrontées à de très graves difficultés lorsqu’elles circulent dans l’Union européenne. Elles rencontrent d’énormes difficultés à faire reconnaître les liens familiaux et à vivre une vie de famille normale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans ce domaine comme dans d’autres, je suis persuadée que l’Union européenne peut être la solution. Dans ce sens, le rapport propose des avancées importantes pour faire face à l’éclatement du paysage juridique des différents États membres de l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense qu’au-delà des réticences qui peuvent s’attacher à tels ou tels aspects, c’est l’intérêt supérieur de l’enfant et, tout simplement, le droit à vivre une vie familiale normale, qui doit guider notre action.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense que la proposition de règlement qui est annexée à ce rapport est le meilleur instrument pour garantir une véritable sécurité juridique et sauvegarder efficacement les droits fondamentaux de ces familles, qui se trouvent confrontées à ces difficultés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce règlement permettrait aux enfants qui se trouvent dans des situations fragiles d’être efficacement protégés contre les risques de traite ou d’adoption qui seraient préjudiciables, tout en permettant une vie de famille sereine dans les cas qui l’appellent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, je me félicite qu’il soit fait une référence solide à l’article 21 de la charte des droits fondamentaux pour lutter contre toute forme de discrimination dans les procédures de reconnaissance d’adoption. C’est un objectif essentiel que nous devons défendre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Étant donné que ce texte présente de véritables progrès pour les citoyens, je pense que lui nous apporterons dans ce Parlement un vote et un plein soutien et j’espère, Madame la Commissaire, que vous en tiendrez compte dans vos travaux futurs.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-087-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">от името на групата ECR. – Г-н Председател, уважаеми колеги, говорим за предложение да се приеме регламент, който позволява автоматичното признаване на съдебни решения за осиновявания, издадени в друга държава членка. Необходимо условие за приемането на правила, които позволяват автоматично признаване на тези решения, издадени в друга държава членка, е да се гарантира пълното зачитане на националните разпоредби относно обществения ред и на принципите на субсидиарност и пропорционалност.</p>
      <p sl="en">Подкрепям засилването на съдебното сътрудничество в областта на основанията, тъй като наш дълг е да осигурим възможно най-доброто за най-уязвимите в обществото. Съгласен съм с докладчика, г-н Звефка, че Регламент (ЕО) № 2201/2003 на Съвета относно компетентността и родителската отговорност не отговори на въпроса за признаване на осиновяванията и че предложеното законодателство би могло да допълни съществуващата регулация, запълвайки празнината в законодателството на признаване на осиновения в съответствие с международното право. Специално се позовавам на Хагската конвенция от 1993 г.</p>
      <p sl="en">В съответствие с член 81, параграф 3 от Договора за функционирането на Европейския съюз съм съгласен, че Съветът, използвайки правото си на дерогация, може да създаде някои мерки, свързани със семейното право, които имат трансгранично значение. Единствената оправдана цел е формулирането на общо семейно право за европейски граждани, живеещи в различни страни на Съюза или които са се преместили в друга страна, така че да не се сблъскват с излишни и неоправдани пречки. Новият регламент обаче изисква да се приеме предварително от всяка една от държавите, дори и тези, които нямат нищо общо с казуса.</p>
      <p sl="en">Въпреки това има и друг аспект, които е важно да бъде спазван, тъй като се отнася до суверенитета в областта на семейното право на държавите. Съгласно член 6 от проекта за регламент признаването и разпореждането за приемане, направени в държавата членка, могат да бъдат отказани, само когато правилата за компетентност не са спазени или приемането противоречи на обществения ред в държава членка. Ето защо всяка крайна намеса на ЕС в националната политика на държавите е неоправдана по тази тематика. Такъв е случаят и с моето предложение, в който е използван най-силният инструмент – регламентът.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-088-0000" speaker_id="28206" name="Jean-Marie Cavada" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ALDE. – Monsieur le Président, je veux remercier Mme Jourová et le rapporteur, M. Zwiefka, qui a fait un travail extrêmement précis et de très bonne qualité.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je ne vais pas faire un long discours pour souligner ce que mes collègues ont déjà dit. Je soutiens donc pleinement ce rapport, qui a pour objectif d'imposer aux pays de l'Union européenne la reconnaissance automatique des ordonnances qui seraient rendues dans un des pays de l'Union, de façon à faciliter la vie des parents adoptifs qui circulent dans l'Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y avait, jusqu'à présent, une contradiction terrible: l'Union européenne avait réussi à régler la question de la libre circulation des marchandises, des capitaux, des hommes et des femmes, mais pas celle des enfants adoptés. Nous sommes sur le bon chemin et je voudrais dire que ce qui me touche dans ce rapport, c'est qu'il tient compte du bien supérieur de l'enfant.</p>
      <p sl="en">Par conséquent, je soutiens pleinement et remercie le rapporteur et la proposition de la Commission.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-089-0000" speaker_id="125061" name="Κώστας Χρυσόγονος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, οι διασυνοριακές υιοθεσίες στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση είναι ένα σημαντικό ζήτημα, το οποίο επηρεάζει τις τύχες χιλιάδων οικογενειών που προχώρησαν ή θέλουν να προχωρήσουν στην υιοθεσία παιδιού. Οι υπάρχουσες ρυθμίσεις όχι μόνο δεν εξασφαλίζουν την προστασία παιδιών και γονέων αλλά ουσιαστικά δημιουργούν εμπόδια στην ελεύθερη μετακίνησή τους ανάμεσα στα κράτη μέλη της Ένωσης καθώς σε πολλές περιπτώσεις απαιτούνται επαναλαμβανόμενες γραφειοκρατικές διαδικασίες που συχνά αποτρέπουν οικογένειες από τη μετακίνησή τους σε άλλο κράτος μέλος. Η προστασία των παιδιών οφείλει να αποτελεί προτεραιότητα όλων μας και η διασυνοριακή αναγνώριση των πιστοποιητικών υιοθεσίας συμβάλλει σε αυτόν το στόχο. Παρότι υπάρχουν επιμέρους ζητήματα προς επίλυση, θεωρώ ότι, γενικά, η έκθεση του έγκριτου συναδέλφου κ. Zwiefka κινείται σε πολύ θετική κατεύθυνση και πρέπει με βάση αυτή να προχωρήσουμε ώστε να βελτιωθούν οι διαδικασίες εξέτασης των υποθέσεων υιοθεσίας, να αρθούν τα εμπόδια που ταλαιπωρούν χιλιάδες Ευρωπαίους πολίτες και κυρίως να μην πληρώνουν τα παιδιά το τίμημα της έλλειψης συνεργασίας μεταξύ των κρατών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-090-0000" speaker_id="124693" name="Pascal Durand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, merci infiniment de me donner deux fois la parole, mais je n'en ferai pas un usage trop long.</p>
      <p sl="en">Simplement, je voudrais tout d’abord remercier M. Zwiefka pour le travail qui a été accompli. Le sujet est un sujet difficile. Il touche parfois à la conscience, il touche aux règles de la famille, il touche donc au plus profond de ce qui constitue nos vies. M. Zwiefka a su trouver un terrain qui était un terrain d'intérêt supérieur. Il l'a dit, ce sont les mots qu'il a utilisés, et je veux les reprendre parce qu'ils justifient à la fois le rapport et le travail que nous avons fait tous ensemble, «l'environnement affectif» et «le bien-être de l'enfant». Merci, Monsieur Zwiefka, d'avoir fondé votre rapport sur ces deux notions: elles résument, effectivement, la position et le travail qui ont été les nôtres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cela a été dit – je ne le répéterai pas –, nous sommes là en présence d'un appel du cœur, pour faire en sorte que les enfants ne subissent pas, à travers l'Union, la disparité entre certaines législations. C'est là le travail que nous avons accompli. La reconnaissance automatique, Madame la Commissaire, est nécessaire. Et, effectivement, M. Cavada l'a dit à juste titre, nous ne pouvons pas avoir une libre-circulation pour les marchandises, une libre-circulation pour la finance et ne pas avoir, pour les enfants, cette même reconnaissance réciproque au sein de l'Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je tenais donc à apporter mon soutien le plus vif à M. Zwiefka et à son rapport, et à remercier l'ensemble de mes collègues pour leur travail, en insistant auprès de Mme la Commissaire pour que l'intérêt supérieur des enfants soit pris en compte au sein de l'Union.</p>
      <a text="(L'orateur accepte de répondre à une question &quot;carton bleu&quot; (article 162, paragraphe 8, du règlement))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-091-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">question "carton bleu". – Monsieur le Président, cher collègue, je crois en effet que l’objectif principal est de promouvoir les droits de l’enfant et c’est également l’objet de ma question.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ne croyez-vous pas que les procédures pour l’adoption sont très longues? Aussi, je pense qu’il est nécessaire d’intensifier la coopération entre les autorités nationales pour aboutir à la mise en œuvre de cet important rapport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-092-0000" speaker_id="124693" name="Pascal Durand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">réponse "carton bleu". – Il n’y a pas de difficultés ni de désaccord entre nous. Oui, les procédures sont trop longues et nous essayons de faire en sorte qu’un espace juridique européen fasse qu’il y ait ce qu’on appelle l’exequatur, c’est-à-dire, en gros, qu’un État reconnaisse une adoption qui a eu lieu dans un autre État au sein de l’Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cela existe pour un certain nombre d’autres droits et il faut que le droit de l’adoption en fasse partie, mais dans un contexte qui est particulier – je l’ai dit, ça touche parfois la conscience des gens. Il ne faut pas que l’enfant soit victime des disparités juridiques au sein de l’Union. C’est tout l’objet du rapport de M. Zwiefka, donc je pense que nous sommes d’accord pour mettre un terme à ces longues procédures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-093-0000" speaker_id="124955" name="Jane Collins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, adoption is a wonderful alternative for otherwise unwanted children, or a child that’s left in an unsafe environment. But what concerns me about this report is that it’s another power grab by Brussels over the jurisdiction of family law. In the UK, there are strict laws about family courts, including the privacy of proceedings for what is and always will be a very emotive subject. But what I fear, with this latest demand for ‘more Europe’, is that the best interests of the child may be put second to the EU’s desire for more and more power. And what happens if it is a disputed adoption? If the grandparents want to adopt? Or one parent is actually fighting the case? How will that work if the child is taken across another country’s border, into another culture, or maybe where the child will be brought up speaking a different language? I believe that we all should be encouraging families to be strong and cohesive units, which is the best environment for bringing up a child, surely. We should not be making it easier for families to be torn apart.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker refused to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8))"/>
      <p sl="en">In this Parliament, a great deal of disrespect was shown to my colleague, Nigel Farage. Unfortunately, until our colleagues can show each other respect, I’m afraid I won’t take any more blue cards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-095-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, l’adoption internationale est un problème délicat qui nécessite de trouver un équilibre entre, d’une part, la prise en compte de l’intérêt des enfants et des familles, et, d’autre part, le respect de la souveraineté des États.</p>
      <p sl="en">La convention de La Haye du 29 mai 1993 a réussi à réaliser cet équilibre délicat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Faut-il dès lors se risquer à aller plus loin? C’est ce que pense le rapport Zwiefka.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout en reconnaissant les bonnes intentions de ce rapport, j’estime qu’il privilégie trop l’intérêt des enfants et des familles au détriment de la souveraineté des États.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il étend en effet l’obligation de reconnaissance automatique aux adoptions nationales, ce qui me paraît imprudent, car si on n’y prend pas garde, cela risque d’obliger les États à reconnaître la validité des adoptions faites par des couples de même sexe ou encore des adoptions réalisées à la suite de gestation pour autrui. Or, beaucoup d’États européens n’admettent pas la validité de telles adoptions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le rapport préconise en outre la création d’un certificat d’adoption européen qui me semble s’immiscer de façon excessive dans les compétences des États membres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour ces raisons je suis défavorable à ce rapport.</p>
      <a text="(L'orateur accepte de répondre à une question «carton bleu» (article 162, paragraphe 8, du règlement)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-096-0000" speaker_id="28301" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. – Szanowny Kolego Lebreton! Chciałbym tylko zapytać, jak to możliwe, że z jednej strony akceptuje Pan konwencję haską z 1993 roku regulującą tylko i wyłącznie adopcje o charakterze transgranicznym, międzynarodowym (przeciwko którym zresztą później się Pan trochę nielogicznie wypowiada), a nie chce Pan się zgodzić na poszanowanie decyzji adopcyjnej wydanej w kraju. Państwo przecież zawsze zabiegają o to, żeby szanować krajowe systemy prawne. I o to właśnie chodzi w tym sprawozdaniu, żeby szanować krajowy system prawny.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-097-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">réponse “carton bleu”. – Vous avez imaginé en effet, quelques garde-fous dans votre rapport, notamment la réserve de l’ordre public national. Le problème, voyez-vous, c’est que je sais très bien comment fonctionne l’Union européenne. Dans un premier temps, elle se contente d’un texte modéré et puis au bout de plusieurs années, on nous expliquera qu’il faut davantage d’intégration et vos réserves, cher collègue, sauteront.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-098-0000" speaker_id="96811" name="Rosa Estaràs Ferragut" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. Presentamos hoy una propuesta de Resolución más un anexo que lo que pretende es llenar un vacío legal y dar recomendaciones detalladas y muy concretas para la elaboración de un Reglamento que pueda llenar este vacío legal y pueda abordar el reconocimiento transfronterizo de las adopciones. Qué duda cabe de que las familias, hoy, en Europa, se mueven y, en muchos casos, estas familias tienen hijos adoptados. En algunos países no hay problemas, pero en otros sí hay problemas, porque para que haya un reconocimiento entre el adoptado y el adoptante se necesita establecer, en algunos países, un procedimiento judicial adicional. Eso genera inestabilidad en las familias y eso va contra todos los derechos del niño y contra la propia Convención de La Haya.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por lo tanto, lo que se pide aquí, yo creo que con mucho acierto —y nuestro ponente Tadeusz Zwiefka, ha sido, yo creo, un gran empuje para que esto pueda ver la luz— es un marco jurídico claro que dé seguridad jurídica, que proporcione a las familias de los niños una familia estable. Y para eso se proponen unas normas mínimas en adopción, se propone mayor cooperación, se propone, también, que se respete la Convención de La Haya, porque todos la han firmado, pero luego en la ejecución hay problemas. Y, por último, que sea automático este reconocimiento transfronterizo de las adopciones.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-099-0000" speaker_id="96998" name="Evelyn Regner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! (Die Rednerin spricht ohne Mikrofon.) … darum. Und dementsprechend ist der Vorschlag der Kommission und vor allem die von Herrn Zwiefka als Berichterstatter geleistete Arbeit ausdrücklich anzuerkennen. Wir müssen als Europäische Union eine Union der Bürgerinnen und der Bürger sein. Das heißt auch, unnötige bürokratische Hürden aufgrund mangelnder Zusammenarbeit der nationalen Behörden abzubauen. Es geht darum, eben aus Gründen des Kindeswohls Adoptionen möglichst leicht zu ermöglichen und all diese Hürden dementsprechend zu beseitigen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte allerdings auch darauf hinweisen, dass wir im Jahr 2017 angekommen sein sollten, und daher noch einmal darauf hinweisen, dass wir als Europäisches Parlament endlich dafür sorgen sollten, dass lesbische und schwule Paare in ganz Europa in diesem Zusammenhang die gleichen Rechte haben. Nochmals: aus Gründen des Kindeswohls.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-100-0000" speaker_id="23704" name="Jiří Maštálka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, paní komisařko, zabýváme se tématem přeshraničních aspektů osvojení. Chtěl bych nejprve poděkovat zpravodaji za skvěle odvedenou práci a vyjádřit mu plnou podporu. V současnosti neexistují žádná evropská ustanovení pro uznávání vnitrostátních rozhodnutí o osvojení. To vytváří značné problémy pro evropské rodiny, které se poté, co si osvojily dítě, přestěhovaly do jiného členského státu. I jako lékař jsem přesvědčen, že rodinné prostředí vytváří nejlepší možné podmínky pro zdravý vývoj dítěte a jakékoliv jiné prostředí mu rodinu nikdy nedokáže plnohodnotně nahradit. Svazek, který osvojením vzniká, nahrazuje plnohodnotně vztah rodinný a to z právního, psychologického i společenského hlediska. Já doufám, že se nám podaří odstraňovat překážky přeshraničních aspektů osvojení a tím zároveň i snižovat množství dětí odkázaných na výchovu ve státních zařízeních.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-101-0000" speaker_id="96674" name="Anna Maria Corazza Bildt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, too many children in Europe are deprived of a family due to bureaucracy, and too often children live in a judicial limbo in which their rights are not recognised throughout the EU. And that is why I fully support your report, Tadeusz, calling for mutual recognition and common standards for adoption. We have to address fragmentation and hurdles in the EU and increase judicial cooperation between the Member States, including through the European e-Justice portal. We need common minimum standards to enable Member States to exchange good practices without prejudice to national laws on adoption.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is important. Adoption procedures will remain a national competence as much as family laws, but too many families cannot fully enjoy the freedom of movement of the European Union, and I support the proposal for a regulation on automatic mutual recognition of cross-border adoption orders, to ensure that the rights of adopted children are recognised and respected across the EU. As a co-Chair of the Intergroup on Children’s Rights in this Parliament, I am committed to make sure that the best interests of the child are recognised in all the adoption procedures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-102-0000" speaker_id="88882" name="Victor Negrescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, subiectul adopțiilor a devenit o temă din ce în ce mai importantă odată cu creșterea mobilității persoanelor. Raportul vine cu o soluție propunând elaborarea unor standarde minime comune pentru adopții. Chiar dacă sunt considerate mai degrabă orientări de bune practici, toate părțile recunosc că orice hotărâre de adopție trebuie pronunțată exclusiv în interesul copilului și analizată în funcție de caracteristicile individuale. Raportul stipulează că, la nivel european, trebuie să li se ofere dreptul părinților biologici să recurgă la toate căile de atac legale, înainte să înceapă procedurile de adopție. Astfel, unele probleme apărute între statele membre sau chiar cu țările terțe ar putea fi tratate mai transparent și s-ar asigura măsuri care să protejeze copiii. În aceste condiții, cazuri precum cele ale familiei Barbu din Marea Britanie sau familiei Bugnariu dintr-o țară terță precum Norvegia vor fi tratate cu o mai mare claritate, cu atât mai mult cu cât raportul indică necesitatea ca autoritățile consulare competente să fie permanent informate cu privire la orice decizie de adopție propusă în ceea ce privește un copil care este cetățean al unui alt stat membru, dar cel mai important este că drepturile copiilor vor fi protejate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-103-0000" speaker_id="125050" name="Ángela Vallina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, en la Comisión de Peticiones de este Parlamento hemos recibido estos años más de trescientas peticiones de particulares, de personas que sufrían problemas con la adopción de menores, y en muchos casos solo porque un país no reconoce la adopción dictaminada por un juzgado o una administración de otro país. Por eso, hoy estamos contentos de aprobar esta Resolución que va a exigir al Consejo una herramienta jurídica necesaria.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero, sin embargo, también echo en falta que no hablemos de los nuevos modelos de familia que existen y que además no se pueden ocultar. Echo en falta valentía para hablar de las adopciones por parejas del mismo sexo o por personas solteras, por poner ejemplos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se trata, en definitiva, con esto, de avanzar y de cimentar una Europa de los derechos civiles y sociales. No, desde luego, de las fronteras, de las burocracias o de la discriminación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-104-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já velmi vítám tuto zprávu. O otázce přeshraničního osvojení se v Evropské unii debatuje již mnoho let. Pamatuji si na debatu v roce 2009, kdy Česká republika předsedala EU, a tehdy jsme vedli debatu, jestli upravit jedno evropské právo, jednu evropskou adopci nebo postavit naopak dopředu princip vzájemného uznávání. Já považuji za správné, že nakonec zvítězila myšlenka vzájemného uznávání, která v zásadě neposiluje princip evropské integrace rodinného práva, ale naopak věří v to, že jednotlivé státy jsou schopny v rámci své jurisdikce provádět adopce správně. Takže já myšlenku velmi vítám, je podle mého názoru kompromisem mezi těmi, kteří chtějí zefektivnit přeshraniční aspekty adopcí na jedné straně, a těmi, kteří nechtějí jednotné evropské rodinné právo. Ta oprava je správná a gratuluji panu zpravodaji a doufám, že v praxi bude fungovat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-105-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'interesse superiore del bambino è connaturato nel rispetto dei suoi diritti fondamentali, di cui si può avere reale contezza solo se si è in grado di invertire la prospettiva cambiando l'angolo visuale dall'adulto al bambino. Agevolare questa capacità è compito delle istituzioni e di tutti gli attori sociali, in primis la famiglia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nelle adozioni internazionali – che sono un incontro di affetti, ma anche di culture profondamente diverse – il nucleo protettivo familiare si sviluppa con un rapporto trilatero: minore, genitore adottivo e biologico, con peculiari elementi di estraneità tipici del diritto internazionale privato. Nell'adozione transfrontaliera poi si nascondono incertezze giuridiche più grandi a causa innanzitutto delle differenti procedure di riconoscimento nazionali e della divergenza dei principi guida.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'unico rimedio e punto di riferimento primario per qualsiasi procedura di adozione transfrontaliera resta quindi il rispetto sostanziale e non formale dell'articolo 21 della Convenzione delle Nazioni Unite sui diritti del fanciullo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-106-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος (" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">NI). – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η ανάγκη απόκτησης παιδιών από διάφορες οικογένειες πολλές φορές καλύπτεται μέσω της υιοθεσίας παιδιών από χώρες διαφορετικές της χώρας των γονέων. Επειδή κάθε παιδί έχει το δικαίωμα να ζει σε περιβάλλον αγάπης, στοργής και φροντίδας, θα πρέπει η διεθνής υιοθεσία να διέπεται από κανόνες που εξασφαλίζουν ένα ελάχιστο δεδομένο και εφαρμόζονται, ει δυνατόν, από όλες τις χώρες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ενώσεως. Οι τυπικές διαδικασίες αυτής της υποθέσεως δεν είναι το κυρίαρχο στοιχείο. Το βασικό στοιχείο είναι να δοθεί η δυνατότητα στο παιδί να μεγαλώσει ισορροπημένα και αρμονικά και γι’ αυτό οι οικογένειες που αναλαμβάνουν υιοθεσία πρέπει να επιδεικνύουν την απαιτούμενη σοβαρότητα και τον αναγκαίο σεβασμό απέναντι στο παιδί. Τέλος, θέλω να επισημάνω ότι, για να μεγαλώσει ένα παιδί σωστά και να μην έχει ψυχολογικά προβλήματα, θα πρέπει να μεγαλώσει σύμφωνα με τους νόμους της φύσεως, με τους δύο γονείς, και με τη μητέρα και με τον πατέρα, και να μην αποτελεί υιοθεσία ενός παιδιού μέσον ικανοποιήσεως νοσηρών σκοπιμοτήτων και διαφόρων μη επιτρεπομένων εμμονών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-107-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, giving priority to the interests of the child may be found in international law and in Member States’ law, and to that end it is necessary to consider two things: that these interests be properly translated into the procedural rules, because they should not be unnecessarily bureaucratic and lengthy; and also how they are applied.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why I am in favour of doing much more in conjunction with the Member States, for instance in the field of training of judges and professionals. The Commission will consider adding this as a new topic amongst other topics: where we train judges on victims’ rights, procedural safeguards for children, Brussels IIA, etc., this could also be covered. So this is my commitment to you from today’s discussion.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the new legislation: family law is the domain of the Member States. We must be very careful here because these are emotional and sensitive topics; unanimity is required for a very good reason. So we will consider this call for legislation, but, as I said before, it must be evidence-based, there must be a test of whether this is a severe pan-European problem; whether there is strong demand from the Member States that we have a European solution; and the third important thing is whether the European Union has any legal competence to regulate on this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-108-0000" speaker_id="28301" name="Tadeusz Zwiefka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">sprawozdawca. – Panie Przewodniczący! Króciutko: chciałbym bardzo serdecznie podziękować wszystkim koleżankom i kolegom, którzy zabrali głos w czasie dzisiejszej debaty, pokazującej jednoznaczne poparcie dla takiego właśnie podejścia do procedur adopcyjnych. Procedur szalenie ważnych, bowiem mówimy o naszych dzieciach, o naszej przyszłości. Zagwarantowanie dobra dziecka, jego prawidłowego rozwoju jest naszym absolutnym obowiązkiem i priorytetem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przy całym szacunku dla przepisów zawartych w konwencji haskiej z 1993 r. o międzynarodowej adopcji dzieci, tam jest mowa tylko i wyłącznie o adopcjach międzynarodowych. Sprawozdanie, nad którym dzisiaj będziemy głosowali w naszej Izbie mówi o uznawaniu krajowych orzeczeń adopcyjnych, i to jest zasadnicza różnica. W tym obszarze nie mamy żadnych regulacji. Stąd moja propozycja, poparta bardzo szeroko podczas dzisiejszej debaty i wychodząca naprzeciw oczekiwaniom rodziców, by ich przenoszenie się do innego państwa członkowskiego nie komplikowało życia, w przypadku gdy towarzyszą im adoptowane dzieci.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bardzo serdecznie dziękuję wszystkim, którzy razem ze mną pracowali nad tym sprawozdaniem. Nietrudno sobie wyobrazić, ile różnych kwestii można by było poruszyć w takim sprawozdaniu, ale dziękuję za to, że koleżanki i koledzy zechcieli skupić się na pracy w zakresie, który jasno określiłem na początku, że nie wrzucaliśmy do tego sprawozdania kwestii, które nie mogą się w nim pomieścić. Dziękuję bardzo raz jeszcze za debatę oraz za obietnicę ze strony Komisji, że będziemy przygotowywać kolejne rozporządzenia, które ułatwią życie naszym rodzinom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-109-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się w czwartek 2 lutego 2017 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-109-0500" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Investiţia în copii este o investiţie în viitorul societăţii noastre, iar creşterea şi educarea acestora în condiţii decente și sigure trebuie să fie permanent în atenția tuturor, indiferent de locul în care se află. În acest context, vorbim despre adopțiile transfrontaliere și despre interesul superior al copilului în astfel de situații. Protecţia copilului este prioritară în orice situaţie, iar în cazul adopţiilor cu caracter transfrontalier intervin o serie de factori care trebuie luați în seamă pentru a garanta protejarea intereselor copiilor. Susțin importanța elaborării unor standarde minime comune pentru adopții, dar și necesitatea unei mai bune cooperări în materie de justiție civilă în domeniul adopțiilor. Întrucât, la nivel european, nu există un cadru obligatoriu pentru recunoașterea hotărârilor de adopție pronunțate în urma unei proceduri naționale, se impune o acțiune legislativă, astfel încât dreptul cetățenilor europeni la viața de familie și la libera circulație să fie respectat în permanență. Comisia și Consiliul trebuie să identifice mecanisme care să garanteze protejarea intereselor copiilor, cetățeni europeni, și atunci când aceștia trăiesc în afara spațiului Uniunii Europene. Este extrem de important ca, în astfel de situații, copiii să aibă posibilitatea de a menţine legătura cu fundalul cultural, de a învăţa şi de a folosi limba maternă.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-110-0000" speaker_id="23868" name="Monika Flašíková Beňová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne – Proces súvisiaci s osvojením či adopciou dieťaťa nie je jednoduchý. O jeho výsledku rozhoduje súd na základe návrhu žiadateľov. V prípade pozitívneho výsledku majú osvojitelia pri výchove detí rovnakú zodpovednosť, práva a povinnosti ako biologickí rodičia. Nedorozumenia však môžu vznikať pri cestovaní, či sťahovaní sa s takýmito deťmi do iných krajín. V súčasnosti, bohužiaľ, neexistuje žiaden medzinárodný ani spoločný európsky rámec, ktorý by zabezpečoval automatické uznávanie vnútroštátnych rozhodnutí o osvojení. Výsledkom nebudú žiadne záväzné regulácie. Ide skôr o vypracovanie odporúčaní a najlepších postupov, podľa ktorých by takéto rodiny, napríklad pri presťahovaní sa do iného štátu v rámci Európskej únie, nemuseli dodatočne žiadať o uznanie už vydaného domáceho rozhodnutia. Odstránili by sa tým niektoré administratívne prekážky a posilnila ochrana práv detí, ako aj ich rodičov. Zjednodušilo by im to život a aspoň v tejto oblasti by boli uchránení od prípadných ďalších stresových situácií.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-111-0000" speaker_id="124817" name="Enrico Gasbarra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – In materia di adozioni sono ancora troppo numerosi gli ostacoli che si frappongono per i tanti casi transfrontalieri che toccano migliaia di famiglie. Con la relazione del collega Zwiefka si pongono sul tavolo misure che da tempo tanti cittadini europei aspettavano. Apprezzo lo sforzo fatto per suggerire proposte omogenee e complessive: reputo anche io che introdurre un regolamento generale possa essere davvero uno strumento di grande efficacia. Mi preme in particolare evidenziare la previsione di norme minime comuni per le adozioni, fondate in particolare sulla convinzione che ogni provvedimento di adozione sia emanato puramente nell'interesse del bambino, e sia valutato in base alle specifiche caratteristiche di ciascun caso. Lo scambio di informazione tra le autorità consolari competenti in merito all'adozione di un bambino avente la nazionalità di un altro Stato membro sarebbe già un passo avanti concreto e di immediata applicazione, e auspico che la Commissione a partire da alcuni degli esempi suggeriti possa proporre norme rapide ed efficaci.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-112-0000" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Przestrzeganie art. 21 Konwencji ONZ o prawach dziecka powinno stanowić podstawę dla wszelkich procedur, działań i strategii dotyczących adopcji o charakterze transgranicznym. W tym kontekście należy poprawić dostęp obywateli do pełnych informacji na temat aspektów prawnych i procesowych adopcji krajowej w państwach członkowskich, co ułatwiłoby adopcję międzynarodową, zwiększając tym samym liczbę adoptowanych dzieci. Zgadzam się, że portal „e-Sprawiedliwość” mógłby być odpowiednim miejscem do wyszukiwania takich informacji. Uważam, że Komisja Europejska powinna przeprowadzić analizę skarg dotyczących adopcji transgranicznych bez zgody rodziców. Takie przypadki nie powinny mieć miejsca. Kiedy dziecko skierowane do adopcji jest obywatelem innego państwa członkowskiego, wydanie jakiejkolwiek decyzji powinny poprzedzać konsultacje z organami konsularnymi danego kraju oraz z rodziną dziecka tam zamieszkującą. Powinno się zachęcać europejskich rzeczników praw dziecka do bliższej współpracy i koordynacji w ramach współpracy w obrębie Europejskiej Sieci Rzeczników Praw Dziecka. Takie działania mogłyby obejmować udział w finansowanych przez UE projektach w dziedzinie szkolenia kadr wymiaru sprawiedliwości.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-112-0500" speaker_id="124898" name="Julia Pitera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Obecnie brak jest w Unii Europejskiej mechanizmu regulującego automatyczne uznawanie krajowych orzeczeń o adopcji wydanych w państwach członkowskich. Komplikacje mogą więc powstać w sytuacji, kiedy dziecko zostało adoptowane w systemie krajowym, a następnie rodzice podejmą decyzję o przeprowadzce do innego państwa członkowskiego. Wtedy takie rodziny mogą zostać zobligowane do poddania się dodatkowym, specjalnym procedurom uznania adopcji w innym państwie członkowskim lub nawet do ponownej adopcji dziecka. A jeśli adopcja nie zostanie uznana, oznacza to, że rodzice natrafią na przeszkody w sprawowaniu władzy rodzicielskiej. Nie będą mogli np. zgłosić dzieci do szkoły lub wyrazić zgody na przeprowadzenie operacji, jeśli dziecko zachoruje. Brak pewności prawa w tej dziedzinie może więc stanowić istotną przeszkodę dla swobodnego przemieszczania się rodzin. Dlatego uważam, że uznawanie krajowych adopcji powinno być automatyczne, chyba że takie uznanie byłoby sprzeczne z porządkiem publicznym danego państwa członkowskiego lub państwo członkowskie, w którym adopcja miała miejsce, nie posiadałoby jurysdykcji. Te dwa wyjątki powinny zostać zachowane. Są one zresztą uwzględnione w propozycji legislacyjnej. Dlatego chciałabym jednoznacznie poprzeć tekst zaproponowany przez posła Zwiefkę.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-113-0000" speaker_id="124850" name="Емил Радев" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">в писмена форма. – Уважаеми колеги, съществуват много проблеми в областта на трансграничните осиновявания, които засягат множество семейства и интересите на техните деца. Аз ще се спра на три от тях. Първо, и най-важното, призовавам Европейската комисия да предприеме необходимите мерки за спиране на порочните практики на осиновяване на деца без разрешението на биологичните им родители в Европейския съюз. Имаме много такива случаи във Великобритания, които направо са се превърнали в бизнес. Надявам се да бъдат направени съответните промени това да се случва само в крайни случаи и то за изключителна защита на висшия интерес на детето. Второ, трябва да насърчим сътрудничеството и обмена на информация, както между съдилищата, които се занимават с осиновявания, така и между социалните служби и националните администрации на държавите членки. Трето, при случаите на трансгранични осиновявания бих искал да акцентирам върху нуждата от зачитане на културните и социалните традиции според произхода на детето. Защото в най-добър интерес на детето е то да остане в кръга на своето семейство, дори и то да не е в обичайното местопребиваване на детето. Подкрепям предложението за въвеждането на общ формуляр за признаването на тези трансгранични осиновявания, тъй като това ще улесни и ще спести средства на родителите. Благодаря за вниманието!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-113-0500" speaker_id="124792" name="Laurenţiu Rebega" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Țin să subliniez că domeniul dreptului familiei la nivel național, deci și adopția, este de competența statelor membre. Atunci când persoanele decid să se mute într-un alt stat membru al Uniunii, apar însă dificultăți legate de recunoașterea și rezolvarea pe cale legală a situației juridice a acestor persoane. Totuși, nu înțeleg de ce este nevoie să creăm o nouă legislație, să impunem noi reguli, în loc să utilizam pârghiile de care dispunem deja, pentru a cointeresa statele membre să ajungă la o abordare uniformă în domeniul adopțiilor. Pe de o parte, trebuie susținute instruirea funcționarilor și judecătorilor naționali implicați în adopții, schimbul de experiență și îmbunătățirea cooperării între aceștia. Pe de altă parte, statele membre trebuie încurajate să evite birocrația inutilă în domeniul adopțiilor. Să nu uităm că ceea ce trebuie să primeze este interesul superior al copilului. În fiecare din țările noastre sunt destui copii abandonați. Este important ca fiecare stat membru să ușureze procedurile naționale, pentru ca acești copii să se poată bucura pe deplin de toate drepturile, și, în primul rând, de dreptul de a avea o familie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-114-0000" speaker_id="124793" name="Claudia Țapardel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Fiecare copil din lume are dreptul la o familie și la un mediu în care să fie iubit și în care să primească educația necesară pentru viața de adult. De aceea, consider că instituțiile europene au o responsabilitate morală de a proteja drepturile fiecărei familii și mă bucur că Parlamentul este primul care propune un set de măsuri pentru cei care au adoptat copii și vor să se bucure de libertatea de a se stabili în alt stat decât cel de origine. În contextul în care numărul cuplurilor și familiilor internaționale este în continuă creștere, legislația comunitară trebuie să se adapteze noilor realități și să ofere oricărei familii din Europa garanția că drepturile sale vor fi recunoscute și respectate de către autoritățile din toate statele membre. Totodată, este regretabil că executivul european nu a răspuns încă la solicitarea PE din 2011 de a lua măsuri de reglementare a aspectelor transfrontaliere în materie de adopție. Aici nu este vorba doar de apărarea unor principii, ci și de protejarea în situații concrete a drepturilor tuturor părinților și copiilor din Uniunea Europeană, oriunde s-ar afla aceștia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-115-0000" speaker_id="96697" name="Valdemar Tomaševski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Tema, apie kurią šiandien kalbame yra labai svarbi ir susijusi su aspektais, darančiais įtaką visam vaiko gyvenimui. Turėdami tai omenyje, privalome nepamiršti, kad įvaikinimo srityje labai svarbu priimti visus sprendimus siekiant vaiko gerovės, gerbiant pagrindines vaiko ir tėvų teises. Įvaikinimo tikslas nėra suteikti suaugusiems teisę į vaiką, bet užtikrinti vaikui stabilią aplinką, kurioje jis harmoningai augs, supamas priežiūros ir meilės. Nepamirškime, kad tarpvalstybinis įvaikinimas turėtų būti vykdomas tik kraštutiniu atveju, nes tai visam laikui nukerta vaiko ryšius su jo kilmės šalimi. Nustatant teisines normas reikėtų siekti pusiausvyros tarp įvaikinto vaiko teisių į savo tapatybės pažinimą ir biologinių tėvų teisių. Jokiu būdu vaikas negali būti atimamas iš tėvų ir atiduodamas tarpvalstybiniam įvaikinimui dėl tėvų skurdo. Atitinkamos kompetentingos valstybių narių institucijos neturėtų pripažinti tokių atvejų, kai materialinės biologinių tėvų sąlygos sudaro išskirtinį pagrindą ir motyvą atimti iš jų tėvų valdžią ir atiduoti vaiką įvaikinimui. Tai nepriimtina ir turi būti aiškiai apibrėžta teisės aktuose. Taip pat reiktų suteikti biologiniams tėvams galimybę pasinaudoti visomis teisių gynimo priemonėmis siekiant išspręsti neigiamą jiems sprendimą. O įvaikinimo atveju vaikas turėtų pakliūti į pilną šeimą, kurioje yra ir motina, ir tėvas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-115-0001" speaker_id="125104" name="Romana Tomc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pisno. – V tem trenutku ni zavezujočih evropskih okvirov za priznanje čezmejnih posvojitev. Z obstoječo Haaško konvencijo je določen le sistem upravnega sodelovanja kadar posvojitelji in otroci ne bivajo v isti državi. Tako pravica evropskih državljanov do družinskega življenja, kot pravica do prostega gibanja sta na vrhu prioritet Evropske ljudske stranke in Slovenske demokratske stranke. Močno se zavzemam za to, da bi EU zagotovila jasen pravni okvir, ki bi olajšal življenje mnogim družinam. Nesprejemljivo se mi zdi, da bi morali starši, ki se na primer selijo v tujino, ponovno dokazovati pravico skrbništva nad svojimi otroci, kar se lahko zgodi pri vpisu v šolo ali pri urejanju zdravstvenega zavarovanja. Evropsko potrdilo o posvojitvah je zato dober predlog, ki bi mnogim družinam prihranil nepotrebne birokratske postopke.V Parlamentu smo slišali mnogo razprav glede vprašanja subsidiarnosti držav članic na področju čezmejnih posvojitev. Ob tem je pomembno vedeti, da bo zakonodaja držav članic s področja družinskega prava še vedno spoštovana. Z zakonodajo bi lahko onemogočili nepotrebne zaplete mnogih družin, prav tako pa bi zagotovili spoštovanje pravice posvojenega otroka do stabilnega pravnega položaja. Tako bomo ravnali v dobro otrok.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Welcome">
    <intervention id="2-119-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">J'ai également le plaisir de saluer, dans la tribune officielle, M. Irakli Kobakhidze, Président du Parlement de Géorgie, et la délégation qui l'accompagne.</p>
      <a text="(Applaudissements)"/>
      <p sl="en">Ils effectuent ce jour une visite de travail au Parlement européen et nous ont fait l'honneur de leur présence lors du débat et du vote d'aujourd'hui.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons donc le plaisir de leur souhaiter cordialement la bienvenue.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Voting time">
    <intervention id="2-121-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordre du jour appelle l'Heure des votes.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="7.1. An integrated approach to Sport Policy: good governance, accessibility and integrity (A8-0381/2016 - Hannu Takkula)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="7.2. Cross-border aspects of adoptions (A8-0370/2016 - Tadeusz Zwiefka)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="7.3. Bilateral safeguard clause and stabilisation mechanism for bananas of the EU-Colombia and Peru Trade Agreement (A8-0277/2016 - Marielle de Sarnez)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="7.4. Sustainable management of external fishing fleets (A8-0377/2016 - Linnéa Engström)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="7.5. Third countries whose nationals are subject to or exempt from a visa requirement: Georgia (A8-0260/2016 - Mariya Gabriel)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="7.6. Rule of law crisis in the Democratic Republic of Congo and in Gabon (RC-B8-0120/2017, B8-0120/2017, B8-0121/2017, B8-0122/2017, B8-0123/2017, B8-0124/2017, B8-0125/2017, B8-0126/2017)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-129-0000" speaker_id="4262" name="Jo Leinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, we wish to express the fact that a political dialogue has been organised by Ali Bongo but it has not happened yet. So the new version should read ‘the intended political dialogue’. That is the change, because it has not happened yet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-131-0000" speaker_id="4262" name="Jo Leinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this is another adaptation to the current situation. We say that ‘certain members of the opposition have not signed the agreement’ with Mr Kabila for the next elections, but in the meantime they have signed the agreement. So we have to delete this part.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="7.7. Implementation of Erasmus + (A8-0389/2016 - Milan Zver)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-134-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ceci clôt l'Heure des votes.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8. Explanations of vote"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="8.1. An integrated approach to Sport Policy: good governance, accessibility and integrity (A8-0381/2016 - Hannu Takkula)">
    <intervention id="2-138-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Chciałem zwrócić uwagę, że to sprawozdanie jest de facto swoistym apelem: apelem o walkę z dopingiem, apelem o czysty sport, ale także apelem o obniżenie rozmaitych podatków. I chcę tu wyraźnie podkreślić, że – to co jest kluczowe – jest on skierowany przede wszystkim do dzieci i do tych, którzy uprawiają sport masowy. Z tego powodu poparłem to sprawozdanie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-139-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, given my sporting background I supported this report in the light of its comprehensive evaluation of sporting policy within the European Union. Transcending all social spheres, I firmly believe that sporting initiatives could serve as a vital vehicle for social inclusion, sporting involvement in growth, employment and indeed society as a whole.</p>
      <p sl="en">However in recent times we have borne witness to a growing trend of corruption within the sporting climate. The series of recent high-level corruption cases on both the European and international stage have made it clear that transparency and greater regulation and cohesion in sporting policy must now define our path. Sport reflects society, and we must safeguard this sector for the benefit of generations to come.</p>
      <p sl="en">Molaim an tUasal Takkula as an jab atá déanta aige.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-141-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-жо Председател, уважаеми колеги, докладът на г-н Такула разглежда широките социални, икономически, образователни и здравни ползи от спорта в Съюза и настоящите предизвикателства. Призовава за многостепенно действие при насърчаването на добро управление, борба с корупцията, като същевременно се зачита независимостта на спортните организации. Като цяло посоката, която дава крайният компромисен вариант, е позитивна и трябва да бъде подкрепен фактът, че масовият спорт играе ключова роля в социалното сближаване и борбата с радикализацията, както и че доброволческата дейност в спорта е от голямо значение.</p>
      <p sl="en">Има необходимост от по-ефективно използване на средствата на Европейския съюз за спорт. Смятам също, че е необходимо, и дори задължително, да се намали административната тежест за местните спортни организации. Гласувах обаче против доклада, защото съм против параграфа, който задължава националните спортни федерации да използват знамето и символа на Съюза, заедно със съответните национални знамена и символи, когато се провеждат международни спортни прояви.</p>
      <p sl="en">Това е много повече федерализъм, отколкото мога да приема. Смятам себе си за защитник на националните интереси в Съюза, който трябва да работи заедно в определени политики за общото благо и добросъседски отношения, но ще отстоявам винаги неприкосновеността на знамето, символите и националните традиции.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-142-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem se u této zprávy nakonec zdržel a chci tedy vysvětlit proč. Já v žádném případě nechci vystupovat proti sportu, jsem si vědom, jak je to důležitý aspekt lidského života, ale kladu si otázku, nakolik téma sportu má zrovna řešit EU a nakolik toto není přesně téma, které si mají řešit jednotlivé národní státy. Nicméně i přesto jsou ve zprávě věci, kvůli kterým jsem se nakonec zdržel. Například snaha prosadit specializovaná státní zastupitelství, která by řešila trestné činy v oblasti sportu, já to považuji opravdu za věc dosti zvláštní, nevím, proč bychom měli mít specializovaná státní zastupitelství, zvláště pro tento typ trestné činnosti. V malých státech to naopak povede k tomu, že by takovéto úřady asi neměly moc práce a naopak by tedy jejich odbornost spíše klesala. Takže sport určitě ano, ale je otázka, nakolik přijímat takovéto zprávy na úrovni EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-143-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, from my point of view of the main task of sport is to propagate a healthy lifestyle among young people. Sports make an important contribution to social values such as tolerance, solidarity, peace, respect for human rights, and understanding among nations and cultures. Recent corruption scandals have tarnished the image of sport, raising questions about the need for structural reforms of sports governing bodies and organisations. We need a zero tolerance policy for corruption and other types of crime in sports. Fighting corruption in sport requires transnational efforts and cooperation among all stakeholders, including public authorities, law enforcement agencies, the sport industry, athletes and supporters.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-144-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem se rozhodla podpořit usnesení Evropského parlamentu o integrovaném přístupu k politice v oblasti sportu, protože stejně jako kolega Dzhambazki je považuji za určitý apel na podporu sportu a také ochranu sportu právě před jeho zneužíváním, před byznysem. Je to apel na aspekt fair play. Profesionální sport a zdaleka nejenom fotbal, ale i jiné druhy sportu se potýkají s negativními jevy, jako je korupce, ovlivňování výsledků zápasů, doping, špatný management sportovních klubů či zneužívání sportovců, např. formou vlastnictví hráčů třetí stranou. Souhlasím s kolegou Pospíšilem, že je potřeba zvážit, jaké legislativní nástroje použijeme, ale v každém případě proti těmto jevům se musí bojovat, abychom udrželi pozitivní obraz profesionálních i amatérských soutěží, aby sport zůstal sportem, zejména fair play.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-145-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, sport is surely the supreme example of a non-political, non-state activity, the ideal of a civil society. A sporting club or association exists for no higher purpose than to give mutual pleasure to its members and supporters. Nobody is forced to join, people stay only if they want to. So why do we need to have a sport policy? How have we got to the point where politicians need to get their hands on something that ought to lie outside the purview of government?</p>
      <p sl="en">Having a sport policy always struck me as a sign of an insecure dictatorship. It was the kind of thing that the Comecon states used to do in the Cold War, to treat sporting success as a symbol of national virility. Surely we in advanced democracies should hold ourselves to a higher standard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-146-0000" speaker_id="28316" name="Hannu Takkula" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, äänestin luonnollisesti tämän mietinnön puolesta. EU:lla on rajoitettu toimivalta urheilun suhteen ja sen puitteissa tämä mietintö on tehty. Ottaen huomioon, mikä on EU:n toimivalta. Osa jäsenistä näytti lukeneen mietinnön ja osa ei. Sen vuoksi kaikkiin äänestysselityksiin, mitä tässä tänään on käyty läpi, en halua puuttua. Sen verran sanon, että kun täällä lippuasia nousi esille ja ymmärsin, että sen vuoksi monet ECR-ryhmästä äänestivät sitä vastaan, että kysymys ei ole mistään sitovista asioista vaan suosituksista. Itsekin vastustin tuota ajatusta, mutta tämä on suositus, ja koska se on suositus, se ei sido ketään. Voi laittaa sen lipun vaikka paidan sisäpuolelle tai jättää kokonaan laittamatta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mitä tulee sitten taas itsenäisten valtioiden vapauteen päättää asioistaan. Kuinka sivistyneitä ollaan? Juuri äskettäin Hannan lopetti. Minä tiedän, että kun Iso-Britanniassa mennään olympialaisiin, on Team GB, ja kun pelataan jalkapalloa, Wales, Skotlanti, Englanti ja Pohjois-Irlanti ovat erikseen. Kun taas pelataan rugbya, on Irlanti, missä Pohjois-Irlanti, Wales, Skotlanti ja Englanti ovat erikseen. Voi sanoa näin, että tälläkin hetkellä me otamme huomioon tämän moninaisuuden. Puhumme urheilun yleismerkityksistä liikuttaa ihmisiä ja taistella niitä ongelmia ja sairauksia vastaan mitä meillä Euroopassa on ja taata kansalaisille hyvinvointia yli erilaisten rajojen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="8.2. Cross-border aspects of adoptions (A8-0370/2016 - Tadeusz Zwiefka)">
    <intervention id="2-173-0000" speaker_id="124864" name="Michela Giuffrida" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'Unione europea deve essere un'opportunità per i cittadini e non un ostacolo. La situazione di una famiglia con bambini adottati che decide di trasferirsi all'estero si può trasformare in un incubo burocratico: potrebbe addirittura succedere che il procedimento di adozione non venga riconosciuto, potrebbe essere necessario avviare nuove pratiche – sarebbe come chiedere, in pratica, a un bambino di rinascere. E se la valutazione del secondo paese fosse diversa, che cosa succederebbe? Si creerebbero situazioni paradossali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ho votato a favore di questa relazione perché chiarisce che l'adozione non è il diritto di una coppia a diventare genitori ma il diritto di un bambino a vivere in un ambiente stabile, affettuoso e premuroso. È comprensibile che gli ordinamenti giuridici degli Stati membri siano diversi, ma nel rispetto del principio della sussidiarietà è necessario intervenire. Il primo passo potrebbe proprio essere l'adozione di un regolamento per il riconoscimento automatico dei provvedimenti di adozione nei paesi membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-174-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, svým hlasováním jsem podpořila zprávu o návrhu nařízení Rady o přeshraničních aspektech osvojení, které navrhuje zavést automatické uznávání vnitrostátních rozhodnutí o osvojení vydaných v jednom členském státě jiným členským státem. Takové pravidlo umožní uznat rozhodnutí soudu nebo jiného příslušného orgánu o adopci vydané v jiném členském státě. Avšak v žádném případě nezasahuje do vnitrostátních pravidel adopce. Považuji za důležité toto uvést jako pravý důvod, proč jsem podpořila tento návrh zprávy. Já osobně nesouhlasím s tím, aby děti byly dávány k osvojení registrovaným partnerům, ale jsem přesvědčena o tom, že tento návrh zprávy není o tomto rozhodnutí a nezasahuje do vnitrostátních legislativ, které plně rozhodují o podmínkách adopce ve své působnosti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-175-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the adoption of children is a very important and sensitive task for our societies, and is especially so for Latvia. It is a shame that a lot of children still live in special state institutions, not in their families. States should take all decisions in adoption matters with the best interests of the child in mind, and with respect for his or her fundamental rights, while always taking into account the specific circumstances of the particular case. The child should always be given the opportunity to be heard without pressure and express his or her view on the adoption process, taking into account his or her age. No decision on adoption should be taken before the biological parents have been heard. I am convinced that the interests of the children have to be taken in consideration as the only main criterion. I voted in favour, of course.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-176-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-жо Председател, уважаеми колеги, гласувах „въздържал се“ по доклада на колегата Звефка, тъй като не смятам, че е необходима намеса на Съюза в сфери, които попадат в суверенитета на държавите членки. Изборът на най-силния правен аргумент за хармонизация на законодателството – регламента по конкретна тема, е също доказателство за намеса във вътрешната политика на държавите – членки на Съюза.</p>
      <p sl="en">Същевременно подкрепям засилването на съдебното сътрудничество в областта на осиновяванията, защото е наш морален дълг да осигурим максимална възможност за защита на една от най-уязвимите групи в обществото. Семейството е основата на едно общество. Именно поради тази причина трябва да съумеем да намерим баланса, така че едновременно да защитим правата на семейството и да не отнемаме правомощията на държавите членки по политики, формирани въз основа на културни и исторически фактори и традиции.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-177-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Adopcia musí byť v najlepšom záujme dieťaťa. To, kedy je tento záujem splnený, si zákonmi definujú členské štáty. Ak Európska únia štátom nariadi automaticky uznávať aj osvojenia, ktoré ich vlastné zákony neumožňujú, bude to hrubý zásah do ich výlučných právomocí v oblasti rodinného práva. Výsledkom takéhoto zásahu bude, že najlepší záujem dieťaťa pre celú Úniu definuje členský štát s najliberálnejšími zákonmi. V ostatných štátoch vznikne schizofrenická situácia a ich súdy budú musieť riešiť diskriminačné žaloby. Snaha spravodajcu definovať minimálne normy pre osvojenie je chvályhodná. Mala sa však zastaviť tam, kde sa pohľad členských štátov na rodinu a osvojenie dieťaťa rozchádzajú. Preto som túto správu nemohla podporiť.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-178-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, now here is a subject with an apparently cross-border aspect. Adoptions do take place across national borders, and it seems sensible to have a framework. Of course, immediately one runs up against the fact that most cross-border adoptions are not limited to EU Member States. There is a lot of adoption that takes place from outside the EU. And here’s the good news: it is regulated by an international framework; it is regulated by the Hague Convention of 1993. So why do we need additional EU regulation that applies narrowly only to one part of the world? I suppose it is conceivable that there are some gaps that need to be filled in. But again countries could surely opt in on a bilateral or multilateral basis without needing to involve the entire bureaucracy of the European Union? I have said it before and I’ll say it again: international cooperation beats supranational government every time.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-179-0000" speaker_id="124927" name="Branislav Škripek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, a European regulation where the rights of the child are prioritised should be welcomed. However this report calls for measures that we should absolutely reject. In the name of convenience and harmonisation of documents, children would be at the risk of being trafficked across borders. Already some Member States have seen a dramatic rise in the number of children being taken into care away from their biological parents. Research into abuse consistently shows that natural parents are the ones least likely to abuse their children.</p>
      <p sl="en">We cannot put children at risk by loosening the strict adoption procedures in place, by imposing a poor, one-size-fits-all European regulation. A child needs both father and mother to flourish. Let us invest in supporting that most important family unit, helping biological parents raise their children even in difficult circumstances.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="8.3. Bilateral safeguard clause and stabilisation mechanism for bananas of the EU-Colombia and Peru Trade Agreement (A8-0277/2016 - Marielle de Sarnez)">
    <intervention id="2-205-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, kolegyně a kolegové, dovolte, abych se vyjádřila k hlasování o tomto bodu. Produkce banánů tvoří důležitou součást zemědělské produkce některých členských států EU a vytváří významné množství pracovních míst v této oblasti. Proto je také třeba usilovat o zachování evropské produkce banánů. Svým hlasováním jsem proto podpořila zprávu o návrhu nařízení, jímž se mění nařízení provádějící dvoustrannou ochrannou doložku a mechanismus stabilizace pro banány mezi EU na straně jedné a Kolumbií a Peru a dále státy střední Afriky na straně druhé. Vzhledem k rozšíření preferenčních celních sazeb pro obchod s banány také na Ekvádor vítám rozšíření působnosti ochranné doložky a mechanismu stabilizace také na Ekvádor. Souhlasím také s uložením povinnosti Komisi monitorovat dodržování stanoveného objemu dovozu banánů a s povinností informovat Evropský parlament v případě, kdyby hrozilo závažné narušení tohoto trhu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-206-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it is curious, isn’t it, that the European Union has trade restrictions on bananas. It is not exactly as though there is a domestic banana industry in the European Union that requires protection. A friend of mine in Cornwall did once show me banana tree in his garden, but I don’t think it was on a scale that was of significant mercantile importance.</p>
      <p sl="en">The reason we have these restrictions is well-intentioned. We think we are sticking up for largely former French and British colonies in the Caribbean, the ones that produce the little squashy bananas, if I can put it that way, rather than the big long straight ones. But we’re not doing those territories any favours. We are keeping them in a sense of dependency, we are preventing them from expanding into other areas, diversifying their economies and competing in world markets.</p>
      <p sl="en">And as a price for doing this, we are slightly pushing up prices in Europe, taking a little bit of money out of the pockets of our consumers which would otherwise be spent on stimulating the economy at home. So everybody ends up being a loser from these restrictions. It would be easier by far to have free trade rather than these rules, which are bananas.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="8.4. Sustainable management of external fishing fleets (A8-0377/2016 - Linnéa Engström)">
    <intervention id="2-230-0000" speaker_id="124939" name="Diane James" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the European Union Common Fisheries Policy has incurred much criticism, and I believe rightly so. Fish stocks, due to overfishing, are now in many instances at critically low levels. Not content, though, with inflicting this ecological damage on waters surrounding the British Isles, the North Atlantic and the Mediterranean, the European Union has established arrangements to conduct the same activities in the waters beyond its jurisdiction.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proposed regulation would establish a new authorisation framework and extend the scope of the authorisation system to all European Union fishing activities outside European Union waters. But when the United Nations remarks that the European Union practice is endangering 1.5 million African jobs, and when Greenpeace and the United Nations are able to identify the source of the overfishing issue as being the European Union, I’m very sorry, I was just unable to support the motion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-231-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, as a new member of the Committee on Fisheries, I was pleased to vote in favour of this report, which calls for a clarification on licensing rules for EU vessels fishing outside EU waters. This regulation would also extend the current licensing system to include private agreements between EU companies and third countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">The current regulation dates back to 2008 and the update of the legislation would apply to all EU vessels fishing outside EU waters and to third—country vessels fishing in EU waters. This is extremely relevant for Ireland as it clarifies certain rules which would impact on our fishermen, who are such hard workers but have been affected greatly by EU legislation. Providing more clarifying eligibility criteria for third—country vessels would help Irish fishermen as it would ensure that those who do want to fish in our waters are fully and properly licensed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-232-0000" speaker_id="124864" name="Michela Giuffrida" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la politica comune della pesca è forse la politica che ha avuto l'impatto peggiore sul suo comparto produttivo di riferimento. Certo, sono stati raggiunti grandi risultati dal punto di vista ambientale, della sostenibilità, del ripopolamento dei pesci, ma i pescatori hanno visto moltiplicarsi le regole e le norme da rispettare e hanno dovuto avviare costose ristrutturazioni. Hanno fatto tutto questo pur di continuare nella loro attività, nel rispetto dei principi imposti da Bruxelles.</p>
      <p sl="en">La dimensione esterna della pesca è un altro punto dolente. È sicuramente positivo che l'Unione europea adempia alle sue responsabilità di Stato di bandiera, ma sarebbe il caso che l'Unione adempisse anche alle responsabilità di tutela dei pescherecci che pescano in condizioni di grande insicurezza e che sono esposti a grandi rischi. Voglio citare ancora il caso dei pescatori siciliani che rischiano la vita in conflitti con la polizia dei paesi confinanti, in particolare della Libia. È quella che noi chiamiamo la guerra del pesce, perché si tratta di sequestri e sparatorie, e anche di questo l'Unione europea si deve far carico e si deve occupare.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8.5. Third countries whose nationals are subject to or exempt from a visa requirement: Georgia (A8-0260/2016 - Mariya Gabriel)">
    <intervention id="2-256-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem podpořil toto usnesení, myslím si, že je nutné s Gruzií stejně jako s dalšími spojenci v rámci Východního partnerství udržovat nadstandardní vztahy. Já zde nebudu opakovat to, co přináší bezvízový styk do budoucna, tzn. posílení ekonomických a jiných aspektů. Pro mě je osobně nejdůležitější aspekt geopolitický, tzn. země, která leží v bezprostředním sousedství Ruska a je více méně Ruskem permanentně ohrožována, nachází v EU svého partnera a my tímto gestem na cestě říkáme, že nám na Gruzii záleží a že Gruzii za svého partnera považujeme. Takže ta geopolitická rovina je pro mě více důležitá než to, že bezvízový styk povede k prohlubování vzájemných vztahů, k ekonomickým výhodám na obou stranách atd. Je to pro mě nutné, pokud nechceme, aby země v okolí Ruska postupně dále spadaly pod vliv této země.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="8.6. Rule of law crisis in the Democratic Republic of Congo and in Gabon (RC-B8-0120/2017, B8-0120/2017, B8-0121/2017, B8-0122/2017, B8-0123/2017, B8-0124/2017, B8-0125/2017, B8-0126/2017)">
    <intervention id="2-283-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, mně se bohužel nepodařilo vystoupit k tomuto bodu v řádné rozpravě, proto aspoň využívám tohoto institutu. Chci říci, že já považuji za důležité, že Evropský parlament se zabývá agendou lidských práv i v jiných státech mimo evropská teritoria a že je to důležité zvláště vůči zemím, kam plynou silné ekonomické podpory. Ze strany EU jasně říkáme, že v těchto zemích by měla být dodržována základní lidská práva a také by tam měly být respektovány základní principy ústav a řekněme právního státu, zdali je to vůbec možné. Proto jsem podpořil toto usnesení, je dobře, že upozorňujeme jak Gabon, tak Kongo na to, že tamní prezidenti porušují tamní ústavy, že se nechovají demokraticky, že jsou potlačována práva opozice, práva veřejného projevu atd. A do budoucna jsem přesvědčen, že bychom v případě, že se situace v těchto zemích nezlepší, měli omezit ekonomickou pomoc do této oblasti, do tohoto regionu Afriky.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="8.7. Implementation of Erasmus + (A8-0389/2016 - Milan Zver)">
    <intervention id="2-304-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca, szanowni Państwo! Chcę zwrócić uwagę, że zaczęliśmy pracę nad sprawozdaniem dotyczącym „Erasmus+” od pojawiających się opinii, które kwestionowały program jako taki. Dziś na tej sali, także w tym momencie, siedzi sporo młodych ludzi, więc chcę wyraźnie odnotować, że pracę nad sprawozdaniem kończymy czterdziestoprocentowym zwiększeniem nakładów na programy stypendialne. To bardzo ważny sukces. Jednocześnie dodam, że w tym samym czasie zredukowaliśmy tzw. zobowiązania wymagalne, co poprawiło realizację programu i korzystnie wpływa na opinie pojawiające się na jego temat w chwili obecnej. Bardzo chcę wszystkim podziękować za pracę nad tym sprawozdaniem, która była dosyć długa i towarzyszyła jednocześnie sprawozdaniu z wykonania budżetu za rok 2014, a potem 2015.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-305-0000" speaker_id="124939" name="Diane James" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I have a very contrary view and that is because I see the Erasmus project as one of the many European Union sacred cows. It is directed at young people and it is focused solely on developing and encouraging the European Union project. For the period 2014-2020, as we have just heard, Erasmus has seen its project budget increase by 40%. I recognise that propaganda comes at a cost, and this is recognised by the European Union when influencing young people as to the so-called ‘merits’, and I put merits in quotation marks, of the European Union federalist project.</p>
      <p sl="en">But a country doesn’t need to be a member of the European Union to be part of the Erasmus project, and as an internationalist I see the cultural and educational experience that should be available to all within the educational sector irrespective of European Union borders. It should not be conditioned, it should not be directed, and it should not be focused just on the European Union. And it certainly should not be controlled by the European Union. It is a big wide world out there, and I want to see more done with Australia and Asia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-306-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I have always advocated strongly for initiatives such as Erasmus +, and in recent years I have observed its true potential being realised for Irish and European citizens alike. I therefore supported this report, due to the rapporteur’s balanced reassessment of the inter—relationship between education and innovation. In line with the principle of lifelong learning, the future of the EU may henceforth be bolstered by teams of creativity, competence and entrepreneurship.</p>
      <p sl="en">The budget increase towards this scheme reaffirms the high political and economic value of Erasmus +, and I hope to see this scheme continue to grow from strength to strength, and especially be availed of by more Irish people to improve their language skills, which need improving from an Irish context, and also the Erasmus + aspect which now encompasses sport. I know that one body that was involved with it, the Leinster GAA Council, are hoping to avail of that. That would be a wonderful fillip and a great way of bringing Europe closer to EU citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-307-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-жо Председател, уважаеми колеги, гласувах за доклада по приложението на програмата „Еразъм+“, над който работихме дълго време и постигнахме някои добри компромиси. „Еразъм+“ е най-успешната и емблематична програма на Европейския съюз и нейното продължаване и бъдещо съществуване би трябвало да се насърчава и подкрепя.</p>
      <p sl="en">Искам обаче да подчертая, че в доклада има и неща, по които беше постигнато съгласие без мое участие. И едно от тях засяга т.нар. бежанска политика на Комисията, която се възхвалява категорично против моите убеждения. Многократно съм изказвал своето мнение в това отношение и няма да пропусна да го направя и сега. Интеграцията на мигрантите от последната мигрантска криза няма да се случи по начина, по който се предлага и по който се възхвалява в доклада. А Европейската комисия със сигурност не предлага никаква добра алтернатива или разрешаване на проблема.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-308-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President. Erasmus + is one of the most successful EU programmes. It is a major EU tool to support activities in the fields of education, training, youth and sport, giving the opportunity to more than 4 million Europeans to study, train and volunteer in another country. At a time of particular crisis with regard to the fundamental values of the European Union, the Erasmus+ instrument can provide a fundamental opportunity to promote integration, understanding and solidarity among young people. It is very important because they will be the next generation of Europeans. They will be active society members, decision makers, voters and parents. This programme is working well, but the European Parliament has made some recommendations on how to improve its performance. In my point of view we should find more resources for this programme, for the next period until 2027. Of course, I voted in favour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-338-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ceci clôt les explications de vote.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="9. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="10. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="11. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="12. Dates of forthcoming sittings : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem27" title="13. Adjournment of the session"/>
</text>
