<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20171211.EN" lang="en" date="2017-12-11" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die am Donnerstag, dem 30. November 2017, unterbrochene Sitzungsperiode für wieder aufgenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Approval of the minutes of the previous sittings">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Protokolle und die angenommenen Texte der Sitzungen vom 29./30. November sind verfügbar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-009-0000" speaker_id="124996" name="Peter Lundgren" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the President of Parliament, who unfortunately is not here today, announced that he would sign the Joint Declaration on the EU priority files for 2018 and 2019. That wish list is full of unrealistic political proposals. There is no joint position. The House failed to reach an agreement. Only his own Group and the Liberals support the Declaration, but six Groups have refused it. Mr Tajani clearly has no mandate for signing the Joint Declaration on behalf of Parliament. When he got elected he declared he would act as a President for all Members. Mr Tajani, please stick to your commitment. Do not sign the Joint Declaration. You do not have a mandate for that.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also ask the Commission and the Council Presidency whether, if Mr Tajani signs the Joint Declaration in Brussels at the European Council against all the warnings of six political Groups and without the mandate of Parliament, his signature on that document would be valid? How do you feel about that? Will you insist on signing a Joint Declaration that is not approved of by Parliament?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-010-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Lundgren! Ich gehe davon aus, dass Herr Präsident Tajani Ihre Einwände berücksichtigen wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Protokolle der Sitzungen vom 29./30. November sind genehmigt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Composition of Parliament : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-013-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Der endgültige Entwurf der Tagesordnung dieser Tagung, wie er in der Konferenz der Präsidenten in ihrer Sitzung vom Donnerstag, dem 6. Dezember 2017, gemäß Artikel 149 der Geschäftsordnung festgelegt wurde, ist verteilt worden. Zu diesem Entwurf wurden folgende Änderungen beantragt:</p>
      <p sl="en">Montag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Keine Änderungen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dienstag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Fraktion der Europäischen Volkspartei hat beantragt, am Nachmittag eine Aussprache über den Einwand gemäß Artikel 106 GO gegen den Vorschlag der Kommission zur Genehmigung der Verwendung von Phosphorsäure, Phosphaten, Di-, Tri- und Polyphosphaten (E 338-452) in tiefgefrorenen vertikalen Fleischspießen abzuhalten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-014-0000" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe PPE. – Monsieur le Président, effectivement, cette question des phosphates présents dans les viandes a été particulièrement médiatisée dans un certain nombre d’États membres de l’Union européenne et nous estimons que ce sujet-là mérite donc un débat au sein de notre plénière.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est pour cela que, au nom du groupe PPE, je vous suggère d’inscrire ce débat mardi pour que nous ayons un vote en plénière mercredi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-015-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament nimmt den Antrag der PPE-Fraktion an)"/>
      <p sl="en">Eine Aussprache über den Einwand gegen den Vorschlag der Kommission zur Genehmigung der Verwendung von Phosphaten in tiefgefrorenen Fleischspießen wird am Dienstagnachmittag auf die Tagesordnung gesetzt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die GUE/NGL-Fraktion beantragt, infolgedessen die Sitzung bis 24.00 Uhr zu verlängern.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-016-0000" speaker_id="28248" name="Gabriele Zimmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Ja, in aller Kürze. Wir sind dafür, diesen Tagesordnungspunkt mit aufzunehmen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir machen aber darauf aufmerksam, dass wir am Dienstagnachmittag bis 23 Uhr eine sehr volle Tagesordnung haben. Wenn wir den Punkt tatsächlich ernsthaft bereden wollen, würde es sich als sinnvoll erweisen, die Tagesordnung an diesem Tag bis 24 Uhr zu verlängern.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-017-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank.</p>
      <a text="(Das Parlament nimmt den Antrag der GUE/NGL-Fraktion an)"/>
      <p sl="en">Die Sitzung wird damit morgen bis 24.00 Uhr verlängert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die EVP-Fraktion beantragt außerdem, die Abstimmung über den Einwand von Dienstag auf Mittwoch zu verschieben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-018-0000" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe PPE. – Monsieur le Président, j’ai précisé pourquoi je demandais à ce qu’il y ait un débat au nom du groupe PPE, qu’il y ait un débat concernant cette question, en expliquant qu’elle a été terriblement médiatisée. Donc, si nous avons un débat le mardi soir, il est important de reporter le vote en plénière au mercredi, c’est assez logique.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020-0000" speaker_id="96840" name="Knut Fleckenstein" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich wollte nur fragen, ob sichergestellt ist, dass dieser wichtige Punkt hinten angestellt wird, wenn er diskutiert wird. Denn wir reden an diesem Nachmittag über die Situation in Libyen, wir reden über den Irak-Deal, wir reden über die gemeinsame Sicherheits- und Verteidigungspolitik, und vielleicht sollten wir über Kebab dann anschließend reden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Fleckenstein! Das ist wie im Leben: Die Schönheit liegt immer im Auge des Betrachters. Aber ich gehe davon aus, dass wir das im Anschluss an alle übrigen Tagesordnungspunkte behandeln.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Rechtsausschuss hat zwei Immunitätsberichte der Berichterstatter Lebreton und Cavada angenomen. Gemäß Artikel 9 Absatz 9 der Geschäftsordnung werden diese beiden Berichte in der Abstimmungsstunde am Dienstag zur Abstimmung gestellt. Die Tagesordnung wird entsprechend geändert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mittwoch:</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Einvernehmen mit den Fraktionen schlage ich folgende Änderungen des endgültigen Entwurfs der Tagesordnung vor: Die Reihenfolge der beiden letzten Punkte am Mittwochnachmittag wird geändert. Die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung zum Untersuchungsrecht des Europäischen Parlaments wird als vorletzter Punkt behandelt. Darauf folgt als letzter Punkt der Bericht von Frau Corazza Bildt über die Umsetzung der Richtline zur Bekämpfung des sexuellen Missbrauchs und der sexuellen Ausbeutung von Kindern sowie der Kinderpornografie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gibt es Einwände? Das ist nicht der Fall. Dann ist das so beschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donnerstag:</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Fraktion der Europäischen Volkspartei beantragt, die Aussprache über die Große Anfrage zum Streit zwischen der EU und Norwegen um die Befischung der Arktischen Seespinne in den Gewässern der Inselgruppe Spitzbergen zu vertagen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to return to our original proposal, which was to have this major interpellation on the agenda in January. That was our original request, but for some reason it was decided to have it this week. So I would like to return to our original proposal.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Verification of credentials : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Negotiations ahead of Parliament's first reading (Rule 69): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Delegated acts (Rule 105(6)): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Signature of acts adopted under the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 78)">
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">In dieser Woche wird der Präsident zusammen mit dem Präsidenten des Rates gemäß Artikel 78 der Geschäftsordnung 16 Rechtsakte unterzeichnen, die gemäß dem ordentlichen Gesetzgebungsverfahren angenommen wurden. Die Titel dieser Rechtsakte werden im Protokoll dieser Sitzung veröffentlicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben noch eine Wortmeldung zur Geschäftsordnung: Frau Kollegin Fotyga.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="28353" name="Anna Elżbieta Fotyga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wanted to state to Parliament that in the evening of December 8, a major terrorist attack was committed by ADF rebels in North Kivu province of the DRC, killing 15 UN peacekeepers and seriously wounding more than 53 soldiers stationed there belonging to the MONUSCO UN Mission deployed to eastern DRC.</p>
      <p sl="en">On behalf of the Subcommittee on Security and Defence, I would like to convey our deepest sympathy to the families of those who perished in that Islamist terrorist attack.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank, Frau Kollegin Fotyga. Ich werde den Inhalt Ihrer Wortmeldung auch an Präsident Tajani übermitteln.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Action taken on Parliament’s resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Major interpellations (Rule 130b) (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Amendments to various Regulations in the field of agriculture and rural development (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als erster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Ausspracheüber den Bericht von Albert Deß im Namen des Ausschusses für Landwirtschaft und ländliche Entwicklung über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates über die Haushaltsordnung für den Gesamthaushaltsplan der Union und zur Änderung der Verordnungen (EU) Nr. 1305/2013, (EU) Nr. 1306/2013, (EU) Nr. 1307/2013, (EU) Nr. 1308/2013 und (EU) Nr. 652/2014 des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates (COM(2016)0605 - C8-0404/2017 - 2016/0282B(COD)) (A8-0380/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Sehr geehrter Herr Präsident, sehr geehrte Vertretung der Kommission, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! In den Verhandlungen, in dem sogenannten Omnibus-Verfahren, haben wir es im Trilog erreicht, dass der Agrarausschuss gezielte Verbesserungen für die vier Verordnungen der gemeinsamen Agrarpolitik - Direktzahlungen, ländliche Entwicklung, gemeinsame Marktordnung und horizontale Verordnung – erzielt hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich freue mich umso mehr, dass es uns gelungen ist, dass diese wichtigen Verbesserungen für den Agarteil rechtzeitig zum 1. Januar 2018 in Kraft treten können. Ich bedanke mich an dieser Stelle für die gute – ja exzellente – Zusammenarbeit im Sinne der europäischen Landwirtschaft bei dem Verhandlungsteam des Europäischen Parlaments, insbesondere bei Paolo de Castro und Michel Dantin, die in diesem Arbeitsprozess von Anfang an tatkräftig mitgewirkt haben. Auch bei unserem Vorsitzenden Czesław Siekierski bedanke ich mich sehr herzlich und bei den Schadenberichterstattern, die über alle Fraktionen hinweg sehr konstruktiv mitgearbeitet haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bedanke mich bei der Kommission und hier stellvertretend bei Michael Niejahr und Rudolf Moegele, dem Verwaltungs- und Funktionsteam, den Mitarbeitern in den Abgeordnetenbüros. Zuletzt danke ich Inge Gräßle und der Konferenz der Präsidenten, die die Aufspaltung des Kommissionsvorschlags unterstützt haben. Nur durch deren Unterstützung war die Erstellung eines gesonderten Legislativberichts über die Bestimmungen des AGRI-Mandats möglich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Agrarausschuss wurden 505 Änderungsanträge eingereicht. Nach intensiven Verhandlungen wurde ein Paket von 16 Kompromissänderungsanträgen ausgearbeitet. Eine breite Übereinstimmung zwischen anderen wichtigen politischen Gruppen führte zu einer sehr erfolgreichen Abstimmung im Ausschuss im Mai, mit 34 Ja-, 10 Nein-Stimmen und einer Enthaltung. Diese Abstimmung gab uns ein eindeutiges Mandat für die Verhandlungen zwischen den drei Institutionen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es genügten vier Triloge, um am 12. Oktober eine politische Einigung zwischen Parlament, Rat und Kommission über die Änderungen der vier GAP-Verordnungen zu finden. Der Agrarausschuss billigte die Einigung dann mit einer eindeutigen Mehrheit von 39 zu 5 Stimmen. Der Kompromiss bedeutet für unsere Landwirte mehr Optionen beim Greening und mehr Sicherheit beim Dauergrünland. Zahlreiche Maßnahmen werden vereinfacht, beispielsweise auch die Definition „aktiver Landwirt“. Es ist uns gelungen, die Möglichkeit zu mehr Biodiversität zu schaffen. In Zukunft können im Rahmen der Ökologisierung auf Vorrangflächen sowohl Honigpflanzen, Durchwachsene Silphie wie auch Elefantengras angebaut werden. Honigpflanzen und Durchwachsene Silphie sind Blühpflanzen, worüber sich die Imker sicher freuen. Elefantengras trägt dazu bei, Bodenerosion zu verhindern, nachdem es im Winter stehen bleibt, bietet es auch dem Niederwild Schutz.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zudem wurden die Gewichtungsfaktoren bei Eiweißpflanzen von 0,7 auf 1,0 angehoben. Dies war auch deshalb notwendig, nachdem für mich unverständlich der Kommissar das Verbot von Pflanzenschutzmitteln auf Vorrangflächen durch einen delegierten Rechtsakt ausgesprochen hat. Dadurch werden hunderttausende Hektar Eiweißpflanzen in Europa nicht mehr angebaut. Da hat der Faktor 0,7 nicht mehr gepasst.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ebenfalls haben wir den Faktor für mehrjährige Umtriebsplantagen von 0,3 auf 0,5 angehoben. Dieses Programm ist bisher sehr wenig in Anspruch genommen worden. Durch dieses Anheben können wir davon ausgehen, dass es mehr in Anspruch genommen wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Einen Durchbruch gab es auch beim Dauergrünland. Nach dem unverständlichen Urteil des Europäischen Gerichtshofs zu Dauergrünland war es notwendig, eine Klarstellung zu erzielen. Durch dieses Urteil des Europäischen Gerichtshofs wurden allein in meinem Heimatland Bayern ca. hunderttausend Hektar Grünland umgepflügt, mussten umgepflügt werden, um die Fünfjahresfrist einzuhalten. Dies war ein unmöglicher Zustand.</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, mir ist gesagt worden, ich habe sechs Minuten Redezeit: vier plus zwei. Deshalb bitte ich noch einmal um kurze Redezeit, weil ich mich darauf eingestellt habe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Entscheidend bei dieser Einigung ist, dass sie rückwirkend gelten wird und auch für die Zukunft Rechtssicherheit gibt. Erheblich verbessert wurden auch die Bedingungen für die Zusatzprämie für Junglandwirte. Die Mitgliedstaaten haben jetzt die Möglichkeit, die an die Junglandwirte gerichteten Fördersätze erheblich zu erhöhen und für volle fünf Jahre auszuzahlen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Unterstützung junger Landwirte kann besser auf ihre Bedürfnisse abgestimmt werden. Die Instrumente des Risikomanagements im Rahmen der Entwicklung des ländlichen Raums wurden gestärkt. Es wird ein neues sektorspezifisches Instrument zur Einkommensstabilisierung eingeführt. Eine wichtige Forderung der EVP-Fraktion zur Stärkung der Position der Landwirte in der Lebensmittelkette ist in diesem Kompromiss ebenfalls verankert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Anders als in der Vergangenheit können nun alle anerkannten Erzeugerorganisationen ihre Produktion und ihre Lieferverträge im Namen ihrer Mitglieder aushandeln. Wichtig war hier, eine Ausnahmeregelung für die Genossenschaften zu schaffen, damit es zu keinem Verstoß gegen die Wettbewerbsregeln kommt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich darf am Schluss die Kommission bitten, dass sie die ganzen Beschlüsse sehr unbürokratisch umsetzt. Damit erreichen wir mehr für die Ökologie in Europa und mehr Rechtssicherheit für die Landwirte in Europa. Ich freue mich, dass alles so gut gelaufen ist und bedanke mich bei allen, die mitgewirkt haben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am here this afternoon on behalf of Commissioner Hogan, who is in Buenos Aires for the ministerial meeting of the World Trade Organization. But, as you know very well, rural development is something which for me, as the Commissioner for Regional Policy, is very close to my heart.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mr Deß, for this report and for his work in getting us to this point. We have been waiting a long time for this debate, both in agriculture and cohesion policy, in order to make the lives of beneficiaries in both fields much easier. Indeed, the text to be voted on tomorrow is the result of complex negotiations which started in the summer. I am glad that preliminary agreement was reached in October between all three institutions. As you know, this agreement covers a very wide range of issues in all four basic acts of the common agricultural policy. It contains many changes, which come from amendments proposed by both the Council and Parliament. Some of them go beyond the original Commission proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">The text on which you will vote tomorrow is the result of a compromise. It was achieved through a constructive approach by all parties. However, as you know and as was outlined during the conclusion of the trialogue process, the Commission has some misgivings about the end results. This is particularly the case regarding the new provisions in favour of producer organisations and their possible consequences for effective competition. We also have reservations about the limited role that the Commission and the national competition authorities will play in safeguarding competition.</p>
      <p sl="en">Having said that, we are nevertheless very happy to see that many of the important simplification proposals put forward by the Commission are in the final text. I am thinking of, for example, the simplification of rules for financial instruments, the improvement of risk management tools, and the possibility for greater flexibility for active farmer provisions. Commissioner Hogan has been taking this simplification agenda forward for the last two years. Member States and farmers are now anxious to see these important simplification measures and other improvements to the common agricultural policy rules enter into force as soon as possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">These measures will reduce the administrative burden on Member States and farmers. It was with this in mind that the Council and Parliament agreed to have the agriculture provisions separated from the rest of the Omnibus proposals. The original objective was to have them adopted as a stand-alone legal instrument to enter into force on 1 January 2018. Well, I would like to assure you that the Commission also wants to see these simplification measures coming into effect as early as possible for the benefit of farmers in all Member States. The Commission’s Omnibus proposal is a single proposal. It covers diverse, but interconnected, provisions, and the Commission would like to see them all enter into force as soon as possible. For this to happen, we need to progress swiftly on the remaining parts of the Omnibus proposals, which also contain significant simplification provisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quick implementation of these provisions will benefit everyone. With a view to achieving tangible results as soon as possible, I can tell you that the Commission will not oppose the agreement reached on the new stand-alone text introducing changes to the basic regulations of the common agricultural policy. Therefore, the Commission will continue its constructive and cooperative approach in order to move further forward in this important area so that efforts can rapidly bear fruit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="23787" name="Czesław Adam Siekierski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy PPE. – Prace nad przeglądem śródokresowym WPR w ramach rozporządzenia zbiorczego zakończyły się sukcesem w wyniku zgodnej współpracy trzech zaangażowanych instytucji: Komisji, Rady i Parlamentu. Zmiany, które zostały przeprowadzone, można bez wahania nazwać małą reformą, chodzi tu bowiem o istotne zmiany niektórych kluczowych instrumentów WPR. Szczególnie ważne są wprowadzone elementy upraszczające i dające większą elastyczność państwom członkowskim. Na zmianach zyskają młodzi rolnicy, których tak bardzo potrzebujemy na obszarach wiejskich. Będą oni mogli uzyskać nawet podwojenie dotychczasowych płatności i otrzymywać je przez pięć lat bez względu na to, kiedy o taką płatność wnioskowali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podjęto kolejne kroki na rzecz wzmocnienia pozycji rolnika w łańcuchu żywności, m.in. dzięki rozszerzeniu możliwości kolektywnego negocjowania cen przez organizacje producentów i wyłączenie rolników spod zasad unijnego prawa konkurencji. Zapewniliśmy również lepsze narzędzia zarządzania ryzykiem w przypadku trudności rynkowych, anomalii pogodowych czy epidemii chorób roślin lub zwierząt. Prace nad rozporządzeniem zbiorczym były także dobrą rozgrzewką, cennym doświadczeniem przed zbliżającą się reformą WPR na okres po 2020 roku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jeszcze raz dziękuję wszystkim stronom za wytężoną, a co najważniejsze, owocną pracę. Szczególne podziękowania kieruję pod adresem naszych wspaniałych sprawozdawców, pana posła Dessa i pana posła De Castro …</p>
      <a text="(Przewodniczący odebrał mówcy głos.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-0000" speaker_id="96891" name="Paolo De Castro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo S&amp;D. – Signor Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, a soli 15 mesi dalla pubblicazione della proposta di regolamento omnibus, ci troviamo a esprimere il voto finale sul pezzo forte di questa legislatura europea per quanto riguarda il settore agricolo. L'omnibus ci ha infatti offerto l'opportunità di intervenire sull'attuale struttura della PAC, opportunità che si è concretizzata soprattutto grazie al determinato e determinante contributo del Parlamento europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">I piccoli aggiustamenti e le timide aperture presentati nella proposta iniziale della Commissione andavano sicuramente nella giusta direzione, ma non apparivano all'altezza delle sfide che i sistemi agroalimentari stanno affrontando. Proprio per questo abbiamo sentito la responsabilità di dare ai cittadini e agli agricoltori europei risposte che fossero qualcosa di più di un semplice ritocco, con un'iniziativa ambiziosa, attraverso la quale siamo riusciti a potenziare e integrare gli spunti offerti dalla Commissione.</p>
      <p sl="en">La portata delle innovazioni introdotte nell'ambito della semplificazione, della gestione dei rischi e delle misure di mercato fa sì che questo lavoro si configuri come una vera e propria riforma di medio termine della politica agricola comune.</p>
      <p sl="en">Una riforma di metà percorso con un duplice valore: da un lato, è la risposta all'ormai certa posticipazione della riforma della PAC alla prossima legislatura europea e al prossimo Commissario; dall'altro, ha potuto fissare un punto di partenza per le riflessioni sul futuro delle politiche agricole, indirizzando in modo significativo anche la recente comunicazione della Commissione sulla PAC post-2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">La corposa mole di proposte di modifica del Parlamento ha generato un intenso dibattito, ma il punto di equilibrio trovato è accolto con grande soddisfazione da tutti gli agricoltori europei, e ci restituisce un ottimo esempio del lavoro svolto dalle nostre tre istituzioni, rispettando in pieno gli ambiziosi obiettivi temporali inizialmente definiti dalle commissioni competenti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo – concludo – voglio ringraziare la Presidenza estone, il Commissario Hogan e i suoi servizi, e tutti i colleghi e i relatori ombra per il lavoro straordinario, anche dal punto di vista procedurale, essendo riusciti a questa estrapolazione, e ringrazio il Commissario anche per la non opposizione.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="4507" name="Bas Belder" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Ook ik wil alle betrokkenen bedanken voor het bereikte resultaat. Dit is een goede stap naar vereenvoudiging en, naar ik hoop, een vermindering van de administratieve lasten voor boeren. Ik ben er bijzonder mee ingenomen dat mijn amendementen ook in de tekst zijn opgenomen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ten eerste, de steun voor jonge boeren. Jonge boeren krijgen straks de top-upsteun voor de volledige vijf jaar. Iedere jonge boer kan daar optimaal gebruik van maken op het moment dat de steun het hardst nodig is. Ten tweede, mijn amendement over spelt. Ik ben er blij mee dat spelt zo dadelijk in alle gevallen meetelt voor gewasdiversificatie. Voor sommige boeren is dit een belangrijke optie, bijvoorbeeld voor boeren op zware kleigrond.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daar gaat het ten slotte om: goed werkend beleid, daar heeft iedereen baat bij. Nogmaals dank dus aan alle betrokkenen voor dit bereikte resultaat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="124862" name="Ulrike Müller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ALDE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Auch ich möchte mich herzlich bei den Berichterstattern Albert Deß und Paolo De Castro bedanken. Am 14. September 2016 hat die Kommission den Vorschlag zur Überprüfung des mehrjährigen Finanzrahmens vorgelegt. Wir vom Agrarbereich waren mit vier Basisrechtsakten betroffen. Oft werden ja die europäischen Institutionen belächelt und beschimpft, dass die Dauer der Prozesse zu lang ist. Hier ist das allerdings unbegründet. Wir haben tatsächlich bewiesen, dass, wenn man zusammenarbeitet, es sehr, sehr schnell gehen kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Umso wichtiger ist es für uns jetzt, dass wir morgen über den Agrarteil der Omnibus-Verordnung abstimmen. Wir wollten alle Vereinfachungen erreichen, und die Vereinfachungen müssen am 1. Januar 2018 in Kraft treten. Die wichtigsten Bereiche wurden bereits genannt: Es geht um den aktiven Landwirt, es geht um die Junglandwirte. Für mich war auch wichtig, dass wir den Ackerstatus klar definieren und diese Grünlanddefinition jetzt endlich ordentlich niedergeschrieben ist. Die wichtigsten Punkte allerdings sind natürlich das Greening gewesen und die Ausweitung der Pflanzen bei den ökologischen Vorrangflächen. Hier sind ganz explizit zu nennen die Durchwachsene Silphie und auch die Honigpflanzen für die Bienen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kritisch sieht die ALDE-Fraktion allerdings Änderungen an der gemeinsamen Marktordnung, weil wir der Überzeugung sind, dass die gemeinsame Marktordnung, so wie sie jetzt besteht, tatsächlich zum Erfolg führen kann, wenn sie in allen anderen Mitgliedstaaten auch so angewendet wird. Hier waren wir etwas unterschiedlicher Meinung. Trotzdem ist für uns wichtig, dass wir hier positiv abstimmen, dass wir eine Verbesserung für die Landwirte erreichen. Denn wir wissen nicht, ob der nächste gemeinsame Finanzrahmen und die Gemeinsame Agrarpolitik rechtzeitig kommen.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner ist damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel 162 Absatz 8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="97025" name="Ivari Padar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mina kui põllumeeste organisatsiooni liige sooviksin omalt poolt samuti tänada kõiki osapooli, kes selle suurepärase töövõidu on teinud. See annab usku põllumeestele, et keerulise Euroopa Liidu bürokraatiaga on võimalik muutusi teha. Nii et suur tänu kõikidele nendele, kes on selle suure töö ära teinud!</p>
      <a text="(Sõnavõtja andis mõista, et soovib esitada sinise kaardi küsimust.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Colleague, I regret to underline that this was not a question. You have made a statement and I am afraid that this will go down against you. Next time I will hesitate over whether to give you the opportunity because you have clearly misused the instrument. So, Ms Müller, I’m afraid there was no question.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">We can now proceed with Mr Flanagan for one minute and a half for the GUE/NGL Group.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="124985" name="Luke Ming Flanagan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, generational renewal is the oft-used buzz phrase in the Committee on Agriculture, and I think that what we have done here does something to help generational renewal. Young farmers now will be able to get five years of payment irrespective of when they apply, as long as it is within the first five years of their taking over the farm. Although I say that they can get it, the Council has unfortunately made a change concerning my country, the Republic of Ireland. As ‘shall’ has become ‘may’, we fear in our country that the generational renewal will end up getting nothing and ‘may’ will be never, but you’ve done your bit and congratulations on that.</p>
      <p sl="en">One thing, though, that young farmers don’t necessarily need is a crutch. What they need is to have the blocks taken off their back and to do that – and there is something done here – we need to strengthen farmers’ position in the food chain and their way to make money. Whatever the profession, whether it’s hairdressing, carpentry, or anything else, you don’t ask why we can’t get people to go into it if there is no money: we know the answer. We need more money to come to farmers, and it worries me when I hear the Commission say that it has misgivings about the whole idea of competition in this area, whereas there are no misgivings about supermarkets having a massive market share. There are very few misgivings about meat processors merging or the case in Ireland that happened recently, when we were told, well it’s not European-wide. That needs to change if you want more young farmers. Farmers are no different from anyone else. They want a fair price, and that’s how we get them interested.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="96752" name="Martin Häusling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen. Ich finde, die Bilanz ist zumindest durchwachsen. Nicht alles ist gelungen, und nicht alles kann man jetzt als wirklichen Fortschritt bezeichnen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich finde, es wurden einige überfällige Entbürokratisierungen verwirklicht, die wir auch begrüßen. Eine bessere Definition von Grünland, oder dass nicht mehr nach fünf Jahren umgebrochen werden muss – das sind, glaube ich, Selbstverständlichkeiten. Aber andererseits sind ja die Gewichtungsfaktoren beim Greening jetzt schwächer geworden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Liebe Kollegin Müller, ich habe da eine andere Definition: Warum man Elefantengras und die durchwachsene Silphie jetzt als Bereicherung der europäischen Agrarlandschaft betrachtet, das erschließt sich nur denen, die Biogas machen. Also tatsächlich würde ich da ein großes Fragezeichen dranmachen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein Fragezeichen würde ich auch an die Sache mit dem „aktiven Landwirt“ machen. Die Kommission wollte die Definition ja ganz abschaffen. Jetzt überlassen wir es den Mitgliedstaaten. Aber wir müssen da eine Regelung finden, denn es ist wichtig, dass die Zahlungen der Europäischen Union tatsächlich an die gehen, die sie brauchen. Nämlich die, die aktiv im Geschäft sind, und nicht an irgendwelche Investoren, die im Hintergrund vielleicht das Geld aus der Europäischen Union abziehen. Deshalb ist das noch ein Punkt, über den wir mit Sicherheit noch weitere Diskussionen brauchen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben jetzt einen Reformvorschlag vom Herrn Kommissar gehört. Da hat sich für uns noch mehr Unklarheit aufgetan. Einen Punkt müssen wir auf jeden Fall besprechen, und das ist leider nicht gelungen: Die Vorschläge, die Herr Dantin, der immerhin der PPE-Fraktion angehört, immer wieder einbringt, dass wir aktiv ins Marktgeschehen eingreifen können. Dass wir es wieder nicht geschafft haben, uns zum Beispiel bei Milch darauf zu einigen, dass wir freiwillige Mengenreduzierungen in Zukunft auch als Möglichkeit in Betracht ziehen können. ES tut mir wirklich leid, dass wir das nicht geschafft haben. Bei der nächsten Milchkrise werden wir wieder da stehen und keine Antworten für die Bauern haben. Ich denke, darauf müssen wir als Parlament noch mal Gewicht legen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir brauchen eine funktionierende Marktordnung und wir brauchen auch ein schnelles Eingreifen der Kommission. Das haben wir in diesen Punkten nicht erreicht.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in the last Parliament, with much fanfare, the EU claimed to be reforming the agricultural policy. It told us that it would make it fit for purpose. It told us that it would simplify it. It told us that it would cut red tape and ease the regulatory burden. Well it hasn’t worked, has it? That’s why we’re having this debate on something called Omnibus. So now, almost sneakily and by the back door, begins the process of trying to undo what we were doing in the last term. If the last reform was working, then Omnibus would be totally unnecessary, certainly on this size and scale. Moreover, we know that it is only the first step.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner Hogan has already announced that 2018 will bring more change, further agricultural reform to try to undo some of the many mistakes of the last reform. Furthermore, we already see scope for new mistakes to be made to replace the old ones. Is allowing collusion and price-fixing really a solution, or will this turn out to be yet another case of further regulation reinforcing earlier failure with ever more complexity?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="125684" name="Philippe Loiseau" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, en France, un vieux proverbe dit que «le mieux est l’ennemi du bien». La position de mon groupe, dans cette assemblée, est plus souvent «le mieux est l’ennemi du moins pire».</p>
      <p sl="en">Mes homologues des autres groupes en commission de l’agriculture savent, en effet, que je ne porte pas la politique agricole commune dans mon cœur, loin s’en faut. Néanmoins, je tiens à souligner quand même les efforts faits sur ce texte, dans le but de corriger le tir sur les dysfonctionnements à la mi-parcours de la PAC. Tout le monde a été concerné, oui, tout le monde, même notre groupe, ce qui n’est pas toujours le cas, il faut le dire. Je tiens donc à remercier l’ensemble de mes collègues, et tout particulièrement M. De Castro, qui ont écouté notre voix, qui est celle des agriculteurs que nous défendons.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur le fond, je dois dire que l’on sent poindre des petites remises en cause justement de la politique européenne en matière agricole. C’est donc une bonne nouvelle que la définition de l’agriculteur actif – qui conditionne le paiement des aides, comme vous le savez – soit laissée à l’appréciation des États membres.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est aussi une bonne nouvelle que les producteurs, qu’ils soient seuls ou regroupés en organisations, soient plus écoutés. Cela est important également. Ou encore que les mesures d’écologisation et de verdissement soient moins punitives pour les agriculteurs. C’est rare, mais rassurant, quand l’Union européenne va dans le bon sens. Cela l’est d’autant plus quand elle avoue à demi-mot ses propres erreurs en revenant sur ses propres réglementations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qui sait, d’ailleurs, peut-être qu’un jour l’Union acceptera aussi de revenir sur ses propres fondations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="22418" name="Esther Herranz García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señora comisaria. En primer lugar quisiera expresar mi agradecimiento a todos quienes han trabajado duro para conseguir que la tramitación de este informe entre en vigor el próximo día 1 de enero.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esperemos que todas estas modificaciones de la política agrícola común sirvan para mejorar el día a día de los agricultores y ganaderos, porque corrigen defectos de la reforma de la PAC de 2013. Para España, uno de los principales problemas era que se había corregido la definición de pastos permanentes. Es un placer decir que, a partir del 1 de enero, los pastos mediterráneos, como la dehesa, quedan reconocidos en el Reglamento, y esto implica el fin de las penalizaciones impuestas a las ayudas destinadas a los ganaderos españoles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Otro de los grandes logros de este Reglamento es la posibilidad de incrementar sustancialmente el apoyo a los jóvenes agricultores: medida muy necesaria para mejorar el relevo generacional, que es el principal problema que aqueja al sector agrícola europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, por último, como riojana, celebro también las modificaciones que se han introducido para la concesión de autorizaciones de nuevas plantaciones de viñedo. Con ellas se va a conseguir un reparto más equitativo, más justo y que favorece la permanencia de los jóvenes en el sector agrícola.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, quería felicitar a los dos ponentes, a Paolo De Castro y a Albert Deß, y a los ponentes alternativos, por el buen trabajo realizado. Creo que el Parlamento ha apostado mucho en esta reforma intermedia. Que no se atreven a llamarla así, pero es eso, es algo más que eso. Las propuestas de simplificación de la Comisión son interesantes, pero este Reglamento Ómnibus queda mucho mejor con las aportaciones de todos los grupos de este Parlamento. No es casual esta unanimidad de todos los grupos y que todos estemos de acuerdo en que se ha hecho un buen trabajo. A ver si sirve para la próxima reforma a partir de 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay mejoras interesantes para los jóvenes agricultores, las organizaciones de productores de frutas y hortalizas, el pago acoplado o las ayudas asociadas. Pero especialmente —como ha dicho la señora Herranz— para el problema que había en mi país con la dehesa y los bosques mediterráneos. Esto y además la excepcionalidad del derecho a la competencia son cuestiones muy importantes para los agricultores europeos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="125049" name="Maria Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a negociação do Omnibus foi pouco transparente e podemos dizer que acabou numa reforma intercalar da PAC. Aprofunda o desmantelamento da organização comum dos mercados, a desregulamentação das produções agrícolas, prima a concorrência e a vocação exportadora da agricultura europeia, aprofunda também a introdução de seguros de estabilização de rendas e a aplicação geral de instrumentos financeiros em vez de subsídios. Desmantela o atingido com a introdução da figura do agricultor ou agricultora ativa.</p>
      <p sl="en">O fortalecimento da posição dos agricultores na cadeia de valor não é real porque os mecanismos propostos não funcionam, como é o caso das organizações de produtores. Quando se fala na simplificação da Política Agrícola Comum, aguardo que não seja como sempre, que acaba por complicar-se ainda mais.</p>
      <p sl="en">Os aspetos destacados como positivos e as mudanças na definição de pastagens, pasto ou pasto permanente, ou o aumento das ajudas para jovens são uma decisão do Estado—Membro, de modo que a flexibilidade e a subsidiariedade também são introduzidas no primeiro pilar da PAC.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="125237" name="Marco Zullo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ringrazio i relatori. Personalmente sono molto soddisfatto per i risultati positivi che abbiamo ottenuto con il regolamento omnibus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il primo è che siamo riusciti ad accelerare la procedura di approvazione per avere il regolamento operativo già dal 1o gennaio, e questa è la dimostrazione che quando c'è la volontà politica si può davvero semplificare la burocrazia, e io spero che questo approccio diventi sempre più frequente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il secondo risultato positivo è che con il regolamento omnibus attuiamo una piccola riforma della PAC in corso d'opera: andiamo a correggere, ad aggiustare, quelle regole che hanno dimostrato di essere lacunose, complesse e non efficienti, andando così verso il sostegno agli agricoltori, il miglioramento del sistema di produzione agroalimentare e la tutela dell'ambiente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il terzo risultato positivo è che il quadro normativo è stato migliorato dopo aver ascoltato le critiche e i suggerimenti degli agricoltori europei, coloro che lo applicano e lo vivono quotidianamente, e questo è importante perché le istituzioni hanno bisogno di ascoltare di più i cittadini e chi opera nel settore specifico. Abbiamo già visto che le decisioni semplicemente calate dall'alto non funzionano, e vogliamo lo stesso approccio condiviso per la definizione della nuova PAC.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamnă comisar, doamnelor și domnilor colegi, aș dori în primul rând să salut și să apreciez munca colegilor mei Albert Dess și De Castro, dar, în același timp, și munca tuturor celor care au lucrat la acest raport. Prin prezentul document, s-a încercat rezolvarea unei părți din problemele sectorului agricol, câteva dintre acestea fiind combaterea fenomenului de îmbătrânire accentuată în spațiul rural, dar și dificultățile de negociere pe care fermierii le aveau în circuitul agroalimentar. În acest context, apreciez faptul că statele membre vor putea să sporească plățile către tinerii agricultori în primul pilon cu până la 50 % din plafon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Extrem de important este instrumentul general de stabilizare a veniturilor, care poate fi folosit în ipoteza în care veniturile agricultorilor scad cu mai mult de 30 % din venitul mediu anual comparativ cu anul precedent. Acest instrument, împreună cu contractele de asigurare, trebuie să devină însă instrumente apropiabile fermierilor în toate statele membre, iar, sub acest aspect, apreciez că rolul autorităților naționale este unul hotărâtor în implementarea acestora.</p>
      <p sl="en">Totodată, relevante sunt modificările care permit întărirea poziției de negociere a fermierilor, cu respectarea normelor antitrust și a condițiilor de concurență echitabilă în lanțul de aprovizionare agroalimentară. Astfel, nevoile fermierilor sunt satisfăcute, iar consumatorii au posibilitatea de a beneficia de o hrană ieftină și de calitate. Regret însă faptul că sectoarele cărnii de porc și de pasăre nu se regăsesc între sectoarele care pot beneficia de sprijinul cuplat, deși acestea se află în dificultate în multe state ale Uniunii Europene.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, congratulo-me com a evolução deste processo que permitiu fazer os ajustes possíveis com o objetivo de responder prontamente à realidade das pastagens mediterrânicas e aos desafios do emprego jovem na agricultura e das oscilações bruscas de preços.</p>
      <p sl="en">No entanto, o pacote do leite, com medidas agora alargadas a todos os setores, não impediu a mais recente crise de preços no setor do leite, da qual muitos agricultores, aqueles que persistiram, estão ainda a recuperar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Medidas como a concertação pontual da oferta são difíceis de implementar por todos. Por exemplo, em zonas de montanha ou nas regiões ultraperiféricas, dadas as condicionantes geográficas, é difícil atingir um volume negocial relevante face aos outros elos da cadeia de valor.</p>
      <p sl="en">São positivas as alterações no âmbito dos seguros e dos instrumentos de estabilização de riscos, mas não podemos pretender que estes se substituam a uma política pública forte na agricultura, sob pena do abandono da produção e da sua concentração em apenas algumas zonas do território europeu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-0000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Erstens könnte man sagen: Agrarpolitiker können liefern. Wir hatten ein gemeinsames Ziel: Wir wollten bis Dezember fertig werden, und wir haben es geschafft. Vielen Dank an die Berichterstatter, an die Schattenberichterstatter, an die Kommission und an den Rat dafür, dass wir gemeinsam hier fertig geworden sind.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zweitens: Damit haben die Landwirte Planungssicherheit. Landwirte sind belastbar, sie sind innovativ, aber sie wollen natürlich wissen, was auf sie zukommt. Auch hier haben wir Wort gehalten. Die guten Dinge, die wir aufnehmen konnten, haben meine Vorredner schon alle erwähnt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Drittens: Es bleiben natürlich auch noch Wünsche offen. Zwei Dinge waren für mich wichtig, die das Europäische Parlament auch beschlossen hat, die aber leider nicht in der Omnibus-Verordnung widergespiegelt wurden. Erstens hätte ich mir gewünscht, dass der Omnibus prolongiert wird, also dass wir ihn quasi bis 2024 hätten fahren lassen. Das hätte noch mehr Planungssicherheit gerade für die Förderprogramme im ländlichen Raum bedeutet. Hier bitte ich einfach die Kommission, falls wir nicht rechtzeitig mit der neuen Reform in die Spur kommen, dass wir diese Idee noch mal aufgreifen und ganz einfach prolongieren. Und zweitens hätte ich mir gewünscht, dass das Entbürokratisierungsprogramm – Stichwort ELER RESET – deutlicher in der Omnibus-Verordnung widergespiegelt worden wäre. Aber es ist nicht aller Tage Abend.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr! Ez a munka több mint egy évvel ezelőtt kezdődött, s akkor tiszta üzenetet fogalmaztunk meg: Tehát üdvözlendő a KAP egyszerűsítését célzó minden lépés, bár eleinte aggodalomra adott okot, hogy vajon képes lesz-e az ún. „omnibus” eszköz kezelni a közös agrárpolitika szakpolitikai specifikusságát. Az intézményközi egyeztetések során ezek a félelmek azonban eloszlottak, a jelentést kimagasló többséggel támogatta az AGRI szakbizottság. Ezúton is szeretnék tehát gratulálni a jelentés kidolgozásában részt vevő kollégáknak, különösen Dess, de Castro uraknak, valamint Andrieu és Dantin uraknak egyaránt. Bízom abban, hogy ezek az egyszerűsítések tényleges könnyebbséget jelentenek a termelők felé.</p>
      <p sl="en">A jövővel kapcsolatban viszont szeretném megerősíteni a közös agrárpolitika közös jellegével kapcsolatos elkötelezettségemet. Nem támogatok semmilyen renacionalizálást ezen a fronton, nem leszünk partnerek az idő kerekének visszaforgatásában. Közös, konzisztens politikával egy sikeres fejlődést elérni, és olyan projekteket kell megvalósítani, mint például az „okos falvak”. Vizünk, földünk, tudásunk, szorgalmunk van bőségesen, ezért nem kéne a különböző kormányzati, akaratvezérelt torz …</p>
      <a text="(Az elnök megvonta a szót a képviselőtől)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-0000" speaker_id="129164" name="Tom Vandenkendelaere" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">De maatregelen waarover we morgen stemmen zullen echt wel een verschil maken voor de boeren vandaag.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ten eerste - en dat is heel belangrijk - krijgen de lidstaten de kans om jonge landbouwers een duwtje in de rug te geven. En dat is nodig. Het aantal actieve landbouwers daalt. Er is geen toekomst voor de landbouwer zonder jonge landbouwers. Meer centen voor beginnende boeren kan dus echt wel een verschil maken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tweede belangrijk punt: de positie van de landbouwer in de voedselketen. Geen eerlijke prijs zonder een sterkere positie voor de boer. Met dit akkoord kunnen nu producentenorganisaties in alle sectoren opgericht worden. In de groente- en fruitsector zien we dat die aanpak echt wel werkt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Om af te sluiten, ten derde, nog dit punt van zorg: er moet controle zijn over de uitbetaling van Europese steun. Indien het facultatief maken van de definitie "actieve landbouwer" opnieuw de deuren open zet voor een oneigenlijk gebruik van de Europese landbouwcenten, dan zou dat het landbouwbeleid ondermijnen. Landbouwgrond die wordt gebruikt als recreatiegebied verdient geen cent steun. Jonge, actieve landbouwers verdienen die wel.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="124836" name="Maria Noichl" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich möchte mich ganz herzlich bei denjenigen im Haus bedanken, die mit zahlreichen Änderungsanträgen dazu beigetragen haben, dass keine Reform entstanden ist. Denn einige hier im Haus dachten, das wäre die Hintertür für eine neue Agrarreform, ohne die Gesellschaft mit einzubeziehen. Einige dachten, wir machen hier auf dem ganz schnellen Durchmarsch neue Reformschritte in eine Richtung, die ich nicht mittragen hätte können, ohne die Gesellschaft, ohne die NGOs, ohne die Verbraucherverbände mit einzubeziehen. Unsere Aufgabe war es, Vereinfachungen und Nachbesserungen vorzunehmen, und nur durch die zahlreichen Änderungsanträge ist es zu Vereinfachungen und zu Nachbesserungen gekommen. Somit kann ich diesem Omnibus-Verfahren jetzt auch zustimmen. Doch der Anfang war holprig, und der Anfang war dieses Hauses nicht würdig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eine Agrarreform ist keine Reform, die in einer Nische stattzufinden hat, und es ist keine Reform, die ausschließlich im Agrarausschuss stattzufinden hat. Eine Agrarreform ist ein Gesellschaftsvertrag, ein Vertrag, bei dem viele, viele Gesellschaftsgruppen mitsprechen sollen und wollen. Das müssen wir tun: Eine Agrarreform in Europa anstoßen in Zukunft in der Gemeinschaft, mit der Bevölkerung, nicht nur im Agrarausschuss.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="97296" name="Michel Dantin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, vous me permettrez d'abord de remercier mes collègues, Albert Deß et Paolo De Castro, pour le climat de confiance dans lequel nous avons pu travailler tous les trois ensemble.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans cette affaire, le Parlement est une véritable force de proposition. D'un texte qui se voulait simplement correcteur, nous avons fait un bilan de santé de la PAC. Nous avons été les seuls – me semble-t-il – à mesurer l'importance des crises qui viennent de se succéder sur les exploitations agricoles, l'attente des agriculteurs sur le terrain. Nous avons fait un premier pas, avec une évolution – cela a été dit, il y a quelques instants – en matière de droits conférés aux organisations de producteurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Néanmoins, Madame la Commissaire, nous attendons d'autres pas et des propositions de la Commission. Nous attendons d'abord des propositions sur le fonctionnement de la chaîne alimentaire. Le commissaire Hogan nous les a promis pour le mois de mai. Nous espérons que cette échéance sera tenue.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lors des discussions en trilogue, nous avons aussi buté sur les outils de gestion de crise et sur la réserve de crise. Il faut absolument que, dans le cadre de la préparation de la réforme à venir, nous travaillions tous ensemble pour mettre en place une réserve flottante à partir des sommes non dépensées sur le budget de l'agriculture, qui, si au bout de deux ou trois ans, n'était pas consommée, serait rendue aux États, comme aujourd'hui. Mais nous ne pouvons pas vivre sans une cagnotte financière qui nous permette de gérer les crises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trop de gens, trop d'agriculteurs, dans nos différents pays, sont restés sur le bord du chemin au cours de ces derniers mois. Trop d'exploitations ont mis la clé sous la porte. Nous ne pouvons pas être fiers du résultat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="94282" name="Jean-Paul Denanot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, l’objectif initial de ce règlement était de favoriser une simplification de la politique agricole commune (PAC), mais le Parlement européen a souhaité aller plus loin et tracer ainsi un certain nombre d’orientations pour la future politique agricole commune.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je salue dans ce texte l’extension des dérogations des règles de la concurrence à tous les secteurs agricoles, le renforcement du rôle des organisations de producteurs dans les contrats, la généralisation des mesures exceptionnelles de crise à tous les secteurs et, enfin, la meilleure répartition de la valeur ajoutée dans la chaîne alimentaire. Ces mesures sont nécessaires mais seront très insuffisantes pour lutter contre la volatilité des prix en cas de crise de marché. Le secteur a besoin de davantage de régulation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je me félicite, par ailleurs, que l’«Omnibus» ait permis de rendre éligibles des surfaces de pâturage extensif dans les zones méditerranéennes. En outre, je tiens à saluer dans ces textes l’adoption de deux de nos amendements importants pour la viticulture: l’un sur la méthode soustractive des vins liquoreux, l’autre sur le contrôle des plantations dans le Cognac.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, je voudrais souligner ici – et vous le savez, Madame le Commissaire – que ces adaptations ne remplaceront jamais une vraie réforme de la PAC, que nous attendons de nos vœux le plus rapidement possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-0000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Čestitke kolegoma Dessu in De Castru za ta omnibus. S tem smo kmetijsko področje dali pred ostala področja in začenjamo te spremembe izvajati v naslednjem letu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pomembni so napredki na tem področju, da najprej določimo, kaj je pravzaprav aktivni kmet, kako dati ta kmetijski denar dejansko v roke tistim, ki kmetujejo in ustvarjajo tudi poseljenost podeželja. Pomembno je področje mladega kmeta, da lahko to ponovno oživitev podeželja pomagamo urediti tudi s tem, da damo mladim kmetom večji dodatek k subvencijam in na ta način jih privabimo, da ostanejo na podeželju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zavarovanje rizikov tako vremenskih kakor tudi rizikov trga so zelo pomembni, kakor tudi status v pogajalskem procesu, da preko organizacij proizvajalcem kmetijstvu dajemo večjo težo v neenakopravnih pogajanjih, ki jih ima danes v trgovinski verigi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pomembno pa je tudi to, da medovite rastline dobijo mesto v ozelenitvi in da bo tudi na tem področju napredek narejen v naslednjih letih.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'intesa raggiunta offre la prospettiva di una vera e propria riforma di medio termine: la definizione di agricoltore attivo è stata mantenuta, il ruolo dei giovani agricoltori è stato valorizzato, sono stati semplificati i regimi dei pagamenti diretti ed il greening. Viene anche migliorato l'accesso degli agricoltori a strumenti assicurativi, fondi di mutualità e meccanismi di stabilizzazione dei redditi.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'accordo raggiunto sull'omnibus costituisce quindi un risultato importante per l'agricoltura europea, e mi congratulo con i relatori Dess e De Castro per il lavoro fatto. Relativamente al grande capitolo delle misure di mercato è stata data maggiore forza contrattuale alle formule organizzative degli agricoltori OP e AOP.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia ciò non è sufficiente: vanno individuate soluzioni per assicurare una condivisione più equa dei rischi lungo l'intera filiera agroalimentare, al fine di contrastare le pratiche sleali. Ad oggi non abbiamo una normativa europea, ed è fondamentale che il diritto europeo della concorrenza tenga conto delle caratteristiche specifiche dell'agricoltura per garantire benessere ai produttori europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-0000" speaker_id="124733" name="Sofia Ribeiro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a defesa da agricultura não é uma questão setorial. Ela visa garantir que todos os europeus tenham acesso a produtos agrícolas de alta qualidade a baixo preço. E, por isso, é muito importante que olhemos para a cadeia de valor de uma forma diferente. E, por isso, é muito importante que, neste documento, tenhamos reforçado as organizações de produtores e a criação de organizações de negociação, garantindo a existência de mecanismos de partilha de lucros e de perdas na fileira, de modo a que quando baixam os preços no mercado todos se portem de igual forma, quer aquando da queda como da subida.</p>
      <p sl="en">Queria também ressalvar a importância de termos criado um novo instrumento de gestão de riscos, nomeadamente o seguro de rendimentos, e permitirmos aos Estados-Membros fazerem contribuições financeiras para estes prémios.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oxalá a Comissão tenha estas normas em consideração, na medida em que são essenciais para as regiões ultra periféricas, nas quais também é muito importante darmos um apoio à renovação geracional, prestando um maior apoio aos jovens agricultores para as novas instalações agrícolas e criando mecanismos de renovação geracional e de transmissão de conhecimentos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="23868" name="Monika Beňová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani komisárka a vážení spravodajcovia. Minulý týždeň som mala stretnutie so zástupcami slovenskej a českej poľnohospodárskej komory. Dovoľte mi, aby som tlmočila niektoré ich obavy a otázky, ktoré majú v oblasti poľnohospodárskej politiky. Napriek tomu, že sa nám darí riešiť rozdiely v priamych platbách a v rôznych európskych dotáciách, stále nám jednotný trh zásadným spôsobom deformuje rôzna forma štátnej pomoci a štátnych dotácií na úrovni členských štátov. A teda bolo by dobré, aby, keď hovoríme o jednotnom trhu, sme rozmýšľali o tom, ako zjednotiť aj tieto opatrenia. Ďalším obrovským problémom pre našich poľnohospodárov je aj to, že v neposlednom rade viac ako klimatické zmeny ich ohrozuje politika obchodných reťazcov. Obchodné reťazce skutočne pristupujú práve k malým farmárom a k poľnohospodárom veľmi zlým spôsobom, a takisto majú obrovský podiel na tom, že mnohé firmy zanikajú. A posledná téma, ktorú by som chcela spomenúť je, aby nám tie jednotlivé pomoci európske nenarážali na seba a aby to, že podporujeme biomasu a pestovanie bioplodín do biomasy, neničilo pôdu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, στην πενταετία 2005-2010 εξαφανίστηκαν 2,4 εκατομμύρια γεωργικές εκμεταλλεύσεις, ενώ η οικονομική κρίση που ακολούθησε δημιούργησε ακόμη μεγαλύτερα προβλήματα. Οι αγρότες του ευρωπαϊκού Νότου, που παράγουν το 50% του αγροτικού προϊόντος της Ένωσης, έχουν κυριολεκτικά γονατίσει λόγω της λιτότητας και της βίαιης δημοσιονομικής προσαρμογής. Το ρωσικό εμπάργκο επέτεινε τα αδιέξοδα στον αγροτικό κόσμο της Ένωσης, γι’ αυτό χρειάζονται δραστικά μέτρα στήριξης των νέων αγροτών και των ομάδων παραγωγών. Η στήριξη πρέπει να προέλθει και από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και από τα κράτη μέλη.</p>
      <p sl="en">Στην Ελλάδα οι αγρότες έχουν φτωχοποιηθεί από το μνημονιακό φορολογικό ρεσάλτο στις τσέπες τους, καθώς επίσης και από τις κατασχέσεις των κοινοτικών επιδοτήσεων. Κυρία Crețu, με ενδιαφέρον έλαβα την γραπτή απάντηση του κυρίου Hogan, ότι για το 2017 χορηγούνται εκτάκτως 9,3 εκατομμύρια ευρώ στους έλληνες αγρότες που καλλιεργούν ροδάκινα και νεκταρίνια και οι οποίοι ζημιώθηκαν από το ρωσικό εμπάργκο. Χρειάζονται όμως και άλλα μέτρα στήριξης των ελλήνων αγροτών και κτηνοτρόφων, ιδίως των νέων και των γυναικών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the Members once again for their participation in this evening’s debate. I know very well that Mr Deß, Mr De Castro and all of you have been the soul of this initiative, which is very important, as it will enable you, with your vote tomorrow, to make the lives of farmers much easier all over Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am particularly happy – together with Commissioner Hogan, of course – about the change in the relationship with young farmers. The payment will always be granted per farmer for a period of five years, as long as a young farmer applies for the payment within five years of setting up for the first time. This goes hand in hand with our work together.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mr Hogan, as the Commissioner for Agriculture and Rural Development, and myself, as the Commissioner for Regional Development, are both in favour of doing something for villages in order to keep young people there: otherwise we shall be in danger of having food agglomerations and empty countryside. Regarding this proposal you have, I think, given us very good results. So, hand in hand, we have to work for rural development, and of course we have more support for farmers, not least in Greece, and more activities in villages.</p>
      <p sl="en">This Omnibus is a very important next step in the Commission’s simplification agenda, an agenda on which, with Parliament’s support, much progress has been made. Indeed, the Commission produced the Omnibus proposal precisely because we believe that there is significant potential for simplification across a range of policy areas, including the area for which I am responsible.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we are a bit behind. Tomorrow morning we will have the last trialogue about cohesion policy. The Commission hopes that those who are negotiating other aspects of the Omnibus proposal can take a lead from all of the agriculture negotiations, for we are setting an example.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I said, I want to acknowledge the role played by the rapporteur and all his colleagues in the progress that you have managed to make in such a short time. I would also like to thank the Estonian Presidency for its leadership in the Council and for its collaboration with the other institutions in the trialogues.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me reiterate that the Commission will not stand in the way of the agreement when it is put to the vote tomorrow. Although, as I said, we had reservations from the point of view of competition, you, the European Parliament, have agreed this, so the Commission will stand by you. This is because of the progress that you have made and the benefits that will arise for millions of farmers and other common agriculture policy beneficiaries. Thank you once again and congratulations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Frau Kommissarin! Ich mache es ganz kurz, nachdem ich ja die Redezeit in Anspruch genommen habe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bedanke mich für alle Wortmeldungen, die ja fast alle zustimmend waren. Ich hoffe, dass wir jetzt das Ganze morgen mit einem guten Ergebnis gut über die Runden bekommen, damit wird das abschließen können und zum 1. Januar alles in Kraft treten kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das Thema Junglandwirte ist nochmals angesprochen worden. Hier möchte ich darauf hinweisen, dass heuer unsere Delegationsreise nach Kroatienstattgefunden hat. Dort haben gerade die Junglandwirte darauf gedrängt, auch Esther Herranz aus Spanien hat sich hier stark dafür eingesetzt. Wir haben hier jetzt ein sehr flexibles Instrument – je nach Bedarf. Es gibt Länder, wo wenig junge Landwirte sind, dort kann man es erhöhen. Wo genügend Junglandwirte sind, muss man es nicht erhöhen. So stelle ich mir europäische Agrarpolitik vor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich glaube, Frau Kommissarin, dass wir am Ende dieser Verhandlungen ein Musterbeispiel dafür geliefert haben, dass in der Europäischen Union sehr schnell Union gearbeitet werden kann, wenn der Wille da ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich habe in meiner Eingangsrede vergessen, mich bei Staatssekretär Marco Gorban aus Estland zu bedanken, der sehr fachkundig und konstruktiv für den Rat verhandelt hat. Sonst wären auch diese schnellen Ergebnisse nicht möglich gewesen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich hoffe, dass die Gesellschaft entsprechend mitwirkt, wie in einem Kommentar gesagt worden ist. Ich würde mir aber manchmal wünschen, dass sich die Gesellschaft mehr für die Probleme der Landwirtschaft interessiert. Wir haben so viele Landwirte, die ihre Betriebe aufgeben. Da werden viele Betriebe freiwerden, wo NGOs uns dann zeigen können, wie man bäuerliche Landwirtschaft betreibt. Aber da ist der Andrang sehr gering: Die harte Arbeit auf den Bauernhöfen wollen halt viele nicht verrichten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank für das ganze Verfahren, und vielen Dank, dass wir so schnell fertig geworden sind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 12 December 2017.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-2500" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – Finalmente siamo giunti a conseguire misure positive di semplificazione e di tutela dei nostri agricoltori. La politica agricola comune, adesso, dovrebbe essere più vicina alle esigenze delle aziende. Sono veramente soddisfatto del lavoro svolto dal nostro gruppo, specialmente dal collega Marco Zullo, e dal fatto che i nostri emendamenti alla proposta originaria siano stati recepiti con un voto favorevole. Un punto fortemente voluto anche dalla nostra delegazione, ad esempio, sono le novità introdotte alla misura della consulenza aziendale che, pur se inserita negli attuali PSR, risulta praticamente inapplicata a causa di limiti oggettivi previsti nella regolamentazione di base. Si è ottenuto che le organizzazioni di produttori e Associazioni di OP potranno al proprio interno derogare alle regole sulla concorrenza che riguardano la produzione, la vendita e la trasformazione dei prodotti agricoli, affinché vi sia maggiore autonomia di gestione. Un importantissimo traguardo per noi, perché rappresenta una novità importante per la nostra agricoltura, è quello di aver ottenuto l'accessibilità alle tradizionali assicurazioni contro le avversità atmosferiche.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-5000" speaker_id="124711" name="Norbert Erdős" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Felkérem a Tisztelt Képviselőtársakat, hogy szavazatukkal támogassák a mezőgazdaság és a vidékfejlesztés területén érvényben lévő rendeletekhez fűzött módosításokról szóló szöveget. Ez az elfogadott szöveg kiemelt jelentőséggel bír a gazdáink részére. Minden területen - termelői szerveződések, zöldítés, termeléshez kötött és első pilléres fiatal gazda támogatások, uniós pénzek elszámolása - sikerült jelentős könnyítéseket elérni az európai gazdák és a tagállami hatóságok számára. Példaként itt most két dolgot emelnék ki. Egyrészt sikerült megerősítenünk a termelői alkupozícióját az erőfölényükkel gyakran visszaélő kereskedőkkel és feldolgozókkal szemben. A 2010-es ún. Tejcsomag rendelkezéseihez hasonlóan ugyanis az elismert termelői szervezet a jövőben a tejágazaton túl a többi mezőgazdasági ágazatban is megtervezheti a termelést és tagjai nevében tárgyalhat a kereskedőkkel a beszállítói szerződésekről, így egy erősebb kivétel lesz az uniós versenyjog szabályai alól.</p>
      <p sl="en">Másrészt, a túlságosan bürokratikus és a gyakorlatban nehezen végrehajtható zöldítési szabályok számos ponton egyszerűsödtek. Például a jövőben az elefántfű, a csészekóró és főleg a mézelő növények – melyek számunkra kiemelten fontosak a beporzás biztosítása és méhek megtartása miatt – is elszámolhatóak lesznek a gazdálkodásból kivett ún. ökológiai jelentőségű területeken.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-7500" speaker_id="124792" name="Laurenţiu Rebega" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Salut și subscriu la „mică reformă a PAC”, care prevede, în ansamblu, o politică pentru agricultori mai simplă și mai echilibrată. Dar nu mă pot abține să nu critic faptul că actuala PAC, la care am ajuns astăzi, nu și-a atins unul dintre obiectivele cele mai importante: volatilitatea prețurilor. Acesta rămâne o consecință catastrofică pentru țara mea. Toate prevederile din acest nou regulament deschid ușa către noi acorduri cu țări terțe, cu care aș fi de acord dacă agricultorii europeni, și mai ales cei dezavantajați, nu ar fi folosiți ca valoare de schimb pentru alte politici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am afirmat de mai multe ori, din 2014, că nu ar fi o idee rea crearea unei noi forme a PAC, care să pună accent pe un protagonism național, dar am fost mereu acuzat că doresc o renaționalizare. Astăzi, citesc cu surpriză că unul din obiectivele acestui regulament este acela de a acorda un rol central statelor membre.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Sustainable management of external fishing fleets (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the recommendation for second reading from the Committee on Fisheries on the sustainable management of external fishing fleets, and repealing Council Regulation (EC) No 1006/2008 (11382/2/2017 – C8—0358/2017 – 2015/0289(COD)) (Rapporteur: Linnéa Engström) (A8-0374/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="128588" name="Linnéa Engström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">föredragande. – Herr talman! Fru kommissionär Crețu! Jag vill tacka alla som har deltagit i förhandlingarna och arbetat med denna förordning.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi har ju lyckats att radikalt höja standarderna för vem som ska fiska under EU-flagg, och jag är stolt att säga att EU-flottan kommer att vara den mest transparenta, och den tar störst ansvar globalt till havs efter vårt arbete. En stor seger. Det här är det enda sättet att på ett trovärdigt sätt påbörja en dialog med andra stora fiskenationer om hur vi höjer standarder internationellt och hur vi hållbart förvaltar våra gemensamma resurser för framtida generationer.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det pågår en kamp om de marina resurserna. När vi extraherat det vi kan på land så börjar vi nu titta på den blå ekonomin och vad den kan göra för att mätta vårt omättliga behov. Men för att inte äventyra matsäkerheten för miljoner människor genom överfiske och rovdrift så behöver EU ta sitt ansvar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Om vi inte ser att vårt beteende påverkar andra, då kommer vi att se en värld med ökande flyktingströmmar, ökad fattigdom och svält. För människor på den afrikanska kontinenten är fisk den viktigaste proteinkällan, för att bara nämna ett exempel. EU ska ta sitt ansvar till havs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kommissionens förslag var därför en väldigt bra grund till att börja med för att den för första gången samlade alla typer av aktiviteter utanför EU:s vatten. Partnerskapsavtalen, privata avtal, fiske inom RFMO och fiske på öppet vatten. Detta är ett mycket positivt steg och jag är väldigt glad att ministerrådet delade dessa mål.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jag skulle vilja börja berätta om våra vinster från Europaparlamentets håll. Vi lyckades få in flera nya bestämmelser för att förbättra fiskets hållbarhet, både på öppet hav och i privata avtal. Vi har nu striktare regler vad gäller uthyrning av båtar, s.k. chartering, inklusive en definition av vad som ingår och ett förbud mot detta i EU:s partnerskapsavtal. Detta är viktigt. Chartering är det tydligaste sättet att kringgå regler kring både social och miljömässig hållbarhet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi har lyckats förhandla fram en mer konsekvent anpassning till IUU-förordningen vad gäller när fisket måste upphöra om kommissionen beslutar sig för att ge landet ett rött kort för illegalt fiske. Det ska inte längre vara tillåtet att fiska i vatten där landet tydligt bryter mot internationella överenskommelser om illegalt fiske.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi lyckades också med kravet på bättre information om ett fartygs historia och verksamhet när det återvänder till EU:s fartygsregister. Detta är viktigt för att veta att båten som bär EU-flagg inte har fiskat illegalt eller hyrt ut sin flagga till mindre nogräknade länder.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fiske på öppet vatten kommer nu att kräva en vetenskaplig bedömning för att visa att de planerade aktiviteterna är hållbara. Öppet vatten ska inte vara vilda västern för vem som helst att bara roffa åt sig. Vi måste noggrant reglera aktiviteterna där.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi krävde strängare regler för omlastning till sjöss och lyckades få igenom regler som kräver en förhandsanmälan till medlemsstaten och en årlig rapport till EU-kommissionen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Men som i alla förhandlingar så nådde vi inte alla våra mål. Behörighetskriterierna – vi önskade att fartyg inte skulle vara berättigade till fisketillstånd om de hade begått en grov överträdelse eller ett brott året innan fisket påbörjades. Ministerrådet vägrade att ta hänsyn till detta, och vi fick lägga oss till sist. Detta till stor del för att medlemsstaterna inte tillämpar kontrollförordningen på samma sätt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi ville verkligen stärka EU-kommissionens möjlighet att återkalla ett tillstånd om medlemsstaten inte tillämpar villkoren korrekt. Detta är mer känt som the claw back clause. Vi kom fram till en kompromissformulering som ger EU-kommissionen rätt att sätta större press på medlemsstaten om medlemsstaten inte gör någonting vid grova brott eller överträdelser, och det återstår att se om EU-kommissionen kan använda sig av den här möjligheten på ett effektivt sätt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det betyder att vi måste fortsätta att opinionsbilda och hålla koll på våra egna båtar. Vi vill också ha större transparens och insyn i fiskeflottan. Europaparlamentet vill att namnen på ägaren och den slutgiltiga betalningsmottagaren publiceras offentligt men vi kom inte hela vägen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uppgifterna kommer att samlas in och finnas … (talaren avbryts av talmannen) … Det här är huvuddragen i den nya förordningen och jag lämnar nu över till debatten där jag ser fram emot inlägg.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, my sincere thanks go to the rapporteur, Ms Engström, for her work on this report, also for the shadows and their teams who have worked hard on this Commission proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">You know very well that this is an important element of the reform of the common fisheries policy, which is being implemented by my colleague Karmenu Vella. The proposal on the sustainable management of the external fleets is crucial to reinforce the role of the European Union as a key global actor in fisheries, ocean governance and the fight against illegal, unreported and unregulated fishing.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is very happy that the Council and Parliament have agreed on a compromise text based on the Commission proposal regarding the sustainable management of external fishing fleets. With this agreement and these new rules that should enter into force early next year, the European Union is creating a benchmark at international level on the management of external fleets. The European Union also takes the lead in ensuring sustainable fishing at a global level and is strengthening its capacity to tackle illegal fishing worldwide.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me illustrate this with some of the main achievements. First of all, a comprehensive system of fishing with authorisation to fish outside European Union waters that applies wherever the fishing takes place based on strict eligibility criteria. This is of the utmost importance, especially for the outermost regions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I had the pleasure to be with President Juncker and President Macron in French Guyana, which has now the Presidency of the outermost regions. I know how important this is for the population, for whom fishing is the main activity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, fishing activities will be better regulated and monitored independently, whether fishing takes place under public agreement, direct authorisation by third countries, or on the high seas. In particular, scientific evidence should be given showing that the fishing activities are sustainable.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abusive reflagging of new vessels in order to avoid the rules will also be discouraged and penalised. The new rules will increase transparency on fishing operations globally, as the proposal was for the creation of a public register of all fishing authorisations granted. Finally, chartering and transhipment in the high seas and under private agreements will also be regulated.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is a very balanced compromise. The objective of better regulating fishing activities goes together with a reduced administrative burden as well as simple and harmonised rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">The role of each actor is clear in defining this proposal. The responsibility of the Member States as flag states is reinforced while the European Commission will play an important role in supervising the implementation of the rules and ensuring compliance with international obligations regarding the activities of EU-flagged vessels.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union has now become a strong global actor in shaping international oceans governance and this is now well reflected in our legislation, which we need to implement. I therefore trust that together we will manage to improve fisheries governance for a more sustainable future and a better livelihood. Mr President, honourable Members, let me thank you once again for all your work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-0000" speaker_id="28400" name="Francisco José Millán Mon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, el texto que hoy se debate es fruto del acuerdo alcanzado en los diálogos tripartitos el 20 de junio y aprobado sin problema alguno en la Comisión de Pesca el 21 de noviembre. El texto contempla las actividades llevadas a cabo por nuestra flota exterior también en el marco de los llamados acuerdos privados, hasta ahora insuficientemente regulados por el Derecho de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es un texto equilibrado, alcanzado tras un largo y trabajoso proceso de diálogo y negociación con el Consejo y la Comisión. El texto tiene en cuenta las tres dimensiones de la pesca: la medioambiental, la económica y la social. Por todo ello, yo confío en que el texto sea confirmado mañana tal y como se encuentra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quisiera destacar que se ha presentado una enmienda pidiendo la inclusión de la llamada doble sanción, que penalizaría sin licencia a los barcos sancionados el año anterior a la petición de autorización. Mi Grupo siempre se ha opuesto a esta inclusión por tres razones, básicamente: en primer lugar, es discriminatoria; en segundo lugar, penalizaría principalmente a los buques de aquellos países que aplican de forma más estricta el Reglamento de control en materia de sanciones, que, como es sabido, desgraciadamente no se aplica de forma homogénea en los Estados miembros; y, en tercer lugar, supondría una fuerte pérdida económica para los buques de la flota exterior de la Unión, que, por sus características especiales, muchas veces no pueden reconvertirse y faenar en aguas de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Espero por todo ello que la enmienda no prospere, y si prosperara, además, todo el trabajo hecho hasta ahora no habrá servido para nada pues no veo posible que se llegue a una conciliación con el Consejo en este punto. Todos debemos ser responsables y no poner en peligro el trabajo realizado. Hago un llamamiento a la responsabilidad.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-0000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo S&amp;D. – Senhor Presidente, felicito, novamente, a relatora pelo trabalho inclusivo que realizou com os relatores-sombra e as respetivas equipas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parece-me que se chegou a um bom compromisso e a um resultado final equilibrado. O combate à pesca ilegal, não declarada e não regulamentada é uma prioridade de todos. Dado haver níveis de implementação diferentes entre Estados-Membros, foi preferível retirar os chamados critérios de elegibilidade para pescar fora das águas da União. Assim, garantiu-se que não há uma dupla penalização, a qual apenas seria aplicável aos pescadores e às embarcações oriundos de países que já estão a cumprir por completo a regulamentação de controlo. Sairiam beneficiados os prevaricadores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Garantir que os acordos internacionais de pesca e as pescarias europeias não são utilizados como ferramenta de branqueamento de capitais e para evasão fiscal é uma prioridade. O registo de informação sobre as embarcações que pescam nas águas internacionais, quais as oportunidades de pescas associadas, quem são os seus armadores e, muito importante, os beneficiários finais, torna mais transparente toda a atividade realizada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Num tempo em que se procura combater a evasão fiscal, surpreendeu-me a dificuldade que foi assegurar este ponto específico. É necessário continuar o combate à pesca INN e fomentar o respeito pelo ambiente e pelas comunidades locais dos países terceiros, pelo que devemos fomentar acordos de pesca com origem na União Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não podemos deixar que os acordos internacionais europeus ineficientes e dormentes se prolonguem. Os recursos marinhos são um bem comum e fomentar uma exploração sustentada, equilibrada e transparente pela frota comunitária é uma forma de demonstrar aos parceiros internacionais o quanto estamos empenhados nisso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este documento é mais uma peça que ajuda a garantir a segurança alimentar e pescado oriundo de mananciais sustentáveis, assim como o combate à pesca INN e ao crime transnacional organizado na indústria das pescas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would also like to give my thanks to the rapporteur, with whom it was a pleasure to work, and also to the rest of the Committee on Fisheries. We are to be commended, I think – and I include myself in this – because this second reading before plenary today marks a real change in one or two areas.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is an established truism that simple law makes good law. The overdue changes to the PHARE Regulations, a fundamental pillar of the CFP, will ensure the sustainable, transparent and harmonised regulation of Community waters. But it will also extend the strict rules to those Union vessels operating in third-party waters or upon the high seas. As such, the Union will give effect to internationally agreed obligations, while recognising systemic abuses, such as reflagging. This legislation does what the fishermen of the region I represent want most. It is clear and it gives guidelines; it closes loopholes; and it is a precautionary acceptance of the fact that ecosystem-based protection must extend over borders if it is to be effective.</p>
      <p sl="en">Article 5 of the eligibility criteria is central to the whole Regulation, and it is to be welcomed that for the first time non-sensitive information will be made publicly accessible. I and some others would have liked to go further and apply enhanced transparency requirements, but I see this as a clear way forward, albeit not as far as I would have liked to have gone. The fight against illegal fishing is a tough one, but this Regulation puts us firmly on the right road.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor presidente. Quiero solicitar el voto favorable para este informe porque es decisivo para mejorar la sostenibilidad y la transparencia de las actividades de la flota de la Unión Europea fuera de nuestras aguas. Su aprobación es consecuencia directa de la introducción, en la última reforma de la PPC, de un capítulo destinado a la dimensión exterior. Su objetivo, garantizar que las actividades pesqueras de la industria europea se rijan por las mismas normas dentro y fuera de la Unión. Actualmente esta flota exterior está formada por más de 700 buques comunitarios, que aportan una cuarta parte de las capturas comunitarias.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los colegisladores hemos alcanzado un acuerdo que aclara las lagunas existentes en la normativa y la división de tareas entre los Estados y la Comisión y que va a aportar un control más eficiente y transparente a las actividades pesqueras. Contribuimos así a mejorar la sostenibilidad y la reputación de la Unión Europea en esta materia y a potenciar los valores comunitarios en todo el mundo en contra de la pesca ilegal, no declarada y no reglamentada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para ello, el Acuerdo incluye en el ámbito de aplicación del Reglamento a todos los barcos de la Unión Europea que pescan fuera de nuestras aguas, sea cual sea su tipo de autorización. Así se incluyen expresamente las autorizaciones privadas y los acuerdos de fletamento. Se establecen además criterios comunes de legibilidad para obtener licencias y reglas más estrictas contra el cambio de abanderamiento. Habrá más transparencia pública sobre las actividades pesqueras de cada buque y más competencias para que la Comisión intervenga en los procesos de concesión o retirada de autorizaciones de pesca cuando los Estados no cumplan el presente Reglamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finalmente, este acuerdo obliga a mejorar el Reglamento de control, que se va a revisar en el primer trimestre del próximo año. El vigente propicia que no todos los Estados ejerzan el mismo tipo de control sobre sus propios buques porque no garantiza ni una vigilancia ni sanciones homologables. Hasta que no se den esas condiciones, un registro de infracciones graves penalizaría a los Estados y las flotas más cumplidoras. Por eso esta propuesta no se ha podido incorporar al Acuerdo, y por ello no votaremos a favor de la enmienda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-0000" speaker_id="125023" name="Anja Hazekamp" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de GUE/NGL-Fractie. – We spreken vandaag over het duurzame beheer van de externe vissersvloot. Dat zijn de schepen die ver buiten de Europese wateren vissen. Maar van het woord duurzaam is hier eigenlijk geen sprake. Europa heeft één van de grootste externe vissersvloten ter wereld. Duizenden schepen registreerden zich sinds 2010, vooral om de Afrikaanse wateren leeg te vissen. De grootste schepen vangen 400 ton vis per dag: dat is 7000 ton per week. Die vangen meer vis per week dan 7000 Afrikaanse traditionele vissersboten in een heel jaar. De helft van alle vis die we in Europa eten, komt uit de derde wereld.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deze roofexpedities worden mede mogelijk gemaakt door de EU. Die sluit zogenaamde partnerschapsovereenkomsten met ontwikkelingslanden, van Mauritanië tot Madagaskar en van Kiribati tot Micronesië. Maar niet alleen Europa sluit zulke roofakkoorden, ook eigenaars van monsterboten mogen op eigen houtje en vaak geheel onder de radar, privédeals maken met de regeringen van ontwikkelingslanden. Dat willen we met dit verslag aan banden leggen. Ook met deze nieuwe regels is de Europese vissersvloot nog maar nauwelijks duurzaam, maar het is in ieder geval een hele goede stap in de juiste richting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="124835" name="Rosa D'Amato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il focus della relazione è il rilascio e la gestione delle autorizzazioni per i pescherecci europei operanti al di fuori delle acque dell'Unione, e soprattutto per i pescherecci di paesi terzi che pescano nelle nostre acque.</p>
      <p sl="en">La cooperazione tra le istituzioni europee ha prodotto un nuovo regime che prevede norme trasparenti e armonizzate, mira ad ottimizzare la governance e a migliorare il monitoraggio e l'attuazione. Grande attenzione è riservata a tutte le misure di protezione dalla pesca illegale, non dichiarata e non regolamentata, che è una delle principali minacce per i nostri pescatori professionisti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il nuovo pacchetto di norme raggiunge molti obiettivi legati alla sostenibilità ambientale ed economica dell'attività di pesca, ma senza punire gli operatori del settore. Difatti, a differenza della situazione attuale in cui i piccoli pescatori sono esonerati da ogni forma di sostegno finanziario, anche in caso di fermo biologico, semmai avessero commesso infrazioni nel periodo successivo all'erogazione del fondo, adesso per avere l'autorizzazione in acque terze devono dimostrare di non essere nell'elenco delle navi illegali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi sì al rispetto delle norme, ma senza gravare sulle spalle dei pescatori con una burocrazia cieca e pretestuosa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="96936" name="Gabriel Mato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señora comisaria, este conjunto de normas modernizadas nos aportará mayor transparencia, supervisión y una mejora en la gestión de las flotas de pesca de larga distancia. Con el registro electrónico y la publicación de determinados datos del buque se mejorará la gobernabilidad y se dará un paso más en la lucha contra la pesca ilegal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si, además, se evitan la desproporcionada burocracia y los elevados costes para los operadores y los Estados miembros que conllevaba la propuesta inicial, podemos sentirnos satisfechos. Como lo estamos de que finalmente se desterrara la injusta y desproporcionada doble sanción que hoy algunos aún defienden con una enmienda legítima pero que no puede contar, de ninguna manera, con el apoyo de aquellos que, cediendo en pos de un acuerdo, contribuyeron a alcanzar, tras una dura negociación, el resultado que hoy sometemos a segunda lectura.</p>
      <p sl="en">A la flota de larga distancia de la Unión Europea se le exigen los más altos estándares y que sea ejemplares donde opera, pero en ningún caso la podemos penalizar en relación con flotas extranjeras que pescan las mismas especies en las mismas zonas y comercializan sus productos en los mismos mercados.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, yo quería felicitar a la ponente y a todos lo que han hecho este gran trabajo. Creo que la palabra con la que podíamos coincidir todos en este Reglamento de gestión sostenible de las flotas pesqueras exteriores es la de «equilibrio». No era fácil. No era fácil porque había posiciones diferentes, posiciones encontradas, y yo creo que se ha conseguido un equilibrio entre todos los aspectos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para mí era muy significativo y muy importante que se tuviese en cuenta la sostenibilidad ambiental, pero también la socioeconómica. Creo que es un aspecto que no debemos olvidar, porque detrás de cada una de estas decisiones hay personas y muchas poblaciones que viven de la actividad pesquera. Y, por lo tanto, esa sostenibilidad ambiental tenemos que acompañarla también con la atención hacia esas personas que viven de esto. Hay más de 700 barcos que faenan fuera de aguas comunitarias y, por tanto, tiene una importancia y una gran relevancia para la Unión Europea y, por supuesto, para mi país.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo me quiero sumar en esta intervención a que este consenso equilibrado y justo, que añade transparencia y que añade, además, unas características esenciales recogidas en la política pesquera común, no se salte con esa enmienda, y pido que se vote «no» a la enmienda del Grupo GUE/NGL y que se apoye lo que hemos aprobado entre todos: esta buena propuesta que espero que mañana salga aprobada con una gran mayoría.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-0000" speaker_id="96809" name="Peter van Dalen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Soms zie je toch dat de drie Europese instellingen samen goede wetgeving kunnen maken. De verordening "Duurzaam beheer van externe visserijvloten" is daar een prima voorbeeld van. De verordening heeft als doel een bestaande wetgeving te moderniseren met strikte, transparante en geharmoniseerde voorschriften voor EU-visserijschepen die in de wateren buiten de Europese Unie vissen, maar ook voor buitenlandse schepen die in de Europese wateren willen vissen. Daarbij moet ook illegale visserij verder worden teruggedrongen met deze nieuwe wetgeving.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stuk voor stuk uitstekende maatregelen in combinatie met betere handhaving en dat alles met als doel beter beheer van de visbestanden in de wateren van onze blauwe planeet. Dat steun ik 100%.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-0000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, no subject illustrates the EU’s expansionist – even colonialist – nature better than the fisheries policy set out in this report. Quite simply, the European Union thinks it knows best. It thinks it is entitled to impose its thinking on others. As with Brexit, so in the world’s oceans and seas.</p>
      <p sl="en">For the European Union there is only the EU approach: a single set of rules to be imposed on everybody else. There can be no taking account of the thinking, the wishes or the needs of others. There can be no mutual recognition: there can only be alignment and harmonisation. They sound so nice, so innocuous, don’t they. What reasonable person could object to aligning things, to harmonising them? But these words are euphemisms, they conceal the authoritarian one-size-fits-all ‘we know best’ way that the European Union seeks to impose its will upon others. This is a thinking of colonialism, and I am not a bit surprised that these colonial masters have no plans to hand back the UK fishing waters post Brexit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the general objective of this proposal is to improve the transparency and governance of EU vessels operating in non-EU waters and to ensure the sustainable exploitation of the stocks. However, while we seek these goals, we should not forget about increasing the effectiveness of the current system or promoting a level playing field for Union operators vis-à-vis third-country operators.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am talking about the effective closure of EU markets for products coming from third-country vessels that do not meet the requirements of this legislation. The EU should create a level playing field so that EU fishing vessels can compete with the vessels from these countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this context, I would like to congratulate the negotiating team on their successful conclusion of the trialogue negotiations. I believe this deal is balanced and we should support it during tomorrow’s vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="114279" name="Isabelle Thomas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, mes chers collègues, dans le contexte actuel d’accélération des échanges internationaux, nous nous devons à une vigilance extrême. Nous devons ainsi établir des règles strictes, transparentes et harmonisées pour la délivrance et la gestion des autorisations aux navires de l’Union pêchant en dehors des eaux communautaires et aux navires étrangers opérant dans les eaux de l’Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est l’objet de ce règlement, puisqu’il définit un cadre durable de nos activités de pêche dans le monde: durable parce qu’il vise les opérations de changement de pavillon, phénomène bien connu pour contourner les règles; durable parce qu’il conditionne la délivrance des autorisations de pêche au respect des règles de la politique commune de la pêche et de la gestion raisonnée des ressources halieutiques; durable, enfin, parce que des règles claires qui participent à la lutte contre la pêche illégale, non déclarée et non réglementée sont établies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour ces raisons, je soutiens cette résolution et vous invite à la soutenir. Je souhaite toutefois vous alerter sur l’autre volet à mettre en place pour réellement atteindre cet objectif de durabilité, à savoir le contenu des accords internationaux en matière de commerce. Mettons en place une vraie politique de promotion de nos normes sociales et environnementales lors de la négociation de ces accords et, là, nous aurons une politique cohérente de promotion de la pêche durable au niveau mondial.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, nova zajednička ribarstvena politika pred nas je stavila nove ciljeve i izazove, naročito u sferi dugoročne održivosti ribolovne djelatnosti, a ova će ih uredba ugraditi u upravljanje vanjskim ribarskim flotama.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zbog nedovoljno razrađenih i kratkovidnih politika iz prošlosti te neosviještenosti dijela ribara došli smo u situaciju da je ribe sve manje, dok je, s druge strane, konkurencija iznimno jaka. Ne treba čuditi stoga da su cehovi i udruženja ribara iz država članica često problematizirali djelatnost ribarskih plovila trećih zemalja u vodama Unije i zato je bilo iznimno važno na kvalitetan način nadograditi postojeću regulativu za izdavanje ribolovnih odobrenja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato mislim da smo s ovom regulativom dobili jednu novu dimezniju koja će ribarima osigurati profitabilno bavljenje ovom djelatnošću i u desetljećima koja dolaze.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'accordo raggiunto sul nuovo quadro legislativo per la gestione sostenibile delle flotte da pesca esterna è sicuramente un ottimo risultato, mi congratulo quindi con la relatrice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il nuovo regime prevede norme rigorose, trasparenti e armonizzate per il rilascio e la gestione di autorizzazioni di pesca per i pescherecci dell'Unione europea operanti al di fuori delle acque dell'Unione e per i pescherecci di paesi terzi che pescano nelle acque dell'Unione. Trattasi di norme essenziali per migliorare la governance, aumentare la trasparenza e ottimizzare il monitoraggio e l'attuazione delle norme, soprattutto in casi specifici, quali ad esempio le autorizzazioni dirette, i trasbordi o il cambio di bandiera.</p>
      <p sl="en">Grazie alle nuove norme più trasparenti, l'Unione europea sarà maggiormente in grado di contrastare la pesca illegale, non dichiarata e non regolamentata. Era una revisione necessaria per far sì che le attività di pesca al di fuori delle acque dell'Unione rispettino norme e principi analoghi a quelli applicati all'interno dell'Unione europea, ed è importante, in questo contesto, la previsione di elenchi di navi che praticano la pesca illegale, non dichiarata e non regolamentata.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, ο αλιευτικός στόλος της Ένωσης συνεισφέρει στην απασχόληση και φυσικά στην προμήθεια ψαριών στην αγορά της ΕΕ. Σε πολλά κράτη μέλη οι παράκτιες και νησιωτικές περιοχές αντιμετωπίζουν σημαντική ύφεση, μείωση του πληθυσμού και φυγή των κατοίκων τους. Η βιώσιμη διαχείριση των εξωτερικών αλιευτικών στόλων μπορεί να διασφαλίσει οπωσδήποτε τη βιώσιμη αλιεία υπό τον όρο βεβαίως ότι τηρούνται οι προϋποθέσεις του νόμου. Απαιτείται, λοιπόν, ένα ευέλικτο σύστημα χορήγησης αδειών και εδώ κομβικό ρόλο αναμένεται να διαδραματίσει το κράτος μέλος της σημαίας. Ταυτόχρονα όμως θα πρέπει τα αλιευτικά σκάφη τρίτων χωρών να σέβονται τους κανόνες. Αυτό ισχύει ιδιαίτερα για τα τουρκικά αλιευτικά σκάφη, τα οποία εισέρχονται παράνομα στα ελληνικά χωρικά ύδατα, και μάλιστα με την προστασία της τουρκικής ακτοφυλακής. Αλιεύουν παράνομα δίπλα από τα χωρικά ύδατα στα Δωδεκάνησα, στα Ίμια, στο Βόρειο Αιγαίο. Κυριολεκτικά διαπράττουν πειρατεία.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you very much once again. Thank you for your various interventions. I really note with satisfaction that you have expressed major support for the compromise reached in our trialogue, which opens the way towards the adoption of this legislation by you as co-legislators.</p>
      <p sl="en">I wish to stress that the European Parliament has been strong in its defence of the Commission’s original proposal. Thanks to this, this new legislation contains essential elements to ensure sustainable fishing, such as strict eligibility criteria for obtaining a fishing authorisation, a reference to scientific evaluations, a clear division of tasks between Member States and the Commission, and also rules to ensure full transparency on fishing activities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thanks to you, the European Parliament, the regulation has also become more ambitious as regards the high seas and guarding the rules on transhipment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Honourable Members, this is an excellent result and I would like to thank you sincerely for your contribution to its success. Now it is time for implementation. You can count on the Commission to play its role so that we achieve effectively better monitoring of fishing vessels and improve the governance of the oceans.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-0000" speaker_id="128588" name="Linnéa Engström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">föredragande. – Herr talman! Kära kollegor och fru kommissionär! EU ska ta sitt ansvar till havs och det är det vi gör nu med alla de processer som pågår både i EU-kommissionen och här i Europaparlamentet med t.ex. kommunikationen om havsförvaltning och alla delar av den reformerade grundförordningen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi har också arbetet inom FN, vårt hållbarhetsmål 14 som stipulerar friska hav, ett stop för överfisket och nedsmutsningen. Våra hav spelar ju en avgörande roll som buffert för klimatförändringarnas konsekvenser, så de absorberar stora mängder koldioxid.</p>
      <p sl="en">Men både försurningen av haven och den globala uppvärmningen påverkar fiskebestånden och de marina ekosystemen som i snabb takt förändras framför våra ögon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jag är dedikerad till att fortsätta arbeta med alla aktörer inom EU-systemet: industrin, EU-kommissionen och ideella organisationer, för att stoppa illegalt fiske och överfiske.</p>
      <p sl="en">Arbetet med den här förordningen är ett viktigt steg på vägen men det räcker inte. Vi kan absolut inte nöja oss. Vi är långt ifrån att förvalta våra gemensamma resurser på ett hållbart sätt. Vi måste göra mycket mer, och där spelar Europaparlamentet en otroligt viktig roll.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi är ju medborgarnas direkta röst och den ska vi använda till att öka transparensen och ansvarstagandet i fiskesektorn. Jag vill verkligen uppmana kommissionen att använda sig av möjligheten att sätta hårt mot hårt mot medlemsstater som inte sköter sig. Om en båt upprepade gånger gör sig skyldig till överträdelser och grova brott, då bör det tillståndet dras in.</p>
      <p sl="en">Om medlemsstaten inte klarar av att göra detta så måste EU-kommissionen kunna vidta åtgärder. Det handlar ju om vårt rykte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jag vill också uppmana EU-kommissionen att verka för större transparens i fiskesektorn. Alltför lång tid har våra gemensamma tillgångar beslutats om på stängda och hemliga möten. Våra skattepengar ska inte gå till att stödja överfiske. Det måste bli ett slut på rovdrift och brottslighet till havs. Bara så bygger vi en fredlig och hållbar värld.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet morgen, Dienstag, 12. Dezember 2017, statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. EU Emissions Trading System (EU ETS): continuing current limitations of scope for aviation activities and preparing to implement a global market-based measure from 2021 (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Julie Girling im Namen des Ausschusses für Umweltfragen, öffentliche Gesundheit und Lebensmittelsicherheit über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates zur Änderung der Richtlinie 2003/87/EG zur Aufrechterhaltung der derzeitigen Einschränkung ihrer Anwendung auf Luftverkehrstätigkeiten und zur Vorbereitung der Umsetzung eines globalen marktbasierten Mechanismus ab 2021 (COM(2017)0054 - C8-0028/2017 - 2017/0017(COD)) (A8-0258/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am pleased to be able to speak this evening in plenary on the interinstitutional agreement reached in trilogue in October under the Estonian Presidency. Aviation accounts for approximately 2.1% of global CO2 emissions. In the EU, direct CO2 emissions from aviation account for approximately 3% of the total.</p>
      <p sl="en">This might not sound like very much, but when you think about the anticipated growth in air traffic emissions – by 2050 they are expected to be seven to ten times higher than in 1990, according to ICAO – these projections are really quite scary. We need to take very strong action.</p>
      <p sl="en">Clearly such a growth is unsustainable and necessitates a policy response. We must work hard over the next few years to ensure we are on track to reach our climate ambitions under the Paris Agreement. In the European Parliament, we have taken the view that we must reduce the carbon impact of the growth of air travel. We all know the history of ‘stop the clock’, so I do not intend to repeat that, but I do want to emphasise the European Parliament’s commitment to continuing to work with ICAO to ensure the next few years deliver what they must: carbon reductions in line with our Paris commitments.</p>
      <p sl="en">Since the proposal was made by DG CLIMA in 2017, earlier this year, we have moved at a fast pace in Parliament in order to reach an agreement with Council by the end of this year. From the publication of my draft report in May, I have fully supported the Commission’s approach that we await the progress on the GMBM. I did, however, make some additional calls, and I am glad to say we reached a satisfactory agreement during the trilogue negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The most important addition is the application of a time limit on the ‘stop the clock’ derogation. Whilst welcoming the agreement reached at international level, having an end date on this reflects Parliament’s legitimate concerns over the robust development of the GMBM and whether it would deliver on its commitment to ensure carbon-neutral growth from 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">At present, based on the current negotiations within ICAO, progress on the offsetting provisions appears to be slow, with some parties – China and India notably – objecting to ICAO’s role in setting the rules for the GMBM. As such, I believe it would be remiss to make a decision on the future of the ETS in support of a GMBM that is currently still vague and of an imprecise framework.</p>
      <p sl="en">With this regulation we are effectively outsourcing all our climate action on aviation to ICAO, an organisation that routinely makes decisions behind closed doors and does not allow full participation and transparency. A time-limited derogation will maintain political pressure on the Council and Commission to develop a long-term regulatory solution. We must learn from the issues encountered with previous iterations of the legislation and provide the sector with much needed investor certainty by completing work on the GMBM’s reporting provisions and the transparency and environmental integrity of its offset registry.</p>
      <p sl="en">With a trilogue agreement on ETS Phase 4 reached in early November, Parliament won a delegated act on the CORSIA MRV rules. We believe we should have the opportunity to assess the provisions when the time comes. The political agreement on the need for ICAO to act in full transparency and reach out to all stakeholders to inform on progress and decisions made must move from rhetoric to reality as the implementation of these measures progresses.</p>
      <p sl="en">The trilogue agreement also safeguards the Commission’s proposal to introduce an annually declining cap from 2021 and the possibility to reassess this, with a view to increasing the percentage of allowances auctioned. With exemption lapsing on 31 December, we give ICAO time to introduce the global carbon-offsetting scheme for the sector in 2021.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, unfortunately my colleague, Mr Arias Cañete, has been delayed by the bad weather, so I also have to represent him on this report. It is my pleasure to stand again in front of you for him and take part in your deliberations on the proposal on the European Union emission trading system for aviation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is glad that, on 18 October, the co-legislators were able to reach an agreement on this very sensitive file. I want to express a special gratitude to the rapporteur, Ms Girling, for her excellent work. It was instrumental to reaching a swift agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to thank the shadow rapporteurs for their contributions and support. It was imperative to conclude this file before the end of the year. If the amendment to this directive does not enter into force by early 2018, the full scope – covering all flights to and from third countries – will kick off again.</p>
      <p sl="en">The agreement between this Parliament and the Council is a balanced and fair one. Firstly, the deal ensure the continuation of the European Union ETS for intra-European flights beyond 2017. From 2021, the European Union ETS for aviation will be strengthened through the application of the 2.2% yearly emissions reduction.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are also committed to assessing how the sector passes its carbon costs onto its customers, with a view to increasing the auctioning share in the next review.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, the Commission will report regularly to the European Parliament and the Council on international developments, notably on the implementation of CORSIA, carbon offsetting and a reduction scheme for international aviation.</p>
      <p sl="en">We know that a lot of work is still needed to make CORSIA operational by 2021. Its rule book is being negotiated now and we have to remain vigilant. It is clear that we still have some challenges ahead before we can say that we have a robust and effective global scheme delivering what it is supposed to deliver.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also have to watch out to see whether and how our partners will translate these international measures into the concrete operationalisation of CORSIA rests on domestic action.</p>
      <p sl="en">As agreed, the Commission will submit a new proposal to amend the ETS Directive, with the aim of implementing CORSIA in a way that is consistent with our climate target.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally the text agreed by the co-legislators contains an empowerment to adopt delegated acts on monitoring, reporting and verification of the emissions, and this is in order for the European Union to be able to implement CORSIA in that regard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Honourable Members, in our view the agreed text strikes a good balance between the leadership we should continue to have by addressing aviation emissions, the reinforced European Union ETS, and the responsiveness of European Union policies to international developments, notably the expected operationalisation of the scheme based on the assessment of their robustness and their effectiveness, which you asked the Commission to produce. I am confident it can get wide support in the European Parliament so that the legislation can enter into force early next year as planned.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-0000" speaker_id="1928" name="Werner Langen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser der Stellungnahme des mitberatenden Ausschusses für Industrie, Forschung und Energie. – Herr Präsident! Die Vorlage stammt vom 3. Februar 2017, das Parlament hat am 13. September seine Stellungnahme verabschiedet, und unter der Federführung der Kollegin Girling ist jetzt die Einigung erzielt worden, die auch im Rat angenommen wurde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meine Aufgabe ist es, die Stellungnahme des Industrieausschusses kurz zu erläutern. Wir sind mit dem Vorschlag der Kommission von Anfang an im Wesentlichen einverstanden gewesen. Wir haben den eingeschränkten Anwendungsbereich befürwortet, wir haben die Ausnahmen für nicht gewerbliche Luftfahrzeugbetreiber mit jährlichen Gesamtemissionen von weniger als 1 000 Tonnen CO2 befürwortet, und wir haben die Kommission aufgefordert, die Entwicklung des globalen marktbasierten Mechanismus CORSIA voranzutreiben. Womit sich der Ausschuss nicht befasst hat, das ist ein Punkt der Einigung: Vorbehaltlich dieser Überprüfung wird der lineare Reduktionsfaktor auch für den Luftverkehrssektor eingeführt. Damit sind wir aber einverstanden. Der Bericht wurde mit 51 gegen 5 Stimmen angenommen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="124952" name="Seb Dance" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Ich kann nicht für die EVP sprechen.</p>
      <p sl="en">I could try. Aviation is the largest, fastest—growing sector when it comes to CO2 emissions. It is not the biggest contributor on its own, but as the fastest—growing sector, it is incumbent on us to take action on it. It would make a mockery of the Paris Accord were we not to do so.</p>
      <p sl="en">The ICAO scheme, CORSIA, which will commit to carbon—neutral growth by 2020, is of course a very welcome step forward. Actually I have a grudging respect and admiration – a genuine admiration in fact – for ICAO, the work that they do and the fact that they have adapted to the needs to tackle climate change. You look surprised, Bas, but it is true. The admiration is real. But of course we cannot rely solely on these processes, because we know that they are not transparent and we do not know what the final result will be.</p>
      <p sl="en">But the Commission and the Council both started this process by saying they wanted indefinite exemptions for international flights from the ETS. This would of course give a blank cheque, and it is frankly an absurd idea, given that we do not know what the outcome of the ICAO process will be. So the deal of putting a limit on the exemption to 2023 is an excellent step, and this Parliament should congratulate itself on having ensured that. I pay tribute, as ever, to the work of the rapporteur, Ms Girling, for helping to secure that, as well as the work of all the other groups that supported her.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is not only the right thing to do: it also puts pressure on ICAO to deliver a CORSIA package that would be ambitious and would prevent the European Union from placing international flights under the ETS. It is obviously not in ICAO’s interests to do so, and we would therefore want them to be as ambitious as possible. However, it is essential that this process is transparent. The Aarhus Convention obliges signatories to grant access to the public to information, participation and access to justice. This process is opaque and is in contravention of these principles.</p>
      <p sl="en">One final point: there is an amendment saying that there should be protection for UK companies for the ETS scheme against UK companies dumping. My appeal to the UK Government is to just commit now to being in the ETS. We know what the outcome of phase one means. It means that the UK will be in the single market and the customs union, barring miracles. Commit now and you remove …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="117477" name="Mark Demesmaeker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – De luchtvaartsector is goed voor ruim 2% van de globale CO2-uitstoot, vergelijkbaar met de totale uitstoot van een land zoals Duitsland. De uitstoot neemt bovendien ook toe. Om de doelen van het klimaatakkoord van Parijs te bereiken moeten alle sectoren een inspanning leveren, dus ook de luchtvaartsector. Vluchten binnen Europa vallen sinds 2012 onder het Europees emissiehandelssysteem. Voor internationale vluchten geldt nog altijd die uitzondering op de regel. Met de voorliggende tekst verlengen we die uitzondering een allerlaatste keer. Zo geven we het globale ICAO-akkoord alle kansen op slagen, maar een blanco cheque schrijven we niet uit. Door de duidelijke einddatum voor de uitzondering voor internationale vluchten houden we de druk op de ketel van ICAO en een stok achter de deur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik wilde collega Girling van harte feliciteren met haar doordachte aanpak. De NVA-delegatie zal het akkoord voluit steunen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-0000" speaker_id="96940" name="Gerben-Jan Gerbrandy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, let me start by congratulating Julie Girling for this wonderful result and I can only wish to have the same kind of result this Wednesday when we have the final trilogue on the effort sharing regulation.</p>
      <p sl="de">I’m particularly happy with the time limited derogation. We had to fight for that very strongly and I’m very happy that that was part of the general compromise in the end. Last month, once again in Montreal, ICAO showed how important it is that we have at least one instrument to keep pressure on the ICAO process when the ICAO council decided to take over only two of the 12 sustainability criteria for biofuels that their own environment committee had proposed.</p>
      <p sl="de">It’s a very, very weak outcome of the sustainability criteria for biofuels and the same might happen with the offsetting criteria that are being set by ICAO. It’s very strange that an organisation like ICAO, which does not have any real knowledge about this, is dealing itself in the criteria for offsets.</p>
      <p sl="de">At the same time, in the EU with the ETS we’ve had a very bad experience with offsetting, with huge windfall profits being made and almost destroying our system. So I’m very happy that we are keeping pressure on them by emphasising the transparency that will be asked for by all European institutions.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, Mr President, I would like to emphasise the need for further technological breakthroughs. In the end it’s the only way to limit CO2 emissions from the aviation sector. Only through electronic or hydrogen aeroplanes can we fight this fight against climate change through aviation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-0000" speaker_id="23699" name="Kateřina Konečná" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu GUE/NGL. – Pane předsedající, také mně dovolte poděkovat kolegyni Julii Girlingové, která se stala jakýmsi ambasadorem všech reforem ETS v tomto parlamentu. Myslím si, že je dobře, že na těch věcech dělají ti lidé společně, protože my jsme to letectví díky vlivu mezinárodních organizací museli dostat mimo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ale na druhou stranu je třeba říci, že nám patří do celého systému, na který se připravujeme a který se, pevně věřím, podaří v nejbližší době dokončit tak, abychom emise neomezovali jenom u těch, které máme nejblíže, ale abychom se je snažili omezovat i tam, kde nám v tom bohužel neustále brání i například některé mezinárodní organizace tak, jak je to v ICAO, ale jak je to také i v IMO v rámci emisí z lodní dopravy. Tam narážíme na úplně stejný odpor, kde nechtějí být přístupní tomu, abychom se bavili o tom, jak to udělat jinak.</p>
      <p sl="en">My jako GUE/NGL určitě se zapojením letectví do systému ETS a postihováním jeho globálních emisí souhlasíme a považujeme to za zcela nezbytné. Stávající omezení musí platit a chápu, že se na to sektor musí patřičně připravit. Na druhou stranu si uvědomme, jakým způsobem se chováme k evropskému sektoru v rámci systému obchodování s emisními povolenkami a kolik času dáváme těm nadnárodním korporacím a společnostem k tomu, aby se přizpůsobovaly. Já bych si přála, abychom zařídili rovnost a zároveň bych si dovolila říct, že my tento dokument samozřejmě podpoříme, ale prosím, dívejme se na to vždy globálně a v celé šíři toho spektra.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="96725" name="Bas Eickhout" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all, I would like to join the choir of people thanking the rapporteur, Ms Girling, for her very good work on this file, as well as on the other file, but we will do that for next month I guess. The way in which you dealt with his file is really appreciated, as is the way in which you managed to get a broad majority in this House on board. That was a very good job on a not necessarily easy topic, so in that sense, I offer my congratulations.</p>
      <p sl="en">So what does this deal really mean? It means that aviation for intra-EU flights will now also come under the decreasing cap of emission trading, which was not the case until now. Until now, they were part of ETS but they got a lot of free allowances and no decrease in caps. Finally, some shortage of emission allowances will hit this sector, because in the end every sector needs to play its role. Until now, aviation has been excluded. But that’s only for intra-EU flights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, for international flights outside the EU we still have an exemption and we still rely on the international organisation ICAO. First of all, I would like to stress to the Commission, which sometimes gets cold feet when making new proposals, for example on maritime and on shipping emissions, that if there is one thing that is very clear from this experience, it is that if the EU did not take a step in 2008, ICAO would never have come to the deal that they have on the table now. EU policies do influence global policies, and the Commission should not shy away from it, rather it should learn from it and step up its efforts regarding the maritime sector, because that is the only other sector still not playing any role.</p>
      <p sl="en">But secondly, we still have to wait and see what ICAO is really going to deliver. We know that ICAO has now delivered on their principle, but many countries still said that they do not agree with the target of a neutral greenhouse gas growth path after 2020. We do not yet know how many countries will really fulfil that target.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, they allowed for huge offsetting for themselves, and that’s why I looked a bit surprised at my colleague Seb Dance, who talked about admiration for ICAO. I think that’s a bit too early. We need to know what they’re going to deliver, and how they are going to develop their offsetting scheme is going to be key. If we had just said ‘okay, we trust the global deal and that’s it’, we would have made a very big mistake. That is why it is good that we time-limited the derogation until 2023. I would have loved to be a bit stricter, but I can live with this compromise. ICAO has until 2023 to deliver on an offsetting scheme, otherwise the EU needs to take action on its own.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="106202" name="Julia Reid" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, less than 1.5% of global carbon dioxide emissions are attributable to international aviation, and I am sceptical that emissions from this sector will increase by 300-700 per cent by 2050 whether action is taken or not.</p>
      <p sl="en">Imposing even more taxes on flights will not deter people from flying, so is unlikely to mitigate any impact on climate change. However, the rapporteur believes that the Commission’s implementation report on the ICAO’s market mechanism should be in line with the EU’s commitments under the Paris Agreement and should ensure that all environmental standards of the EU ETS are maintained.</p>
      <p sl="en">To date, the ETS, in conjunction with other legislation designed to reduce emissions and increase energy costs, has had a devastating effect on heavy industries within the EU, leaving them unable to compete with countries such as China, India and the USA. Consequently, energy-intensive businesses, such as steel, aluminium and chemicals have closed, exporting jobs and investment out of the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="124803" name="Isabella De Monte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, le attività di trasporto aereo sono un'enorme fonte di emissione di gas a effetto serra, e in assenza di misure di riduzione dovrebbero quadruplicare entro il 2050 il loro livello rispetto al 2010.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per tali ragioni, la riduzione globale delle emissioni nazionali di gas a effetto serra è un obiettivo fondamentale della politica dell'Unione europea. In tal senso il sistema ETS è uno strumento essenziale per una riduzione economicamente efficiente di tali emissioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nell'attesa che l'Organizzazione mondiale dell'aviazione civile internazionale stabilisca i dettagli del meccanismo di un accordo basato sul mercato per affrontare a livello globale l'aumento delle missioni, è necessario che il Parlamento europeo e il Consiglio approvino la revisione di questo regolamento. Una celere approvazione entro la fine dell'anno permetterà di evitare, per gli operatori aerei europei, qualsiasi vuoto giuridico rispetto alla normativa ETS nell'anno in corso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questo garantirà certezza e chiarezza del diritto e permetterà il rispetto degli obblighi di conformità previsti dal sistema ETS dell'Unione europea relativo al trasporto aereo e la proroga della deroga fino al 31 dicembre 2023, per i voli all'esterno dello spazio economico europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine, voglio ricordare che sarà importante la piena realizzazione del Cielo unico europeo. Ciò permetterà di evitare la frammentazione dello spazio aereo e ottimizzare il flusso del traffico, con conseguente diminuzione delle emissioni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich möchte mich auch ganz herzlich bei der Berichterstatterin bedanken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Dank und das Lob kommen jetzt von allen Seiten. Ich muss sagen: So wie es vorher das Parlament verlassen hatte, war ich nicht ganz einverstanden. Das Ergebnis des Trilogs finde ich sehr gut. Es ist ja so, dass das Parlament eine Aussetzung des Luftverkehrsemissionshandels zwischen EU und den Drittstaaten sogar nur bis 2020 wollte. Ich denke mal, das wäre wirklich zu früh gewesen, denn bis 2021 soll CORSIA eingeführt werden. Ich finde es großartig, dass es bei der ICAO endlich passiert. Die ICAO loben will ich gar nicht so. Aber ich muss sagen, ich beschäftige mich seit vielen Jahren damit und ich war zuerst sehr skeptisch, ob von der ICAO überhaupt ein weltweiter Vorschlag für ein globales Emissionszertifikatssystem kommen würde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jetzt kommt das, und das ist sehr gut. Nun müssen wir aber auch erst mal sehen, dass es wirklich eintritt. Wir haben nämlich vorher schon 2012 gemerkt, dass die anderen sich wehren, wenn die EU versucht, sie in ein System zu zwingen, das sie nicht wollen. Ich denke mal, es ist vollkommen klar: Beim globalen Luftverkehr brauchen wir auch globale Instrumente, um das Klima weltweit zu retten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="124863" name="Stefan Eck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, verehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Zuerst einmal möchte ich der Berichterstatterin für ihren Bericht danken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber ich muss auch sagen, dass das ETS die Emissionen nicht wesentlich reduziert hat. Es ist in seiner derzeitigen Ausstattung, im Hinblick auf die Klimaziele und die Kosten ineffizient. Weder in diesem Haus und schon gar nicht im Europäischen Rat gibt es derzeit den Mut und die Mehrheiten, um einen Mindestpreis für CO2-Zertifikate, zumindest temporär, festzulegen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ohne grundlegende Reformen halte ich das ETS geradezu für betrügerisch und ein klassisches Beispiel für ein greenwashing von umweltverschmutzenden Sektoren wie beispielsweise dem Luftverkehr. Die Luftverkehrsemissionen werden 2020 voraussichtlich um 70 % höher sein als 2005, und bis 2050 könnten sie um weitere 300 bis 700 % ansteigen. Daran wird das derzeitige System gar nichts ändern und das wissen Sie, meine Damen und Herren. Wir haben ja bald Weihnachten, und Sie könnten Ihre Wählerschaft einmal damit beschenken, dass Sie ihnen die volle Wahrheit über das ETS sagen. In diesem Sinne: Ich wünsche Ihnen allen ein frohes Fest.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-0000" speaker_id="183338" name="Jakop Dalunde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Medan vi talar så fortsätter utsläppen från flyget att öka, och det är dags att EU nu agerar för att vända utvecklingen och kraftigt minska utsläppen från flyget.</p>
      <p sl="en">Flyget måste betala för sin del av klimatpåverkan precis som alla andra. Det är bra att EU nu tar ett steg framåt för att så faktiskt ska ske när det gäller flygets del av EU:s utsläppshandel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Men det får inte stanna här. Vi måste inkludera de s.k. höghöjdseffekterna. Det skadar klimatet tre till fyra gånger mer när man släpper ut klimatpåverkande gaser uppe i luften men trots det så räknar vi utsläppen som om de vore på marken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi måste också inkludera resor till och från flygplatser utanför Europa. Om man reser med flyg från Stockholm till New York eller Bangkok så betalar man i dagsläget ingenting alls för sin klimatpåverkan, och så får det faktiskt inte fortsätta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi måste minska hela flygets utsläpp och till och från alla flygplatser i världen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="124750" name="Mireille D'Ornano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, l’Organisation de l’aviation civile internationale (OACI), qui rassemble 191 États, a défini, depuis 2016, les objectifs et principaux éléments d’un marché mondial des émissions de CO2 issues de l'aviation internationale, pour l’après 2021. Ce programme «CORSIA» s’emploiera à stabiliser les émissions aux niveaux de 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pourtant, ce texte demande à la Commission de publier, au 1er mars 2020, un rapport jugeant de la pertinence des normes et pratiques recommandées par l’OACI, des instruments adoptés, ou encore de l'ambition et de l'intégrité environnementale du mécanisme. Il est en outre demandé à la Commission de rendre compatibles les instruments de l’OACI avec le droit de l’Union européenne, ce qui crée un écran entre les décisions de l’OACI et les États qui en sont membres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans un secteur aussi sensible et concurrentiel que l’aviation, rendons-nous à l’évidence: seul un système mondial est réellement légitime, juste et efficace.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-0000" speaker_id="185619" name="Tiemo Wölken" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sehr geehrter Herr Präsident, vielen Dank! Auch ich begrüße es, dass die Internationale Zivilluftfahrt-Organisation einen Plan zur Reduktion und Kompensation von Kohlenstoff vorgelegt hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sollten diesen aber sehr kritisch prüfen. Meine Skepsis beruht dabei auf drei Punkten. Erstens: CORSIA wird nur etwa ein Fünftel der weltweiten Klima-/Flugemissionen abdecken, denn es gilt unter anderem nicht für Inlandsflüge und auch nicht für andere Emissionen als Kohlenstoffdioxid.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zweitens: Es ist noch nicht klar, wie die Emissionen kompensiert werden sollen. Dabei haben wir bisher weltweit schlechte Erfahrungen mit der Kompensation gemacht. Nicht umsonst dürfen EU-Mitgliedstaaten ab 2021 für ihre nationalen Klimaziele keine Kompensationsprojekte mehr nutzen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Drittens, was ich auch hervorheben will: Eine Kompensation von Treibhausgasausstoß ist nur die zweitbeste Lösung. Wir müssen möglichst nah an das Ziel herankommen, gar keine Treibhausgase mehr auszustoßen. Daher sind aus meiner Sicht technische Lösungen besser, die den Ausstoß an der Quelle verhindern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Um meine Standpunkte zusammenzufassen: Klimawirksame Emissionen der Luftfahrt gehen uns alle an. Die zivile Luftfahrtorganisation sollte daher ein Verfahren entwickeln, das transparent ist, und die Öffentlichkeit stärker miteinbeziehen. Insofern ist es sehr wichtig, dass gerade das Europäische Parlament diesen Plan sehr kritisch überprüfen kann. Daher werde ich dem Kommissionstext morgen zustimmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="183022" name="Lieve Wierinck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ik denk dat we het er allemaal over eens zijn dat we in de mate van het mogelijke inspanningen moeten leveren voor het klimaat. Tegelijkertijd moeten we ervoor zorgen dat de Europese luchtvaartsector, die een belangrijk deel van onze economie uitmaakt, competitief blijft. Net omdat ik uit Zaventem kom, weet ik maar al te goed hoe belangrijk luchthavens zijn voor de lokale, maar ook voor de nationale economie. Daarom blijf ik erop hameren dat we steeds een goede balans moeten vinden tussen onze ecologische ambities en het vrijwaren van de concurrentiepositie van onze luchtvaartsector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Het mag dan ook niet de bedoeling zijn om het gebruik van hét vervoermiddel van de 21e eeuw te verminderen. Daarom moeten we investeren in O&amp;O die de luchtvaartsector efficiënter en groener gemaakt. Ik ben dan ook voorstander van het volgende: de inkomsten, verkregen via veiling van uitstootpakketten, moeten worden gebruikt voor het investeren in onderzoek. In navolging van het Clean Sky-programma geeft deze investering in onderzoek een competitief voordeel aan onze luchtvaartindustrie op lange termijn en vormt ze een nieuw wapen in de strijd tegen klimaatverandering.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, le emissioni di gas a effetto serra prodotte dalle attività di trasporto aereo sono in forte aumento e, in assenza di opportuni provvedimenti, entro il 2050 potrebbero raggiungere un livello pari a quattro volte quello del 2010.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'aumento delle emissioni nel settore dell'aviazione rischia di compromettere gli sforzi compiuti dall'Unione europea e a livello mondiale per affrontare efficacemente i cambiamenti climatici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Anche io esprimo il mio parere favorevole al prolungamento fino al 2020 dell'attuale sistema ETS dell'Unione, che consente di ridurre le emissioni di circa 17 milioni di tonnellate di CO2 l'anno, fino a quando non vi sarà sufficiente chiarezza circa la natura e il contenuto degli strumenti giuridici adottati dall'ICAO per l'attuazione di una misura a livello globale, la cosiddetta CORSIA. Ciò significa che all'interno dello Spazio economico europeo, il settore aereo continuerà a contribuire, come ogni altro settore economico, agli sforzi volti alla riduzione delle emissioni interne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Occorre però accelerare i lavori all'interno dell'ICAO in vista dell'effettiva adozione e applicazione di una misura globale in grado di risolvere tutti i problemi legati al traffico internazionale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-0000" speaker_id="96885" name="Dominique Riquet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, le problème est que nous sommes pris entre deux feux, si je puis dire: d’une part, la nécessité de répondre à l’urgence climatique et, donc, de réduire les émissions de CO2 d’un secteur qui est exclu des accords internationaux; d’autre part, l’absence de visibilité technologique pour l’avion vert et aussi l’explosion volumétrique du système aérien et du transport aérien, ainsi que le problème de la concurrence internationale pour nos compagnies aériennes, qui d’ailleurs est aussi un sujet sur la table de notre institution.</p>
      <p sl="en">En fait, nous soutenons le message envoyé par le trilogue, qui est un message d’unité à la communauté internationale et qui va éviter toute incertitude juridique. Nous devons avoir confiance dans la mise en place d’un nouveau système fort dès 2021 pour la phase pilote. Aujourd’hui, en 2018 déjà, 72 pays ont signalé qu’ils rejoindront ce système mondial, et on s’attend à plus dès 2020. Faisons maintenant en sorte que le SEQE et le CORSIA puissent s’aligner correctement en temps voulu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-0000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Letalstvo je najhitreje razvijajoč se sektor v prometu in že danes predstavlja izpust 1,3 % vseh C02 plinov, zato je nujno, da preprečimo, da se ne zgodi ta črn scenarij, da bi se do 2050 ti izpusti povečali še za 3 do 7 krat, kolikor so napovedi glede na rast prometa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Evropa ne more sama rešiti tega problema, svoja prizadevanja izvaja v okviru ETS, prav tako pa v okviru Pariškega sporazuma želi k sodelovanju privabiti ostale akterje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Veseli me, da je tudi Svetovna organizacija civilnega letalstva (ICAO) pristala in da je pripravila prve sheme, kako si ta bremena porazdeliti tudi v prihodnje, in upam in verjamem tudi, da bo zavedanje, da smo za planet odgovorni vsi, pripeljalo do tega, da bo po letu 2021 na globalnem nivoju sprejeto določilo, na osnovi katerega bodo bremena pravično razdeljena, da ne bo trpela konkurenčnost posameznih delov sveta na tem področju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr! Jómagam azokkal a képviselőtársaimmal értek egyet, akik a kutatás-fejlesztésre helyezték a hangsúlyt. És ezt szeretném egy kicsit jobban is megindokolni. Mindazok a repülőgépek, amelyeket ma a világ különböző fejlett országaiban legyártanak, ezek 15-20-25 évig is akár működésben lesznek, és ontani fogják azt a szén-dioxidot, aminek kiontására ma tulajdonképpen őket megtervezték. Ennélfogva ez egy nagyon-nagyon nehezen mozgó ágazat, és itt az elején kell megfogni tulajdonképpen a folyamatokat, és én éppen ezért gratulálok Girling asszonynak, aki nagyon elokvens módon támogatta ezt a bizonyos perspektivikus cselekményt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Összességében tekintve azt hiszem, hogy a szén-dioxid-kibocsátás az a légi forgalomban, ami tulajdonképpen hosszabb távon akár le is tudja nullázni mindazokat az erőfeszítéseket, amelyeket más területeken, az ipar, vagy a közlekedés más területein tud hozni Európa, illetve világ, és éppen ezért kell nagyon odafigyelni. Kutatás-fejlesztés!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, περίπου το 1,3% των παγκόσμιων εκπομπών διοξειδίου του άνθρακα προέρχεται από διεθνείς αερομεταφορές. Έτσι λοιπόν αυτό το ποσοστό, το 1,3% των παγκόσμιων εκπομπών –αυτό είναι το ακριβές ποσοστό– αναμένεται να αυξηθεί, καθώς τα επόμενα χρόνια αναμένεται και αύξηση των αερομεταφορών. Η αύξηση αυτή των εκπομπών μπορεί να φτάσει μέχρι και το 700% το 2050. Είναι προφανές λοιπόν ότι τα μέτρα που έχουν ληφθεί από τη γενική συνέλευση του Διεθνούς Οργανισμού Πολιτικής Αεροπορίας έχουν οδηγήσει, όπως γνωρίζουμε όλοι, στο σύστημα αντιστάθμισης και μείωσης ανθρακούχων εκπομπών για τις διεθνείς αερομεταφορές, το σύστημα Corsia. Το ερώτημα όμως είναι εάν αυτό το σύστημα μπορεί να εφαρμοστεί περιφερειακά, χωρίς να το τηρούν οι άλλες δυνάμεις, όπως είναι οι Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες και η Κίνα. Εάν δεν υπάρξει παγκόσμια ρύθμιση για το θέμα αυτό, δεν θα έχουμε σοβαρά αποτελέσματα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-0000" speaker_id="125072" name="Ελευθέριος Συναδινός" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το σύστημα εμπορίας δικαιωμάτων εκπομπών προσπαθεί να εξισορροπήσει το ισοζύγιο άνθρακα και των λοιπών αερίων σε συνάρτηση με το δαιδαλώδες σύστημα αεροπορικών μεταφορών. Ο κατακερματισμός όμως του ευρωπαϊκού εναέριου χώρου και η εμπορευματοποίηση των εκπομπών αερίων μέσω των πλειστηριασμών δικαιωμάτων δεν συνάδει ακριβώς με την προστασία του περιβάλλοντος ως πρωταρχικό μέλημα της Ένωσης, λαμβανομένου υπόψη ότι το περιβάλλον δεν γνωρίζει σύνορα. Επιπρόσθετα, όταν οι αεροπορικές εταιρείες που δεν επιτυγχάνουν τους στόχους σταθεροποίησης των εκπομπών λαμβάνουν πιστοποιητικά αντιστάθμισης, αυτό καταστρατηγεί έμμεσα τη βασική αρχή της Ένωσης για το περιβάλλον που είναι: «ο ρυπαίνων πληρώνει».</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι συζητήσεις και τα ψηφίσματα για τις περιβαλλοντικές πολιτικές αποτελούν ευκαιρία διακομματικής συνεννόησης και συμφωνίας. Η περιβαλλοντική κουλτούρα και προστασία δεν πρέπει να χτίζει αριστερές πολιτικές καριέρες ούτε να μονοπωλείται από την Αριστερά και τους Πράσινους. Το περιβάλλον δεν πολιτικοποιείται. Αφορά όλους μας και ειδικά τις επερχόμενες γενεές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I appreciate very much the support expressed by the Members of this Parliament for this legislative proposal. We are all looking forward to a positive vote on it.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also take note of your concerns as regards International Civil Aviation Organisation, which the Commission shares. We know that this organisation should work in a more transparent manner, and we have agreed on a joint statement from the three institutions on these issues.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are also aware that the rules being developed in the International Civil Aviation Organisation are far from securing a robust system, but we’ll have a chance to report on this and react accordingly. That is precisely one of the key elements of the legislation we are discussing today.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me conclude by thanking you once again on behalf of Mr Arias Cañete, who very much regrets not being here with us today. Thank you for processing this file in a swift manner and for your valuable contributions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, my colleague Věra Jourová has just informed me that she is in very heavy traffic, so I should continue with her file. However, before I continue I need a two-minute break, if it is possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-0000" speaker_id="23768" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Very well, Madam Commissioner, maybe I will ask the rapporteur to take the floor first.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Will you allow me to be absent for one minute?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="23768" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Yes, I will give you five minutes in the name of good cooperation between the Commission and Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-0000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you. Thank you, Madam Commissioner, that is no problem at all with me, and I’ll be very brief anyway. I’d just like to give my final thanks to the shadows. It is rather ironic that we are here talking about an aviation item, when so many people have been unable to make what I know they saw as a very important debate, and because of aviation difficulties.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would just like to make a couple of points: I think we all agree that aviation has to pay its way in the same way as road and rail transport do, and that the GMBM, whilst not perfect, does encompass our principles of protecting the single market and preventing unfair competition. It is the only game in town when it comes to a global measure. So we do need to stand by it, but we also need to be really, really clear that it is going to take some really careful watching.</p>
      <p sl="en">I appeal to all of the colleagues who will be here when I will sadly not be, over the next several years, to make sure that they hold both the Commission and ICAO’s feet to the fire on this issue and that when we get reports, as we’ve seen this week, about biofuels and how ICAO have reneged on commitments made only a short time ago, that must signal alarm bells that we need to use the mechanisms laid down in this report to hold them to account.</p>
      <p sl="en">And finally, for the record, for my colleague Mr Dance, I would like to agree with him that the UK Government should indeed signal, as soon as possible, that they intend to continue commitments under both this and the main ETS scheme. There seems absolutely no reason why they should not, and indeed I would encourage them to do so – and do – at every opportunity.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się we wtorek 12 grudnia 2017 r.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. EU Citizenship Report 2017: Strengthening Citizens' Rights in a Union of Democratic Change (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Beatriz Becerrę Basterrecheę w imieniu Komisji Petycji w sprawie sprawozdania na temat obywatelstwa UE z 2017 r. Wzmocnienie praw obywateli w Unii demokratycznych zmian (2017/2069(INI)) (A8-0385/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-0000" speaker_id="125040" name="Beatriz Becerra Basterrechea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señor presidente, señora comisaria, gracias por estar aquí. La Unión Europea no es solamente un conjunto de instituciones ni una unión bancaria, por importante que nos pueda parecer. Si la Unión Europea significa algo, significa ciudadanía. Significa los derechos y libertades de quinientos millones de personas. Significa la igualdad ante la ley y el fin de la discriminación. Significa formar parte del mayor espacio democrático del mundo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto es lo que convierte a Europa en un ejemplo para todos los países. Un espacio político y moral que ofrece una alternativa a modelos autoritarios pujantes en lo económico, como el chino, o amenazantes en lo militar, como el ruso. Por eso, es para mí un orgullo muy especial ser ponente de este informe, del que me gustaría destacar algunos puntos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pedimos desbloquear las negociaciones para la Directiva europea de lucha contra la discriminación, que lleva una década guardada en el cajón. Y pedimos para ello la participación decidida, sobre todo de los Estados miembros. No puede quedar un solo resquicio de discriminación, por el motivo que sea, en el terreno de la Unión. No puede haber una auténtica ciudadanía sin seguridad. Por eso, el informe pide una agenda europea de seguridad contra cualquier amenaza terrorista presente o futura, que incluya la armonización de acciones en los Estados miembros y que debe pasar, en mi opinión, por unos servicios de inteligencia europeos. Contra peligros globales, soluciones europeas.</p>
      <p sl="en">La prevención, detección y desactivación de la radicalización es también un elemento de seguridad esencial. Necesitamos dotarnos de programas y recursos para hacer frente a los desafíos de nuestras sociedades abiertas y multiculturales. Europa fracasa cada vez que un joven europeo se pasa al bando de los que quieren destruirla. La ciudadanía tiene una relación estrecha con la verdad. Si no conocemos los hechos, nuestros derechos estarán en peligro. Europa debe dotarse de las herramientas para luchar contra la propaganda y las noticias falsas, que buscan socavar la democracia y que, en demasiadas ocasiones, llegan a nosotros bajo el patrocinio de regímenes autoritarios.</p>
      <p sl="en">La igualdad de género es otro de los campos en los que nos jugamos el verdadero significado de la ciudadanía. Es hora de concluir la adhesión al Convenio de Estambul y de promulgar una Directiva contra la violencia de género. Es hora de ayudar, en resumen, a derribar el muro de silencio que protege a los que acosan a las mujeres y abusan de ellas. Muchos países de la Unión Europea han estado entre los primeros en reconocer los derechos del colectivo LGTBI, pero la ciudadanía no puede trocearse, de modo que debemos asegurar que tales derechos se respetan por igual en cualquier país de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="en">A día de hoy, muchos europeos con distintas formas de discapacidad tienen imposible o muy difícil ejercer su derecho al voto. Dado que sin sufragio no hay ciudadanía, es urgente eliminar los obstáculos de forma inmediata. También las trabas burocráticas y el exceso de papeleo y de instancias que se convierten en un obstáculo a los derechos de los europeos. Proponemos que las oficinas de la Unión en los países miembros se conviertan en ventanillas únicas que faciliten el acceso a la información y a los servicios de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y hablando de ciudadanía, es inevitable hacer una mención al brexit. Por primera vez, un Estado miembro dejará de serlo si no se corrige el rumbo. Y quiero recordar, como hago siempre, que el artículo 50 es reversible. Tal vez no hemos hecho lo suficiente hasta ahora para explicar lo que significa dejar la Unión Europea en términos de derechos, en términos de ciudadanía. Nadie ganará con la salida del Reino Unido, pero los británicos perderán unos derechos que —estoy segura— terminarán echando de menos.</p>
      <p sl="en">En definitiva, cuando celebramos los 25 años del Tratado de Maastricht, cuando celebramos los 25 años en los que por primera vez dimos carta de naturaleza a la ciudadanía europea, quiero darles las gracias a todos los ponentes alternativos, a todos los equipos que nos han ayudado a hacer este informe de consenso, trabajado en colaboración con la Comisión, que espero que sea una herramienta muy potente para que este tercer informe sobre la ciudadanía sea lo que necesitamos tener en nuestra mano para hacerlo efectivo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur for her work in this vital area of European construction. Indeed behind the immense symbolic value of common citizenship binding people into one European community, there is a complex legal and political foundation. ‘EU citizens’ covers many areas of immense importance, starting from the much cherished freedom of movement, via democratic participation in local and EU governance, to protection outside EU borders, to name only a few.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nothing highlights better, the value of these achievements and the problems painfully exposed by the Brexit process for the lives of millions of citizens facing great uncertainty and anxiety regarding their future. But EU citizenship is far from being a finished project. If I were to point out one single aspect that is conspicuously missing today from this endeavour, it would be the effective protection of EU values in the case of autochthonous minorities. EU minority citizens who are still subject to discriminatory practices today rightly feel that this gap needs to be addressed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Violeta Bulc" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, EU citizenship lies at the core of the European Union. It is a powerful sign that we, as Europeans, belong to a union of common values. Moreover, EU citizenship brings with it a range of rights, including the much cherished right of free movement and rights of democratic participation. All EU citizens can stand and vote in both local and European Parliament elections in their state of residence, and all citizens have the right to participate in a European …</p>
      <a text="(The speaker was interrupted by the President following interpretation problems.)"/>
      <p sl="en">In addition, every citizen of the Union has the right to petition the European Parliament, and I use this opportunity to recognise the work undertaken by the Parliament’s Committee on Petitions to help our citizens protect and enforce their EU rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU citizenship is also inextricably linked to equality. EU citizens have the right to be treated equally regardless of their nationality. Our citizens are protected by the Union’s legislation and actions against discrimination based on sex, racial or ethnic group, religion or belief, disability, age or sexual orientation. The regular EU Citizenship Report is a demonstration of the Union’s continuing commitment and outreach to its citizens. It gives us the opportunity to reflect together on what the EU can do better to improve and strengthen the rights of EU citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">I thank Parliament for the structured input it gave to the Commission for this year’s report. I would also like to thank the rapporteur, Beatriz Becerra Basterrechea, for her tireless work in steering Parliament’s reaction to the Commission’s report to its conclusion.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission Citizenship Report 2017 priorities include the promotion to the status of EU rights and values of: participation in democratic life, simplification of the daily lives of our citizens and strengthening security. In relation to each priority, the Commission has set out in the report its ongoing and future activities for delivering.</p>
      <p sl="en">My short intervention does not allow me to do justice to all the activities, but let me say a few words on two particular areas of action. Firstly, as regards both promoting EU citizenship rights and enhancing participation in the democratic life of the Union, our research showed that on average only 54% of EU citizens were aware of their right to vote and stand in municipal elections in their country of residence. We are committed to improving this figure by raising awareness on electoral rights and developing best practices to make it easier for EU citizens to vote in both local and European elections.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, on free movement, rights and security, the Commission’s 2018 work programme will include two specific initiatives to enhance EU citizens’ rights to consular protection when traveling outside of the EU. We are currently looking at improving the security features of the EU common format emergency travel documents. The aim is to improve the security of EU documents used to cross our common external borders. At the same time, we will be raising awareness of our EU citizens’ right to consular protection by the authorities of any Member State.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are looking at options to improve the security of EU citizens’ national identity cards and residence documents. The aim is to improve the security features of such documents to address security gaps and document fraud, and to help remedy practical obstacles faced by EU citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, promoting, protecting and strengthening EU citizenship is a challenge for us all. Raising awareness and encouraging our citizens to use their rights is part of the challenge, but we also need to remove obstacles to improve the operation of such rights and to ensure effective enforcement. I count on you to make this happen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139-0000" speaker_id="124883" name="Krystyna Łybacka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autorka projektu opinii Komisji Kultury i Edukacji. – Panie Przewodniczący! Obywatelstwo europejskie opiera się na dwóch filarach. Pierwszym z nich jest znajomość praw obywateli Unii Europejskiej, drugim natomiast jest jednolite przestrzeganie tych praw wobec każdego obywatela. W obu tych aspektach ogromną rolę odgrywa edukacja oraz kultura i sztuka. To dzięki edukacji właśnie na każdym poziomie nauczania możemy szerzyć wiedzę o wspólnych wartościach europejskich, jak również o prawach przysługujących obywatelom Unii. Ale żeby to szerzenie wiedzy było właściwe, konieczne jest merytoryczne wsparcie nauczycieli i osób nauczających, tak aby oni mogli włączać w proces nauczania informacje o prawach obywatelskich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dzięki kulturze i sztuce możemy umacniać poczucie europejskiej przynależności i pobudzać dialog międzykulturowy, co ma ogromne znaczenie w kontekście integracji migrantów. Takie programy jak Erasmus+, jak Kreatywna Europa, jak Europa dla Obywateli, to są programy, które właśnie realizują te cele. Ale aby były realizowane poprawnie, muszą być dostępne dla każdego, w tym także dla osób niepełnosprawnych i osób ze środowisk defaworyzowanych, oraz adekwatnie finansowane. Zwracam się także do Komisji, aby opracowała przejrzyste i wspólne kryteria oceny działania europejskich programów promujących obywatelstwo europejskie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="125050" name="Ángela Vallina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Derechos de la Mujer e Igualdad de Género. – Señor presidente. Desde la Comisión de Derechos de la Mujer e Igualdad de Género creemos firmemente que los Estados miembros y las instituciones de la Unión Europea y, en especial, la Comisión tienen la obligación de aplicar medidas integrales contra la discriminación de las mujeres. Y así hemos propuesto múltiples acciones. Se debe adoptar ya una Directiva contra la discriminación. Todos los Estados deberían ratificar el Convenio de Estambul, y se debe luchar contra la discriminación del colectivo LGTBI, sobre todo contra el acoso y la intimidación en las redes.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión debe hacer caso a nuestra demanda de adopción de políticas de género en todo el marco de las políticas de la Unión. Se deben potenciar programas de educación cívica de calidad contra los prejuicios, la discriminación, los estereotipos, etc. y, sobre todo, también, trabajar en campañas para romper los estereotipos de género.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señoras y señores de la Comisión, les reitero estas demandas. Recuerden que sin voluntad, sin financiación y sin una administración fuerte no existen ni Estado de Derecho ni Estado del bienestar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="124930" name="Pál Csáky" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a PPE képviselőcsoport nevében. – Elnök Úr! Kedves Becerra Basterrechea Asszony, tisztelt Kollégák! Jó érzés egy ilyen pozitív témáról beszélni az év utolsó ülésén. A közös munka a Petíciós Bizottságon belül meghozta eredményét: egy olyan jelentést tudunk letenni az asztalra, amely új elemekkel gazdagítja, és erősíti az uniós polgárság intézményét. Fontosnak tartom, hogy felhívjuk az Európai Bizottság figyelmét az uniós polgársághoz tartozó jogok és kötelezettségek következetes módon való megismertetésére az uniós polgárokkal, különösen a fiatalokkal, és fontosnak tartom azt is, hogy az EU szerepéről is folyjon mély tájékoztatás, nemcsak európai uniós szinten, hanem tagállami szinten is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kiemelném az őshonos, vagyis a történelmi kisebbségek helyzetét is, akikkel néhány bekezdés erejéig szintén foglalkozik a jelentés. Megjegyzem, hogy az Európai Unió polgárai közül minden tizediknek van történelmi kisebbségekhez tartozó kötődése, jómagam is egy ilyen kisebbséghez tartozom. Néha ezek az emberek, ezek az EU-s polgárok nyílt, vagy rejtett módon is diszkriminációt szenvednek el, mindannyiunknak sok munkánk van még az ügyben, hogy ezt a kérdést is rendezzük.</p>
      <p sl="en">És végezetül a Brexit ügyében szeretnék még egy mondatot elmondani: nagyon sok petíciót kapott a Petíciós Bizottság, foglalkoztunk a kérdéssel, és figyelemmel kísérjük majd a Brexit tárgyalásokat is. Az Európai Néppárt támogatja ezt a dokumentumot. Köszönöm, Elnök Úr!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="124692" name="Δημήτρης Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας S&amp;D. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η τρίτη έκθεση της Επιτροπής για την ευρωπαϊκή ιθαγένεια συμπίπτει με την 25η επέτειο που κατατέθηκε η ιδέα για την κατοχύρωσή της. Οι κάθε είδους διακρίσεις αποτελούν κύρια ζητήματα στις αναφορές των πολιτών: διακρίσεις λόγω φύλλου, εθνικότητας, σεξουαλικού προσανατολισμού, γλώσσας, εθνοτικής καταγωγής. Σημαντικά προβλήματα αντιμετωπίζουν τα άτομα με αναπηρία στην καθημερινή τους ζωή, στον τόπο εργασίας, στην πρόσβαση σε ιατρική περίθαλψη, στην εκπαίδευση, στην ευρωπαϊκή κάρτα αναπηρίας και σε θέματα που άπτονται της προσπάθειας εφαρμογής της συνθήκης του Μαρρακές στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η απαίτηση των πολιτών της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης για άσκηση των εκλογικών δικαιωμάτων τους ακόμη και όταν διαμένουν σε άλλο ευρωπαϊκό κράτος μέλος αποτελεί συχνό αντικείμενο αναφορών, γι’ αυτό θα πρέπει να εξασφαλίσουμε σε κάθε πολίτη το δικαίωμα να ψηφίζει σε όποιο κράτος της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης διαμένει.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ελεύθερη διακίνηση αποτελεί μια από τις ισχυρές κατακτήσεις, καθώς παρέχει στους πολίτες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης το δικαίωμα να ταξιδέψουν, να σπουδάσουν, να κάνουν επιχειρήσεις, να εργαστούν και να ζήσουν αρμονικά σε άλλες τις χώρες της. Τα τελευταία έτη όμως έχει καταγραφεί αυξανόμενος αριθμός αναφορών που σχετίζονται με τα προβλήματα που αντιμετωπίζουν οι πολίτες στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση σε σχέση με τα δικαιώματά τους για ελεύθερη διακίνηση.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πρέπει να προχωρήσουμε σε άμεση εξεύρεση λύσεων χωρίς άλλες καθυστερήσεις, γιατί δεν πρόκειται μόνο για μια απλή άσκηση δικαιωμάτων των πολιτών που διασφαλίζονται στις Συνθήκες και στον Χάρτη των Θεμελιωδών Δικαιωμάτων της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, αλλά συνδέονται άμεσα με την ίδια την εικόνα της και την αποδοχή από τους πολίτες, καθώς αγγίζουν τον πυρήνα των ενδιαφερόντων τους, αφορούν την καθημερινότητα τους.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ως Ομάδα των Σοσιαλιστών και Δημοκρατών, λαμβάνοντας σοβαρά υπόψη τα πιο πάνω ζητήματα που αφορούν κάθε ευρωπαίο πολίτη, συμβάλαμε στο να έχουμε μια αποτελεσματική και λειτουργική έκθεση, όπως αυτή διαμορφώθηκε. Με αυτό τον τρόπο αποκαθίσταται η εμπιστοσύνη στο ευρωπαϊκό εγχείρημα, ένα αίσθημα που τα τελευταία χρόνια δυστυχώς μειώνεται ραγδαία.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας ECR. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η ευρωπαϊκή ιθαγένεια αποτελεί πηγή ειδικών δικαιωμάτων όπως το δικαίωμα αναφοράς στο Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο ή το δικαίωμα καταγγελίας στον Ευρωπαίο Διαμεσολαβητή. Ταυτόχρονα, τα δικαιώματα των πολιτών της Ένωσης προστατεύονται από τον Χάρτη Θεμελιωδών Δικαιωμάτων της ΕΕ. Όμως η λιτότητα, η βίαιη δημοσιονομική προσαρμογή, η μείωση μισθών και συντάξεων, η διάλυση του κοινωνικού κράτους έχουν οδηγήσει στη μείωση και στην παραβίαση βασικών δικαιωμάτων των πολιτών της Ένωσης τα οποία υποτίθεται ότι προστατεύονται από τον Χάρτη.</p>
      <p sl="en">Έχουμε παραβίαση του δικαιώματος στην αξιοπρεπή διαβίωση, του δικαιώματος στην υγεία, του δικαιώματος στην περιουσία, και αυτό συμβαίνει με αποφάσεις της Τρόικας, του Εurogroup και της Ευρωπαϊκής Κεντρικής Τράπεζας, τριών οργάνων τα οποία λειτουργούν με αδιαφάνεια, τα οποία δεν έχουν εκλεγεί. Επομένως, εκεί πρέπει να εστιάσουμε την προσοχή μας, για να σταματήσει αυτή η παραβίαση των δικαιωμάτων των ίδιων των πολιτών της Ένωσης από όργανα τα οποία λειτουργούν αντιδημοκρατικά και δεν έχουν εκλεγεί.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-0000" speaker_id="125092" name="Κωνσταντίνα Κούνεβα" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. –Κύριε Πρόεδρε, γεννήθηκα και μεγάλωσα στη Βουλγαρία, στα σύνορα με τη Ρουμανία. Εργάστηκα στην Ελλάδα. Στο Ευρωκοινοβούλιο με εξέλεξε η Ελλάδα. Για χρόνια έζησα στη Γαλλία, όπου μεταφέροντας τα ασφαλιστικά μου δικαιώματα με το ευρωπαϊκό έγγραφο S1, έκανα τις αναγκαίες θεραπείες.</p>
      <p sl="en">Είμαι ένα ζωντανό παράδειγμα ευρωπαϊκής ιθαγένειας, πόσοι όμως αξιοποιούν τα πλεονεκτήματα της ιθαγένειας; Λίγοι είναι. Υπάρχουν τεράστιες ανισότητες μεταξύ των χωρών στη γνώση και στην εφαρμογή των δικαιωμάτων της κοινής ιθαγένειας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Το Συμβούλιο, αντί να βοηθά, εμποδίζει. Για παράδειγμα, παγώνοντας την οδηγία για την άρση των διακρίσεων, τρέφει τη δυσπιστία των πολιτών στη Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Ας μην απορούμε, λοιπόν, που μόλις το 42% των Ευρωπαίων ψήφισε στις ευρωεκλογές του 2014.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-145-0000" speaker_id="4531" name="Jean Lambert" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I apologise that our shadow in the Committee on Petitions has not yet been able to arrive here this evening. I wanted to start by saying that we’ve heard a lot of expressions in the Committee on Petitions and elsewhere by people affected by the Brexit experience about how much they value their European citizenship and how its potential loss has really affected their sense of identity as European citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think that is something which is very powerful. We need to look at how we can build on that for those who will be able to enjoy that in future. What we’re certainly learning from this experience – and indeed we see this in the report – is the importance of clear information to citizens, the right to good administration, so that the rights that they have are developed. But we do need, and we thoroughly agree with the report here, on the need to extend the work on anti—discrimination. European citizenship is an unfinished task at the moment, so we need to strengthen the anti—discrimination legislation, strengthen people’s access to the law to defend their rights and indeed to strengthen the tools that citizens have.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think we should also look at the fact how shameful it is that even within the European Union now we have people who’ve lived here for years, whose family have lived here for years and yet are still stateless.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need to pay attention to the gaps that we see opening between Member States when people move – the loss of voting rights, the loss of nationality and potentials, and how that will affect children – the way in which different states have a different attitudes towards dual nationality and indeed different attitudes to the treatment of the right to family life, because we’re talking here about citizens, not just workers.</p>
      <p sl="en">We still have a lot of work to do to complete European citizenship.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-0000" speaker_id="124779" name="Eleonora Evi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, cosa significa essere cittadini europei? Significa godere di diritti e di garanzie che si aggiungono ai diritti e ai doveri che derivano da ogni cittadinanza nazionale, ma se non si vuole rimanere nell'ambito della pura retorica, la cittadinanza europea deve concretizzarsi in maggiori diritti e migliori condizioni di vita materiali per i cittadini europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Purtroppo, la relazione del 2017 sulla cittadinanza che la Commissione europea ha presentato è un documento lacunoso e per nulla ambizioso. Il Parlamento ha dovuto lavorare molto per colmare i vuoti lasciati dalla Commissione, e ringrazio la relatrice per il lavoro che ha svolto. Purtroppo però è riuscito soltanto in modo parziale, nonostante vengano ribaditi alcuni concetti importanti, tra cui ad esempio garantire il pieno godimento di tutti i diritti umani, economici, sociali e culturali, la piena occupazione e la più alta protezione sociale, l'adozione di una governance democratica che consenta ai cittadini di partecipare attivamente ed efficacemente ai processi decisionali, e molto altro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parte di questo Parlamento continua a non voler guardare in faccia la realtà: la richiesta del gruppo PPE di cancellare ogni riferimento alle politiche di austerità è paradossale. Ormai è sotto gli occhi di tutti come le politiche di austerità abbiano causato l'inasprimento delle diseguaglianze sociali e dell'aumento della povertà, e certo non hanno contribuito al pieno godimento dei diritti garantiti dalla cittadinanza europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chiudo dicendo che con questa relazione, se non vogliamo ribadire l'ovvio, non possiamo permetterci di indebolirla ulteriormente.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, officiellement, la citoyenneté européenne aurait dû s’exercer dans un cadre approprié que l’Union appelle un espace européen de prospérité. Le moins que l’on puisse dire, c’est que c’est raté! Les politiques européennes d’austérité ont produit des dizaines de millions de pauvres en Europe. Ce sont les sacrifiés de l’ultralibéralisme, pour lesquels la citoyenneté européenne s’exprime par des droits épouvantables, qui sont la marque de leur désespoir: droit au déclassement social pour tous ceux qui ont perdu leur travail ou qui n’en ont jamais trouvé, droit des Grecs d’aller à la soupe populaire et même droit des agriculteurs français, poussés à bout par une politique agricole commune devenue folle, de se suicider.</p>
      <p sl="en">Face à cet échec, l’Union nous propose trois remèdes dérisoires. Le premier consiste à tenter de redynamiser le droit de pétition. Vaine promesse, quand on sait que la Commission européenne enterre illégalement les pétitions qui lui déplaisent, à commencer par celles qui protestaient contre le TAFTA. Par contre, elle met en avant celles qui lui plaisent, comme, par exemple, les pétitions qui ont protesté contre le Brexit. Bafoué ou instrumentalisé, selon les cas, le droit de pétition n’est qu’un alibi démocratique destiné à camoufler la nature oligarchique de l’Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le deuxième remède est tout aussi hypocrite, chaudement recommandé par la majorité du Parlement européen. Il consiste – je cite le paragraphe 31 de sa proposition de résolution – à définir clairement une politique européenne de lutte contre la propagande anti-européenne, admirable antiphrase par laquelle l’Union accuse les souverainistes de propagande alors que c’est elle qui la pratique massivement et avec notre argent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais il y a encore pire! Je veux parler du troisième remède, qui consiste à remplacer progressivement, pour les élections européennes, les listes nationales par des listes européennes. L’objectif est d’arracher les citoyens à leur nation pour parfaire leur transformation en consommateurs dociles, à la merci des multinationales et des lobbies. Mais les peuples se révolteront avant que vous réussissiez à l’atteindre, car les nations sont toujours vivantes et leur énergie vitale vous emportera.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-0000" speaker_id="124832" name="Udo Voigt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, werte Kollegen! Wenn hier schon von einer Stärkung der Bürgerrechte in der Union des demokratischen Wandels die Rede ist, dann bitte ich Sie dringend, aus gegebenem Anlass Ihren Blick auf die Bundesrepublik zu richten. Das, was sich in diesen Tagen in meinem Land vollzieht, ist eine Farce und schlägt jeder Vorstellung einer freien demokratischen Gesellschaft geradezu ins Gesicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wie viele von Ihnen vermutlich nicht wissen, wurde im Mai dieses Jahres nach sage und schreibe fünf Jahren ein Prozess vor dem Landgericht in Koblenz wegen überlanger Verfahrensdauer eingestellt – nach unglaublichen 337 Verhandlungstagen. Den meisten von Ihnen dürfte auch nicht bekannt sein, dass dieser Mammutprozess der bislang größte Prozess in der deutschen Geschichte ist. Die Anklageschrift umfasst fast 1 000 Seiten. Und weil die meisten Angeklagten zu Prozessbeginn in Untersuchungshaft saßen, reichten die Zellen im Koblenzer Gerichtsgebäude nicht mehr aus. Ein halbes Dutzend Angeklagte wurde während der Prozesstage in Transportfahrzeuge gesperrt, die außerhalb des Gerichtes im Innenhof waren, und die Innenmaße dort betrugen 80 mal 80 Zentimeter. Das ist zu niedrig, um auch nur aufrecht stehen zu können. Das sind Begleitumstände, wie man sie eher in Nordkorea und in Pakistan als in einem EU-Land wie der Bundesrepublik erwarten dürfte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-0000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Dieser Bericht zur europäischen Bürgerschaft ist ein wichtiger Bericht, der die Rechte der EU-Bürger promoten und stärken soll, und er gilt für alle EU-Bürger gleichermaßen. Neben den Stärken werden in diesem Bericht auch noch Schwachstellen bei der Umsetzung der europäischen Bürgerrechte in der EU aufgezeigt, die uns auch oft durch Petitionen verdeutlicht werden. Und ich muss sagen, für mich ist es außerordentlich wichtig, dass sich Bürgerinnen und Bürger an den Petitionsausschuss wenden. Den Kollegen von der ENF muss ich hier verbessern: Der Petitionsausschuss ist der Kommission weder unterstellt noch rechenschaftspflichtig. Wir entscheiden, wie wir mit den Petitionen im Europäischen Parlament umgehen, und da kann uns auch keiner reinreden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte mich bei dieser Gelegenheit bei unserer Berichterstatterin, Frau Becerra Basterrechea, für die gute und enge Zusammenarbeit in unserer Fraktion bedanken und möchte noch mal bedauern, dass einige Fraktionen diesen Bericht auch nutzen wollten, um ihre eigene politische Agenda durchzubringen, also Dinge reinzuformulieren, die vielleicht politisch interessant sind, aber mit der Unionsbürgerschaft nichts zu tun haben, zum Beispiel bedingungsloses Grundeinkommen, gleiche Rechte für Immigranten und andere Drittstaatsangehörige wie für EU-Bürger. Das kann man politisch diskutieren, gehört aber in diesen Bericht über die Unionsbürgerschaft nicht hinein, und es konnten schon die wichtigsten kritischen Punkte im Petitionsausschuss herausgestimmt werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich gehe fest davon aus, dass wir im Parlament bei der Abstimmung ein ähnlich gutes Ergebnis erreichen und meine Fraktion diesem Bericht dann auch zustimmen kann. Und natürlich: Wir sind hier auf einem Weg, und wir werden hier weitermachen müssen. Wichtig ist, dass wir weiterkommen in Zusammenarbeit mit dem Parlament, mit der Kommission und dem Rat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-0000" speaker_id="103845" name="Virginie Rozière" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, je voudrais d’abord remercier l’équipe à l’initiative de ce rapport, notre rapporteur fictif, M. Papadakis, et, au-delà des remerciements d’usage, remercier sincèrement la rapporteure, Mme Becerra Basterrechea, qui a su organiser ses travaux dans une attitude extrêmement ouverte et constructive: qu’elle en soit ici vraiment remerciée.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est d’autant plus regrettable de voir qu’aujourd’hui un groupe – le PPE – essaie de remettre en question les équilibres qui ont été obtenus en commission des pétitions. C’est pour cela que nous tiendrons bon et refuserons de soutenir des amendements déposés par le PPE, parce que, pour nous, il est absolument essentiel d’affirmer et de reconnaître l’impact négatif des politiques d’austérité sur l’effectivité des droits pour les citoyens.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous ne reviendrons pas sur l’importance de protéger les minorités et sur les actions qui sont aujourd’hui nécessaires pour combattre l’homophobie et pour assurer les droits transfrontaliers des familles LGBT. Nous ne reviendrons pas non plus sur notre demande que le Conseil adopte enfin la directive contre les discriminations. Le délai inconcevable depuis lequel ce texte est bloqué par le Conseil – bientôt dix ans – est absolument inacceptable. C’est un devoir de démocratie pour nos concitoyens de débloquer ce texte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, pour conclure, nous allons soutenir ce rapport, qui affirme clairement que, pour que la citoyenneté européenne existe, ce sont les droits des citoyens qui doivent être assurés, les droits votés par ce Parlement. En cela, nous demandons à la Commission d’être encore plus ferme dans son rôle de gardienne des traités et de garante de la bonne application du droit de l’Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-0000" speaker_id="23791" name="Kazimierz Michał Ujazdowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">W tej dyskusji mieszają się rzeczy dotyczące bezpośrednio obywatelstwa Unii Europejskiej z problemami, które są bardzo luźno związane z tym zagadnieniem, jak spór o model polityki gospodarczej czy nacisk, żeby dyrektywa antydyskryminacyjna została przyjęta, chociaż ona budzi zastrzeżenia właśnie z punktu widzenia praw jednostki w tych krajach, w których budzi zastrzeżenia. Jestem za tym, żeby się skoncentrować na tym, co dotyczy istoty sprawy – na dobrym stosowaniu praw obywatelskich, praw wyborczych, na odblokowaniu europejskiej inicjatywy obywatelskiej, na swobodnym stosowaniu petycji, na warunkach praw obywatelskich, na transparentności i na tym, o czym mówiła jedna z koleżanek – na prawie obywateli do dobrej administracji. I wreszcie na trzecim bardzo istotnym zagadnieniu: na podglebiu praw obywatelskich, jakim jest edukacja i kultura. Z tym wiąże się postulat rozwoju programów kulturalnych i programów edukacyjnych Unii Europejskiej. Skupmy się na tym, gdyż będzie to miało więcej sensu i przyniesie więcej pożytku.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-0000" speaker_id="185974" name="Jordi Solé" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, quisiera mencionar lo que me parece una contradicción en este informe. El título del tercer informe sobre ciudadanía europea, el cual nos ocupa, nos habla acertadamente de una unión de cambio democrático, porque, efectivamente, la democracia puede y debe propiciar cambios respaldados por mayorías legítimas y mandatos democráticos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, el considerando G nos habla de las fronteras de los Estados miembros como algo inalterable, como si estuvieran grabadas en piedra. Y de forma absolutamente falsa afirma que una eventual alteración de fronteras iría en contra de los valores y derechos fundamentales de la Unión.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que es una lástima que un informe sobre derechos de ciudadanía y cambio democrático no reconozca que en el siglo XXI el ejercicio de la democracia y de los derechos democráticos puede permitir, si así lo desea una mayoría, plantear cambios dentro de la Unión en relación con la existencia de los límites de los países realmente existentes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="124940" name="Patrick O'Flynn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the notion of EU citizenship is based on a flawed rule that orders every EU country immediately to accord all the benefits and rights it gives to its own citizens to anyone from 27 other countries. This ignores and overrides the widely—held view that national governments have higher obligations to their own citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the UK, our welfare state is funded by National Insurance and includes our National Health Service. These names symbolise the kinship British people feel towards each other and grew out of our shared national effort of 1939 to 1945. Many British people do not support full access instantly for foreign nationals to services like the NHS, strongly believing a new arrival should pay into the pot for a while first. This report says it seeks to restore citizens’ confidence in the EU. You won’t do that by trampling over the primacy of nations, and Brexit will ensure the UK will not be trampled over in any case.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="125072" name="Ελευθέριος Συναδινός" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η έκθεση αρνείται την πραγματικότητα και προτείνει την αλλαγή της ισχύουσας νομικής τάξης επί θεμάτων τα οποία de jure είναι εθνικής αρμοδιότητας. Μερικά εξ αυτών αποτελούν φαιδρότητες, όπως οι παρεμβάσεις στο οικογενειακό δίκαιο, η θέσπιση ευρωπαϊκού δελτίου ταυτότητας και η εμφανέστατη προσπάθεια νομιμοποίησης μιας εμπροσθοβαρούς ευρωπαϊκής ιθαγένειας έναντι της εθνικής.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι υπέρμαχοι της ομοσπονδοποίησης δεν αρέσκονται στην ειλικρίνεια δίχως περιστροφές, δηλώνοντας πως στόχος είναι η κατάλυση των εθνικών κρατών και η δημιουργία των Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών της Ευρώπης. Αντιθέτως, είναι δεδηλωμένη η απόρριψη των πολιτών, οι οποίοι γίνονται μάρτυρες μιας προσπάθειας βίαιης παγκοσμιοποίησης φυλετικής, θρησκευτικής, οικονομικής και πολιτισμικής.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η λεγόμενη ευρωπαϊκή ιθαγένεια αφορά στην απόδοση ορισμένων δικαιωμάτων και είναι παράγωγο αποτέλεσμα της ιθαγένειας κράτους μέλους, η οποία εκφράζει τη νομική δέσμευσης της σχέσης κράτους-πολίτη και συνδέει το άτομο με το έθνος στο οποίο ανήκει και με το οποίο μοιράζεται κοινές αξίες και πολιτισμό, εμπίπτει δε στην αποκλειστική δικαιοδοσία των κρατών μελών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Europeans are more than ever aware of their status as EU citizens, and the proportion of Europeans wanting to know more about their rights continue to increase. It is a valuable status which gives citizens more freedoms, such as free movement, consular protection and the right to vote and stand as candidates in their municipal and European Parliament elections, wherever they live in the European Union. Citizens need to be aware of their rights in order to benefit from them. While some rights are well known and implemented effectively, gaps and misunderstandings remain. The effectiveness of EU citizenship rights depends on this awareness amongst the citizens, Member States’ governments and local and regional authorities. It is very important to deliver concrete, tangible solutions for European citizens to continue living and enjoying an area of longstanding peace, security and prosperity, of shared values, principles of fundamental rights and freedoms. We need to empower the citizens so they know more about what they can do, so they can use their rights more easily and more effectively.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-0000" speaker_id="124953" name="Jude Kirton-Darling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this report demonstrates the importance of EU citizenship. Tragically, Brexit potentially represents the first instance of people losing these valuable rights. Three million citizens from elsewhere in the EU live in the UK and 1.5 million UK citizens live in the rest of the EU. These people have built their lives in good faith that their rights would not be infringed or jeopardised, and we in this House have a moral responsibility. Neither EU nationals in the UK nor UK nationals abroad for more than 15 years were able to vote on the decision which affected their lives the most acutely. As the Brexit negotiations reach a critical juncture, a strong signal must be sent to those on both sides of the negotiating table that we take citizens’ rights seriously. We will not accept a reduction in rights and we refuse to allow people’s lives to be used as bargaining chips for any longer.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-0000" speaker_id="124815" name="Arne Gericke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Werter Herr Präsident, werte Frau Kommissarin! Ich habe heute in dieser Debatte über die Unionsbürgerschaft 2017 einige technische und juristische Reden gehört. Kollegen, die Details in Einzelproblemen benennen. Aber es geht hier nicht zentral um Randgruppen, ohne dass sie vergessen werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erlauben Sie mir gerade hier in Straßburg, der parlamentarischen Bürgerhauptstadt Europas, einen anderen Blickwinkel, den Blickwinkel derer, über die wir gerade reden, Bürgerinnen und Bürger der Europäischen Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und ich weiß: Wir alle hier haben unsere Wahlkreise, ja unsere Heimatregionen. Wir fahren Donnerstag wieder zurück, und wer sein Mandat ernst nimmt wie ich, wird zurück in der Heimat auf Menschen treffen, sich mit dem Bürger vor Ort unterhalten. Genau darüber sollten wir heute Abend diskutieren. Nicht, wie wir die Unionsbürgerschaft interpretieren. Nein, es geht darum wie unsere Nachbarn – die Fischverkäuferin ums Eck, der Beamte im Rathaus, die Bäuerin und der Jugendliche gegebenenfalls ihre Unionsbürgerschaft erleben. Wie sie Europa für sich finden und ob sie ganz persönlich sagen können: Ja, das ist mein Europa. Ein Europa, das liefert. Ein Europa, das mich betrifft und mich vertritt. Kurzum: ein Europa der Bürger und Regionen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Solch ein Grundsatz als Leitfaden unseres Handelns ist Grundlage einer vermittelbaren, einer spürbaren Unionsbürgerschaft. Eine, die einem Identität und Heimat bietet. Eine, die man gerne hat. Eine, auf die man stolz ist. Das wünsche ich mir, dafür setze ich mich weiter ein.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-0000" speaker_id="96933" name="Milan Zver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ideja evropskega državljanstva ima lepo zgodovino, pred 25. leti pa je v okviru Maastrichtske pogodbe postala pravnopolitični koncept in zaživela novo življenje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poročilo pred nami naslavlja nekatere prave izzive, od prostega gibanja, boja proti diskriminaciji vseh vrst, do demokratične participacije na evropski ravni. Končni cilj politik Evropske unije o državljanstvu je, da se vsi državljani Evropske unije počutijo enako doma, kjer koli v Uniji bodo. Do uresničitve tega cilja pa bo še dolga pot.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naj še omenim eno asimetrijo v poročilu, izjemno veliko pozornosti namenja pravicam LGBT iz skupine, ne omenja pa na primer skupine, ki si že desetletja prizadeva za popravo svojih krivic. Govorim o slovenskih razlaščencih, ki niso dovolj slišani ne v domačih ne na evropskih sodnih inštancah. Kljub temu lahko s ponosom poudarimo, da se ena od ključnih pravic evropskega državljanstva vse bolj uveljavlja. To, da je mobilnost, zlasti med mladimi, vse večja, je zasluga tudi evropskih programov, zlasti Erasmus+.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naj zaključim, Evropska unija mora biti utemeljena na dveh temeljih – je skupnost državljanov in je skupnost njihovih držav. Tisti, ki tega dejstva ne sprejemajo, ne mislijo in delajo evropsko.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-0000" speaker_id="125041" name="Soledad Cabezón Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. La ciudadanía europea es uno de los mayores logros de la Unión Europea. El equipararnos en derechos y en obligaciones ha generado el necesario sentimiento de pertenencia, y el Parlamento Europeo es la voz democrática de la ciudadanía. Pero esta democracia no puede ser real si no puede participar toda la ciudadanía, y por eso quiero aprovechar la oportunidad y centrarme en las personas con discapacidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y es que, mientras la Comisión ponía como lema para el Día Internacional de las Personas con Discapacidad «Yo también soy europeo», lo cierto es que cientos de miles de personas en Europa que presentan problemas de discapacidad no pueden ejercer el derecho al voto en las elecciones, tanto nacionales como al Parlamento Europeo, incumpliéndose los artículos 12 y 19 de la Convención de las Naciones Unidas sobre los derechos de las personas con discapacidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello, aprovecho la ocasión para mejorar este concepto de ciudadanía europea y hacer que cumplamos la obligación establecida por la Comisión de que en las próximas elecciones del año 2019 participen toda la ciudadanía y, en concreto, las personas con discapacidad.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani komisárka, niekedy je ťažké obhajovať Európu pred občanmi, keď jej vlastný Parlament takýmito správami potvrdzuje ich obavy. Karta základných práv jasne hovorí, že právo využívať lekársku starostlivosť je garantované za podmienok ustanovených vnútroštátnymi právnymi predpismi. Táto správa však v paragrafe 12 vyzýva Komisiu, aby uľahčila plný prístup k službám sexuálnej a reprodukčnej zdravotnej starostlivosti vo všetkých členských štátoch. Odkazuje občanom, že Európsky parlament nerešpektuje ich zákony, chartu ani zmluvy. Za škodlivé považujem aj vytvorenie nadnárodných volebných zoznamov. Takéto zoznamy len prehĺbia nedôveru voči Európe. Občania zistia, že poslanci, ktorých majú voliť, nehovoria ich jazykom a nepoznajú ich problémy. Volebná účasť nestúpne, naopak, klesne ešte viac.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-0000" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef Weidenholzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Die Zustimmung zu Europa steigt. Aber oft können sich die Menschen nicht konkret vorstellen, was das individuell für sie bedeutet. Daher ist die Unionsbürgerschaft sehr wichtig. Sie bedeutet viel mehr, als über einen europäischen Pass zu verfügen. Die Unionsbürgerschaft ist etwas Konkretes, das mit den Wünschen und Sorgen der Menschen zu tun hat und sie auch irgendwie erfüllen sollte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aus Sicht der Sozialdemokratie ist es wichtig, den Bezug zur Grundrechtecharta herzustellen, weil die sozialen Rechte hier eine zentrale Rolle spielen. Für uns stellt sich vor allem die Freizügigkeit als ein wichtiges Element der Unionsbürgerschaft dar. Es muss besonders hier gesagt werden, dass es auch für jene Menschen gelten soll, die jetzt beim Brexit Gefahr laufen, diese Rechte zu verlieren.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-0000" speaker_id="188906" name="Francis Zammit Dimech" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Iva, dana huwa eżerċizzju importanti ħafna għaliex, kif nafu, jaħbat ukoll mal-25 anniversarju li l-kunċett taċ-ċittadinanza Ewropea kien anki rikonoxxut fit-Trattat ta' Maastricht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Għalija, norbot iċ-ċittadinanza, fost elementi oħrajn, mal-ħarsien tad-drittijiet taċ-ċittadini Ewropej u li ċ-ċittadini Ewropej jistgħu jħarsu lejn l-istituzzjonijiet Ewropej biex ikunu t-tarka ta' dawk id-drittijiet tagħhom. F'dan is-sens nagħmel referenza b'mod partikolari għall-paragrafu 31 tar-riżoluzzjoni li għandna quddiemna li titkellem dwar il-libertà tal-espressjoni. Libertà tal-espressjoni li, kif nafu, hija wkoll dritt li jinkludi d-dritt tas-soċjetà li tirċievi l-informazzjoni kollha li s-soċjetà tħoss li hi intitolata għaliha.</p>
      <p sl="en">Għalhekk, f'dan ir-rigward, dak li kien diġà msemmi f'dan il-Parlament Ewropew, il-każ, pereżempju, ta' bank f'pajjiżna, ta' bank f'Malta, il-Bank Pilatus, li għamel pressjoni straordinarja fuq midja indipendenti biex jikkontrolla l-kontenut ta' dik il-midja, huwa aġir mhux aċċettabbli.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nagħlaq bil-ħsieb li ċ-ċittadini Ewropej għandhom iħarsu lejn l-istituzzjonijiet biex verament ikunu t-tarka tagħhom, b'mod partikolari, it-tarka tad-drittijiet fundamentali tagħhom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, tato zpráva podává velmi komplexní obraz o respektování občanských práv na úrovni Evropské unie. V této zprávě je řada informací, se kterými jistě mohu souhlasit, ale také některá doporučení, která nepodporuji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bezpečnost je jedním ze základních práv občanů Evropské unie a je to právě bezpečnost, o kterou dnes občané v Evropské unii mají velkou obavu. Zpráva proto správně vyzývá Komisi i členské státy, aby zajistily právo občanů na svobodu a bezpečnost, a to zejména s ohledem na nárůst hrozeb terorismu. Tato opatření by měla být jak na úrovni lokální, tak národní i celounijní. Zpráva velmi dobře zmiňuje nedostatečnou účast žen na politickém životě a jejich zastoupení v řídících funkcích. Také vyslovuje obavy z počtu žen, které čelí chudobě a sociálnímu vyloučení, což brání naplnění jejich práv. V této souvislosti bych chtěla dodat, že je třeba bojovat s diskriminací, které čelí matky a také rodiče, když pečují o děti nebo o své blízké.</p>
      <p sl="en">Právo souvisí s informovaností. Proto také vítám to, že zpráva uvádí řadu příkladů, kde mohou občané čerpat informace, jako je Europe Direct, portál Vaše Evropa, portál</p>
      <p sl="en">e-Justice či síť Solvit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolegyně a kolegové, nepodporuji nadnárodní kandidátky pro volby do Evropského parlamentu, které by mohly vést k ochromení důvěry v politickou reprezentaci.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I deeply regret that this report took place not at a time of togetherness and idealism but at a time when the threat of the UK leaving the European Union is dominating our discussions about what it means to be a citizen of Europe today. Conducting this report through feedback from petitions has highlighted the strength of feeling in the UK about EU citizenship, and I am not at all surprised about the strength of feeling, as day on day I receive distressing messages from EU citizens in the UK and UK citizens living in the EU, as well as their friends, colleagues and loved ones, who are demanding that negotiators stop playing with their future. I would like to remind you that every single person in the United Kingdom is currently still a citizen of the European Union, and we must question what is being done to protect the 48.1% of British European citizens who voted to remain so. What is being done to protect young people whose citizenship will be stolen from them? What is being done to protect us all about the serious threat that these rights will be removed?</p>
      <p sl="en">And despite the recent movement in negotiations, many details and questions are still unresolved. The lengthy wait for people’s futures to be determined is causing psychological and emotional distress, and the EU has a duty of care towards these citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, izvješće se nažalost ne bavi unaprjeđenjem prava građana u područjima u kojima Europska unija ima nadležnosti, već želi ući u ona područja za koja Bruxelles nije nadležan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moram priznati da sam se već pomalo umorila od konstantnih pokušaja da se s europske razine državama članicama nametnu politički i kulturni obrasci koje njihovi građani odbijaju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ako smo doista „Ujedinjeni u raznolikosti“, onda poštujmo tu raznolikost. Ne možemo dopustiti da se vrednote nekolicine država članica jednostrano i bez ikakve rasprave proglašava univerzalnima i potom ih se nasilno nameće ostalima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ovo nije samo vaša Unija, ovo je i naša Unija. Unija kršćanskih društava koja su spremna tolerirati druge i drukčije, ali se neće povlačiti pred ovom ideološkom kolonizacijom nego će joj se odlučno suprotstaviti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η χορήγηση της ιθαγένειας από ένα κράτος στους πολίτες του είναι ένα πολύ σοβαρό αντικείμενο και ως τέτοιο πρέπει να εξετάζεται. Δεν μπορεί να χορηγείται η ιθαγένεια αδιακρίτως, χωρίς να τηρούνται κάποιες προϋποθέσεις και να μην εξετάζονται κάποια κριτήρια. Κατ’ αρχάς κάποιος ο οποίος έχει την ιθαγένεια ενός κράτους πρέπει να αισθάνεται ότι αποτελεί μέλος του κράτους αυτού. Πρέπει να σέβεται, να αγαπά το κράτος και να είναι έτοιμος να το υπερασπιστεί όταν αυτό κινδυνεύει. Εφόσον πληροί αυτές τις προϋποθέσεις, τότε μπορεί να του χορηγηθεί ιθαγένεια, και το κράτος οφείλει να τον προστατεύσει, όποιος και αν αυτός, ακόμη κι αν ανήκει σε κάποιο εθνοτική μειονότητα που ενδεχομένως να ζει στο κράτος αυτό.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η προστασία η οποία παρέχεται από το κράτος στους πολίτες του είναι αρμοδιότητα του εθνικού κράτους και δεν μπορούμε να το εντάξουμε σε ένα γενικότερο πλαίσιο χορηγήσεως μιας ευρωπαϊκής ιθαγένειας. Πρέπει να τηρούνται προϋποθέσεις και με βάση αυτό τα κράτη συνεργαζόμενα θα επιτύχουν ούτως ώστε ο πολίτης τους να έχει το ευρωπαϊκό κεκτημένο.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'obiettivo finale delle politiche di cittadinanza dell'Unione è che tutti i cittadini europei si sentano a casa in qualsiasi Stato membro. Ciò significa rafforzare i diritti e fare in modo che possano essere apprezzati nella quotidianità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dobbiamo identificare le aree in cui rimane ancora del lavoro da fare, dare un significato reale e concreto della cittadinanza europea, consacrata dall'articolo 20 del trattato sul funzionamento dell'Unione europea e dal capo quinto della Carta dei diritti fondamentali dell'Unione europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diritti e prestazioni sociali, diritti dei consumatori nel mercato interno digitale e riconoscimento delle qualifiche professionali come cittadini europei sono solo alcuni dei temi su cui agire. L'Unione europea ha ancora molto da fare anche per le minoranze, sebbene tali diritti debbano essere principalmente garantiti a livello di Stato membro.</p>
      <p sl="en">La cittadinanza dell'Unione e i diritti che essa conferisce sono il fulcro dell'Unione europea, e garantirne l'esercizio concreto è una nostra responsabilità primaria. Dobbiamo fare di più per aumentare nei cittadini la consapevolezza dei diritti di cui possono godere.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-170-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the honourable Members very much for their input. Let me also inform you that the Council welcomed the EU Citizenship Report 2017 in the conclusions adopted in May 2017 and highlighted that all EU institutions and Member States must join forces to deliver on the priorities for European citizens. I am glad to see the same positive attitude in your report and I wish you a successful adoption.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-0000" speaker_id="125040" name="Beatriz Becerra Basterrechea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señor presidente, señora Jourová, gracias por haber estado aquí para las conclusiones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ser ciudadano europeo tiene que significar mucho más de lo que significa hasta ahora. Tiene que reconfortar, tiene que dar confianza, tiene que proteger, dar autonomía. Tiene que ser motivo de orgullo. Tiene que significar tanto que ningún ciudadano europeo quiera que su país abandone la Unión porque, si tal cosa sucede, sus habitantes perderán algo muy valioso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ser ciudadano europeo significa ser parte de un marco legal y de valores, y eso es la integridad de la ciudadanía europea. El señor Solé expresaba antes una supuesta contradicción en este informe acerca de cómo se compatibilizaba lo que establecen los tratados, que es la integridad territorial, es decir, el marco legal que nos protege, con la posibilidad de que un número de ciudadanos decidiera cambiar esa integridad territorial. El deseo o la voluntad permanece dentro del ámbito de lo particular, pero la ley prevalece siempre por encima del deseo de algunos.</p>
      <p sl="en">La ley es lo que nos protege. La ley es la que nos hace ser parte de este proyecto y nos garantiza los derechos que nos hacen sentirnos protegidos. Por eso, quiero recordar a los diputados que han estado acompañándome en este informe —que ha sido trabajoso, pero yo creo que muy valioso― que debemos recordar cada día lo que hacemos aquí, a quién representamos, quién nos ha traído hasta este escaño. Que son ni más ni menos que quinientos millones de ciudadanos europeos, que son los que ocupan el centro de esta Cámara. Todos ellos. Porque cada uno de nosotros los representa a todos ellos, no solamente a los que nos han elegido.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si lo hacemos de verdad, si representamos como es debido y somos también ciudadanos —porque nadie nos puede decir que los que estamos como eurodiputados no somos ciudadanos, debemos ser los primeros en dar ejemplo y en defender esa ciudadanía—, evitaremos que el populismo y el nacionalismo destruyan la base de este incomparable proyecto de unidad. Muchísimas gracias a todos y espero que su voto sea a favor mañana.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dziękuję bardzo pani sprawozdawczyni. Jeżeli wolno mi, to chciałbym tylko odnotować, że pani komisarz uczestniczyła w większości naszej debaty, a jej spóźnienie było usprawiedliwione i zastępowana była przez panią komisarz Bulc, co chciałbym docenić.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę. Głosowanie odbędzie się we wtorek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-5000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">At the core of the European Union lie European citizens and their rights. At least 15 million EU citizens are living in a different Member State than their home country and – for them and not only – free movement of travelling, work and study is highly appreciated. Following last year’s Brexit referendum, the right to petition and the right to free movement of persons, in particular, have risen the interest of EU citizens. This is why I believe that now, more than ever, it is time for the EU to gain credibility by overcoming any obstacle and any discrimination against EU citizens. Let’s not forget that European citizenship created also new configurations, which gradually extended to third-country nationals legally residing in the EU, leading to greater social and political inclusion. To conclude, I believe that European citizenship is slowly becoming a direct source of rights outside the economic context and in this framework, the Union of Democratic Change will develop within full democratic engagement and civic participation.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. EU-Kazakhstan Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement (Resolution) - EU-Kazakhstan Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement (Consent) (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-174-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest wspólna debata nad:</p>
      <p sl="en">zaleceniem sporządzonym przez Liisę Jaakonsaari w imieniu Komisji Spraw Zagranicznych w sprawie projektu decyzji Rady dotyczącej zawarcia, w imieniu Unii, umowy o wzmocnionym partnerstwie i współpracy między Unią Europejską i jej państwami członkowskimi, z jednej strony, a Republiką Kazachstanu, z drugiej strony (12409/2016 - C8-0469/2016 - 2016/0166(NLE)) (A8-0325/2017) oraz</p>
      <p sl="en">sprawozdaniem sporządzonym przez Liisę Jaakonsaari w imieniu Komisji Spraw Zagranicznych zawierającym projekt rezolucji nieustawodawczej w sprawie projektu decyzji Rady dotyczącej zawarcia, w imieniu Unii, umowy o wzmocnionym partnerstwie i współpracy między Unią Europejską i jej państwami członkowskimi, z jednej strony, a Republiką Kazachstanu, z drugiej strony (2017/2035(INI)) (A8-0335/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-0000" speaker_id="96684" name="Liisa Jaakonsaari" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">esittelijä. – Arvoisa puhemies, pitkän prosessin jälkeen Euroopan unionin ja Kazakstanin välinen tehostettu kumppanuus- ja yhteistyösopimus on nyt parlamentin täysistunnon käsittelyssä ja parlamentin vallassa on joko hyväksyä tai hylätä tämä sopimus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentti puoltaa sopimusta mutta edellyttää ihmisoikeustilanteen parantamista. On hyvä, että tämä sopimus vahvistaa poliittista dialogia ja yhteistyötä kansalaisyhteiskunnan kanssa. Ihmisoikeuksien kunnioittaminen ja oikeusvaltion periaate muodostavat perustan tälle sopimukselle ja tulevalle yhteistyölle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sopimus vahvistaa poliittisen ja taloudellisen yhteistyön syventämisen Keski-Aasian tärkeän maan, Kazakstanin, kanssa. Euroopan unioni on Kazakstanin suurin investoija ja hyvin merkittävä kauppakumppani. Maa on tärkeä myös Euroopan unionin Keski-Aasian strategian toteuttamisessa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yhteistyö vahvistaa kaupan, energian ja kestävän kehityksen kysymyksiä sekä tiivistää yhteistyötä ulko- ja turvallisuuspolitiikassa, esimerkiksi joukkotuhoaseiden leviämisen ja terrorismin vastaisessa työssä. Ihmisoikeuskysymyksissä parlamentti edellyttää tuntuvia ja konkreettisia uudistuksia. Talouden intressit eivät saa polkea ihmisoikeuksia vaan niiden on kuljettava käsi kädessä. Eurooppa menettää sielunsa ja ideansa, jos ja kun muut prioriteetit syrjäyttävät ihmisoikeudet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tässä Euroopan parlamentin päätöslauselmassa vaaditaan sanan- ja kokoontumisvapauden sekä järjestäytymisvapauden tunnustamista ja turvaamista. Oikeusvaltio edellyttää myös riippumatonta ja puolueetonta oikeuslaitosta. Rohkaisemme Kazakstania jatkamaan yhteistyötä Venetsian komission kanssa lainsäädäntötyön parantamiseksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentti edellyttää, että Kazakstan noudattaa kansainvälisen työjärjestön ILO:n sopimuksia ja sallii riippumattoman ammattiyhdistysliikkeen toiminnan sekä vapauttaa kolme ammattiyhdistysliikkeen johtajaa vankilasta. On turvattava toimittajien ja kansalaisjärjestöjen aktivistien mahdollisuudet toimia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kazakstanilla on nyt mielestämme yhdestoista hetki muuttaa maan lakeja, jotka rajoittavat työntekijöiden oikeuksia. Ei ole todellakaan hyväksyttävää, että rauhanomaisesti maareformia vastaan mieltään osoittavat tuomitaan jopa viideksi vuodeksi vankilaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentti edellyttää, että Maks Bokayev ja Talgat Ayan vapautetaan vankilasta, kuten YK:n ihmisoikeusneuvosto on edellyttänyt. Myös lehdistön vapautta on kavennettu ja kriittisten toimittajien työ on yhä vaikeutunut. Ei ole tämäkään hyväksyttävää, että toimittajien ja kansalaisyhteiskunnan aktivistien työtä rajoitetaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentti vetoaa korkeaan edustajaan Federica Mogheriniin seuraavasti: Kun tehostettu kumppanuus- ja yhteistyösopimus on tullut voimaan, on saatava aikaan demokraattista valvontaa varten kokonaisvaltainen valvontajärjestelmä EU:n ja parlamentin kesken. Parlamentti pitää erittäin hyvänä aloitettua ihmisoikeusdialogia ja toivoo Kazakstanilta tahtoa varmistaa säännöllinen yhteistyö kansalaisyhteiskunnan edustajien kanssa. Toivomme vilpittömästi, että kunnianhimoinen yhteistyösopimus toteutetaan kohta kohdalta molempien osapuolten toimesta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission, on behalf of the Vice-President of the Commission / High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the honourable Members for the opportunity for this debate on the EU—Kazakhstan Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement, signed by the High Representative, Federica Mogherini, two years ago.</p>
      <p sl="en">This Agreement is the very first of this kind in Central Asia and reflects the new level of ambition in our relations with one of the EU’s closest partners in the region. Our relationship with the Central Asian countries has never been stronger. The EU and our partners in Central Asia share many common objectives: regional peace and stability, fighting terrorism, fostering the rule of law, increasing prosperity and trade. The reinforced cooperation between the EU and Kazakhstan is an excellent example of how to advance in practice the goals and interests shared by both sides.</p>
      <p sl="en">To begin with, the Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement provides for a new level in the quality of our economic cooperation. The EU has become Kazakhstan’s first trade partner, representing over one third of its external trade, and also Kazakhstan’s first foreign investor. The Agreement promotes a better regulatory environment for economic operators in areas such as trade in services, the establishment and operation of companies, capital movements, raw materials, government procurement and intellectual property rights. We appreciate Kazakhstan’s commitment to promote the green economy with ambitious targets for economic diversification and investments in energy efficiency. These areas represent significant opportunities for European companies.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Enhanced Partnership reflects this progress in our energy cooperation, as this is the first time that we have concluded a chapter on raw materials and energy in a non—preferential agreement with an oil-producing country with rules going beyond WTO and Energy Charter Treaty commitments.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have not only built strong economic ties with Kazakhstan, we are also keen on consolidating our cooperation in other fields such as in nuclear non—proliferation, further reforms towards pluralism and democracy, and also to enhance the mobility of people between the two regions. In international relations, Kazakhstan has become an increasingly important partner in the promotion of peace and security. It provides an essential contribution to the implementation of the EU Strategy for Central Asia, notably in the EU’s regional cooperation programmes and platforms.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, we should not forget that democratic reforms play a crucial role too. The Agreement puts a strong emphasis on democracy and the rule of law, human rights and fundamental freedoms, as well as civil society cooperation, including on the involvement of civil society in public policy-making. On 29 November, the EU and Kazakhstan held their ninth Human Rights Dialogue.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU has been promoting a more active role for civil society in the implementation of the Agreement. Ahead of the dialogue, we have held consultations with civil society representatives, both in Brussels and in Kazakhstan, and we have discussed specific recommendations from civil society that were then reflected in the dialogue with the Government of Kazakhstan. Moreover, just before the dialogue, our EU delegation in Astana visited an imprisoned civil society activist, Max Bokayev. The EU discussed his situation, as well as several other individual cases of human rights activists and journalists, during the dialogue. Notably, it was confirmed to us that former head of the Union of Journalists, Seitqazy Mataev, who was sentenced to six years in prison last year, was granted early release this month.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the specific issue of trade unionists and the independence of trade unions were specifically discussed. Kazakhstan committed to amend its law on trade unions to bring it in line with the Agreement provisions and the conventions of the International Labour Organization. The EU also finances a substantial programme that contributes to judicial reforms and supports the rule of law in Kazakhstan. In all of its actions, the EU seeks to be a stabilising factor and will continue to put forward the view that non—extremist political pluralism and broad participation are the best foundations for creating, maintaining or strengthening the resilience and security of Central Asian societies.</p>
      <p sl="en">On other aspects of our mutual relations with Kazakhstan, we broaden our political dialogues on trade, customs, energy, transport, environment and climate change. We are now further enhancing the Humans Rights Dialogue and consultation with civil society representatives. More exchanges of views will follow during the Cooperation Council with Foreign Minister Abdrakhmanov, planned for 26 February in Brussels.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me conclude by stating that the Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement has started to bear fruit and to produce successful common projects. This agreement with Kazakhstan is an excellent precedent for our relations with other countries in Central Asia. Negotiations for an Enhanced Agreement with Kyrgyzstan will start later this month, and we are hopeful for enhanced relations with Uzbekistan. The EU will continue to press for more open markets, both in the WTO and in our bilateral agreements, to spur economic growth and trade, as well as democratisation and sustainable development in Central Asia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-0000" speaker_id="96651" name="Eduard Kukan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Madam Commissioner, colleagues, first: congratulations to the Republic of Kazakhstan on celebrating the 26th anniversary of its independence later this week, on 16 December. With tomorrow’s vote, we will mark an important milestone in our bilateral relations with Kazakhstan as we ratify the first enhanced partnership and cooperation agreement in Central Asia.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU is Kazakhstan’s first trade and investment partner, and I believe that trade with the EU can positively reinforce human rights and the rule of law. There are valid concerns, however, about the state of freedom of media, expression and association in Kazakhstan, which must be improved by releasing a number of political prisoners and activists.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EPCA should serve as a basis for further enhancing our ties and reflect a genuine commitment to democracy, the rule of law, good governance and respect for human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kazakhstan should continue its reform process, which should go hand-in-hand with its third modernisation strategy. I would also like to encourage Kazakhstan to follow the Venice Commission and the OSC electoral recommendations. We appreciate and welcome Kazakhstan’s increasingly important international role and would like to encourage it to positively contribute to deepening regional cooperation. In this respect we welcome the accession to the WTO in 2016. I am looking forward to the further fruitful cooperation with Kazakhstan.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Agreement between the EU and the Republic of Kazakhstan comes at a time when we see a sharp deterioration in the human rights situation in Kazakhstan. Freedom of speech and freedom of assembly and association are being attacked by the authorities, who have organised a crackdown against free voices in Kazakh society. Kazakhstan is publicly neglecting its international human rights obligations. Politically motivated criminal prosecutions are becoming more frequent and demonstrate that the authorities are unwilling to accept dissident voices.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am very concerned by the detention of political prisoners and the ongoing use of torture. Human rights organisations have registered more than 35 cases of persons subjected to politically motivated prosecution for civil and trade union activities, for public criticism of the authorities, for participating in peaceful rallies, for publishing and sharing posts on social media, and for conducting journalistic investigations. This is so in the case of Mr Max Bokayev, a Kazakh civic activist, Mr Mukhtar Dzhakishev, Mr Iskander Yerimbetov, and Mr Muratkhan Tokmadi – political prisoners who fell victim to the lack of proper medical care. They need urgent hospitalisation, but are subject to ill-treatment and severe torture instead. So I hereby call on the Kazakh authorities to release all political hostages and cease further human rights abuses.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I told the Kazakh Government in a letter I sent out two months ago, I believe that the fulfilment of Kazakhstan’s international human rights obligations should be a non—negotiable condition for the ratification of the Agreement, and as this condition is not yet met, I will be voting against the Agreement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-0000" speaker_id="125105" name="Helga Stevens" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Als lid van de parlementaire samenwerkingscommissie EU-Kazachstan ben ik blij met dit debat. De samenwerking tussen het Europees Parlement en de Centraal-Aziatische staten is belangrijk om de politieke dialoog te bevorderen en de economische en culturele interactie te promoten. De partnerschapsovereenkomst EU-Kazachstan van 2015 droeg bij tot de internationale en regionale vrede, stabiliteit en economische ontwikkeling. Een samenwerking bovendien die gestructureerd is rond de internationale verplichtingen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kazachstan is een strategische partner inzake de energiesector. De EU is de belangrijkste handelspartner van Kazachstan. Er is echter nog werk aan de winkel inzake democratie, ook al zijn er recent positieve ontwikkelingen te zien op het gebied van constitutionele en bestuurlijke hervormingen en werkt Kazachstan nu samen met de Commissie van Venetië. Vandaar het belang van deze overeenkomst, want mensenrechten en de rechtsstaat staan erin centraal. Noteren we ook dat via internationale mensenrechteninstrumenten, maar ook via fondsen in de periode 2014-2020 ruim 1 miljard euro naar Centraal-Azië gaat voor onder andere een verbetering van de rechtsstaat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-0000" speaker_id="124745" name="Iveta Grigule-Pēterse" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ALDE grupas vārdā. – Godātais priekšsēdētāj, kolēģi! Sadarbības līgums ar Kazahstānu tika parakstīts 2015. gada decembrī pirms diviem gadiem, un 18 Eiropas Savienības dalībvalstis to jau ir ratificējušas. Šobrīd līgums ir nonācis Eiropas Parlamentā, un rītdien mums ir balsojums. Kā jau minēja Kukan kungs, šis balsojums notiek ļoti zīmīgā dienā priekš Kazahstānas, jo 16. decembris ir valsts neatkarības diena, un 26 gadi valsts attīstībā ir ļoti niecīgs posms, salīdzinot ar valstīm, kuru demokrātiskā pieredze ir simtiem gadu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kazahstāna ir stabils, prognozējams un konstruktīvs Eiropas Savienības partneris ar ļoti svarīgu lomu reģionā, ar ļoti svarīgu lomu Centrālāzijā. Kazahstāna ir drošības, stabilitātes un cīņas pret terorismu garants reģionā. Viņi nodrošina ne tikai drošību savā valstī un kaimiņvalstīs, bet lielā mērā arī mūsu — Eiropas Savienības — drošību.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jaunais nolīgums ir svarīgs instruments gan uzņēmējiem, gan iedzīvotājiem. Tā ir jauna platforma, lai attīstītu jaunus sadarbības veidus, investētu šajā valstī, lai saņemtu investīcijas Eiropas Savienībā. Protams, problēmu vēl ir daudz, bet galvenais ir virziens, un virziens ir ļoti pozitīvs. Tāpēc es aicinu balsot rītdien par šo nolīgumu. Eiropas Savienība vēlas būt pirmrindniece, vēlas būt ietekmīga ārpolitikas spēlētāja, tāpēc jābūt aktīvākai, un šādus nolīgumus sagaida arī pārējās Centrālāzijas valstis. Paldies!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-0000" speaker_id="125035" name="Lola Sánchez Caldentey" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor presidente. Kazajistán es considerado por la Unión Europea como un país estratégico por sus intereses geopolíticos y económicos. Así, la Unión Europea y Kazajistán han establecido una estrecha asociación económica y comercial en los últimos tiempos. Tanto es así que la Unión Europea es el primer socio comercial de Kazajistán —representando un tercio del comercio total del país— y también su mayor inversor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, la situación de los derechos humanos allí es dramática. El relator de las Naciones Unidas sobre el derecho a la libertad de reunión y asociación, que visitó Kazajistán en el año 2015, exigió una investigación internacional sobre la represión y las torturas que siguieron a las manifestaciones pacíficas de trabajadores del petróleo ocurridas en el año 2011, que, según cifras oficiales, dejaron quince muertos y más de cien heridos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Según Human Rights Watch, con el telón de fondo de una recesión económica, las autoridades kazajas encarcelaron en 2016 a manifestantes pacíficos, enjuiciaron a activistas y periodistas independientes y, es más, en el Parlamento se aprobaron leyes que imponen cargas y restricciones injustificadas a las organizaciones de la sociedad civil.</p>
      <p sl="en">La misión de observación electoral de la OSCE señaló que las elecciones parlamentarias de 2016 tuvieron graves errores e irregularidades durante la votación y el escrutinio y concluyó que el marco legal de Kazajistán restringe los derechos civiles y políticos fundamentales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las relaciones de la Unión Europea con Kazajistán son un ejemplo más de instrumentalización cínica de los derechos humanos, que quedan siempre subordinados a los intereses comerciales. Nunca dejaremos de pedir coherencia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-183-0000" speaker_id="124755" name="Jean-Luc Schaffhauser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, nous n’avons rien appris, nous n’avons rien compris. Je vous parle des rapports de l’Union européenne avec les pays de notre voisinage proche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Au lieu de nous remettre en question et de renouer les fils du dialogue avec la Russie et l’Union économique eurasiatique, certes, nous changeons de méthode: ce n’est plus l’agressivité illustrée, par exemple, par M. Barroso qui menaçait l’Arménie en 2013 en disant «qui n’est pas avec nous est contre nous». Non, ce n’est plus cette agressivité car nous n’en avons plus les moyens, notamment après les échecs répétés de l’élargissement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Après le bâton menaçant, on préfère aujourd’hui la carotte bienveillante du soutien aux pays de l’Union économique eurasienne, mais pour les mettre dans notre camp. Nous risquons une fois de plus l’échec, car l’Asie centrale est l’une des zones les plus dangereuses au monde, où se joue un grand jeu entre Américains, Chinois et Russes.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, face au rouleau compresseur islamiste venant du sud, face à la montée en puissance de la Chine, seul un accord eurasiatique prôné par l’Union avec la Russie peut stabiliser et maintenir la paix dans cette région, dont le verrou est le Kazakhstan. Ce n’est pas votre chemin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si les États membres, avec la Commission comme porte-parole, souhaitent véritablement apporter quelque chose aux équilibres de la paix à venir, il nous faut raccrocher notre wagon au train du monde multipolaire défendu par le président Nazarbaïev. Mieux, nous devons en être la locomotive; nous éviterons ainsi les morts, comme ces 10 000 morts d’Ukraine – les morts de la division, alors qu’il nous faut unir.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-184-0000" speaker_id="28276" name="Laima Liucija Andrikienė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Commissioner, colleagues, this agreement shows our commitment to help Kazakhstan to exploit in full scale the possibilities offered by the Enhanced Partnership and Cooperation Agreement. It will boost our bilateral trade and support businesses, all in line with fundamental WTO rules and principles.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, there is still a series of concerns as regards political reforms and real progress with respect for human rights, the rule of law, good governance and democratisation. Continued restriction of media, freedom of expression and belief, criminal prosecution and imprisonment of independent activists and political opposition leaders by the Kazak authorities are not in line with our principles and shall be subject to scrutiny. Therefore, we urge Kazakhstan to resolve these negative trends.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the implementation of the EPCA should be subject to effective monitoring, strictly applying the principle: more for more and less and for less.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-185-0000" speaker_id="28424" name="Tunne Kelam" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Madam Commissioner, I must say, I was inspired and impressed by colleague Jaakonsaari’s presentation. I think it should be seen as a model of our approach toward third countries, balancing economic interests and human values. Therefore, we should say that in Kazakhstan there’s still much to be worried about – persecution of opposition and journalists – and therefore I think the EU has to stand up first for European values and condition enhanced cooperation on convincing progress in the field of human rights. Such progress should include fully providing freedom of media, of expression and association. Also it’s crucial for the credibility of Kazakhstan to allow freedom of religion to be exercised equally for all denominations, not only for Orthodox and Muslim communities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore I call for our High Representative to act decisively and forcefully for the release of all political prisoners.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-0000" speaker_id="23693" name="Alojz Peterle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pozdravljam sklenitev sporazuma o okrepljenem sodelovanju in partnerstvu med Evropsko zvezo in Kazahstanom. Čas je, da nadgradimo sporazum iz leta 1999. Podpiram ambicijo, da z njim poglobimo in razširimo sodelovanje, in se strinjam s celovitim pristopom kolegice poročevalke.</p>
      <p sl="en">Odločitev za diverzifikacijo kazahstanskega gospodarstva in reformiranja države je strateškega pomena. Oboje lahko uspe samo, če bomo ostali zavezani istim vrednotam in načelom, s katerimi smo sodelovanje začeli. Restriktivnost do nevladnih organizacij in tistih, ki mislijo drugače, ni v skladu z duhom sporazuma.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το Καζακστάν έχει σημαντικές οικονομικές σχέσεις με την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Υπάρχει συνεργασία στα θέματα του φυσικού αερίου, του πετρελαίου, στα μέταλλα, στα θέματα της επεξεργασίας ουρανίου και στα χημικά. Υπάρχει ζήτημα βέβαια με τη χρήση της πυρηνικής ενέργειας και παραμένει το ερώτημα κατά πόσο η ραδιενέργεια η οποία ανιχνεύθηκε πρόσφατα προέρχεται τελικά από το Καζακστάν. Περιμένουμε μία απάντηση πάνω στο θέμα αυτό.</p>
      <p sl="en">Επιπλέον, οι ευρωπαϊκές πολυεθνικές είναι ιδιαίτερα δραστήριες οικονομικά στην περιοχή. Όμως δεν υπάρχει από τη συμφωνία επαρκής προστασία στα προϊόντα γεωγραφικών ενδείξεων. Αυτό είναι πάρα πολύ σημαντικό για την Ελλάδα και θέλουμε μία διαβεβαίωση ότι πράγματι τα προϊόντα και οι γεωγραφικές ενδείξεις των προϊόντων προστατεύονται.</p>
      <p sl="en">Φυσικά, στο πολιτικό μέρος έχουμε παραβίαση των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων, του κράτους δικαίου, του πλουραλισμού και της δημοκρατίας και διώξεις Χριστιανών. Είναι σημαντικά ερωτήματα, στα οποία θα πρέπει να μας απαντήσετε, κυρία Jourová.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, είναι γεγονός ότι το Καζακστάν αποτελεί έναν σημαντικό εμπορικό εταίρο της Ευρωπαϊκής Ενώσεως, η οποία δραστηριοποιείται ποικιλοτρόπως στην περιοχή αυτή με διάφορες εμπορικές και άλλες πράξεις. Αυτός είναι ένας από τους λόγους για τους οποίους η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση θέλει να ενισχύσει τις διμερείς σχέσεις με το Καζακστάν. Από στρατηγικής απόψεως το Καζακστάν, λόγω του ότι βρίσκεται και στο μαλακό υπογάστριο της Ρωσίας, αποκτά ακόμη μεγαλύτερη στρατηγική αξία και αποτελεί σημαντικό παράγοντα για τη σταθερότητα και την ειρήνη στην ευαίσθητη περιοχή της Κεντρικής Ασίας, όπου συγκρούονται συμφέροντα πολλών και μεγάλων δυνάμεων.</p>
      <p sl="en">Όμως υπάρχουν και κάποιες παράμετροι που πρέπει να ληφθούν σοβαρά υπόψη, δεδομένου ότι το Καζακστάν είναι μία χώρα που παραβιάζει τα ανθρώπινα δικαιώματα και τις αρχές του κράτους δικαίου και παράλληλα τα προϊόντα τα οποία έρχονται από εκεί είναι δυνατόν, εάν δεν προσεχθούν, να αποτελέσουν πηγή και κατάσταση αθέμιτου ανταγωνισμού με τα αντίστοιχα ευρωπαϊκά προϊόντα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-191-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission, on behalf of the Vice-President of the Commission / High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this has been a very useful exchange and I thank the honourable Members for their interventions. I greatly appreciate the discussion and your interest in the EU-Kazakhstan Partnership and Cooperation Agreement, both during the negotiations and now for the consent, as reflected also in the accompanying resolution.</p>
      <p sl="en">The debate has shown strong support for the strengthening of EU—Kazakhstan relations through this Agreement. This new Agreement gives us the opportunity to consolidate our achievements and advance on a range of issues relevant to the challenges of our time. We hope for the continuation of your support in the implementation of the Agreement and in strengthening our bilateral relations with Kazakhstan. I am looking forward to your vote tomorrow.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-192-0000" speaker_id="96684" name="Liisa Jaakonsaari" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">esittelijä. – Arvoisa puhemies, kiitoksia keskustelusta. Aivan kuten komissaari Jourová sanoi, tämä yhteistyösopimus on jo tuottanut hedelmää, koska vankeja vapautettu. Uskon, että Kazakstan ottaa nämä tänään parlamentissa esitetyt kriittiset mielipiteet huomioon. Mielestäni Euroopan unionin suuri arvo, oikeastaan kaikkein suurin arvo, näkyy juuri tässä sopimuksessa: halutaan dialogia ja kehitystä mutta pidetään kiinni omista perusarvoista, kuten oikeusvaltioperiaatteista ja demokratiasta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Haluan kiittää varjoesittelijöitä rakentavasta työstä, ja itse asiassa haluan ihan vilpittömästi kiittää myös komissiota ja ulkosuhdehallintoa erittäin avoimesta ja hyvästä yhteistyöstä tämän Kazakstanin sopimuksen suhteen. Olemme saaneet kaikki tarvittavat tiedot ja käyneet koko ajan teidän asiantuntijoidenne kanssa hyödyllistä ja rakentavaa keskustelua.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-193-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Președinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votul va avea loc marți, 12 decembrie 2017.</p>
      <p sl="en">Declarații scrise (articolul 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194-0000" speaker_id="124712" name="Andrea Bocskor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Üdvözlöm, hogy Kazahsztán következetesen közeledik az EU-hoz, és hogy az ország jelentős mértékben hozzájárult a 2019-ben alapos felülvizsgálatra kerülő EU–Közép-Ázsia stratégia végrehajtásához. A megerősített partnerségi és együttműködési megállapodás az EU és Kazahsztán közötti gazdasági kapcsolatok jelentős mértékű fellendítésére törekszik. A jelentés emlékeztet, hogy a megállapodás bevezette egy vízumkönnyítési megállapodás megtárgyalásának lehetőségét az EU és Kazahsztán között. Az állásfoglalás javasolja továbbá, hogy az EU folytassa a közép-ázsiai regionális együttműködés támogatását, különös tekintettel a jogállamiságra, bizalomépítő intézkedésekre, a víz- és erőforrás-gazdálkodásra, a határigazgatásra, valamint a stabilitásra és biztonságra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Magyarország a visegrádi csoport (V4) soros elnökeként is a legfontosabb feladatként tűzte ki, hogy fejlessze a V4-ek és Közép-Ázsia közötti együttműködést. Magyarországnak ehhez komoly gazdasági érdeke fűződik, és mivel Kazahsztán vezető szerepet tölt be a közép-ázsiai régióban, az országgal elsősorban az olajipar, a mezőgazdaság és a vízgazdálkodás területén kíván együttműködni. A kétoldalú kereskedelem is rendkívül dinamikusan bővül, 2017 első negyedévében a hatszorosára nőtt a forgalom. Ennek fő oka, hogy Magyarország jelentősen növelte kőolajimportját Kazahsztánból, és növelte gyógyszerexportját az országba. Ezenkívül a két ország közötti oktatási kapcsolatok is dinamikusan bővülnek: Budapest 200 kazah diák számára ajánlott fel ösztöndíjat magyarországi felsőoktatási intézményekbe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194-5000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Przedstawione sprawozdanie zawiera projekt rezolucji nieustawodawczej w sprawie wzmocnienia partnerstwa i współpracy między Unią Europejską i jej państwami członkowskimi a Republiką Kazachstanu. Rezolucja ma na celu uściślenie stosunków politycznych, ekonomicznych i kulturalnych między Wspólnotą a Kazachstanem, opartych na zobowiązaniach z obydwu stron. Odnoszą się one do wspólnych wartości takich jak demokracja, praworządność, prawa człowieka. Należy podkreślić, że wolność mediów i wolność słowa są fundamentalną częścią w tworzeniu trwałej demokracji. Niestety, UE niepokoi się projektem ustawy, która próbuje narzucić odgórne restrykcyjne zasady dla dziennikarzy. Trzeba przypomnieć, iż kraje UE są pierwszym partnerem handlowym dla Kazachstanu, a Kazachstan jest głównym partnerem dla Centralnej Azji. Umowa jest zgodna z EPCA (Europejskie Stowarzyszenie Petrochemiczne), by wzmocnić stosunki w takich sektorach jak zrównoważony rozwój, polityka zagraniczna i obronna, sprawiedliwość i handel. Dodatkowo zaznacza, jak ważne są obecne stosunki handlowe obejmujące głównie ropę naftową i gaz.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sprawozdanie uwidacznia wielkowymiarowość relacji dotyczących międzynarodowej siły roboczej, ochrony środowiska, praw człowieka obejmujących opiekę zdrowotną, bezpieczeństwa, edukacji, bezstronnych instytucji i zwalczania korupcji. Państwa członkowskie Unii zamierzają pomóc w walce z korupcją. Tekst popiera dołączenie Kazachstanu do WTO w dniu 1 stycznia 2016 r., które sprzyja gospodarczemu i administracyjnemu rozwojowi tego państwa. Umowa o wzajemnym partnerstwie i współpracy z pewnością urozmaici ekonomię obydwu państw.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Towards a digital trade strategy (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-196-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este prezentarea succintă a raportului Marietjei Schaake referitor la tema Către o strategie în domeniul comerțului digital (2017/2065(INI)) (A8–0384/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-0000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you very much, Commissioner, colleagues. Commissioner Malmström and some of our INTA International Trade Committee colleagues working on this important topic cannot be here as they are in Buenos Aires for the WTO ministerial. But the good news is that both here and in Argentina we are working on European leadership towards rule- and value-based trade.</p>
      <p sl="en">After intense and fruitful cooperation among the shadow rapporteurs, I am happy that we can present a broadly supported call for an EU strategy on digital trade, and hopefully our resolution with broad support can inspire a common position from the Commission and thus the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">So why are digital trade rules important at all? Digitisation is becoming a key element or a layer of almost every industry or sector. Small and medium-sized enterprises, as well as larger companies, can reach customers all over the world at the click of a button.</p>
      <p sl="en">Digitisation and universal and affordable access to the internet are also key to achieving the sustainable development goals. But there are not only opportunities to be reaped; we also see challenges in growing digital protectionism. European companies that are being hindered by forced data localisation requirements and the lack of respect for people’s rights online is an increasing challenge worldwide.</p>
      <p sl="en">So what do we want to achieve with a digital trade strategy for Europe?</p>
      <p sl="en">Rules must defend the public interest. One of the trends that we see is that its private companies that are essentially setting the norms in the digital economy, from deciding what is and is not acceptable speech to proposals for entire online free-trade zones. But ensuring fair competition, protecting net neutrality and data protection rules cannot be left to private companies to safeguard.</p>
      <p sl="en">So an EU digital strategy should ensure that access to the open internet is prioritised globally, that data transfers are enabled while respecting privacy, and that encryption is understood to be essential for security.</p>
      <p sl="en">Currently, the EU relies on adequacy decisions to assess the level of data protection in third countries, and we’ve seen two such decisions with 20 of our trading partners, so there is a lot more that can be done. We need more agreements along with more predictable and transparent criteria.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I end with a note of hope. For the EU position at the WTO in Argentina, it is a related topic to this debate that we are having about digital trade. I hope that the Commission continues its efforts there towards developing a set of binding, multilateral disciplines on e-commerce and to transform the moratorium on banning tariffs on electronic transmissions into a permanent agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">President, colleagues, the world of trade is rapidly changing and the EU has a key opportunity to lead. Not only is the USA taking a step back and China pushing forward, we also need to look at how digitisation changes the nature of the rules that we seek to ensure our principles remain leading, whatever we do in a changing world.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think here, with this EU Digital Trade Strategy, we once more have an opportunity to be rule-makers instead of rule-takers and we should take that opportunity.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-199-0000" speaker_id="125064" name="Μαρία Σπυράκη" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, έχουμε μπροστά μας μία πολύ σημαντική ευκαιρία, μία ευκαιρία που σε αριθμούς μεταφράζεται σε πεντακόσια εκατομμύρια δυνητικούς καταναλωτές. Η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση βρίσκεται μπροστά στην πρόκληση να καθορίσει εκείνη το πλαίσιο, ώστε στην πραγματικότητα το εμπόριο της ψηφιοποίησης να είναι εκείνο το οποίο θα προχωρήσει με ταχύτατους ρυθμούς.</p>
      <p sl="en">Τι πρέπει πρώτα και κύρια να προσέξουμε: κατ’ αρχήν την ενθάρρυνση της ψηφιοποίησης των μικρών και των μεσαίων επιχειρήσεων. Δεν είναι η ταχύτητα ίδια σε όλα τα κράτη μέλη. Δεν είναι η ταχύτητα ίδια σε όλες τις μικρές και τις μεσαίες επιχειρήσεις. Είναι απαραίτητο να δοθεί έμφαση και έτσι να δημιουργηθούν πολλές καινούργιες θέσεις εργασίας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεύτερον, στο πεδίο των εθνικών ρυθμίσεων, την ενθάρρυνση της εκπαίδευσης των νέων ανθρώπων, ώστε να μπορέσουν να καλύψουν αυτές τις νέες θέσεις εργασίας. Είναι τέλος απαραίτητο ο καθορισμός των ελεύθερων online περιοχών να γίνει από τους θεσμικούς παίκτες, με την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση σε πρωταγωνιστικό ρόλο, και να μην αφεθεί στις ιδιωτικές εταιρείες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-0000" speaker_id="133316" name="Karoline Graswander-Hainz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Werter Herr Präsident, werte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wenn die EU ein Global Player sein will, muss sie den digitalen Handel unbedingt regeln.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es braucht ein faires, zeitgerechtes System, das sowohl den Fluss von Daten ermöglicht, als auch gleichzeitig unsere hohen europäischen Datenschutzbestimmungen nicht aufweicht. Der Datenschutz in der EU ist nicht verhandelbar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zu beachten ist, dass die digitale Kluft nicht nur zwischen Industrie- und Entwicklungsländern, sondern auch in entwickelten Staaten überbrückt werden muss. Allen Bürgerinnen und Bürgern muss der Zugang zum Internet ermöglicht werden. Fragen zur Durchsetzung von Kunden- und Verbraucherrechten, aber auch zur Datensicherheit bei Online-Käufen, zur Besteuerung der digitalen Wirtschaft sowie zu den neuen Beschäftigungsverhältnissen gilt ist dringend zu beantworten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen Maßnahmen setzen, um die negativen Auswirkungen der Digitalisierung einzuschränken und den digitalen Handel gerecht und fair zu machen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kύριε Πρόεδρε, οι σύγχρονες προκλήσεις για την ευρωπαϊκή οικονομία απαιτούν μια ολοκληρωμένη στρατηγική για το ψηφιακό εμπόριο, διότι μόνο έτσι θα ενισχυθεί η ανταγωνιστικότητα της ίδιας της ευρωπαϊκής οικονομίας και κυρίως οι οικονομίες των χωρών του ευρωπαϊκού Νότου. Έτσι αποδεικνύεται ότι η ευρωπαϊκή ανταγωνιστικότητα δεν θα στηριχθεί στην κινεζοποίηση των μισθών αλλά μπορεί να στηριχθεί μόνο στην ψηφιακή οικονομία και κυρίως στην εκπαίδευση και στην κατάρτιση.</p>
      <p sl="en">Με αυτό τον τρόπο μπορεί να δημιουργηθούν πολλές νέες θέσεις εργασίας, μπορεί να ενισχυθούν οι μικρομεσαίες επιχειρήσεις και έτσι να έχουμε μια αποτελεσματική παρέμβαση σε αυτό που ονομάζουμε ψηφιακό εμπόριο, τη στιγμή μάλιστα που απευθυνόμαστε σε πεντακόσια, τουλάχιστον, εκατομμύρια καταναλωτές στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και σε πολύ περισσότερους σε όλο τον κόσμο. Όμως πρέπει να προσέξουμε ώστε το σύστημα που θα διαμορφωθεί να εγγυάται την τεχνολογική ουδετερότητα την αναλογικότητα και την πρόσβαση των νεοεισερχομένων στην ίδια την αγορά.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-0000" speaker_id="1185" name="Viviane Reding" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, en tant que premier exportateur de services au monde, nous voulons, nous pouvons et nous devons écrire des règles du jeu solides garantissant, primo, l'accès aux marchés étrangers pour nos entreprises, secundo, des avantages concrets pour les consommateurs et, tertio, le respect des droits fondamentaux.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europe s'est dotée de standards numériques avant-gardistes. Ils doivent être pleinement sauvegardés et promus dans les accords commerciaux. Donc, oui à la protection des données, à la neutralité du Net, à l'accès aux réseaux télécoms et aux droits de propriété intellectuelle. Non à la localisation forcée des données, aux spams, à la surtarification des appels internationaux et du roaming ou, encore, au transfert obligatoire des codes sources.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les droits numériques ne doivent connaître aucune frontière et, face à des visions et des intérêts divergents, l'Europe doit affirmer son leadership, ancrer le commerce sur des valeurs et défendre un internet libre, ouvert et sûr.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, chci poděkovat především paní zpravodajce za komplexní zprávu. Digitalizace je samozřejmě téma pro Evropskou unii, ale je to také globální nástroj, tedy digitální obchod. Proto je správné reagovat na digitální vývoj a zaměřit se na odborné vzdělávání tak, aby časem nevznikaly hluboké sociální propasti. Proto je nutné na jednotném digitálním trhu zachovávat zásady spravedlivé soutěže, neutrality sítě a ochrany spotřebitelů. Proto je samozřejmě nutné zdůraznit nutnost ochrany osobních údajů tak, aby spotřebitelé měli důvěru v digitální obchod. Při vyjednávání obchodních podmínek a dohod nesmí Evropská unie nikdy snížit vysoké nároky na ochranu svých podnikatelů, spotřebitelů a vždy se řídit právním řádem Evropské unie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-205-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me first thank the European Parliament, the Committee on International Trade and rapporteur Ms Schaake for the report. The Commission considers your report an important contribution to the discussion on responses to the challenges brought by the digital revolution that we are witnessing all around us. Modern trade is increasingly enabled by digital technologies. Digital trade is therefore a priority for a variety of European industries.</p>
      <p sl="en">The global e—commerce market is now estimated to be worth over EUR two trillion and continues to grow at a fast pace. The EU is the world’s largest exporter of services and is therefore in a strong position to benefit from the opportunities of digital trade. This highlights even more the role the EU should take in shaping the global rules on digital trade.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission, in the Trade for All Communication, stated that the facilitation of digital trade constitutes an important part of EU trade strategy. This should be achieved within a trade and investment policy that is consistent with broader European values. Our digital trade strategy should ensure market access for European companies. It should at the same time ensure and deliver benefits from EU consumers who stand to benefit from a broader choice of products and lower prices, and always respect and fully safeguard the fundamental rights enshrined in the EU Charter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Many of the proposals made in the report concern issues that we already pursue in trade negotiations and that were tabled in the recent negotiations with Mexico and Indonesia. The agreement with Japan can also serve as a good example of the EU’s current approach on digital trade. Just to mention a few concrete examples: we included ambitious rules prohibiting mandatory source code disclosure, consumer trust enhancing rules such as disciplines on consumer protection, electronic trust services, electronic contracts and unsolicited communications such as spam. However, there are areas which will require further work. This will give us an opportunity to follow up, with you, in detail on other issues raised in the report.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards data protection, the Commission made clear in its Communication on exchanging and protecting personal data in a globalised world that protecting personal data goes hand in hand with the promotion of free flows of data. The General Data Protection Regulation equips the EU with numerous tools to facilitate data flows, while ensuring that when the personal data of Europeans are transferred abroad the protection travels along with the data. This includes adequacy decisions, but also contractual arrangements.</p>
      <p sl="en">We certainly take good note of the European Parliament’s position on the issue of data flows. We also took note of the European Council conclusions of October that highlighted the importance of ensuring adequate rules on data flows with third countries in trade agreements without prejudice to EU legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Within the Commission, a dedicated project team on data flows was set up in January. The Commission’s objective is to develop a proposal on how the EU should facilitate trade and tackle protectionist practices abroad, while ensuring that there is no possibility to use trade agreements to challenge existing and future EU legislation on personal data and privacy.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can assure you that when it comes to privacy and personal data in trade agreements, the position of the Commission is crystal clear. Personal data protection is a fundamental right enshrined in Article 8 of the EU Charter of Fundamental Rights. Therefore, trade agreements are not the place to set standards for, or to negotiate on, data protection rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me assure you that your observations and recommendations will be taken into consideration by the Commission so as to develop, in cooperation with the European Parliament, a digital trade strategy for the European Union.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-206-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Președinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votul va avea loc marți, 12 decembrie 2017.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-208-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct pe ordinea de zi sunt intervenții de un minut privind chestiuni politice importante (articolul 163 din Regulamentul de procedură).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-209-0000" speaker_id="124714" name="Andor Deli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the ‘roaming like at home’ rule was one of the most significant success stories of the EU this year. Now we have to take it one step further by expanding it to the Western Balkan candidate states already during the accession negotiations. By cancelling roaming charges, we could reach out to every citizen in the Western Balkan region, proving to them that the EU’s commitment to enlargement is sincere. This would be beneficial to the economies too, through market integration and better services.</p>
      <p sl="en">As we all know, telecommunication and connectivity are the driving forces of development, which is greatly needed in that region. The first bilateral steps have already been taken by Bulgaria, Macedonia and Serbia, but we need a Europe—wide approach. Therefore, I call on the Commission to draw up a special roadmap as soon as possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-210-0000" speaker_id="188624" name="Wajid Khan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, three months ago, I raised the plight of the Rohingya. Today, I speak out again about the atrocities being committed by the Burmese military, which clearly amount to ethnic cleansing and genocide. Myanmar and Bangladesh have recently reached an agreement for the return of the Rohingya to their homes, yet any returns must be voluntary and done under UN peacekeeping supervision. But what would they return to? An apartheid system, an open-air prison and a system of repression with every aspect of their daily lives severely restricted.</p>
      <p sl="en">The world must not stand by in the face of this oppression, and this week’s resolution must demand concerted global action. We must apply maximum pressure on the Burmese military with targeted sanctions against all those involved. The time for rhetoric has finished. We must show the Rohingya community that we stand shoulder to shoulder with their struggle for human rights. The Myanmar Government must be held to account for its actions. We are the hope for our desperate Rohingya brothers and sisters. Let us get justice, dignity and equality for them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-211-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-н Председател, уважаеми колеги, искам да обърна Вашето внимание върху една провокация, която направи за пореден път министър-председателят на Република Турция, това е г-н Ердоган. Той заяви териториални претенции за пореден път над мюсюлманското население в Тракия. Това е изключително нахално, изключително неприемливо, изключително арогантно, защото този човек за пореден път си позволи да иска преначертаване на границите на Балканите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Всички ние, особено Вие, г-н Председател, знаем добре какво означава да се иска преначертаване на границите на Балканите. Това е нещо твърде опасно и твърде нередно. Г-н Ердоган си позволи и си позволява да прави провокации към суверенитета на нашите държави и нашите граници. Ние не можем да позволяваме това, особено когато той прави това в съучастие с външни сили, които са вредни и които са срещу интереса на Европейския съюз на Балканите. Ние трябва да се противопоставим.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-212-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señora comisaria, los conflictos territoriales son peligrosos, generan inestabilidad. La Unión debe prevenirlos protegiendo lo que funciona y denunciando marcos jurídicos y actitudes políticas que vetan el diálogo y la negociación como herramientas de convivencia. Por eso, pido a las instituciones de la Unión su apoyo al Concierto Económico vasco y al Convenio Económico navarro, sistemas centenarios de responsabilidad fiscal constitucionales, respaldados por mayorías cercanas al 90 % en las Cortes Generales, que implican riesgo unilateral y son transparentes, solidarios y eficaces para el desarrollo del autogobierno regional.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los informes anuales de fiscalidad de este Parlamento reiteran que Concierto y Convenio fomentan la responsabilidad fiscal y financiera, previenen el déficit y la corrupción e impulsan actuaciones de profundo contenido social y políticas de apoyo a la economía real que combaten la marginación y generan empleo. Los tribunales de la Unión los consideran plenamente legales por su autonomía institucional, económica y normativa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Impidan que la demagogia, el oportunismo, el más rancio nacionalismo y la irresponsabilidad enfrenten a comunidades y creen problemas de convivencia donde no existen, como acaba de reconocer el presidente del Gobierno de España.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213-0000" speaker_id="124984" name="Lynn Boylan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Jean—Claude Juncker likes to refer to PESCO as the sleeping beauty of Lisbon, but I am not sure exactly what the Commission President finds beautiful about wasting billions of euros of public money on weaponry. I prefer it when he is more up front about his intentions, such as in 2015 when he called for an EU army. PESCO and its references to structured cooperation belie what is really afoot: this is a war alliance – a war alliance dreamed up by imperialist nations like France who are still playing their imperialist games in Africa.</p>
      <p sl="en">In 2008, the Irish people recognised the threat posed by the Lisbon Treaty to their neutrality. They were forced to vote again on the basis that they would have constitutional protection that Ireland would be excluded from any EU common defence programme. Yet here we are in 2017, and the Irish Government has pandered to the EU and its arms industry by joining Ireland up to the PESCO war alliance and committing to increased military expenditure when we have people dying on our streets.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-214-0000" speaker_id="185974" name="Jordi Solé" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last week around 50 000 Catalans demonstrated in Brussels, asking Europe to finally ‘wake up’. Instead of defending fundamental rights and democracy, the EU has preferred to support Rajoy, the leader of one of the most corrupt parties in Europe and also the leader of a government which, among other things, is unable to control public finances, to the extent that it has completely emptied the public pension fund.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am sure that, sooner or later, the European Union will realise how wrong it has been with Catalonia because you simply cannot defend the very idea of Europe and, at the same time, by looking the other way, endorse repression against voters, the jailing of political opponents and the seizing of self—government institutions. Without taking into account the people, their needs and their legitimate aspirations, the European Union has no future. We, the Catalans, love Europe, but we want another European Union.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-215-0000" speaker_id="21817" name="Mario Borghezio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'Unione europea – venendo all'argomento – volta lo sguardo dall'altra parte quando si tratta dei diritti umani del popolo catalano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma io vi voglio parlare di un evento tragico di dieci anni fa a Torino, la mia città: in una fabbrica della ThyssenKrupp sono morti sette operai, sette operai italiani, eroi del lavoro. A distanza di dieci anni i responsabili di quel gravissimo incidente, che non avevano previsto le misure più elementari di sicurezza, solo gli imputati italiani sono stati incarcerati, ma i due maggiori responsabili, i due grandi manager della società tedesca vivono tranquillamente, anzi hanno fatto carriera in Germania nella loro società.</p>
      <p sl="en">Solo qualche settimana fa la Procura di Essen ha iniziato la lunga procedura, ripeto, a distanza di dieci anni. Io chiedo che si intervenga perché la Germania rispetti gli accordi europei in tema di giustizia: chi ha queste responsabilità – ripeto: sono morti sette operai, le loro vedove e i loro figli chiedono giustizia – devono essere incarcerati i responsabili.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-216-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το χτύπημα στο δικαίωμα στην απεργία αποτελεί στρατηγική επιλογή του κεφαλαίου, της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, των κυβερνήσεών της. Αποφάσεις του Ευρωπαϊκού Δικαστηρίου, νόμοι ουσιαστικής υπονόμευσης και στην πράξη κατάργησής του σε χώρες όπως το Βέλγιο, τη Βρετανία, την Ιταλία στρώνουν το έδαφος. Η κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ, στον ίδιο δρόμο, με ράμματα στη γούνα της αμέτρητες δικαστικές αποφάσεις παράνομων και καταχρηστικών απεργιών, εν ισχύ πολιτικές επιστρατεύσεις, ξυλοδαρμούς και συλλήψεις απεργών στηρίζει και ενισχύει την εργοδοτική τρομοκρατία, την αντεργατική επίθεση που φουντώνει, και με τη στήριξη των εργατοπατέρων.</p>
      <p sl="en">Προκειμένου να ικανοποιήσει τις απαιτήσεις του κεφαλαίου δείχνει το φόβο της απέναντι σε κάθε οργανωμένη κινητοποίηση των εργατών. Οι εργαζόμενοι, το ταξικό τους κίνημα υπερασπίζονται το δικαίωμά τους να παλεύουν για το βιος και τις ανάγκες τους. Στις 14 Δεκέμβρη υπερασπιζόμαστε το απεργιακό δικαίωμα με απεργία, έχοντας τη στήριξη και αλληλεγγύη δεκάδων ταξικών συνδικάτων από την Ευρώπη και όλο τον κόσμο. Το χτύπημα στο απεργιακό δικαίωμα δεν θα περάσει.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-217-0000" speaker_id="39726" name="László Tőkés" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">1989. december 15-én, Temesváron vette kezdetét a Ceausescu-diktatúrát megdöntő romániai forradalom.</p>
      <p sl="en">70 éve, 1947 decemberében döntötték meg a román alkotmányos monarchiát, és fosztották meg trónjától, majd űzték el az országból I. Mihály királyt a hatalomra jutó kommunisták. A romániai kommunista uralom kezdetét és végét jelentő két történelmi évforduló szolgáljon memento gyanánt arra nézve, hogy Románia népe szabadságban akar élni, és nem hagyja „ellopni a forradalmát”. Mihály király, az egykori alkotmányos uralkodó mostani halála is erre emlékeztessen bennünket!</p>
      <p sl="en">A romániai magyar közösség osztozik a román nép gyászában és reménységében.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-218-0000" speaker_id="96847" name="Claudiu Ciprian Tănăsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, dragi colegi, în actualul context în care euroscepticismul câștigă teren bazându-se pe lipsa de informare a cetățenilor privind importanța Uniunii Europene, pe mesaje eronate, denaturate, referitoare la rolul instituțiilor europene în viața de zi cu zi a cetățenilor, consider că este important să combatem aceste curente de opinie prin care sunt induse anumite idei deformate, conform cărora toate lucrurile rele sunt dictate de la Bruxelles, statul național și-a pierdut suveranitatea sau că Uniunea Europeană este o construcție menită să distrugă spiritul național.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prin urmare, pentru a avea un succes real în lupta de idei cu cei care doresc dezmembrarea Uniunii Europene, vă supun dezbaterii propunerea de a cere Comisiei Europene adoptarea unor reglementări prin care să introducem, la nivel european, în programa școlară a anilor terminali de colegiu a unei materii despre Uniunea Europeană. Scopul acesteia este o prezentare a instituțiilor europene, a locului și rolului acesteia în societate și în viața de zi cu zi a cetățenilor Uniunii Europene. Personal, consider că, fără o educație în acest sens, noi europenii lăsăm viran un terenul unde sloganurile și discursurile eurosceptice sădesc încet, dar sigur, sămânța neîncrederii în viitorul Uniunii Europene.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-219-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, ο πρόεδρος της Τουρκίας, Ερντογάν, συνεχίζει τις προκλήσεις του κατά της πατρίδας μου της Ελλάδας. Έτσι, χωρίς να σέβεται καν τους κανόνες της διπλωματίας αλλά και της φιλοξενίας, κατά την πρόσφατη επίσκεψή του στην Ελλάδα, ακόμη και εντός του Προεδρικού Μεγάρου, μίλησε για αναθεώρηση της Συνθήκης της Λωζάννης, για γκρίζες ζώνες στο Αιγαίο και για δήθεν τουρκική μειονότητα στη Θράκη μας, στη Θράκη, όπου κατά την επίσκεψή του ήταν ιδιαίτερα προκλητικός.</p>
      <p sl="en">Κι όλα αυτά τη στιγμή που έχουμε αμέτρητες παραβιάσεις του ελληνικού εναέριου χώρου, των ελληνικών χωρικών υδάτων, τη στιγμή που η Τουρκία διατηρεί το casus belli κατά της Ελλάδας, για να αυξήσει τα χωρικά της ύδατα στα δώδεκα μίλια. Mε διαρκείς παρεμβάσεις μου στο Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο έχω κρούσει τον κώδωνα του κινδύνου για τις επικίνδυνες τακτικές της κυβέρνησης Ερντογάν αλλά και για το καθεστώς ατιμωρησίας που διέπει τις σχέσεις Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης-Τουρκίας. Όμως ο ελληνικός λαός δεν ανέχεται τις προκλήσεις της Τουρκίας και του Ερντογάν και για άλλη μια φορά τούς απαντά: «Μολών λαβέ».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-220-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, 22 years ago we stopped the war in Bosnia by pushing a constitution on that country that nobody wanted. This created a country with three presidents, believe it or not 280 ministers, two entities, 10 cantons – and every one of these has a right of veto. The country is obviously impossible to govern and now, 22 years later, one of the main reasons why Bosnia is not to be considered a frontrunner for the coming Commission Strategy for the Western Balkans is the lack of progress, but that lack of progress was created by the constitution we pushed on that country. Nobody wanted it – no Bosniaks, no Serbs, no Croats, no Jews – so it is time to stop pretending. I demand that the Commission include all that country in the coming strategy and not exclude anyone.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-221-0000" speaker_id="124879" name="Janusz Korwin-Mikke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tydzień temu mówiłem w Parlamencie o poczynaniach pana Michała Saakaszwilego, byłego prezydenta Gruzji, na Ukrainie. Nikt się tym nie zainteresował. W międzyczasie pan Saakaszwili znalazł się w więzieniu i nadal dzielnie przemawia przeciwko skorumpowanemu reżimowi na Ukrainie. Chciałbym zauważyć, że my jako Unia Europejska ten reżim wspieramy. Również państwo polskie wspiera ten reżim. A z kolei pan Saakaszwili jest kawalerem Orderu Odrodzenia Polski nadanego mu przez prezydenta Polski. Tak się składa, że im więcej pieniędzy daje się jakiemuś krajowi, tym bardziej rośnie w nim korupcja. Można to zauważyć na przykład w Wietnamie, kiedy Amerykanie popierali Południowy Wietnam, to można zauważyć również, kiedy Amerykanie popierali demokratyczną armię Syrii – jaka tam była korupcja. To samo jest niestety z pieniędzmi dawanymi reżimowi pana Poroszenki. Moja sympatia jest tutaj po stronie pana Saakaszwilego i uważam, że Unia powinna się zainteresować jego losem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-222-0000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last week, with almost zero public debate, the Fine Gael—Fianna Fáil Government signed Ireland up to PESCO. Among the most ludicrous of arguments the proponents asserted was that we needed to sell off Irish neutrality in order to show support for the EU and its values. Since when did increasing national defence budgets, creating new military capabilities, fuelling the arms industry and compromising respect for human rights and democracy become core values of the European Union? It is no coincidence that this military push is taking place, concurrently but entirely separately, to discussions on the future of Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Has democracy in the European Union become such a farce that the response to growing disenchantment is to do exactly what was always intended, only quicker and with even less oversight than was originally envisaged? Citizens want an EU that delivers for them, their families, their communities and their countries. There is no evidence that they want EU military expansion.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-223-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doresc în această seară să aduc în atenția Parlamentului European situația inadmisibilă a unei instituții din România prin care se derulează fonduri europene pentru agricultură, respectiv Agenția de Intervenție și Plăți pentru Agricultură.</p>
      <p sl="en">Funcționarii acestei instituții denunță politica salarială a guvernului PSD-ALDE, în condițiile în care urmează ca de la 1 ianuarie 2018 să aibă loc o scădere a salariului cu sume de pana la 500 de euro. Nemulțumirile sunt generate și de diferențele salariale dintre aparatul central și cel teritorial, unde salariile ar urma să fie mult mai mici, cu toate că aceștia sunt cei care procesează dosarele fermierilor, desfășurând practic cea mai grea activitate. În același timp, existența unor diferențe salariale față de alte instituții care derulează fonduri europene pentru agricultură generează o situație profund inechitabilă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Atrag atenția Ministrului Agriculturii și premierului Mihai Tudose că România oricum este deficitară la capitolul absorbției fondurilor europene, iar nemulțumirile din acest sector pot duce la blocarea plăților pentru fermieri, cu consecințe incomensurabile pentru agricultorii din România.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-224-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Christmas rush is coming and in some ways it felt a bit like Santa’s grotto, with people busily packing up parcels, when I visited the Norwich food bank on Friday. But the cheerful staff, volunteers and generous-hearted donors cannot mask that it is deeply shocking that 114 879 boxes of three-day emergency food supplies were given out in my constituency last year. That is a 13.8% increase in food bank use in the East of England. It should not have to be like this. With Christmas around the corner, the school holidays and the cold snap sending energy bills up, Norwich’s food bank coordinator told me that she expects a spike in demand, with over 1 000 parcels of food needed this December from the city’s food bank. The Europe 2020 Strategy shows that the EU takes fighting food poverty seriously. Our government must too, to make sure that nobody goes hungry this Christmas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-225-0000" speaker_id="113959" name="Martina Anderson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Sunday, 10 December marks International Human Rights Day, and whilst rights are being exercised, they are being violated too. In the north of Ireland, rights enshrined in the Good Friday Agreement and subsequent agreements remain outstanding; rights for Irish language speakers, for our LGB&amp;T brothers and sisters, for families of victims of the conflict awaiting inquests, are all under attack. Ireland remains the only Member State yet to ratify the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, and the basic right to a home is wilfully ignored as 3 000 children are homeless across Ireland tonight.</p>
      <p sl="en">Brexit threatens to rip the north of Ireland out of the EU, away from the European Court of Justice and its protections. Britain has torn up the Charter of Fundamental Rights and wants to dilute access to the Convention. The letter today to An Taoiseach, signed by 200 admired citizens, calls for an equality and human rights based society in the here and now and post-Brexit. An Taoiseach, their call should not be ignored or dismissed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-226-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani komisárka, tento Parlament zastupuje hlas občanov zo všetkých členských štátov Európskej únie. Zastupuje záujmy tých, ktorí od Únie očakávajú ochranu, tých, ktorí s jej existenciou spájajú prosperitu, aj tých, ktorí v nej vidia garanciu príležitostí pre svoje deti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vianoce sú však príležitosťou myslieť viac aj na tých, ktorým chudoba bráni v realizácii ich občianskych práv. Je našou povinnosťou zastupovať aj ich, pretože tento Parlament má byť aj ich hlasom. Len vtedy sa zo spoločenstva európskych štátov stane skutočné spoločenstvo všetkých európskych občanov.</p>
      <p sl="en">V tomto zmysle by som chcela popriať, nielen vám, pán predseda a pani komisárka, kolegom a kolegyniam, ale aj všetkým občanom Európskej únie, milostiplné a požehnané Vianoce a všetko dobré do nového roku 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-227-0000" speaker_id="129256" name="Emilian Pavel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamna comisar, dragi colegi, în data de 1 decembrie, cu ocazia Zilei Naționale a României, am aniversat 99 de ani de la decizia istorică a românilor din Transilvania de a se uni cu țara-mamă. Astfel, anul viitor, la fel ca și alte state membre ale Uniunii Europene, vom sărbători împreună centenarul. Acest lucru a fost posibil și datorită sacrificiului soldaților români din primul război mondial, dar și datorită faptului că, încă de atunci, românii s-au luptat pentru un set de valori ce stau și astăzi la baza Uniunii Europene. În rezoluția adoptată în 1918 în prezența a peste o sută de mii de participanți, românii din Transilvania cereau cu tărie drepturi sociale pentru muncitori, dreptul minorităților la educație, religie și reprezentare politică, inclusiv libertatea presei, democrație și vot direct și egal pentru femei și bărbați.</p>
      <p sl="en">Astăzi, la aproape o sută de ani de la acel moment, vreau să salut din Parlamentul European faptul că România este pe deplin integrată în Europa, iar valorile promovate, încă de acum un secol, de bună conviețuire, toleranță și libertate, sunt cu adevărat fundamentul proiectului nostru european.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-228-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a decisão dos Estados Unidos da América de reconhecimento de Jerusalém como capital de Israel constitui uma violação do direito internacional, uma agressão ao martirizado povo palestiniano e uma provocação aos povos árabes, com consequências perigosas e imprevisíveis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma decisão que não pode ser desligada da escalada de tensão em curso no Médio Oriente, das medidas e ameaças dirigidas contra o Irão e o Líbano, das agressões militares de Israel em território sírio, dos conflitos fomentados pela Arábia Saudita, do anúncio da constituição de uma NATO do Médio Oriente: um quadro de degradação generalizada da situação que é fomentado pelos setores mais aventureiros e belicistas do imperialismo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na hora da condenação desta inaceitável provocação reafirmamos a nossa solidariedade com o povo palestiniano, com a sua legítima e heroica luta pelo direito à constituição de um Estado soberano e viável nas fronteiras anteriores a 67 e com capital em Jerusalém Leste e pelo direito de regresso dos refugiados palestinianos vítimas da política israelita de expansão e ocupação da Palestina.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-229-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, včera jsme si připomněli Mezinárodní den lidských práv, který je vzpomínkou na přijetí Všeobecné deklarace lidských práv v prosinci roku 1948. Bylo to v době, kdy ve východní Evropě již začínala tuhá totalita a lidská práva byla brutálně pošlapána.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nyní se přes všechny problémy naše společnost těší svobodě a ochraně lidských práv, které v těchto zemích Evropské unie neměly obdoby. Dnes je tomu přesně sto let, co byla udělena Nobelova cena míru organizaci Červený kříž. Stalo se tak symbolicky uprostřed válečného běsnění první světové války. Lidská práva a mír jsou největší hodnoty, které v Evropě máme. Málo si to uvědomujeme a málo si toho vážíme. Mír není samozřejmostí, musíme jej aktivně bránit tváří v tvář šířícímu se radikalismu a nacionalismu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bohužel lidská práva jsou na mnoha místech ve světě masivně pošlapávána diktátorskými režimy a válkami. Evropa je kolébkou lidských práv a Evropská unie je největší mírový projekt v dějinách. Buďme na to patřičně hrdí! Snažme se toto dědictví uchovat a šířit, nikoliv jako náš import, ale jako inspiraci pro smíření ostatních, třeba pro Blízký východ.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-230-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, amidst chaotic negotiations, Theresa May has chased a hard Brexit at any cost, threatening a complete breakaway from the institutions and programmes that have played a significant role in supporting our growing cultural economy for the past 50 years. Liverpool and Glasgow have been past British recipients of the coveted European Capital of Culture title with Liverpool, in my region, generating a staggering return of GBP 750 million to the local economy from GBP 170 million of spending. But, more importantly, the capital of culture years fostered a real sense of civic pride with a meaningful legacy for the people living in the city and surrounding areas.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is a great shame that the disastrous Tory—led Brexit has now ruined the chances of UK cities accessing the opportunity to regenerate through culture and specifically the Capital of Culture programme, especially as some had spent up to GBP 500 000 to complete their bids. The EU’s decision not to include the UK in the programme is a huge blow for our pro-European cities and the wider arts community. However, the greatest loss for our creative and cultural industries will be the loss of freedom of movement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-231-0000" speaker_id="189490" name="Răzvan Popa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, dragi colegi, Comisia Europeană a recomandat trecerea la faza a doua a negocierilor cu Marea Britanie, constatând că au existat evoluții pozitive în discuțiile dintre cele două părți, mai ales în ceea ce privește protejarea drepturilor cetățenilor europeni din Regatul Unit. Românii din Marea Britanie, ca și toți cetățenii europeni care trăiesc în Regatul Unit, trebuie să primească un răspuns clar și garanții ferme, după o perioadă dominată de temeri și incertitudini, cu privire la statutul lor în perioada post Brexit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi trebuie să fim vocea lor în Parlamentul European în cadrul etapelor care vor urma până la încheierea negocierilor, să le susținem interesele și să ne asigurăm că toate detaliile acordului final sunt în avantajul lor. Brexit este un moment-test pentru Uniunea Europeană, iar modul în care drepturile cetățenilor europeni sunt apărate în acest caz poate consolida încrederea oamenilor în proiectul european sau, dimpotrivă, o poate slăbi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-232-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Acest punct de pe ordinea de zi a fost închis.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Agenda of the next sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
