<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20171023.EN" lang="en" date="2017-10-23" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro ripresa la sessione del Parlamento europeo interrotta giovedì 5 ottobre 2017.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Statement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Prima di dare inizio alla seduta odierna vorrei ricordare le vittime degli incendi boschivi che si sono verificati in Portogallo e in Spagna nelle scorse settimane. Come ho avuto modo di dire nel corso del mio intervento dinanzi al Consiglio europeo, il fenomeno è preoccupante e merita tutta la nostra attenzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Solo quest'anno, in Europa sono andati in fumo più di 750 000 ettari delle nostre foreste e più di 100 persone hanno perso la vita nel solo Portogallo. Per questo sono convinto della necessità e dell'urgenza di istituire un corpo di protezione civile europeo e di semplificare il contesto normativo, al fine di permettere alle popolazioni di ottenere un aiuto immediato in caso di bisogno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi informo anche della decisione che abbiamo preso, di comune accordo con il Presidente Tusk e il Presidente Juncker, di devolvere alle popolazioni colpite dagli incendi boschivi la somma di denaro del premio "Principessa delle Asturie" per la concordia, assegnato quest'anno all'Unione europea, premio che ho avuto l'onore di ritirare venerdì scorso a Oviedo. Questo è un modo simbolico di manifestare la nostra vicinanza a quelle comunità e alle famiglie delle numerose vittime in Portogallo e in Spagna, in ricordo delle quali vi propongo di osservare ora un minuto di silenzio, durante il quale commemoreremo anche le vittime irlandesi dell'uragano Ophelia.</p>
      <a text="(Il Parlamento, in piedi, osserva un minuto di silenzio)"/>
      <p sl="en">Desidero altresì informare l'Aula che domani, prima del voto, avrà luogo un minuto di silenzio in memoria della giornalista maltese Daphne Caruana Galizia, barbaramente uccisa la settimana scorsa in un attentato. Svolgeremo questa brevissima cerimonia domani, perché domani saranno presenti in Aula i familiari della vittima, che ho invitato: loro hanno accettato e saranno presenti in tribuna.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Composition of Parliament : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Election of a Vice-President of the European Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Verification of credentials : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Signature of acts adopted under the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 78): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Decision on the opening of interinstitutional negotiations (Rule 69(c)): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Delegated acts (Rule 105(6)): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Action taken on Parliament’s resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Major interpellations (Rule 130b) (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-022-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Passiamo ora alle modifiche all'ordine dei lavori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-0000" speaker_id="124791" name="Daniele Viotti" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mi dispiace interrompere, ma le notizie di queste ultime ore riportano che un giudice a Teheran ha condannato a morte Ahmadreza Djalali, un professore universitario che insegna all'Università di Stoccolma e all'Università di Torino, in Italia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ci siamo già occupati in questo Parlamento del caso del professore Djalali, perché abbiamo firmato una lettera insieme a moltissimi parlamentari per chiedere l'intervento del presidente della Repubblica islamica dell'Iran perché non si intervenisse in questo processo, che è un processo pieno di ombre in cui il professore è accusato soltanto di essere, in qualche modo, collaboratore di potenze straniere nemiche.</p>
      <p sl="en">È un caso gravissimo; è stata emessa la condanna nei giorni scorsi e io chiedo a Lei di usare tutta l'influenza che può avere per capire cosa sta succedendo e per fermare questo ennesimo scempio alla democrazia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">On. Viotti, Lei sa che per l'Unione europea la lotta contro la pena di morte in tutto il mondo rappresenta una priorità, quindi farò tutto ciò che è in mio potere non soltanto per avere informazioni, ma anche per chiedere al presidente della Repubblica islamica dell'Iran di sospendere l'esecuzione del professore e quindi di fare in modo che non ci sia un'altra esecuzione nel mondo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-0000" speaker_id="124971" name="James Carver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, you quite rightly called the House to order with regard to taking a minute’s silence. Could I ask the Parliament to put my remarks on record. Perhaps you would like to join me in sending condolences to the 300 victims of an al—Shabaab terrorist bomb in Mogadishu in Somalia and to many, many hundreds of victims. Perhaps that could be added to the record of the Parliament.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Assolutamente sì, on. Carver, il Parlamento europeo si è sempre espresso contro il terrorismo. Ricordiamo le vittime non soltanto quando sono europee, ma vittime del terrorismo in tutto il mondo. Quindi mi associo alla sua osservazione: sarà sicuramente messa a verbale – credo a nome di tutto quanto il Parlamento – l'espressione di condanna per quanto successo a Mogadiscio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il progetto definitivo di ordine del giorno, fissato dalla Conferenza dei presidenti, ai sensi dell'articolo 149 del regolamento, nella riunione di giovedì 19 ottobre 2017 è stato distribuito. Sono state presentate le seguenti proposte di modifica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lunedì: nessuna richiesta di modifica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Martedì: il gruppo Verts/ALE ha richiesto di aggiungere una risoluzione a conclusione della discussione sulla dichiarazione della Commissione sulla lotta alle molestie e agli abusi sessuali nell'Unione europea, da votare durante questa tornata. Do la parola all'on. Ska Keller per formulare la richiesta del suo gruppo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-027-0000" speaker_id="96734" name="Ska Keller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we are going to discuss cases of sexual harassment, and, as you have surely seen, we also have reports about cases of sexual harassment happening inside the European institutions, including inside Parliament. So it is really important that we have a debate about it, but it is not enough just to talk about it. We should also put in writing what we are going to do about it – we as the European Union and as the European institutions – so that we commit ourselves to changing this horrible situation. We cannot and will not accept such harassment in this Parliament or elsewhere in the European Union.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-0000" speaker_id="28266" name="Sophia in ’t Veld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, my Group has two requests relating to the same topic. First of all, we feel that, given the scale of the debate around the world on this topic, it should have a more prominent place on the agenda this week. We suggest that, rather than discussing it late on Tuesday night, we discuss it on Wednesday morning.</p>
      <p sl="de">The second request – and Ska Keller has already referred to an article in Politico about harassment inside the EU institutions – is that, before the next part-session, you report to us first of all about what the situation is, and secondly, what measures you are going to take to make sure that it does not happen, that when it does happen people actually have somebody to turn to, and that there are procedures for tackling this.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-029-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Andiamo per ordine. Prima dobbiamo decidere se aggiungere una risoluzione a conclusione della discussione sulla lotta alle molestie e agli abusi sessuali all'interno dell'Unione, cioè la proposta dell'on. Ska Keller. Poi ci sarà la proposta dell'on. in 't Veld di cambiare la data. Ma prima dobbiamo decidere il contenuto, poi decideremo la data. Terza cosa, le rispondo direttamente, senza aspettare la prossima tornata.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'è qualcuno che vuole parlare contro la proposta dell'on. Ska Keller? No.</p>
      <p sl="en">La richiesta è posta in votazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">La richiesta è approvata. Quindi la discussione sulla dichiarazione della Commissione sulla lotta alle molestie e agli abusi sessuali nell'Unione sarà conclusa da una risoluzione, da votare durante questa tornata.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'on. in 't Veld ha chiesto di cambiare l'ordine del giorno e invertire il quinto punto di martedì con la discussione sulla protezione dei lavoratori contro i rischi derivanti da un'esposizione ad agenti cancerogeni o mutageni, che è prevista per mercoledì mattina. Ha chiesto cioè di avere la discussione sugli abusi sessuali il mercoledì, e di tenere invece il martedì sera la discussione sulla protezione dei lavoratori contro i rischi derivanti da un'esposizione ad agenti cancerogeni o mutageni.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'è qualcuno che è contrario a questo cambiamento? Prego, on. Rodrigues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="124737" name="Maria João Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we prefer to keep the order as it is because the Ulvskog report is also very important. Of course we know that this debate is crucial for us but we do not agree to change the order.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Votiamo la proposta dell'on. in 't Veld.</p>
      <p sl="en">La proposta è approvata.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="28229" name="Manfred Weber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Die Kollegin Keller hat zu Recht darauf hingewiesen, dass wir in den letzten Tagen Medienberichte hatten, dass es auch im Haus Vorfälle gegeben hat. Ich möchte deswegen bitten, dass sich das Präsidium des Parlaments mit dieser Frage beschäftigt. Die Vorgänge müssen umgehend geklärt werden und ob es dazu Punkte gibt. Wir haben interne Strukturen, und wir können im Parlament nicht dulden, dass es zu sexuellem Missbrauch in irgendeiner Form kommt.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-0000" speaker_id="124737" name="Maria João Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we are delighted and, of course, we also support this request made directly to the President in the Chamber.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-0000" speaker_id="124947" name="Edouard Martin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, je rejoins l’idée qui est défendue. Néanmoins, vu la gravité des faits qui se produisent, y compris ici, je trouve – et cela fera l’objet du débat de mercredi matin, cela figurera dans nos propositions et j’interviendrai en ce sens – qu’on ne peut pas être juge et partie en même temps. Dès lors, l’idée que je défendrai mercredi matin dans mon intervention sera de faire réaliser une étude par un cabinet extérieur, de manière à cerner exactement la réalité des faits, en toute objectivité. C’était le but de ma demande.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Risponderò poi alle sollecitazioni degli onn. in 't Veld, Weber e Martin.</p>
      <p sl="en">La dichiarazione della Commissione sulla lotta alle molestie e agli abusi sessuali nell'Unione di martedì pomeriggio è scambiata con la discussione sulla protezione dei lavoratori contro i rischi derivanti da un'esposizione ad agenti cancerogeni o mutageni, attualmente prevista per mercoledì mattina, e ci sarà una risoluzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda le sollecitazioni che sono venute dagli onn. in 't Veld, Weber e Martin, il 14 aprile 2014 l'Ufficio di presidenza ha istituito un comitato consultivo per le denunce di molestie riguardanti assistenti parlamentari accreditati, da un lato, e deputati al Parlamento europeo, dall'altro. Il comitato ha due funzioni principali: prevenire qualsiasi comportamento di mobbing da parte dei deputati nei confronti di assistenti parlamentari accreditati e assistere il Presidente nel quadro di eventuali indagini.</p>
      <p sl="en">La procedura interna per la risoluzione dei problemi di mobbing viene avviata a seguito di una denuncia formale di molestia psicologica o sessuale presentata da un assistente contro un deputato. Il comitato, dopo aver ascoltato l'assistente parlamentare, decide di avviare un'indagine se ci sono prove sufficienti. Le due parti sono invitate a presentare prove a sostegno delle rispettive posizioni. Al termine dell'indagine, il comitato trasmette le sue raccomandazioni al Presidente, che adotta una decisione. Tale decisione può consistere in una sanzione, ai sensi dell'articolo 166 del regolamento, mettendo l'Aula del Parlamento a conoscenza dei fatti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aggiungo che anche un assistente fa parte del comitato.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'è poi un altro comitato che si occupa dei problemi che riguardano i funzionari.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aggiungo inoltre che il comitato ha inviato l'anno scorso, a tutti i parlamentari, una documentazione, direi un volume, per combattere le pressioni e le molestie di tipo sessuale e non. È una guida che è stata inviata a tutti i deputati con i nomi, altresì, dei membri che fanno parte del comitato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa sera naturalmente informerò il Bureau, l'Ufficio di presidenza del Parlamento, per valutare tutte le iniziative in proposito; ascolterò il Questore Morin-Chartier, che ha la responsabilità di guidare questo gruppo, per avere tutte le informazioni necessarie. Naturalmente chi ha subito molestie di questo tipo deve rivolgersi, come è previsto dalle nostre regole, a questo comitato che farà tutte le indagini necessarie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Essendoci un comitato presieduto da un Questore eletto dalla Plenaria, non credo che debbano esserci, vista la sovranità del Parlamento, inchieste da affidare ad esterni. Le inchieste le deve fare il comitato ad hoc, presieduto da un Questore eletto dal Parlamento, e di questo comitato fa parte anche un assistente parlamentare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi tutto quello che si dovrà fare sarà fatto. È inaccettabile che accadano vicende di questo tipo, mi auguro che siano limitatissime all'interno del Parlamento. Poi vedremo la quantità delle persone, ma fino adesso non abbiamo un numero così elevato di denunce. Però anche se fosse un solo caso sarebbe, per quanto mi riguarda, inaccettabile.</p>
      <p sl="en">Già ho detto in passato, quando ho dovuto prendere una decisione disciplinare nei confronti di un nostro collega, qual è la mia opinione sul ruolo delle donne nella società europea, quindi da questo punto di vista sarò inflessibile nell'infliggere sanzioni durissime nei confronti di parlamentari che avessero violato il nostro codice e le nostre regole.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mercoledì: il gruppo Verts/ALE ha chiesto che la discussione congiunta sul sistema di ingressi/uscite, attualmente prevista per mercoledì mattina, sia rinviata a una tornata ulteriore.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-0000" speaker_id="96734" name="Ska Keller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to ask that we postpone this vote because the European Court of Justice decided in July that the Passenger Data Agreement with Canada cannot be concluded, and one of the main reasons was illegal data retention. The court made clear that data about European travellers cannot, in general, be retained for years by Canadian authorities. But now, with the entry/exit system, we would actually retain for years the personal data of Canadians coming to Europe – i.e. we would be doing exactly the same to our counterparts, and I really do not see how we could explain that to our Canadian partners.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, we have requested an independent legal analysis of the implications of the court decision, which we will publish tomorrow. That study says clearly that the entry/exit system poses serious problems because the data retention periods are far too long and not justifiable, and because rules on access by law-enforcement agencies are not specific enough – and I think that we as Parliament should not adopt EU legislation that will likely be struck down again by the Court.</p>
      <p sl="en">At the very least, we would ask for help to postpone the vote until we can have more legal expertise on the matter and study it carefully. Therefore, we propose to postpone the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="28397" name="Agustín Díaz de Mera García Consuegra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor Presidente. En mi propio nombre, y en nombre de mi Grupo, rechazo esta pretensión del Grupo de los Verdes, por muchas y muy importantes razones, pero fundamentalmente por tres.</p>
      <p sl="en">En primer lugar, porque el Reglamento contiene un robusto sistema de protección de datos. El señor Buttarelli —el supervisor europeo de protección de datos — es garante de la correcta utilización, retención, tratamiento y almacenamiento de los datos. Así se contempla en el Reglamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">En segundo lugar, los servicios jurídicos de las tres instituciones —Servicio Jurídico del Consejo, de la Comisión y del Parlamento— han dicho, verbalmente y por escrito y también a petición del Grupo de los Verdes, han dicho categóricamente que el dictamen1/15, que se refiere al PNR Unión Europea-Canadá, no tiene ningún impacto sobre el Reglamento por el que se establece un Sistema de Entradas y Salidas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, en tercer lugar y muy importante. Recordarán todos con dolor —y sobre todo los colegas alemanes— que hubo un ataque terrorista contra el mercado navideño de Berlín. Pues bien, quiero decirles que el agresor, el terrorista, utilizó quince identidades diferentes. Si hubiese estado en vigor el Reglamento por el que se establece un Sistema de Entradas y Salidas, esto nunca hubiese sido posible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por tanto, señorías, les ruego que el miércoles pasemos a debatir y, en su caso, a votar el Reglamento por el que se establece un Sistema de Entradas y Salidas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pongo in votazione la richiesta del gruppo Verts/ALE, che chiede di rinviare la discussione sul sistema di ingressi/uscite, prevista per mercoledì mattina, ad una tornata ulteriore.</p>
      <p sl="en">La richiesta è respinta, quindi l'ordine del giorno rimane immutato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mercoledì: il gruppo GUE/NGL ha chiesto di modificare l'ordine del giorno delle discussioni di mercoledì come segue: le dichiarazioni del Consiglio e della Commissione sui meccanismi di risposta agli incendi boschivi nella Spagna settentrionale e in Portogallo saranno il primo punto di mercoledì pomeriggio, prima della discussione su tematiche di attualità.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, já que hoje teve ocasião de prestar tributo às vítimas dos incêndios em Portugal e teve ocasião de assinalar como esta é uma questão da maior importância – e é, de facto –, perante estas tragédias, perante estas catástrofes, importa discutir não apenas o apoio que é necessário mobilizar, no imediato, para prestar às vítimas e às suas famílias, mas também discutir um quadro apropriado para a prevenção deste tipo de catástrofes ao nível europeu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este é um assunto que, por conseguinte, não diz respeito apenas aos dois Estados que, na semana passada, mais diretamente foram afetados pelos incêndios – é uma questão que diz respeito a todos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Atendendo à importância do assunto – que o senhor mesmo sublinhou, e muito bem –, aquilo que pretendíamos era dar uma visibilidade e uma projeção a este debate que colocá-lo às dez da noite ou às onze da noite de quarta-feira não garante e, portanto, daí a proposta que fazemos de o alterar para primeiro ponto da ordem dos trabalhos da parte da tarde, ou seja, às três da tarde.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="125025" name="Marcel de Graaff" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, natuurlijk is het verschrikkelijk wanneer er mensen bij een bosbrand omkomen, maar hier is volgens mij toch sprake van een staaltje slappe symboolpolitiek. Ik heb de GUE/NGL-Fractie niet gehoord toen het ging over de verschrikkelijke aardbeving in Italië – die u toch ook persoonlijk aan het hart moet gaan. Maar nu het hierover gaat en wij toevallig het onderwerp voor het actualiteitendebat hebben ingebracht, moet het opeens verschoven worden en moet daar opeens een ander debat vóór geplaatst worden. Het is hier in dit Huis de gewoonte dat actualiteitendebatten als eerste aan de orde komen op de woensdagmiddag en ik zou u willen vragen deze gewoonte te respecteren. Ik weet dat er hier parlementariërs zijn die zich vergrijpen aan hun eigen assistenten – een stuitend gebrek aan respect voor de medemens. Ook hier in dit voorstel herken ik een dergelijk gebrek aan respect. Ik hoop dat we allen tegen stemmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pongo in votazione la richiesta dell'on. Ferreira, a nome del gruppo GUE/NGL, di cambiare l'ordine del giorno e anticipare al primo punto di mercoledì pomeriggio la discussione sugli incendi boschivi in Portogallo e in Spagna.</p>
      <p sl="en">La richiesta è respinta, quindi l'ordine del giorno non viene modificato.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'ordine dei lavori è così fissato.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. CE marked fertilising products (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la relazione di Mihai Ţurcanu, a nome della commissione per il mercato interno e la protezione dei consumatori, sulla proposta di regolamento del Parlamento europeo e del Consiglio che stabilisce norme relative alla messa a disposizione sul mercato di prodotti fertilizzanti recanti la marcatura CE e che modifica i regolamenti (CE) n. 1069/2009 e (CE) n. 1107/2009 (COM(2016)0157 - C8-0123/2016 - 2016/0084(COD)) (A8-0270/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="131750" name="Mihai Ţurcanu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raportor. – Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, distinși colegi, proiectul de regulament care stabilește normele referitoare la produsele fertilizante cu marcaj european își propune să îmbunătățească actuala legislație în domeniu. Permiteți—mi, vă rog, să vă prezint câteva argumente care m-au făcut să cred în acest raport.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vreau să precizez, în primul rând, faptul că acest regulament face parte din propunerea Comisiei privind economia circulară. Va impacta pozitiv toate țările Uniunii Europene, iar beneficiile aduse se răsfrâng în mai multe domenii de activitate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sectorul economic, în primul rând, este un bun motor prin care industria de profil este stimulată să devină mai competitivă. Printre obiectivele notabile ale acestui cadru legislativ este faptul că se va extinde sfera de produse fertilizante la cele obținute din materii prime secundare. Se vor reduce sarcinile administrative pe care le au producătorii, iar etichetarea va fi mai clară și mai cuprinzătoare.</p>
      <p sl="en">De cealaltă parte, consumatorul, cel pe care dorim să îl protejăm, va avea parte de produse mai sigure. Dorim ca prezența metalelor grele și a contaminanților în produsele fertilizante să fie în limite care nu pun în pericol sănătatea omului.</p>
      <p sl="en">Doresc să subliniez faptul că, în calitate de raportor, am făcut eforturi pentru a obține un consens cât mai larg, în ciuda pozițiilor contradictorii care persistă între țările Uniunii Europene pe această temă. Este datoria noastră să oferim consumatorului european produse alimentare sigure pentru sănătate și la un preț rezonabil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Doresc să fac o trecere în revistă și a principalelor prevederi ale propunerii, și anume faptul că propunerea va permite tuturor produselor fertilizante, inclusiv celor derivate din deșeuri biologice și nutrienți reciclați, să beneficieze de marcajul CE, care să asigure libera circulație pe piața unică. Se vor introduce noi cerințe armonizate pentru toate produsele fertilizante cu marcaj CE în ceea ce privește calitatea, siguranța și etichetarea. De asemenea, vorbim despre norme noi privind libera circulație a tuturor fertilizanților cu marcaje CE. Se va menține o armonizare opțională; spre exemplu, un producător care nu dorește ca produsul său să aibă marcajul CE, dar să aibă acces nelimitat la întreaga piață unică a UE, poate opta pentru respectarea normelor naționale, în conformitate cu principiul subsidiarității.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am avut consultări cu reprezentanții delegațiilor naționale și grupurilor politice, am discutat cu exponenți ai industriei îngrășămintelor chimice ai statelor membre, precum și ai unor țări exportatoare de materie primă către Uniunea Europeană.</p>
      <p sl="en">Marți, dumneavoastră sunteți chemați să vă pronunțați prin vot asupra mai multor propuneri de limite ale concentrației maxime admise de cadmiu. Vă rog să aveți în vedere necesitatea reglementării cât mai urgente în acest domeniu, precum și nevoia industriei de profil de a avea timpul necesar pentru a se adapta la noile standarde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dragi colegi, nu avem dreptul să închidem peste noapte fabrici, să lăsăm fără loc de muncă mii de oameni. Nu avem dreptul să-i condamnăm pe fermierii europeni să cumpere produse fertilizante la prețuri care îi păgubesc. Dar nici nu putem permite în continuare ca solul și, implicit, agricultura europeană să evolueze haotic și nesustenabil, cu riscuri pentru siguranța noastră și a celorlalți consumatori.</p>
      <p sl="en">Iată de ce consider că este necesară stabilirea, încă de la intrarea în vigoare a viitorului regulament, a unui nivel precis de cadmiu admis. De asemenea, trebuie să fim conștienți de faptul că este nevoie de un interval rezonabil de implementare. Cred în profesionalismul colegilor mei și doresc să ne armonizăm pozițiile pentru a putea să ne prezentăm cu fruntea sus în fața propriilor alegători.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dragi colegi, dincolo de acest punct asupra căruia știu că mulți dintre dumneavoastră se vor pronunța în continuare, doresc să precizez faptul că raportul este, în mare măsură, rezultatul muncii depuse de precedentul titular al dosarului, doamna Gáll-Pelcz, până în momentul în care a părăsit Parlamentul European. Îi mulțumesc pentru efort. Le mulțumesc și colegilor care au contribuit cu sugestii și propuneri, în special domnului Andreas Schwab, pentru aportul său consistent în calitate de coordonator PPE în Comisia pentru piața internă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Închei făcând apel la susținerea dumneavoastră, mai ales că vor urma negocieri cu Consiliul European. Avem nevoie, în perspectiva acestora, de un mandat cât mai solid din partea forului europarlamentar. Vă mulțumesc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="58758" name="Elisabetta Gardini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatrice per parere della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, anch'io sono qui a testimoniare un lavoro che è stato laborioso, lungo e complesso. Questo regolamento l'abbiamo salutato con grande favore, perché va a ricomprendere sotto il marchio CE un vasto campo di fertilizzanti che prima ne rimanevano esclusi, però abbiamo anche alcune preoccupazioni. Noi, come commissione Ambiente, avevamo la competenza esclusiva per quanto riguarda i contaminanti e il punto su cui abbiamo più dibattuto è stato sicuramente quello del cadmio, come ha ricordato già il relatore Ţurcanu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le mie preoccupazioni sono molto vive perché anche nei fact sheet della Commissione si valuta che già andare a un limite di 40 milligrammi richiederebbe grandi sforzi e maggiori investimenti in tecnologie, eccetera eccetera, ma la stessa Commissione riconosce in questi documenti che andare addirittura a 20 milligrammi, come ha proposto la Commissione e come ha confermato anche la commissione Ambiente, comporterebbe tali e maggiori investimenti nella decadmiazione e probabilmente, addirittura, necessiterebbe di un riassetto generale del mercato dei fertilizzanti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo io credo che la prudenza sia importante e che forse sia giusto darci un po' di tempo per riflettere, considerando che già a partire da 60 milligrammi siamo a metà del limite più basso che troviamo nel mondo. Voi lo sapete, dai 120 ai 150-160 parliamo di Stati Uniti, parliamo di Canada, parliamo di Australia: non parliamo certo di paesi che non hanno a cuore l'ambiente. Quindi mi unisco all'appello del relatore Ţurcanu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="58789" name="Jan Huitema" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur voor advies van de Commissie landbouw en plattelandsontwikkeling. – Beste commissaris, geachte collega's, de moderne landbouw is in staat om met ecologische en technologische innovaties oplossingen te bieden voor klimaatverandering, een beter milieu en meer biodiversiteit. Daarvoor is het nodig om Europese regelgeving aan te passen. Door verouderde wetgeving is een boer bijvoorbeeld beperkt in het bemesten van zijn land met dierlijke mest, afkomstig van zijn eigen bedrijf. Het overschot aan dierlijke mest moet hij afvoeren. Om toch aan de bemestingsbehoeften van zijn gewas te voldoen, koopt hij kunstmest. De wereld op zijn kop. De boer moet zoveel mogelijk zijn eigen meststoffen kunnen gebruiken in plaats van kunstmest te kopen. Ter vergelijking jaarlijks importeren we 6 miljoen ton aan fosfaatkunstmest, terwijl we 2 miljoen ton fosfaat zouden kunnen terugwinnen uit organische bronnen, zoals mest en afvalstromen. Deze kringloop moeten we sluiten. Het milieu wordt daarmee minder belast en de uitstoot van broeikasgassen verminderd. Gelukkig wil de Europese Commissie dit mogelijk maken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarnaast kan fosfaatkunstmest het kankerverwekkende cadmium bevatten. Dat is een groot risico voor ons milieu en de voedselveiligheid dat we niet kunnen toestaan. Ik stem daarom voor strenge cadmiumlimieten in kunstmest. Argumenten vanuit de industrie dat de prijs van kunstmest drastisch zal toenemen en de boeren het gelag betalen, is bangmakerij en door landbouweconomen tegengesproken. Sterker nog, het omgekeerde is waar. Ik wil niet dat boeren over een aantal jaar worden bestempeld als milieucriminelen, omdat er cadmium gevonden wordt in de bodem, of erger nog, in ons voedsel. Omdat ze meststoffen gebruiken die voldoen aan Europese regels, Europese regels die wij hier vandaag met elkaar maken. Bovendien biedt een nieuwe meststoffenverordening voldoende mogelijkheden voor alternatieven. Met de nieuwe meststoffenverordening komt er namelijk eindelijk meer ruimte voor organische meststoffen om te kunnen concurreren met kunstmest.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all I would like to express my thanks to Parliament for its strong support for the proposed Fertilising Products Regulation. In particular, I thank the rapporteur and shadow rapporteurs for all their valuable input.</p>
      <p sl="en">The regulation is in many ways ground-breaking and also very complex. Being here today gives me a chance to recall its core principles. First of all, with regard to the potential of the circular economy, the proposed regulation is the first deliverable of the Circular Economy Action Plan. It is a very ambitious contribution to that. I say very ambitious because, for the first time, this regulation will open up the single market for products needed by European farmers in the 21st century.</p>
      <p sl="en">The products I am talking about are innovative agro-chemicals produced from organic materials present in by-products and waste. Those products have enormous potential to make European agriculture more efficient and sustainable and to create jobs and opportunities for innovative businesses in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">When organic materials available in Europe are recycled, European farmers get an outlet for agricultural by-products that would otherwise have been wasted. European fertiliser manufacturers become much less dependent on imported, scarce raw materials, such as phosphate, from other regions in the world and, in between, a market is created for innovative European recycling operators and technology providers. So this is a win-win for European farmers, fertiliser producers and innovative businesspeople.</p>
      <p sl="en">In terms of a free market for responsible actors, we are trying with the proposed new regulation to free up the market as much as possible for products that can reform the European agro-industry. Gone are the days when fertilisers had to comply with narrow definitions set by the legislator, or when they had to be halted at every border between Member States for new certification. Nowadays, manufacturers have real freedom to adapt their products to farmers’ needs, using a mix of conventional and innovative raw materials.</p>
      <p sl="en">Farmers understand their own needs much better than any legislator. That is why we have proposed legislation which keeps farmers’ choices as wide as possible. But this presumes that manufacturers take all responsibility for product safety. Spreading products on farmland can pose a risk to health and the environment. Known and unknown toxic contaminants can end up in our water, food and animal feed. So we have proposed that all agro-chemicals covered in the legislation must be subject to a chemical safety assessment under the general Registration, Evaluation, Authorisation and Restriction of Chemicals (REACH) legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">If this proposal is amended, nobody – neither the legislator nor the manufacturer – will be responsible for assessing the safety of using agro-chemicals on land, and crops. That could have dramatic impacts on the environment and on the safety of the food chain, so I urge the European Parliament not to water down our proposal on this point. European fertiliser producers are more than able to take on the responsibility that the new market freedom requires and European farmers and citizens have the right to expect.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, this proposal not only provides new opportunities for the European agro-industry, it also provides you with an opportunity to limit emissions of toxic contaminants to farmland, drinking water and food. I would like to thank you for your general support for this part of our proposal. Together, we will raise environmental standards in an area in which Europeans are lagging behind the rest of the world. Future generations of Europeans will have their health better protected.</p>
      <p sl="en">A particular concern for health and the environment is cadmium in phosphate fertilisers. As far back as 1988, a Council resolution called for a strategy to reduce cadmium in phosphate fertilisers, and the problem has far from disappeared since then. There are a few marginal scientific differences, but the overall picture is clear: the European environment and people are too exposed to cadmium, and the only remaining major polluter of food in the environment is the phosphate fertilisers industry. So it is time for phosphate fertiliser manufacturers make sure that some of the dirtiest phosphate rock is cleaned before it is used in fertilisers, or for them to replace it with cleaner recycled phosphates sourced from Europe. And they can do that. The market is already developing and we are ready to support it further.</p>
      <p sl="en">Please remember that the limit values will also apply to imported phosphate fertilisers sold in the single market with the CE mark. This gives the European industry a golden opportunity to lead the world, not only as manufacturers of clean fertilisers with access to the single market, but also as technology providers to importers. So the industry should work with us, not against us. It is in their interest. It will help them to get a competitive advantage by developing clean technologies in innovative ways.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude my opening remarks, let me thank you again for your support. I look forward to hearing your views.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on International Trade">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, there is one thing I do not understand: how come the Commission can ask for and pay for scientific research, and when the time comes to write European law, this research is thrown out with the garbage? The Smolders study, which should be the basis for the findings of the Commission and for our work as well, shows that 80 mg of cadmium per kilogramme in fertilisers does not lead to accumulation of cadmium in the soil. Don’t make any mistakes: this proposal will not lead to lowering our dependence on imports of phosphate or phosphorus rock. We will be dependant on different sources. What we’re doing right now is we’re going to stuff euros into the Russian hands, and that’s a fact. Please don’t ask me to go back to my home country and tell those people who are going to lose their European jobs that we are doing this to help them out, because it is not true. it is not based on good science, it is not based on good economy, and it is just crazy. We should not propose such a law, because it does not make any sense.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="4319" name="Pilar Ayuso" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, yo le doy la bienvenida a esta legislación, que está inscrita dentro del paquete de economía circular, porque propone fertilizantes orgánicos y reciclados reduciendo así la materia prima inorgánica. Y, además, se establecen criterios armónicos medioambientales y de seguridad alimentaria para impulsar el comercio de estos productos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todo eso está muy bien y es muy loable. Son objetivos estupendos y que tenemos que perseguir, pero a veces el fin no justifica los medios, sobre todo si estos medios con los que contamos no son viables ni asumibles desde el punto de vista práctico y económico para los sectores que tienen que asumirlos y aplicarlos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Favorecer la expansión de materias orgánicas es muy positivo. Sin embargo, no podemos con ello pretender sustituir los productos minerales, al menos mientras no nos aseguremos de que aportan el mismo nivel y eficiencia en términos de fertilización de suelos. No hay que olvidar que los productos fertilizantes son esenciales y garantizan a los agricultores que sus cultivos reciben un aporte suficiente de nutrientes. Por otra parte, aunque es importante impulsar el uso de estiércoles como fertilizantes orgánicos, creo que no es este el reglamento para intentarlo, ya que afectaría directamente a la Directiva sobre los nitratos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero referirme también, como no, al contenido máximo de cadmio. Los límites de cadmio permitidos han generado un gran debate y tienen una gran trascendencia en la competitividad de la industria y de la agricultura, así como otras connotaciones geopolíticas, como se acaba de decir aquí. En mi opinión los límites propuestos por la Comisión son demasiado reducidos. Es más, yo diría que son inaceptables y hay que flexibilizar la propuesta: ochenta miligramos, como apuntan los informes científicos, sería una cifra razonable, máxime cuando ahora no tenemos ningún límite.</p>
      <p sl="en">En cualquier caso, debemos impulsar este Reglamento para apoyar a la industria a fin de que sea más sostenible y más competitiva y fomentar el crecimiento económico sostenible y el empleo. Pero si llegamos demasiado lejos en algunos temas, tendremos que votar en contra.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, la proposition de règlement dont il est question aujourd’hui vise à garantir le fonctionnement du marché intérieur des produits fertilisants, tout en garantissant que les fertilisants marqués CE répondent aux exigences de protection de la santé humaine, animale et végétale et de sécurité de l'environnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les engrais sont bien évidemment cruciaux pour la production agricole, mais leur utilisation peut également avoir un impact négatif sur l'environnement et la sécurité alimentaire, en particulier lorsqu’ils renferment des contaminants.</p>
      <p sl="en">À l’heure actuelle, les fertilisants sont réglementés au niveau européen par le règlement de 2003. Mais, ce dernier ne couvre en réalité qu’une partie du marché des engrais, puisqu’environ 50 % de tous les engrais présents sur le marché européen sont exclus de son champ d'application.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, le règlement existant concerne principalement les engrais conventionnels, dits «inorganiques», qui suivent un modèle d’économie linéaire, puisqu’il s’agit d’extraction de matières premières.</p>
      <p sl="en">La proposition de règlement, quant à elle, amorce un virage vers l'économie circulaire, puisqu’elle vise à accroître la réutilisation des matières premières qui sont actuellement éliminées en tant que déchets.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mettre les engrais organiques sur un pied d’égalité avec les engrais traditionnels peut réduire les déchets et l'impact environnemental de la fertilisation et de l'agriculture. On estime que la récupération des nutriments déjà présents dans l’Union européenne, par exemple sous la forme de déchets, pourrait remplacer environ 30 % des engrais inorganiques actuellement sur le marché – cela a d’ailleurs été précisé précédemment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il s’agit là d’un dossier très technique, avec un partage de compétences complexe entre les différentes commissions qui y participent. Les collègues et moi-même avons travaillé de concert afin d’obtenir un texte qui est à mon sens bien équilibré.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je tiens d’ailleurs à remercier le rapporteur, M. Ţurcanu, qui a succédé à Mme Gall-Pelcz, qui avait fait un excellent travail, ainsi que mes autres collègues rapporteurs fictifs pour leur collaboration.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’espère donc que le vote de demain confortera les acquis que nous avons obtenus par l’intermédiaire de la commission du marché intérieur et de la protection des consommateurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pourtant, à l’heure actuelle, je suis interpellé par la possible réouverture de la directive «nitrates», qui a pourtant, dès le départ, été une ligne rouge pour mon groupe et qui, d’un commun accord, était inenvisageable dans ce rapport.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, la directive «nitrates» comprend deux éléments majeurs: d’une part, le principe de fertilisation équilibrée et, d’autre part, l’obligation de limiter l’utilisation de fumier, permettant d’éviter l’élevage intensif et de favoriser une agriculture raisonnée. Il ne s’agit donc ni du lieu ni du moment pour amender à la va-vite une législation essentielle luttant contre la pollution des sols. J’ajoute que, si l’amendement «nitrates» devait passer – ce qui avait été proposé à diverses étapes du dossier –, je donnerais instruction à mon groupe de voter contre l’entièreté de ce rapport. Je pense que nous ne devons pas prendre ce risque.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quant à l’épineuse question des seuils de cadmium, le compromis soutenu notamment par mon groupe me paraît être la solution la plus équilibrée, car il permet d’appliquer le principe de précaution en la matière, tout en donnant du temps à l’industrie pour se conformer à ces nouvelles exigences.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="132925" name="Edward Czesak" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Propozycja Komisji wprowadzająca drastyczne obniżenie dopuszczalnych norm zanieczyszczenia nawozów metalami ciężkimi, głównie kadmem, budzi kontrowersje. Projekt uderza bowiem bezpośrednio w przemysł nawozowy oparty na eksploatowaniu rodzimych zasobów skał fosforowych w wielu państwach Unii. Unijni producenci nawozów zmuszeni będą do znacznego zwiększenia kosztów produkcji poprzez albo kosztowną technologię oczyszczania rud z metali ciężkich, albo import rud mineralnych z niższymi poziomami zanieczyszczeń od któregoś z eksporterów globalnych. Mam tu na myśli głównie Rosję. W konsekwencji pogorszy to sytuację ekonomiczną przemysłu chemicznego w Unii Europejskiej i wpłynie na podwyższenie cen nawozów. Zagrozi to także znaczną likwidacją miejsc pracy. Normy zaproponowane w sprawozdaniu są drastyczne, a argument ochrony środowiska i zdrowia konsumentów, choć ważny, jednak nie ma jednoznacznych wyników badań wskazujących na potrzebę tak rygorystycznego limitowania zawartości metali ciężkich w produkcji nawozów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nowe regulacje muszą być realistyczne. Nie można wymagać od państw członkowskich, w których od dziesięcioleci działają potężne zakłady chemiczne – niektóre będąc głównym pracodawcą w regionie – żeby nagle z nawozów syntetycznych przerzuciły się na produkcję nawozów organicznych. Apeluję, by głosując, mieli państwo na uwadze, że przyjęcie sprawozdania narzucającego tak restrykcyjne normy środowiskowe dla rynku europejskiego znacznie utrudni naszym narodowym producentem funkcjonowanie na europejskim rynku nawozowym. Otworzy to także pole do niekorzystnych dla firm naszego rynku europejskiego działań zewnętrznych, szeroko rozumianych. Poprawki złożone przez grupę ECR obejmujące 80 ml/kg kadmu w nawozach fosforowych dają szansę, aby ostateczny kształt sprawozdania uwzględnił optymalnie realizację stopniowego ograniczania zawartości metali ciężkich w nawozach, ale też rozsądnie rozłożoną w czasie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="124697" name="Kaja Kallas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, there has been a lot of talk around cadmium, but I will not talk about cadmium: this proposal is not only setting the limits, it is also about opening new possibilities for European producers. Up until now, only mineral fertilisers have benefited from the CE marking and free access to the single market. Today, they are still the most widely used in Europe, but alongside the traditional products more and more companies are looking for new solutions. This partly reflects the global trend in rising environmental consciousness on the one hand, and a drive for increased efficiency on the other. Companies around the world realise that they need to find ways to do more with less.</p>
      <p sl="de">In Europe, a lot of effort has been put into innovation. There is a strong drive in the fertiliser sector to find new sources of raw materials and make products that are more targeted and less wasteful. Often the solutions that are found are at the very forefront of science. By extending the scope of this regulation to such products, we will put in place the necessary framework to maximise the innovative potential of the fertiliser industry.</p>
      <p sl="de">Unified European standards will give producers a clear set of targets to aim for. Removing national barriers from the market will give them access to enough customers to make their investments pay off. Moreover, by asking the Commission to keep looking for new component materials that could be added to the regulation, we recognise that a lot of the potential of this sector is still untapped. We should not only reward existing animation by granting better access to the single market, we should also encourage further research by ensuring the possibility of updating the regulation in the future.</p>
      <p sl="de">By allowing the Commission to revise the regulation, we are telling producers to think outside the box and to keep looking for new solutions. If we follow these principles, we can create legislation that is truly supportive of innovation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="125049" name="Maria Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, no domínio dos fertilizantes e no quadro da economia circular, achamos que se deve trabalhar para diminuir o emprego de fertilizantes químicos, desenvolvendo a agroecologia e promovendo uma maior inter-relação entre a pecuária e a agricultura, potenciando a utilização do estrume e fomentando a compostagem nas próprias explorações agrícolas, para que as agricultoras e os agricultores tenham cada vez uma menor dependência de fatores de produção do exterior e para evitar um maior impacto ambiental e contribuir para a luta contra as alterações climáticas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Isto pressuporia também diminuir os custos de produção, o consumo de energias fósseis e o perigo da libertação de substâncias nocivas para o ambiente e a saúde, tanto das pessoas, como dos animais. No que se refere à rocha fosfatada, uma das matérias-primas fundamentais dos fertilizantes que a União Europeia importa, há que dizer que provém fundamentalmente de Marrocos, dos depósitos nos territórios ocupados no Sara Ocidental. Esta rocha apresenta também elevados níveis de cádmio, que se acumula no solo e na água e passa para a cadeia alimentar, causando problemas de saúde e ambientais.</p>
      <p sl="en">Achamos que as instituições europeias têm que garantir a soberania do povo do Sara sobre os seus recursos, impedir que sejam espoliados por Marrocos e não ceder perante pressões externas quanto ao estabelecimento dos níveis admitidos de cádmio nos fertilizantes. Entendemos ser necessário pôr fim às importações de substâncias para a fabricação de fertilizantes. E as lamas de depuradora não devem ser permitidas nos fertilizantes. Para nós, a marcação CE deveria estar reservada exclusivamente aos produtos da União Europeia. A rotulagem deve ser clara, transparente e facilmente inteligível. Os rótulos devem ser escritos em todas as línguas oficiais dos Estados-Membros.</p>
      <p sl="en">No procedimento de avaliação da conformidade, deve garantir-se que sempre prevaleça o princípio de precaução. Para isso, aos organismos de avaliação da conformidade devem ser públicos e basear-se em estudos e avaliações independentes, transparentes e públicas e ser atualizados continuamente. Só assim poderemos garantir que não se está a comercializar fertilizantes com a marcação CE que apresentem um risco para a saúde humana, animal ou vegetal, ou para o meio ambiente.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="96725" name="Bas Eickhout" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we all know what we are trying to do here. We are trying to create one internal market for all fertilisers, because we know that until now the scope has been very limited. When we are doing that, then one of the key issues is going to be the level of cadmium that is allowed because we all know, it is a fact: cadmium is a heavy metal and carcinogenic to people. We know that, and we also know – this was already investigated by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) – that in 2009 Europeans’ intake of cadmium was at the maximum limit set by EFSA, and the intake for some more vulnerable groups there was a higher of cadmium than was allowed.</p>
      <p sl="en">These are concerning facts that need to be addressed, because we also know that of all the cadmium limits, until now only the fertiliser group has been exempted. If we are going to make a European regulation – and we know that there are many national applications in place – we have to take into consideration that the proposals by the Commission entail, for some countries, a dilution of the current cadmium limits. That is on the table, and then people are saying that this will hamper the fertiliser industry.</p>
      <p sl="en">To them I say: ‘excuse me, can we base this kind of debate on facts?’ Wageningen University have been looking after the research and they say that the cost of meeting the cadmium limits that are being proposed would be minimal. And reducing cadmium limits would also be a stimulus for innovation: getting to clean fertiliser without cadmium would be an example of the circular economy. That is what we are trying to do here.</p>
      <p sl="en">Most of the arguments you hear positing that this is impossible are predicated on a very old-fashioned idea that innovation is not happening. If we can be innovative Europe then we can be the selling market for clean fertilisers. That is what is at stake, and we don’t want to hear any flippant discussions.</p>
      <p sl="en">What is also very important is that in the end, if we are not doing this right, who will pay the price? It is the farmers still using the contaminated fertilisers, because they must use the market. And if we find out there is more and more cadmium in our soils, and who will be getting the blame? It is the farmers.</p>
      <p sl="en">So if you are really concerned about the farmers, you have to make sure that the producers get the limits that they need to get. And that is at stake and all the other arguments are just fake.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the onus of proof must always lie with those who impose the restriction. Regulation must not been made for regulation’s sake, and the rule is made for people and not the other way around. Restrictions and prohibitions must be justified. This means a real risk to human health – not just a hazard. All actions are hazardous, and if that were the criterion we would all do nothing. We would still be living in caves with much shorter lifespans.</p>
      <p sl="en">It also means looking at the real—world impact of this legislation. Are substitutes available? Can the damage of the restriction be mitigated? Have we used a sledgehammer to crack a nut? There is no clear evidence that we need to crack down hard on cadmium, and lots of economic consequences which are real and damaging. Fertilisers are a cost, but they allow modern agricultural productivity essential for the size of the world’s growing population. I am a farmer, and I can tell you that no sensible farmer applies any fertiliser he does not regard as essential, and he selects the most cost-effective option.</p>
      <p sl="en">We believe that the case for a 20 mg cadmium restriction has simply not been made. It will further burden EU agriculture with no identifiable benefit. Limits in the United States, Canada and Australia are over 120 mg, but their people are not suffering. So how can it possibly make sense to add to the cost, enrich the Russians, handicap EU production and reduce our competitiveness? Also, what are we going to do with all this cadmium that we do pull out of the phosphate, if indeed we do that? That is when it will become a real hazard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="124758" name="Mylène Troszczynski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, la mise à jour sur le marché des fertilisants porteurs du marquage «CE» est essentielle pour être conforme aux exigences de protection de la santé, de la sécurité et de l’environnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Actuellement, seuls les fertilisants traditionnels obtenus par extraction ou par des procédés chimiques bénéficient de l’accès au marché intérieur et ont le fameux label «CE», alors que 50 % des engrais actuellement sur le marché en sont exclus – organiques, sous-produits animaux ou agricoles, déchets biologiques. En conséquence, les engrais obtenus sur des principes de l’économie circulaire en sont pour l’instant exclus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette initiative, ce texte a donc deux objectifs. Le premier est d’inciter à la production dans l’Union européenne d’engrais issus de matières organiques ou secondaires pour développer le modèle de l’économie circulaire en transformant des déchets en éléments nutritifs, réduisant ainsi la dépendance de l’Union européenne aux substances nutritives importées de pays tiers. Cette proposition vise à établir pour les engrais organiques des conditions de concurrence égales aux engrais minéraux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le second objectif est d’établir des taux limites de contaminants dans les engrais. Les taux proposés par la Commission sont irréalisables et dangereux pour l’industrie utilisant le phosphate comme source naturelle pour l’élaboration de ses engrais secondaires. L’industrie française des engrais organiques ou secondaires est très développée et a tout intérêt à bénéficier de l’ouverture du marché intérieur et de l’octroi du label «CE». Ces acteurs économiques subissent de facto une distorsion de concurrence face au marché des engrais minéraux et chimiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le soutien obtenu par la société civile française sur ce dossier témoigne de l’enjeu réel pour ce secteur particulier de l’économie française, et je tiens ici à les remercier. En revanche, le soutien sur ce dossier de la part des députés français de tous partis politiques de cet hémicycle est toujours attendu de la part des acteurs de ce secteur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Outre l’enjeu vital pour l’industrie française des engrais phosphatés, la proposition de la Commission aurait également la mauvaise idée de ne nous faire dépendre que d’une seule source d’approvisionnement de phosphates et l’effondrement du marché du phosphate nord-africain pourrait avoir de graves répercussions sur l’équilibre social de ces pays. L’intérêt géopolitique est également un enjeu important de ce texte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Notre groupe a déposé des amendements visant à établir un taux de cadmium à 80 milligrammes par kilo, avec une diminution progressive sur quinze ans pour obtenir un taux de 60 milligrammes, délai raisonnable et pragmatique pour la recherche et le développement, notamment en techniques de décadmiation du phosphate. La délégation française du Front national ne saurait donc demain, lors du vote, choisir de sacrifier de trop nombreux emplois français par une logique idéologique et dépourvue de bon sens, en choisissant des taux de cadmium beaucoup trop faibles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est sans doute préférable que l’industrie française des engrais secondaires et organiques accepte le statu quo en restant temporairement exclue du marché unique, plutôt que de risquer de voir nombre de ses collaborateurs être licenciés. L’instrumentalisation d’un besoin économique au profit d’objectifs contradictoires ne me semble pas le meilleur moyen d’aider le tissu industriel européen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-0000" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the whole idea of the circular economy is just catching on, so it is appropriate that we try and implement it in the agriculture sector with fertilisers. Frankly, for a lot a farmers, they try to operate a circular economy on their farm where they have animals and cropping, and it can work really well. It can also work at the local level – amongst farmers who trade in livestock manure, and I think that is something we should encourage and promote.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this case, what we are talking about is extending what can be used as a fertiliser ingredient. What we need from that is that it is effective – in other words, that it works at farm level and that it is safe and that we do not over-regulate.</p>
      <p sl="en">What is very important is that fertilisers in the past account for 60% of the registered yield increase in the last 50 years, so we absolutely need fertilisers to grow crops. I have listened carefully to the robust debate about cadmium, and I think we have to make sure that what we aspire to is achievable and does not have unintended consequences.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would say here that the cereal sector in Europe is under huge pressure. We import a large volume of cereals that will be produced without our control on the cadmium levels used in the fertilisers in third countries, and we need to be very mindful of the consequences of that on our production here. It is one of the things that we do repeatedly in Europe. I want us to be leaders in this field, but I do not want us to be so far ahead that we are behind. We do it in a whole range of products. If we can encourage the rest of the world to move with us, then I think we could all do that in a very coherent and supportive way. I fear, though, that in this case we will be so far ahead that we are behind and will cause problems on the single market for our farmers, and indeed for our consumers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="124821" name="Nicola Danti" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il regolamento che approveremo domani ci consegnerà un quadro normativo finalmente armonizzato in un settore, quello dei fertilizzanti, che – vorrei ricordare a tutti noi – rappresenta in Europa 100 000 posti di lavoro, centinaia di piccole e medie imprese, con un fatturato annuo che va dai 20 ai 25 miliardi di euro. A me preme sottolineare tre importanti risultati che da questo testo emergono.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il primo è l'etichettatura a marchio CE visibile, leggibile e completa, che garantirà una maggiore tutela dei consumatori e, in primo luogo, degli agricoltori.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il secondo: abbiamo garantito la promozione dell'utilizzo di materiali riciclati e organici per un ulteriore sviluppo dell'economia circolare e la riduzione della dipendenza dall'import di alcune materie prime da paesi terzi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine, vi è quello che rimane il punto più sensibile del regolamento, ovvero la definizione dei valori limite armonizzati su alcuni prodotti contaminanti, quali il cadmio e il cromo. Credo che l'approccio che il nostro gruppo ha posto all'attenzione del Parlamento sia improntato alla ragionevolezza e all'equilibrio. Da una parte l'attenzione alla salute dei cittadini e alla sicurezza ambientale, dall'altra la necessità di tempi ragionevoli di adattamento del sistema industriale ai nuovi limiti previsti, nuovi limiti che, vorrei ricordare a tutti voi, in gran parte dei paesi europei sono nettamente inferiori al limite di partenza di questa direttiva, cioè ai 60 milligrammi che noi abbiamo messo come punto di partenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Credo che qualcuno potrebbe obiettare che i tempi avrebbero potuto essere più celeri per giungere a un quadro armonizzato a livello europeo. Tuttavia ciò che conta – io penso, colleghi – è avviare un percorso in Europa che, attraverso investimenti, ricerca e sviluppo, renda più competitivo questo settore e più ambientalmente sostenibili anche le nostre politiche.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-0000" speaker_id="35135" name="Daniel Dalton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we welcome much of this report and the modernisation of the current regulation, but the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety has simply gone too far on cadmium levels, which they had competence on. Their proposal to lower the amount of cadmium fertilisers to just 40 mg in three years and then just 20 mg in nine years goes against scientific evidence and would have a dramatic effect on our ability to produce food. Our farmers need affordable and high—quality fertilisers. They directly increase the productivity of many crops. The Commission proposed 60 mg, even though they had evidence that 80 mg would do the job and lead to a reduction in the accumulation of cadmium in the soil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fertilisers, we should also remember, are only one reason that cadmium can end up in the soil and in diet: alone, they don’t solve the problem. The EU imports 85% of fertilisers, and most of those inputs will not meet the 60 mg proposal, let alone the 40 mg target or the 20 mg target down the line. So, if this report goes through, our farmers will face massive cost increases, which will make our food even more expensive. I therefore urge colleagues to support the amendments tabled by the ECR Group, which sets a maximum level at 80 mg.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="124989" name="Fredrick Federley" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Tack, kommissionen, för er närvaro vid den här väldigt viktiga debatten. Jag vill också tacka kommissionen för att ha varit väldigt öppen och tillgänglig under hela processen, där vi hanterat väldigt teknisk lagstiftning, men där har vi kunnat få snabba svar på viktiga frågor för att komma vidare i arbetet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Först av allt är det viktigt att påtala de nya marknader som vi faktiskt kan komma att se. Det låter ungefär som om domedagen närmar sig när jag hör högerflanken debattera härinne. Men så är det inte alls. Först ska vi nog börja med att konstatera att det vi pratar om inte är några absoluta förbudsnivåer som sätter hinder och gränser. Är du från Storbritannien och vill tillåta 150 milligram kadmium i mineralgödsel kan du faktiskt göra det. Skillnaden är att du inte får sälja det under CE-märkningen, som är garantin för vad du får sälja på den europeiska marknaden. Det är vad vi faktiskt pratar om.</p>
      <p sl="en">Men en del här, känns det som, är väldigt hårt tryckta av en industrilobby som vill komma åt hela den europeiska marknaden. Då måste vi ställa oss frågan: Vad ligger snittnivån på idag? Den ligger på 34 milligram. Alltså långt under de 40 milligram som vi siktar på att komma till om tre år. Samtidigt är det så att flera länder – Tjeckien, Slovakien, Finland, Sverige, Ungern med flera – har mycket lägre nivåer redan idag. Tre av dem har 20 milligram eller 22 milligram. Väl fungerande länder med väl fungerande jordbruksindustri. Det här tyder så klart på att det går att göra. Men då måste vi ha tydliga signaler, och även om jag tycker att vi i vår kompromiss här nu urholkar en hel del genom att vi förlänger tidsperspektivet till 16 år, kan det vara en kompromiss jag kan leva med för att vi ska få det här på banan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Konsekvensen, om vi driver 80 milligram, handlar inte om er hemmamarknad, det handlar om vad Ungern ska behöva acceptera. Att ni fyrdubblar deras nivåer? Vad ska Finland behöva acceptera? Att ni fyrdubblar nivån av kadmium i deras mineralgödsel? Det kan vi inte göra. Vi måste vara mera progressiva än så. Tack kommissionen för ett gott samarbete och hoppas att vi får ett bra utfall vid omröstningen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, senhor Comissário, qualquer intervenção neste domínio da disponibilização no mercado de produtos fertilizantes não deve perder de vista que a agricultura europeia dominante se afasta em aspetos fundamentais de um modelo de produção sustentável, ao que não serão alheias as políticas e orientações prevalecentes na União Europeia, como é o caso da PAC, que carecem de uma profunda modificação.</p>
      <p sl="en">Considera a relatora que os Estados-Membros devem ser livres de admitir adubos não harmonizados no mercado interno, sem retirar aos operadores económicos a possibilidade de optarem pelos benefícios de um quadro normativo harmonizado. Se nos parece, por um lado, avisado restringir os efeitos da harmonização, tornando-a facultativa, já, por outro lado, os critérios que terão presidido à elaboração do quadro normativo harmonizado afiguram-se-nos mais questionáveis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esperar-se-ia que estes critérios assegurassem elevados padrões de qualidade, segurança e proteção, quer do ambiente, quer da saúde pública, que estimulassem ou, pelo menos, não comprometessem a inovação de produtos e processos e que se alinhassem com o melhor conhecimento técnico e científico disponível, para além de não beneficiarem determinado tipo de interesses e operadores economicamente mais poderosos em detrimento de outros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Levantam-se dúvidas legítimas de que assim seja.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="96752" name="Martin Häusling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich glaube, ein Ziel war ja ganz klar, dass wir eine einheitliche Regelung in Europa bekommen. Dem Ziel sind wir näher gekommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber gestatten Sie mir noch ein paar Worte zum Thema Cadmium. Mich wundert hier die Debatte von einigen Kollegen auf der anderen Seite tatsächlich. Jetzt messen wir uns – sie sind leider nicht mehr da – mit den USA und Australien und sagen, die haben höhere Werte – also wäre das ein Wettbewerbsnachteil für Europa. Wenn man das bei vielen anderen Sachen auch so machen würde, dann wären wir in unseren Verbraucher- und Umweltstandards weit zurück. Deshalb: Europa muss Trendsetter sein. Man muss vorangehen bei dem, was möglich ist. Und das, was der Umweltausschuss bei Cadmium vorgeschlagen hat, ist halt eine Möglichkeit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alles, was irgendwann einmal in den Böden ist, wird auch einmal in die Nahrungsmittel kommen. Alles was wir vermeiden können, müssen wir jetzt vermeiden. Deshalb ist es eine Vorsorgemaßnahme, die vielleicht auch Geld kostet – keine Frage –, aber die langfristig zum Schutz der Umwelt gemacht werden muss. Wir wollen mehr natürliche Düngemittel + das muss Vorrang haben vor chemischen mineralischen Düngemitteln. Das ist ganz klar. Auch diese Zielsetzung unterstützen wir. Aber diese Mittel müssen auch sauber sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gestatten Sie mir, einige Punkte anzusprechen, die wir nicht für wirklich gut gelöst halten. Einer ist, dass die Düngemittelverordnung auf keinen Fall dazu führen darf, dass höhere Nitrateinträge durch Gülle erlaubt werden. Die Gefahr besteht, dass die Nitratrichtlinie durch die Düngemittelverordnung abgeschwächt wird. Die Definition von tierischem Dünger in der Nitratrichtlinie darf durch die Düngemittelverordnung nicht angetastet werden. Es ist klar, dass der übermäßige Nährstoffeintrag zu Umwelt- und Gesundheitsschäden führt. Auch nachhaltige Landwirtschaftssysteme sollten nicht durch die Düngemittelverordnung geschwächt werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein Punkt der uns mit Sorge erfüllt, ist REACH. Die Düngemittelverordnung darf auch nicht genutzt werden, um die REACH-Verordnung zu umgehen. Es dürfen also keine chemischen Substanzen in Düngemitteln eingesetzt werden, die für die menschliche Gesundheit oder die Umwelt schädlich sein können. Der Verordnungsvorschlag für Düngemittel enthält einige Änderungsanträge, die es möglich machen würden, dass Düngemittel zum Einsatz kommen, die ohne ordentliches Risikomanagement zugelassen werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Auch bei Biostimulantien sehen wir mit Sorge, dass da nicht nur natürliche Substanzen eingesetzt werden, sondern im Endeffekt vielleicht auch ein Umgehungstatbestand geschaffen wird und Pestizide eingesetzt werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Einen besonderen Punkt möchte ich noch anmerken: Plastikfolien als Mulchfolien, die dann auf dem Acker verrotten sollen. Davor kann ich nur warnen. Das wird dazu beitragen, dass wir mehr Plastik im Boden und im Wasser haben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-0000" speaker_id="124779" name="Eleonora Evi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il cibo che mangiamo è la principale fonte di contaminazione da metalli pesanti, tra i quali, in particolare, si trova il cadmio, classificato come cancerogeno. Ce lo dice l'EFSA, che ha anche stabilito livelli di assunzione massimi tollerabili nei suoi pareri scientifici. Uno studio dell'Istituto zooprofilattico sperimentale delle Venezie, nel 2015, ha rilevato che chi segue una dieta mediterranea vegetariana o vegana è anche più esposto ad alti livelli di cadmio e quindi a contaminazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Introducendo in questo nuovo regolamento dei limiti stringenti per il cadmio e per gli altri metalli pesanti, quali il mercurio, l'arsenico e il piombo, possiamo mettere al sicuro la salute dei consumatori europei. Non farlo oggi sarebbe folle e irresponsabile.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo anche un'altra grande opportunità da cogliere, quella dell'economia circolare, per rendere un concetto fino ad oggi astratto un qualcosa di concreto. Questo regolamento cerca di trasformare i rifiuti in risorse e creare un mercato dei fertilizzanti organici per incentivare concimi naturali e puliti. E in questa maniera potremmo ottenere un duplice risultato: da un lato diminuire la dipendenza dell'Europa dalle importazioni di materie prime, quali le rocce fosfatiche, ingrediente principale dei fertilizzanti inorganici minerali, che però spesso acquistiamo da zone del mondo in cui non solo queste rocce sono contaminate e molto sporche, ma nei quali la loro estrazione viola i diritti umani. Dall'altro favoriremmo una vera transizione verso un'agricoltura sostenibile e naturale benefica per gli ecosistemi, l'ambiente e, ovviamente, l'uomo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stiamo parlando di un marchio CE e stiamo parlando di criteri stringenti per creare un nuovo mercato. Chi non li rispetta può star fuori e continuare un business as usual, ma dobbiamo mirare al massimo e al miglioramento della salute dei cittadini europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="125684" name="Philippe Loiseau" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, c’est avec mes préoccupations d’agriculteur que j’ai étudié ce rapport. Ne l’oublions pas, les agriculteurs sont les premiers utilisateurs de ces produits fertilisants, une profession qui se sent malheureusement parfois exclue des décisions de l’Union européenne, qui se sent également incomprise, et même méprisée. Je salue donc, pour une fois, la volonté d’avoir associé à ce texte notre voix, celle des députés de la commission de l’agriculture.</p>
      <p sl="en">La seconde remarque porte, quant à elle, sur le rendement des fertilisants organiques. Il faut être sûr que ceux-ci soient aussi efficaces que les produits qu’ils sont censés remplacer. C’est une exigence non négociable, car pouvant remettre en cause la survie de l’agriculture, bien sûr, qui déjà doit faire face à une concurrence de produits importés ne respectant pas toujours les contraintes environnementales de l’Union européenne. L’objectif de dépendre moins des importations est donc particulièrement important et nécessaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est tout aussi capital que notre dépendance aux matières premières ne soit pas envers un seul pays, mais envers plusieurs, pour des raisons géopolitiques. Il est notamment question ici de cadmium. Si l’on abaisse trop le seuil autorisé dans les fertilisants, il est à craindre que la liste de nos pays fournisseurs se réduise à un seul. C’est un risque je ne souhaite pas prendre, personnellement, et un risque que nous devons éviter, je pense.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur cette même question du cadmium, l’Union européenne doit parvenir à un équilibre entre production environnementale et sanitaire et efficacité économique. La proposition de la Commission était bien trop stricte, je pense, en la matière. Notre groupe propose donc un amendement bien plus raisonnable, que j’espère voir soutenu lors des votes prochainement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, j’en profite pour rappeler amicalement à la Commission son rôle: c’est d’abord de protéger les intérêts européens à la fois des particuliers et des professionnels. Certaines entreprises seraient ainsi fortement impactées par un seuil autorisé de cadmium trop bas. Ce sont, bien sûr, les emplois qui en pâtiront en premier lieu. Que la Commission regarde donc ce qui se fait ailleurs! Il serait dangereux que les taux de cadmium autorisés dans les fertilisants deviennent en Europe les plus stricts du monde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je conclurai donc sur ce point, qui me paraît essentiel. Certes, l’Union européenne doit être protectrice sur le plan de l’environnement, mais elle ne doit pas pour autant bouleverser tout un marché par une mesure qui, en plus, ne changera pas radicalement la qualité des sols.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-0000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Erst einmal ein paar Worte zum Verfahren: Ich muss Ihnen ehrlich gestehen, ich war am Anfang ein begeisterter Anhänger des Verfahrens, dass die Ausschüsse getrennte Zuständigkeiten bekommen. Ich muss sagen, am Ende, wenn ich gerade auf dieses Dossier schaue, wäre es besser gewesen, wir hätten einen federführenden Ausschuss gehabt, weil der federführende Ausschuss letztendlich vielleicht die Kompromissbildung erleichtert hätte. Und ich muss wirklich die schüchterne Kritik an den Umweltausschuss richten, der zwar einen Beschluss gefasst hat, aber die Stichworte Arbeitsplätze, geologische Gegebenheiten, Rohstoffsicherheit, Praxistauglichkeit haben den Umweltausschuss nur am Rande interessiert. Und genau daran kranken wir ja, genau darum geht ja die Diskussion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dazu zwei Beispiele. Das erste Beispiel: Wenn man sich die Anträge anguckt – alle sind dafür, den Cadmiumgehalt zu definieren und zu begrenzen, und wir brauchen auch eine europäische Regelung. Das ist richtig. Wir streiten im Prinzip um 40 Milligramm. Das ist der Unterschied. Wenn man sich das einmal ausrechnet: Wenn man wirklich ernsthaft mit diesem Unterschied die Bodenqualität verbessern möchte, braucht man mehrere hundert Jahre. Das wäre genauso, als wenn jemand bei seinem Frühstücksei mit dem Salzstreuer den Eiweißgehalt beim Ei verändern will. Da passiert nämlich gar nichts. Also ich bitte ein klein wenig um Sachlichkeit und darum, zu schauen: Wie ist denn wirklich die Wirkung?</p>
      <p sl="en">Das zweite Beispiel: In Mitteldeutschland, meiner Region, haben wir Kalklagerstätten. Das hat niemand verändert, das hat der liebe Gott so produziert, das hat man so hingestellt. Kalk ist ein Bodenverbesserer. Kalk dient ja dazu, dass man die Löslichkeit der Nährstoffe verbessert, aber die Schadstoffe im Boden bleiben. Wir wenden das natürlich schon seit Menschengedenken an. Die Regelung, die von der Kommission vorgeschlagen wird, unterstützt vom Umweltausschuss, würde dazu führen, dass wir die Kalklagerstätten um die Ecke schließen und unseren Kalk dann von weiter Entfernung herantransportieren müssten. Das ist an sich Unsinn, und deshalb bitte ich morgen in der Abstimmung sich nochmal die Kompromissanträge anzuschauen. Ob nun 80 oder 60 Milligramm – das wäre ein guter Kompromiss im Interesse der Rohstoffsicherheit und im Interesse unserer Landwirte.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="96715" name="Pavel Poc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane komisaři, já musím pochválit Evropskou komisi, protože skutečně ten návrh je dobrý. I kolegové zpravodajové udělali, myslím, výbornou práci a zůstává nám tady jenom otázka kadmia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hovořilo se tady hodně o průmyslu, o zemědělství, ale kromě kolegy Eickhouta málokdo hovořil o zdravotních dopadech. Kadmium je karcinogen, mutagen, reprotoxin, organotoxin a je akumulativní. Zdravotní důsledky můžou přijít ještě deset let potom, co došlo k intoxikaci. To je třeba si uvědomit jako první.</p>
      <p sl="en">Potrava je hlavní zdroj kadmia pro evropskou populaci a je poměrně jasně řečeno i našimi agenturami, že příjem některých skupin kadmia v potravě je dvakrát vyšší než tolerovatelný. Takže je jasné, že je s tím potřeba něco dělat. A pro takové ty příliš složité a diskutující tady – co se nasype na to pole, to tam prostě je a to my sníme, protože z rostlin, z těch plodin, z té vzniklé potravy to kadmium prostě odstranit nejde. Takže tu expozici je potřeba redukovat u zdroje, tam, kde se to hnojivo vyrábí.</p>
      <p sl="en">Teď se podívejme na to, co navrhuje Komise – limit šedesát miligramů ihned. Hovořilo se tady o tom, jak je to složité, co je třeba dělat. Nic není třeba dělat! Průměr je dnes třicet čtyři miligramů, pro čtyřicet miligramů je možná potřeba začít míchat čistý zdroj se špinavým, pro dvacet miligramů je potřeba zavést průmyslově nějaké technologie. Za dvanáct let? Za dvanáct let, přátelé, doletíme na Mars, tak snad budeme umět vyčistit nějaké hnojivo od kontaminantů. Řada členských států už tyto limity má, takže debata o tom, že není zemědělství s těmi limity konkurenceschopné, je nesmysl. Je to dokázáno tím, že ty limity už jsou. Prosím, podpořme ten návrh Komise, je rozumný, je racionální, dosažitelný a vůbec o ničem dalším nedebatujme</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="117477" name="Mark Demesmaeker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, mijn partij, NVA, trekt stevig aan de kar om onze economie meer circulair te maken. Een gelijk speelveld tussen organische en niet—organische meststoffen kan dat kringloopmodel versterken. Vlaanderen zet al 25 jaar in op biologische kringloop. In 2015 werd meer dan 800 000 ton van de bioafvalstroom omgezet in kwaliteitsvolle compost dat ik graag het zwarte goud noem. En verder werd 2,2 miljoen ton van andere bioafvalstromen omgezet in organische meststoffen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vandaag kunnen we die Vlaamse beste praktijken verankeren in Europese wetgeving door te kiezen voor ambitieuze Europese einde-afvalcriteria voor bioafval. Bioafval is een waardevolle grondstof met heel wat economisch potentieel, maar vandaag gaat nog altijd een derde daarvan verloren in de vuilniszak. We moeten het tij keren door bioafval gescheiden in te zamelen en te recycleren. Zo kunnen we een groot deel van de niet—organische meststoffen vervangen. Mijn delegatie steunt alvast ook de ambitie om cadmium stapsgewijs te verminderen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, uvjeren sam da se europsko gospodarstvo može i mora bazirati na vrhunskoj kvaliteti i da samo vrhunski proizvod zaista može dugoročno opstati kao europski proizvod. Stoga sam uvjeren da upravo visoki standardi zaštite okoliša i sigurnosti hrane su preduvjet za našu dugoročnu konkurentnost.</p>
      <p sl="en">Danas govorimo o onome što znači mogućnost izbora za poljoprivrednika i mislim da u tom elementu postoji upravo način da zadovoljimo sve interese u ovoj kući jer poljoprivrednici imaju pravo na svoj izbor, ali mi moramo, uvjeren sam u to, poticati upravo one koji žele maksimalno zaštititi okoliš i sigurnost hrane i, naravno, mislim da moramo i te kako poticati tehnologije i inovacije u poljoprivrednom sektoru. To je put po kojem, uvjeren sam, možemo naći zajednički dogovor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="23704" name="Jiří Maštálka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, nebudu obtěžovat čísly, která tady byla již řečena. Projednávání tohoto návrhu nařízení opět ukazuje, pro koho jsou důležitější obchodní zájmy a komu jde především o lidské zdraví a ochranu životního prostředí.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nejvíce kontroverzní je samozřejmě téma limitů na kadmium. Tato látka, vysoce nebezpečná, představuje závažné riziko pro lidské zdraví. Kromě ovzduší se dostává do lidského těla také potravinami. Z fosforečných hnojiv se dostává do půdy a je přijímána rostlinami. Z nich ho již nelze nijak odstranit, takže jej vesele konzumujeme v našich potravinách. Jedná se přitom o velice jedovatý karcinogen, který se může podílet na vzniku rakoviny a osteoporózy. Tyto informace jsou veřejně známé, a přesto se pravice chystá prohlasovat zvýšení limitu kadmia v hnojivech. To je naprosto neakceptovatelné. Nemůžeme přece dávat přednost ziskům z dovozu nekvalitních surovin před lidským zdravím.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dále bych upozornil na to, že návrh nařízení opomíjí některé jiné důležité aspekty, jako je například doplnění limitu pro celkový chrom. Současná praxe probíhá tak, že se do hnojiv přidává průmyslový odpad, jako jsou odpady z ocelářského nebo kožedělného průmyslu. Ty sice nejsou povoleny jako složkové materiály hnojiv, nicméně pro kontrolní orgány je až nemožné zjistit použití těchto materiálů v hnojivech.</p>
      <p sl="en">Samostatnou kapitolou jsou pak biostimulanty. Jejich drtivá většina se pohybuje v šedé zóně, jsou vydávány za hnojiva nebo pomocné látky. Potřebujeme proto změnu definice přípravků na ochranu rostlin. Nejzásadnější je ovšem fakt, že současná situace s chybějícími limity rizikových prvků u hnojiv v Evropské unii je zcela nevyhovující.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="28394" name="Dariusz Rosati" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we all agree that cadmium content has to be limited – this is not the question we are talking about. The debate here is about the speed and the question of by how much we should reduce it. Seen from this perspective, I find the proposal put forward by the Commission and then changed by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety unacceptable, simply because it goes too far, is far too restrictive and is potentially harmful for EU industrial agriculture.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is for three reasons. The first has already been mentioned: that there is no scientific evidence that would link the level of cadmium in fertiliser with the level of cadmium in food and crops. There is no solid scientific evidence that the limit of 80 mg or 100 mg leads to the accumulation of cadmium and not to the de—accumulation of cadmium. So we should be careful about making such statements.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second argument is that the majority of fertiliser plants in Europe import their phosphate rocks from third countries. There is some cadmium content in these raw materials, but a feasible operational decadmiation technology does not exist and this technology cannot simply be developed overnight. So what is the alternative? The alternative would probably be either to go out of business or simply to look for some other sources of supply, but the single readily available source of supply is the Russian Federation.</p>
      <p sl="en">That brings me to the third argument. The third argument is that for phosphate rock, which has been considered by the Commission as a strategic raw material, we do not want to rely on supplies from an unreliable partner. So, if you want to reduce cadmium content and at the same time not destroy our industry, we should think about extending the period of adjustment in order to give our industry time to develop technologies that would fulfil these noble goals as indicated in the Commission proposal.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. Estamos centrándonos demasiado en el cadmio: es un elemento muy importante, pero no es el único.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se trata de un Reglamento que va a modificar otro, catorce años después; que, además, está dentro del paquete de la economía circular, algo muy importante. Es el Reglamento que quedaba pendiente dentro de la economía circular y que va a regular el mercado interior y va a producir una armonización, por primera vez —por primera vez—, en el uso de los fertilizantes. Una armonización parcial, es verdad, pero muy, muy importante. Además, va a establecer condiciones para la comercialización de los productos y va a proporcionar más seguridad en el uso de estos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero decir que los fertilizantes son esenciales para las producciones agrarias, pero necesitamos fertilizantes que realmente sean útiles y, por lo tanto, que esté demostrada su eficacia y eficiencia agronómica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto es algo muy importante porque, por primera vez, en este Reglamento se incorporan muchos fertilizantes nuevos: fertilizantes orgánicos y fertilizantes minerales o inorgánicos. Más del 50 % está ahora fuera de la reglamentación.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bueno, estos fertilizantes orgánicos son muy importante dentro de la economía circular, pero si aprobamos en un Reglamento fertilizantes orgánicos que no tienen eficacia ni eficiencia agronómica, no son útiles para los agricultores y estaremos también contaminando.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por tanto, seamos prácticos. El cadmio es un elemento sustantivo. Todos estamos de acuerdo en limitar los porcentajes de cadmio, pero vayamos a lo posible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que la Comisión ha ido mucho más lejos, y esto no es útil, esto no es útil para todos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tampoco estoy acuerdo con abrir la Directiva de nitratos que, para mi Grupo —como ha dicho el señor Tarabella— es una cuestión importante, y no lo vamos a permitir, al menos con nuestro voto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Szanowni Państwo! Propozycja Komisji jest szokująca i absolutnie nie do przyjęcia. Jeśli chodzi o limity kadmu, obecnie przemysł europejski opiera się na surowcach afrykańskich o wysokiej zawartości kadmu. Dziś w Unii Europejskiej limity związane z ograniczeniem kadmu nie istnieją. Czas nazwać rzeczy po imieniu: skutkiem wniosku Komisji będzie wzrost zapotrzebowania na złoża niskokadmowe. Kto na tym skorzysta? To jest zasadnicze pytanie. Skorzysta głównie Rosja. Jestem przekonana, że już koledzy Putina zacierają ręce, bo Państwo szykują im naprawdę świetny biznes. Skorzysta również Finlandia, kraj pochodzenia komisarza Katainena. Konsekwencją wniosku Komisji będzie po pierwsze wzrost cen surowców, kosztów produkcji, cen nawozów, a w konsekwencji wzrost cen żywności.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="124732" name="Angélique Delahaye" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, ce rapport est un rapport important pour l’avenir du secteur industriel et agricole. Il couvre des sujets bien plus vastes que la seule question du cadmium. Malheureusement, les discussions se sont cristallisées sur cette question.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je déplore la position de la commission de l’environnement, de la santé publique et de la sécurité alimentaire. En effet, demander une diminution du taux dans l’engrais à 60 milligrammes par kilo maintenant, avec pour ambition d’ailleurs d’atteindre les 20 milligrammes par kilo dans quelques années, n’est absolument pas réaliste.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est primordial de fixer des objectifs, ambitieux certes, mais avant tout accessibles afin de donner un signal aux PME européennes. Il faut évidemment limiter l’utilisation des intrants dans nos sols, mais cela doit se faire de façon pragmatique. Toute mesure visant à la réduction de l’utilisation des engrais minéraux doit être accompagnée par la recherche et l’innovation et doit être encouragée.</p>
      <p sl="en">La question du cadmium est un enjeu géopolitique et cela a été dit par nombre de mes collègues avant moi. Ainsi, si nous suivons le vote de la commission de l’environnement, de la santé publique et de la sécurité alimentaire, nous nous retrouverons dépendants des sources d’approvisionnement en provenance de Russie et de Finlande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quant à la question des nitrates, je pense qu’il est très imprudent d’ouvrir cette question. Certes, la législation actuelle n’est pas parfaite, mais attention à ne pas ouvrir la boîte de Pandore. Je pense qu’il faut être attentif aux surtranspositions des législations européennes en droits nationaux, qui sont très souvent source de distorsion de concurrence. Aussi, chers collègues, je vous invite, lors du vote sur le rapport Ţurcanu, demain, à être attentifs et à considérer tous les secteurs concernés et pas uniquement ce rapport sous l’angle de la question du cadmium.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I welcome the efforts of Parliament and the Commission to shift the balance to organic fertilisers while improving the Single Market for fertilisers. In line with the circular economy principle, we need to find an affordable way for our farmers to switch to more organic alternatives. However, since 80% of the EU market is inorganic fertilisers, we have a responsibility to our citizens and the environment to address maximum levels of contaminants in inorganic fertilisers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cadmium is a Class One carcinogen according to the World Health Organisation, and exposure can lead to pulmonary disorders, kidney disease, cancer, fertility problems and osteoporosis. We have been talking since 2003 of reducing cadmium in fertilisers and it has taken us 14 years to get us to the stage we are at today. I hope in the coming years we will see significantly lower cadmium levels than we see now across the EU and across the world and I welcome these proposals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="125030" name="Annie Schreijer-Pierik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, we stemmen morgen over essentiële Europese wetgeving op het gebied van milieu en interne markt. De Europese kringloopeconomie moet ook bemestingsproducten omvatten. Daarover spreken we hier. Hoogwaardig mineralenconcentraat en andere organische mestproducten op basis van dierlijke mest moeten kunnen worden toegepast in geheel Europa als zij dezelfde werkzaamheid en milieueigenschappen hebben als minerale kunstmest.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fosfaat wordt schaars. Herwinning uit mest en rioolwater door technologie loont en maakt ons onafhankelijk. Het is een goed signaal dat dit Parlement de terugwinning van struviet steunt en einde—dierlijkemestcriteria laat onderzoeken. De discriminatie van hoogwaardige organische bemestingsproducten op basis van mest moeten wij inderdaad gaan stoppen. Onze fractie heeft daarom nogmaals een amendement ingediend. Als u de circulaire economie, waterkwaliteit en Europese bodemgezondheid steunt, reken ik allemaal op uw steun.</p>
      <p sl="en">In heel Europa vragen onze akkerbouwers en tuinders om kunstmest, bodemverbeteraars en innovatieve technieken. Laten we daarom voorkomen dat we voor onze voedselproductie geheel afhankelijk worden van de fosfaatmijnen van maar één land, en dan spreek ik over Rusland. Want naast organische meststoffen is betaalbare kunstmest onmisbaar voor onze Europese bijdrage aan de voedselproductie in de hele wereld. Geef vertrouwen aan onze innovatieve akkerbouwers, onze tuinders en meststoffenproducenten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot, we spreken hier ook steeds over het openbreken van de nitraatrichtlijn. Het gaat erom de verouderde wetgeving bij de tijd te brengen, zoals de nitraatrichtlijn uit 1991, nu hopeloos verouderd en onnodig belemmerend voor hoogwaardige verwerkte meststoffen. En ik kijk naar de heer Tarabella. Als u datgene wilt bereiken wat u net heeft genoemd, zult u hiermee in moeten stemmen. Anders blijven we in dit Parlement praten, praten, praten, en komt er verder niks van de grond.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-0000" speaker_id="103845" name="Virginie Rozière" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, en fait, ce rapport corrige une anomalie, puisque les substances organiques et sous-produits animaux ou végétaux sont utilisés pour amender les sols quasiment depuis que l’agriculture existe, mais aujourd’hui, le marché intérieur ne permet que la circulation des engrais chimiques. C’est donc une anomalie qui est corrigée et un vrai pas supplémentaire pour l’économie circulaire que de permettre désormais également le marquage et la libre circulation des engrais organiques et des sous-produits végétaux et animaux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur le point qui a fait beaucoup débat – je veux parler bien sûr de la réduction du taux de cadmium –, je suis heureuse qu’on se fixe cet objectif de 20 milligrammes par kilo. Là aussi, j’entends la frilosité de certains collègues, mais j’aimerais qu’on se fixe un calendrier un petit peu plus ambitieux que ce qui a pu être discuté, puisqu’il y va de la santé des Européens.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous invite donc demain à être très ambitieux là-dessus. Et puis, si l’industrie européenne vous est si précieuse, je vous invite aussi à prendre en compte ses intérêts lorsqu’on parle, par exemple, de défense commerciale. Cela me semble être plus intéressant que de les mettre en concurrence avec la santé des Européens. Mais, en tout cas, ce sont des avancées pour la santé et l’environnement que je nous invite à soutenir demain.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-0000" speaker_id="1318" name="James Nicholson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, fertilisers are a necessity for producers. In some cases, fertiliser can account for over half of the farmers’ input costs – a price the farmer cannot control. Placing heavy limits on cadmium, despite the lack of scientific evidence to show this is necessary, will reduce supply and hike prices for farmers across the European Union. 80 mg per kilo with provisions to review would still allow risks to public health and the environment to be managed safely. Studies suggest that 80 mg per kilo on average is enough to stop cadmium accumulating in soil. Stronger limits are simply not supported by any available scientific evidence.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would therefore urge Members to support amendments calling for a maximum cadmium level in phosphate fertiliser of 80 mg per kilo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="23785" name="Andrzej Grzyb" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Każdy typ nawożenia musi być zrównoważony. Nie tylko nawozy pochodzenia nieorganicznego mogą być źródłem przenawożenia, ale również nawozy organiczne mogą być źródłem przenawożenia. W związku z tym musimy zwracać uwagę na to, co jest racjonalne w tej regulacji, przede wszystkim – że zwracamy się w kierunku gospodarki o obiegu zamkniętym, że chcemy więcej materii organicznej przywrócić glebom, ale jednocześnie chcemy, aby były stosowane te nawozy, które mają dobrą jakość. Wcale to nie oznacza, że rolnictwo zrezygnuje z nawozów pochodzenia nieorganicznego, że oprze się tylko i wyłącznie na nawozach organicznych, bo to jest niemożliwe ze względu na intensywność tej produkcji. W niektórych działach tylko nawozy organiczne są podstawą produkcji, bo te uprawy są przecież na sztucznych podłożach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlatego chcę powiedzieć, że powinniśmy dążyć do tego, aby jak najwięcej nawozów organicznych było w obiegu, ale też musimy zadbać o jakość gleb, o mikroorganizmy. Nie możemy jednak przeregulować rynku. I tutaj jeżeli wprowadzimy te propozycje, które są związane z kadmem, no to sprawimy, że część naszego sektora nawozowego wypadnie nam z rynku, ponieważ koszty przekwalifikowania na produkcję o mniejszej zawartości wymagają nowych technologii, droższych technologii, w szczególności jeżeli chodzi o fosforyty z Maroka. A innym alternatywnym źródłem są fosforyty z Rosji czy ewentualnie niewielka ilość z Finlandii. Więc jeżeli chcemy odejść od zmonopolizowania rynku surowcowego przez tylko jeden kraj, to powinniśmy dopuścić scenariusz rozsądnego zmniejszania zawartości kadmu w nawozach i wtedy uzyskamy ten efekt, który jest związany z lepszą jakością nawozów, ze zmniejszeniem zanieczyszczeń, w tym również kadmem, ale też uzyskamy cenę, która będzie rozsądna dla przemysłu i również dla rolników, którzy mają te nawozy wykorzystywać w produkcji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0000" speaker_id="96891" name="Paolo De Castro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, l'agricoltura europea è chiamata a ricoprire un ruolo di primissimo piano nella sempre più pressante sfida globale dell'accesso al cibo. In questo senso, la disponibilità di prodotti fertilizzanti di qualità rappresenta una delle condizioni per lo sviluppo di modelli agricoli più produttivi e allo stesso tempo più sostenibili, che nel futuro dovranno essere in grado di produrre di più, utilizzando meno input.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questi motivi il regolamento di cui ci troviamo a discutere non può essere solo un'opportunità di armonizzazione a livello europeo delle norme sui fertilizzanti tradizionali; al contrario, deve rappresentare uno straordinario incentivo alla produzione di prodotti innovativi, efficaci e a ridotto impatto ambientale, in totale coerenza con il modello dell'economia circolare.</p>
      <p sl="en">La posizione ambiziosa del Parlamento europeo dovrà quindi essere in grado di confermare il ruolo dell'Unione come capofila dello sviluppo sostenibile, garantendo allo stesso tempo la disponibilità di prodotti fertilizzanti a prezzi equi, senza creare ulteriori distorsioni di concorrenza a scapito dei nostri agricoltori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-0000" speaker_id="39721" name="Theodor Dumitru Stolojan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, discutăm astăzi o propunere de legislație europeană de care piața îngrășămintelor din Uniunea Europeană are nevoie. Problema care, însă, a ridicat serioase îngrijorări este conținutul de cadmiu care a fost propus de către Comisie la șaizeci de miligrame pe kilogram. Colegii mei au arătat că au îndoieli cu privire la existența unei fundamentări științifice certe cu privire la efectul acestei limite asupra sănătății oamenilor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Propunerea Comisiei, așa cum este făcută, are două consecințe negative. În primul rând, fabricile care importă fosfați din nordul Africii, între care și România, nu au tehnologia necesară pentru a reduce conținutul de cadmiu. Și aici nu discutăm de o îmbunătățire simplă a tehnologiei. Am discutat cu fabrica din România: reducerea conținutului de cadmiu presupune a schimba complet liniile tehnologice din fabrica respectivă. În al doilea rând, a doua consecință negativă este că distorsionează competiția în economia Uniunii Europene, în piața fosfaților, a îngrășămintelor fosfatice, în sensul că aplicarea acestei limite a cadmiului va scoate total în afara pieței fabricile care folosesc materia primă din nordul Africii.</p>
      <p sl="en">De aceea, cred că orice măsură, aici, trebuie însoțită de un număr de ani de tranziție suficient pentru a avea o cercetare științifică care să dea rezultate în acest domeniu. Vă mulțumesc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, health, food safety and sustainable food production are all important aspects in relation to fertilisers. We have to state that these substances are crucial for agricultural production, but, as in many cases, their overuse can be dangerous. Therefore, the precautionary principle should be first, while mitigation can be realised by smart precision techniques.</p>
      <p sl="en">I welcome the harmonisation steps between inorganic and organic fertilisers, and also the steps in the field of cadmium levels. Regarding the latter topic, I think that the proposed Commission timeline could be more ambitious, and I would be glad to introduce even lower levels in the EU. There are already existing low cadmium levels, for example in the case of Hungary, where the limit is set at 20%, and everybody is happy. I can imagine that gradually the levels can be reduced.</p>
      <p sl="en">Because of all these aspects, I am going to support the good results achieved at committee level and also the more ambitious Socialist amendments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="22418" name="Esther Herranz García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señor comisario, señorías, es importante alcanzar un acuerdo satisfactorio que permita la viabilidad de los fertilizantes en el mercado europeo, pero sin reducir la calidad de los productos destinados a los agricultores porque son productos imprescindibles para seguir produciendo alimentos a un precio razonable dentro de la Unión. Los fertilizantes orgánicos, aunque pudieran ser una solución a largo plazo, no han demostrado todavía ser una opción real que ofrezca los mismos estándares de exigencia que los fertilizantes minerales en cuanto a su composición de nutrientes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es muy importante alcanzar una solución para los límites de cadmio que no estrangule a los productores de fertilizantes minerales o aumente nuestra dependencia de importaciones procedentes de terceros países como Rusia y que tenga, al mismo tiempo, consideración con la salud pública.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me gustaría destacar que no todos los suelos son iguales en Europa y que no todos presentan la misma absorción de cadmio, aspecto que lamentablemente no se está teniendo en cuenta en estas negociaciones, en las que se están barajando cifras políticas sin fundamentos científicos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me gustaría dar las gracias aquí a la señora Gardini porque ha desplegado grandes esfuerzos en un asunto muy difícil. Y saludo, desde luego, la enmienda que ha propuesto el Grupo Popular Europeo después de haber sopesado todos los intereses en juego. Creo que se trata de una enmienda equilibrada que no satisface las máximas aspiraciones de nadie, pero que es una forma de encontrar un compromiso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lamento la voz con que me estoy dirigiendo a ustedes en el Pleno, y sobre todo lamento que los intérpretes tengan que estar escuchándome así, pero estoy enferma.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, stimați colegi, s-a vorbit foarte mult despre acest regulament și sigur că merită, este un regulament extrem de important. Ne-am blocat la aceste procente, însă, așa cum raportorul a arătat și alți colegi au arătat, există îmbunătățiri prin acest regulament pentru piața fertilizanților, pentru economia circulară. Însă, vreau să subliniez aici că, din păcate, Comisia nu a cuprins în estimare tot ce trebuia cuprins, de exemplu, ce impact ar avea asupra locurilor de muncă? Nu a spus nimic despre un studiu făcut la Universitatea din Olanda în 2016 - iată, constatările acestui studiu sunt relevante, dar sunt total în opoziție cu argumentele folosite de Comisie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu, ca membră IMCO, sigur, vreau ca orice votăm aici să fie foarte bine echilibrat între protecția consumatorului și susținerea industriei. Sigur că sănătatea oamenilor este importantă, dar dezindustrializarea continuă. Nu pot să nu spun că, din păcate, dacă se va stabili acest procent ambițios … Aici nu vorbim de ambiție, vorbim de rezultate, de cercetare tehnologică și nu putem să impunem un prag peste care industria nu ar putea. De aceea, voi susține propunerea fără scădere graduală și o propunere de 80 de miligrame.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, em 2016, a Comissão adotou uma proposta que estabelece regras relativas à disponibilização no mercado de produtos fertilizantes com marcação CE, passando a abranger um leque mais amplo destes produtos e abrindo o mercado único para a livre circulação de produtos fertilizantes produzidos a partir de matérias orgânicas ou de matérias-primas secundárias.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se é verdade que os adubos proporcionam benefícios relevantes quanto ao rendimento das colheitas, não é menos verdade que não podemos esquecer que existem importantes desafios em termos ambientais, de saúde pública e de segurança alimentar associados à utilização de adubos.</p>
      <p sl="en">O principal objetivo do relatório é incentivar a produção de adubos em grande escala na União, a partir de matérias-primas orgânicas ou secundárias nacionais, em conformidade com o modelo de economia circular, transformando os resíduos em nutrientes para as culturas. No entanto, o atual regulamento não aborda as questões ambientais associadas à contaminação dos solos, das águas interiores e das águas marinhas e, em última análise, dos géneros alimentícios. E o cádmio é disso um triste exemplo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Caros colegas, por tudo isto, entendo que os limites máximos de cádmio devem ser os mais baixos possíveis para, dessa forma, proporcionar um elevado nível de proteção para a saúde humana. E isto é o que eu tenho a dizer neste momento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-0000" speaker_id="124849" name="Massimo Paolucci" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il regolamento sui fertilizzanti è sicuramente un passo in avanti. Finalmente c'è un'armonizzazione delle norme, finalmente viene facilitato l'accesso al mercato di fertilizzanti innovativi, si promuove l'utilizzo di materiali organici e riciclati, finalmente etichette più chiare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Purtroppo non c'è ancora accordo sui limiti per il cadmio. Sul cadmio alcuni colleghi ci hanno invitato a essere prudenti e ragionevoli. Io credo che non sia ragionevole minimizzare o far finta di non sapere che il cadmio è un metallo pesante gravemente cancerogeno che contamina acqua, terra e cibo. Io credo che non sia ragionevole far finta di non sapere che in tanti paesi europei i limiti nazionali sono più bassi, ad Est e ad Ovest: 20, 22. L'Italia, che eccelle nell'agricoltura, ha un limite di 50.</p>
      <p sl="en">E allora è possibile, non proponiamo la luna. Applichiamo con determinazione il principio di precauzione. Cari colleghi, non dividiamoci: la proposta che abbiamo avanzato è ragionevole.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-0000" speaker_id="38420" name="Cristian-Silviu Buşoi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, aș dori să felicit raportorul pentru munca la acest dosar și pentru modul în care a gestionat sensibilitatea acestui subiect. Această inițiativă duce, într-adevăr, la deschiderea pieței unice pentru libera circulație a fertilizatorilor și încurajează, mai ales, utilizarea fertilizatorilor din materiale reciclate și organice, aduce produse sigure pentru sănătate și, de asemenea, standarde de securitate, mai multă calitate, siguranță și mai multă claritate în etichetare. Discuțiile trebuie, însă, să continue, deoarece încă există discrepanțe atât la nivel european, cât și între Uniunea Europeană și statele din care importăm produse agricole sau produse finite. Noi ne dorim ca, la nivel de Uniune, să fim ambițioși, așa cum bine s-a spus, dar, în același timp, trebuie să ținem cont și de realitatea din țările din afara UE și mai ales din regiunea Mercosur, pentru că aceste discrepanțe nu fac decât să creeze o concurență neloială în interiorul Uniunii și asta va dăuna agricultorilor europeni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la proposta di regolamento va nella giusta direzione, incentivando la produzione su larga scala di concimi organici ricavati da rifiuti, in linea con il modello dell'economia circolare, e agevolandone l'accesso al mercato unico in condizioni di parità con i tradizionali concimi inorganici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono positivi anche i limiti massimi per le impurità, come i contaminanti microbici, e il nuovo tenore minimo di nutrienti per categoria funzionale del prodotto, per garantire la qualità dei fertilizzanti con marcatura CE.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia poteva e doveva essere fatto di più per assicurare la sicurezza dei fertilizzanti e per ridurre i limiti per i metalli pesanti, in particolare il cadmio, per ciascuna categoria funzionale. Ritengo la proposta della commissione ENVI ragionevole e ritengo accettabile anche quella della commissione esecutiva, ma il compromesso avanzato – addirittura sedici anni per la riduzione del cadmio a 20 milligrammi per chilogrammo di prodotto – ritengo che rappresenti più un regalo alle aziende produttrici che una posizione seria e responsabile per tutelare ambiente e consumatori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, τα λιπάσματα αποτελούν προϊόντα για τα οποία απαιτείται να υπάρξουν αυστηροί κανόνες, προκειμένου να έχουμε προστασία της ποιότητας των τροφίμων, προστασία του περιβάλλοντος και της υγείας των καταναλωτών. Και νομίζω ότι η στήριξη της ευρωπαϊκής βιομηχανίας λιπασμάτων δεν θα πρέπει να αποβαίνει σε βάρος της υγείας των καταναλωτών, γι’ αυτό πρέπει σίγουρα να υπάρξει μείωση της περιεκτικότητας σε κάδμιο. Θα ήθελα επίσης να σας επισημάνω, κύριε Αβραμόπουλε, ότι είναι αναγκαίο να υπάρξει χρηματοδότηση ενός προγράμματος απονιτροποποίησης της ελληνικής αλλά και υπόλοιπης ευρωπαϊκής αγροτικής γης. Αυτό είναι κάτι που περιμένουν οι έλληνες αγρότες. Θέλουν πολύ μεγαλύτερες ενισχύσεις, για να έχουμε πραγματικά απονιτροποποίηση της ελληνικής γης και στήριξη, φυσικά, των καλλιεργειών, οι οποίες δεν θα αποβαίνουν σε βάρος της υγείας των καταναλωτών. Τέλος, θα πρέπει να επισημανθεί ότι, ενώ απαγορεύεται στην Ελλάδα η εισαγωγή φθηνών βουλγαρικών λιπασμάτων, που όμως δεν τηρούν τις προδιαγραφές, επιτρέπεται η εισαγωγή προϊόντων από τη Βουλγαρία που καλλιεργήθηκαν με τα απαγορευμένα λιπάσματα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, je vous remercie pour ce débat. Je commence par une clarification, cher Marc, en réponse à vos remarques. La Commission ne compte pas et ne souhaite pas rouvrir la directive «nitrates» avec cette proposition, je veux être clair sur ce point.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am confident that the Fertiliser Products Regulation will be really a major contribution to the circular economy in Europe. It will help to turn waste management challenges into economic opportunities for farmers, innovative European technology providers, and manufacturers. It will help us to put more reliance on domestic sources over raw materials that are critical to our agri-industry and it will release agri-chemical manufacturers from many of the regulatory constraints that they are under today.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we must make sure that this new framework does not create new risks. Instead, the regulation must hold manufacturers to account for the safety of their agri-chemicals. At the end of the day, the fertilisers market is a global commodity market, and European manufacturers can compete by adjusting rapidly to the high level of protection that the European farmers and citizens rightly expect.</p>
      <p sl="en">I look forward to your continued support and to constructive discussions on how to strike the right balance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-0000" speaker_id="131750" name="Mihai Ţurcanu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raportor. – Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, dragi colegi, am ascultat cu deosebit interes tot ceea ce s-a spus astăzi aici și vreau să vă asigur că voi ține cont de toate recomandările venite. Important acum este ca rezultatul de mâine să fie unul bun și, în negocieri, după cum am spus, voi ține cont de acest lucru. Rolul meu este să încerc să găsesc un numitor comun între statele membre care au poziții diferite în privința limitării nivelului de cadmiu, subiect fierbinte al acestui dosar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votul va avea loc marți 24.10.2017.</p>
      <p sl="en">Declarații scrise (articolul 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-2500" speaker_id="23816" name="András Gyürk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – A közös piac kiteljesítése a termésnövelő szerek tekintetében javítja az európai mezőgazdaság versenyképességét és lehetőséget ad egy közös egészségi minimum felállítására az unióban. A gazdaság élénkítése azonban nem lehet kizárólagos cél. Nem csak a szabályozás által közvetlenül befolyásolt munkavállalókat kell szem előtt tartanunk, hanem mindazokat, akik közvetve érintettek a kérdésben. Jelen esetben ez egy igen jelentős csoport: minden egyes európai polgár, akik nap, mint nap fogyasztanak az itt megtermelt ételekből. A jelentés legvitatottabb pontja, a foszfát-tartalmú műtrágyák kadmium szintje. A kadmium az emberi szervezet számára mérgező anyag, amely felhalmozódik az emberi testben és bizonyos szint fölött súlyos károsodást és rákot okoz. Mindannyiunk közös érdeke, hogy a műtrágyákon keresztül történő kadmium szennyezést a kritikus szint alatt tartsuk, még akkor is, ha ez a lépés a szennyező üzemek versenyképességének romlásához is vezet. A magyar szabályozás szigorú és előremutató a kadmium kérdésében.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az Európai Bizottság által beterjesztett és az Európai Parlamentben szakbizottsági szinten elfogadott fokozatos kadmium szintcsökkentés éppen a jelenlegi magyar szinthez való igazodást írja elő. Ez a helyes irány és nem támogathatok olyan javaslatot, amely a magyar lakosság által fogyasztott ételekben megsokszorozza a rákkeltő anyagokat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-5000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písemně. – Vážení kolegové, máme před sebou novelu směrnice o hnojivých výrobcích, která klade důraz na přísnější ochranu půdních zdrojů a životního prostředí. Zavádí a snižuje povolené limity pro těžké kovy, jako je kadmium, arsen a chrom, a pro patogenní látky. Také zavádí biostimulanty a umožňuje výrobu CE hnojiv ze zpracovaných zemědělských odpadů, jako je statkový hnůj nebo kompost, a tím snižuje závislost na fosfátech dovážených do EU ze třetích zemí. Pro využití hnoje je důležitá i úprava směrnice o dusičnanech. Lepší využití odpadů a navracení látek zpět do koloběhu není jen logickým krokem dobrého hospodáře, ale i příležitostí k inovacím a novým technologickým postupům. Zároveň je však třeba naleznout takové řešení, které by bylo vyváženou pozicí mezi ochranou životního prostředí, závislosti na fosforitu a účinností hnojiv. Oceňuji snižování administrativní zátěže a dobrovolnou harmonizaci – výrobcům stačí dodržet vnitrostátní předpisy. Nicméně nesouhlasím se začleněním mulčovacích folií do působnosti směrnice.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Criminal acts and penalties in the field of illicit drug trafficking  - Information exchange on, and an early warning system and risk assessment procedure for, new psychoactive substances  I (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-098-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Preşedinte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este dezbaterea privind recomandarea pentru a doua lectură a Comisiei pentru libertăți civile, justiție și afaceri interne, referitoare la infracțiunile și sancțiunile aplicabile în domeniul traficului ilicit de droguri [10537/1/2017 - C8-0325/2017 - 2013/0304(COD)] Raportor Teresa Jiménez-Becerril Barrio (A8-0317/2017)</p>
      <p sl="en">și raportul lui Michał Boni, în numele Comisiei pentru libertăți civile, justiție și afaceri interne, referitor la propunerea de regulament al Parlamentului European și al Consiliului de modificare a Regulamentului (CE) nr. 1920/2006 în ceea ce privește schimbul de informații, sistemul de alertă timpurie și procedura de evaluare a riscurilor pentru noile substanțe psihoactive [COM(2016)0547 - C8-0351/2016 - 2016/0261(COD)] (A8-0359/2016)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-0000" speaker_id="124896" name="Michał Boni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it took three years to achieve the final version of the new psychoactive substances solution with the Council. We have overcome the deadlock thanks to efforts by all partners, especially the Maltese Presidency.</p>
      <p sl="en">Why is this so important? Six hundred and twenty-eight new psychoactive substances were formally notified by the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction (EMCDDA) in 2016 as dangerous for life and health, of which 100 were notified for the first time; 560 substances are now monitored. There were 254 victims of new psychoactive substances who died in EU in 2016 and 2017. In my country – Poland – alone, nearly 3000 citizens were poisoned by new psychoactive substances from January to August this year.</p>
      <p sl="en">So it is a real challenge. New psychoactive substances are so readily accessible because of the new digital channels and lack of clear rules. It is a cross-border phenomenon, so our responses must be cross-border – European. It is our moral and political obligation to act.</p>
      <p sl="en">Together, all Member States and our partners, as well as local authorities and NGOs, must act with determination to protect the health of our citizens, especially the young generation. And they must act as fast as possible, using scientific knowledge to build an early warning system and proper risk assessment arrangements – which are crucial for banning dangerous substances – coordinating far more effectively the measures taken by particular countries, using best practices, promoting the understanding of all threats related to the drugs and new psychoactive substances, giving the proper tools to the EMCDDA and supporting its organisational and financial capability.</p>
      <p sl="en">The new procedure in the regulation will be as follows. Member States will ensure that the national focal points of the drugs network and of Europol provide the necessary information on the new psychoactive substances to the EMCDDA and Europol. The EMCDDA shall gather, together with Europol, all this information and communicate it to Member States and the Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">If there is a suspicion that the new psychoactive substance may pose health or social risks at EU level, the EMCDDA, the Commission or a majority of Member States can ask the EMCDDA to draft an initial report. The initial report shall give the first indication of the nature and scale of incidents, the chemical and physical description of the substance and the involvement of criminal groups in its manufacture. The report has to be prepared within five weeks.</p>
      <p sl="en">If the initial report indicates that the substance may pose severe risks, the Commission requests that EMCDDA prepare a risk assessment report, which should include more in-depth analysis. This will be done by the Scientific Committee of EMCDDA in six weeks.</p>
      <p sl="en">If the risk assessment report shows that the substance poses severe risks, the Commission prepares the delegated act to include this substance on the list of drugs. Member States have to ban this substance as soon as possible, but within six months at the latest.</p>
      <p sl="en">So, as a result, we are shortening the procedure by well over a year, we will have more common European actions, a more precise risk assessment model and an early warning system. This regulation will be a complement to the European Union drugs strategy and is necessary to protect our citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="96806" name="Teresa Jiménez-Becerril Barrio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señor presidente. Según el último Informe Europeo sobre Drogas 2017, presentado por el Observatorio Europeo de las Drogas y las Toxicomanías, las muertes por sobredosis han aumentado considerablemente debido a la falta de conocimientos sobre la peligrosidad de estas nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas.</p>
      <p sl="en">En 2015, hubo entre los veintiocho Estados miembros de la UE, más Noruega y Turquía, un total de 8 441 muertes por sobredosis, en su mayoría relacionadas con la heroína y otras drogas. Las drogas estimulantes ilegales más consumidas en Europa son la cocaína, el éxtasis y las anfetaminas.</p>
      <p sl="en">En mi país, España, se registraron en 2015 un total de 455 muertes inducidas por drogas —15 por cada millón de habitantes, frente a la media comunitaria de 21,3 por cada millón de ciudadanos—.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aparte de las drogas convencionales que ya he mencionado —como la cocaína y heroína—, el consumo de nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas está aumentando cada año. En junio de este año, el comisario Avramopoulos expresó su preocupación por los jóvenes, quienes se encuentran expuestos a sustancias nuevas y peligrosas. Estas nuevas sustancias psicoactivas que son legales, también conocidas como drogas de diseño, son un grupo de compuestos químicos sintéticos o semisintéticos que se producen en laboratorios industriales, la mayoría de ellos en China o en India, y que están circulando en un mercado lícito. La popularidad de estas sustancias ha ido aumentando en Europa y en el resto del mundo debido a su disponibilidad en Internet y a que se venden fácilmente en establecimientos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cada año, muchos jóvenes —particularmente hombres— mueren por haber consumido nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas. El Observatorio Europeo de las Drogas y las Toxicomanías de Lisboa detectó el pasado año 540 nuevas drogas psicotrópicas en la Unión, y la tendencia sigue aumentando cada año.</p>
      <p sl="en">El crecimiento de la venta en Internet de estos tipos de droga y la facilidad de elaborarlas han hecho más difícil que la Unión Europea pueda parar su producción. La Decisión marco de 2014 ya no era eficaz; por eso, era necesario un nuevo instrumento legislativo.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Comisión elaboró en 2013 un nuevo Reglamento —el señor Boni es el ponente del informe sobre ese Reglamento—y, como consecuencia, una nueva Directiva para superar este desafío legal. Casi cinco años más tarde, finalmente, hemos llegado a un acuerdo.</p>
      <p sl="en">El objetivo del paquete legislativo es reducir la disponibilidad de las nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas que presentan riesgos, lo que se llevará a cabo mediante una acción más rápida y eficaz a escala de la Unión en comparación con el instrumento que teníamos, de 2005, que no incluía el intercambio de información, la alerta rápida, la evaluación del riesgo ni el control de las nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Directiva, en particular, ha tenido como objetivo enmendar la Decisión marco 757/2004 para poder criminalizar las nuevas sustancias psicotrópicas. A partir de ahora los Estados miembros pueden adoptar las medidas necesarias para garantizar que los que la fabrican, los que la producen y los que la distribuyen —esta droga de diseño— sean castigados con penas máximas de cinco a diez años de privación de libertad. Tengo que recordar que esta Directiva no penaliza el consumo, sino el tráfico de esta droga.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estos dos instrumentos —Directiva y Reglamento— han recorrido un largo camino. El Parlamento aprobó la propuesta en 2014 pero, hasta hoy, no hemos podido encontrar un compromiso satisfactorio. Ambos informes son un éxito, ya que hemos alcanzado un acuerdo que ayudará a todos los ciudadanos europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero finalmente expresar mi agradecimiento a la Presidencia maltesa por su excelente trabajo para encontrar un equilibrio entre el Parlamento y el Consejo. También quiero dar las gracias a la Comisión por su papel de apoyo durante todas las reuniones de los diálogos tripartitos. Y, por último, quisiera expresar mi gratitud al señor Boni por la cooperación tan fructífera que hemos llevado a cabo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, our debate today is of great importance for our society, and especially our youth, who are our future. None of us here today can ignore this longstanding and continuously evolving threat affecting, directly or indirectly, the lives of millions of citizens in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">More than 93 million Europeans have tried an illicit drug in their lives. Overdose deaths continue to rise. As the Commissioner responsible, I am fully committed to the fight against this threat, which cuts across all generations. Despite, as you know, my particularly heavy obligations and responsibilities in tackling the migration crisis and threats to our security, the fight against drugs – I can assure you – is a key priority for me. Today we are proving once more that Europe is not just about numbers. Europe has a social face, it cares about those in need and it works hard to crack down on unscrupulous criminal networks and their unethical businesses. Drugs is one of these.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like warmly to welcome the successful conclusion, after four years, of the intense and demanding interinstitutional negotiations on the New Psychoactive Substances Package. This result would not have been possible without the great contribution of the two rapporteurs, Teresa Jiménez-Becerril Barrio and Michal Boni. I would like to thank both of them personally for their constant efforts and support, and their commitment.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition to traditional illicit drugs, the number of new and very harmful substances being placed on the European market, often as legal alternatives, is dramatically increasing. Our European Drugs Agency is currently monitoring more than 620 new psychoactive substances that cause severe health problems or even death. In fact, one new psychoactive substance is detected every week.</p>
      <p sl="en">Once the new legislation enters into force, we will leave behind lengthy procedures and will put in place an effective and efficient tool to tackle harmful new psychoactive substances. Information exchanges will improve and the role of the European Drugs Agency will be enhanced, including by working hand-in-hand with Europol. So far, the European Union has banned 19 new psychoactive substances and eight more are in the process of being banned.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank you in advance for adopting your opinion tomorrow on a concrete case of a very dangerous new psychoactive substance, furanylfentanyl, which must be made subject to control measures. Today’s package is part of a wider, comprehensive approach that this Commission has been working on for the past three years, in the context of the EU drugs strategy, in order to support Member States’ efforts in the fight against drugs.</p>
      <p sl="en">In July, the Council adopted the EU Drugs Action Plan for the period 2017 to 2020, on the basis of my proposal. This action plan enhances and updates existing actions, while it also identifies new priority areas such as online awareness-raising activities, targeting young people in particular, and exploring the potential connection between drug trafficking and the financing of terrorist groups, migrant smuggling and trafficking in human beings.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are also working very actively on the new policy cycle on organised and serious crime, towards disrupting activities related to drug production, trafficking and distribution in the European Union. The EU is also in the lead in the worldwide fight against drugs, together with its global partners. For the first time, the Union is speaking with one voice on drugs-related issues in international forums. We hope this will also be the case at the next meeting of the United Nations Commission on Narcotic Drugs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Obviously our fight against drugs is not finished with this legislation, but today we are sending a clear and strong message about our decisiveness and readiness to tackle new and very dangerous threats to our society. We must and we will continue our efforts in close and continuing cooperation with this House, the Member States and stakeholders. I am looking forward to the debate today and I thank you for the attention you are giving to European drugs policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="38420" name="Cristian-Silviu Buşoi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Commissioner, first of all I would like to congratulate Ms Jiménez-Becerril Barrio and Mr Boni on their very good reports. As rapporteur for the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety on the proposal for a regulation as regards information exchange, early warning systems and risk assessment, I confronted a harsh reality. There has been a rapid increase in the past years in the number and type of new psychoactive substances available and launched on the European drug market, with more than 600 substances being monitored by the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs. Of even more concern than this is the unprecedented increase in substance use among young people, which is really very worrying.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have stated, in the Environment Committee opinion, that the rapid growth of the market in these novel products makes it necessary to enhance monitoring and early warning systems so as to assess health, safety and social risks, in order to develop responses. Member States need to provide, without undue delay, all available information on detection and identification, use and patterns of use, prevalence of use, potential as well as identified risks and commercial, as well as medical and scientific, use of these substances.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Pane předsedají, neustálý vývoj a dostupnost nových psychoaktivních látek představují na poli boje proti drogám významnou hrozbu. Je tedy na místě, aby vnitřní trh Evropské unie reagoval na tuto inovaci v oblasti vývoje drog.</p>
      <p sl="en">Problém vidím zejména v syntetickém konopí, kde producenti po zákazu určité substance nepatrně změní složení látky a neustále se tak mění chemické vzorce. To umožňuje opětovnou dostupnost psychoaktivní látky na trhu v některé z členských zemí, v takzvaných smartshopech. Přitom se jedná o zdraví nebezpečné látky, na kterých lze vypěstovat závislost, zvláště u mladistvých. Účinná a fungující výměna informací ohledně těchto látek mezi členskými státy založená na systému včasného varování a hodnocení rizika je proto velmi žádoucí. Oceňuji poskytování informací mezi jednotlivými orgány bez zbytečného odkladu, například mezi Evropským monitorovacím centrem pro drogy a drogovou závislost a Europolem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oceňuji také rozšíření pro posouzení rizika nejen zdravotního, ale také bezpečnostního spojeného s novými psychoaktivními látkami. Rovněž vzhledem k tomu, že se míra podobnosti chemických struktur nových psychoaktivních látek často obtížně určuje, centrum by mělo mít pravomoc stanovit, zda mohou být určité látky považovány za dostatečně podobné.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cílem nařízení i směrnice je podpořit členské země v boji proti obchodu s drogami. Při respektu k subsidiaritě je i na evropské úrovni třeba využít zkušeností expertů a výměny informací pro efektivnější boj proti byznysu s drogami, které občany Evropské unie ohrožují. Proto děkuji Evropské komisi i oběma zpravodajům za jejich vytrvalou práci a věřím, že bude podpořena.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-0000" speaker_id="28131" name="Anna Hedh" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för S&amp;D-gruppen. – Herr talman! Jag vill börja med att tacka föredragandena för ett väldigt gott samarbete och kommissionsledamot Avramopoulos för hans inlägg i debatten. Vi har nu tillsammans, trots att medlemsländerna har dragit ut på tiden, lett den här lagstiftningen i mål.</p>
      <p sl="en">Antalet nya psykoaktiva substanser fortsätter att öka i Europa och orsakar dödsfall. Ungefär 600 substanser finns nu i EU:s databaser, och det finns inget som tyder på att problemet kommer att minska. Samvetslösa kriminella säljer substanserna, ibland under vilseledande beteckningar och i okontrollerade doser. Resultatet är potentiellt livsfarliga ämnen, som kan köpas av vem som helst. Självklart adresseras frågan i medlemsländerna, och det görs bra saker på nationell nivå, men för att kriminella grupper inte bara ska kunna byta medlemsstat krävs det europeiskt samarbete. Gemensamma databaser och kunskap är nödvändigt för att man snabbare ska kunna identifiera nya substanser och få en solid information om deras negativa hälsoeffekter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vad tillför då den nya lagstiftningen? Framför allt kommer paketet att innebära en förenkling av förfarandet på EU-nivå för att bedöma möjliga negativa effekter av ett nytt psykoaktivt ämne. Man kan snabbare fatta beslut om ett eventuellt förbud. Förfarandet kommer nu att vara nästan dubbelt så snabbt som tidigare. De nya bestämmelserna kommer dessutom att ytterligare minska den tid som medlemsländerna har för att genomföra EU-beslutet från tolv till sex månader.</p>
      <p sl="en">Slutligen kommer paketet att förhoppningsvis förbättra informationsutbytet, inte minst mellan relevanta EU-myndigheter, i systemet för tidig varning och riskbedömning på EU-nivå. Allt detta är oerhört viktigt. Ju snabbare vi kan kartlägga en substans och vidta åtgärder, desto mindre spridning. Tiden är en viktig faktor och det är i förlängningen en fråga om liv och död. Jag välkomnar att vi imorgon ska anta detta paket och uppmanar alla medlemsländer att utnyttja dessa instrument till fullo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="125105" name="Helga Stevens" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, collega's, psychoactieve stoffen zijn imitatiedrugs die een aanzienlijk negatief effect hebben op de volksgezondheid. Zo is er bijvoorbeeld de stof acrylfentanyl – een mondvol – een substantie die 50 keer sterker is dan morfine. Sinds de zomer van 2016 heeft die stof 40 slachtoffers gemaakt. Desondanks blijven Chinese producenten het gewoon online verkopen. Het is bovendien legaal in sommige lidstaten. De afgelopen tien jaar is het aantal varianten van psychoactieve stoffen op Europees niveau enorm toegenomen. In 2015 bijvoorbeeld werd gemiddeld om de drie dagen een nieuwe stof aangemeld in het EU-systeem voor vroegtijdige waarschuwing. Het probleem is dat het huidige Europese systeem achterhaald is, want het is enkel gericht op klassieke drugs. Bovendien laat het geen snel optreden toe, vandaar het voorstel voor een richtlijn waarover morgen wordt gestemd. Onder die nieuwe richtlijn blijven imitatiedrugs niet langer buiten schot in de gemeenschappelijke Europese aanpak in de strijd tegen drugs, met als uiteindelijk doel te voorkomen dat er problemen ontstaan bij politionele en gerechtelijke samenwerking in de Unie.</p>
      <p sl="en">De nieuwe richtlijn kort de termijnen voor een snel en doeltreffend optreden sterk in waardoor het EU—systeem voor vroegtijdige waarschuwing veel efficiënter zal werken. Iedereen is het erover eens dat gevaarlijke designerdrugs verboden moeten worden en van de markt moeten verdwijnen. Maar vandaag moet elke gevaarlijke stof die Europa wil verbieden een omslachtige wetgevende procedure doorlopen. Zo gaat er telkens kostbare tijd verloren. Morgen moet het Parlement zich bijvoorbeeld uitspreken over de stof furanylfentanyl. Dealers krijgen ondertussen vrij spel. Mensen worden ernstig ziek of gaan zelfs dood. En wanneer de betrokken stof uiteindelijk verboden wordt, is er al een nieuwe variant op de markt. Zo vechten we tegen de bierkaai. Met deze regels willen we hieraan een einde maken. Het is hoog tijd om de schadelijke drugs waarmee grof geld wordt verdiend, aan te pakken.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-0000" speaker_id="125038" name="Maite Pagazaurtundúa Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor presidente, quiero felicitar, en primer lugar, a la señora Jiménez-Becerril, por su trabajo, y también al señor Boni, a la Comisión y a todos los que han hablado antes que yo porque comparto fundamentalmente todo lo que han dicho. De hecho es repetir hablar sobre la detección de tantas sustancias psicotrópicas que tenemos, por una parte, que atender, evaluar y evitar que estén en el mercado, aunque una parte de lo que tenemos que hacer es educativo.</p>
      <p sl="en">En los años 80 yo pude ver cómo varios jóvenes de mi entorno se convertían en esquizofrénicos o tenían ataques psicóticos por las drogas psicotrópicas que existían en aquel momento y cómo otros fallecieron después de su adicción a la heroína. Hay una parte de lo que tenemos que hacer que es reflexiva y una parte que tenemos que hacer que, por supuesto, tiene que ver con la educación, porque las cifras de lo que estamos hablando no son cifras, son personas: vidas quebradas, abandono escolar, tragedias familiares y sociales, intoxicaciones severas, complicaciones de salud —como ya he dicho— mental o física, y también la muerte de adolescentes que son casi niños. Así que el argumento a favor de una acción de detección y alerta más efectiva y más proporcionada sobre estas sustancias es absolutamente necesario.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nosotros desde el Grupo liberal consideramos muy oportuno que se haya procedido a la revisión del mecanismo de alerta temprana sobre este tipo de nuevas sustancias, dada esa rápida evolución de la que estamos hablando y ese peligro cada vez mayor entre niños —prácticamente adolescentes, casi son niños— que tienen la posibilidad de conseguir estas drogas en internet, una gran accesibilidad, sin conocer los riesgos y los peligros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creemos necesaria una mayor cooperación de Europol con el Observatorio Europeo de las Drogas y las Toxicomanías y la Agencia Europea de Medicamentos. Tenemos que ir unidos en esto porque el problema rebasa las capacidades nacionales y debemos ayudar a superar la fragmentación, los obstáculos y las incertidumbres jurídicas. Llevamos esperando desde 2013 este paquete de medidas, así que esperamos que no haya más retrasos y que podamos aportar mucho, peleando muy poco y nunca más por la interpretación de nimiedades competenciales entre las instituciones. Necesitamos esta legislación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, o intercâmbio de informações entre Estados-Membros, a existência e o funcionamento de um sistema de alerta rápido e os procedimentos de avaliação dos riscos das novas substâncias psicoativas revestem-se de grande importância.</p>
      <p sl="en">O Observatório Europeu da Droga e da Toxicodependência monitorizará atualmente mais de 450 substâncias. Nos últimos anos, registou-se um aumento sem precedentes do número, tipo e disponibilidade de substâncias psicoativas, realidade que coincide com a persistência de uma profunda e arrastada crise social, com níveis de desemprego, de pobreza e de exclusão social muito significativos, com o ataque continuado a direitos sociais e laborais, com a debilitação dos serviços públicos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para intervir sobre esta realidade complexa, é recomendável uma abordagem abrangente, que integre as vertentes da prevenção, da dissuasão, da redução de riscos e minimização de danos, até ao tratamento e a reinserção social. É necessário aprofundar o conhecimento sobre uma realidade em acelerada mutação, quer no que respeita às substâncias, quer aos hábitos de consumo e sua prevalência nos diferentes grupos da população.</p>
      <p sl="en">É necessário identificar os constrangimentos no acesso ao sistema de prestação de cuidados de saúde e ampliar, diversificar e apetrechar devidamente a rede pública de serviços na área da toxicodependência, privilegiando uma resposta de proximidade. Um caminho que exige confrontar e reverter os efeitos das políticas de cortes na despesa pública que vêm sendo impostas pela União Europeia aos Estados-Membros.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="124993" name="Bodil Valero" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Herr talman! Det har skett en rekordartad ökning vad gäller antal, typ och tillgänglighet av nya psykoaktiva ämnen på den europeiska narkotikamarknaden. Michał Boni och andra har redan tagit upp den stora mängd substanser som för närvarande är under övervakning i systemet, men problemet är att vi ser en ständig ökning.</p>
      <p sl="en">De nya psykoaktiva ämnena är en stor utmaning för folkhälsan eftersom de producerar liknande effekter som de traditionella drogerna men ännu inte är narkotikaklassade. Dessa så kallade nätdroger är lätta att köpa in för vem som helst över internet. Vissa av dessa starka psykoaktiva substanser får många allvarliga och ibland dödliga konsekvenser och används tyvärr av många ungdomar i delar av Europa som billiga droger. De uppfattas som förhållandevis säkra och lagliga alternativ till de etablerade olagliga drogerna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det beräknas att EU-medborgare spenderar över 24 miljarder euro på olaglig narkotika varje år, att minst 6 800 människor avled till följd av överdos i EU under 2014 och att uppskattningsvis 17,8 miljoner unga vuxna har använt narkotika under det senaste året. De mänskliga och sociala kostnaderna för narkotikamissbruk är mycket höga. Detta ställer krav på ett snabbare och effektivare gemensamt system än dagens, för att kunna begränsa tillgängligheten av sådana droger i våra samhällen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi välkomnar därför den överenskommelse som institutionerna nu långt om länge ingått om det nya lagstiftningspaketet, som syftar till att väsentligt skynda på förfarandet på EU-nivå när det gäller riskbedömning och beslut om kontrollåtgärder. Vi stöder också beslutet att låta den rättsliga grunden handla om folkhälsa – det är mer naturligt, tycker vi – i stället för den interna marknaden, och vi är positiva till det mer vetenskapliga förhållningssättet i förslagen vid utredning av nya ämnens olika effekter. Förhandlingarna har ju som sagt pågått i mer än fyra år nu och vi har ingen mer tid att förlora. Vi behöver agera skyndsamt, effektivt och samordnat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="124945" name="Margot Parker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, combating the distribution of illegal drugs is a global issue that requires all countries to cooperate in order to effectively fight. How best to tackle this issue is, however, up for debate. Some countries have chosen to take a softer approach, whereas others – most notably the Philippines – enact a zero—tolerance policy on drugs. The EU, however, decides that the best way to tackle illegal drugs is via legislation. And whilst this may appear to show the EU taking the issue of drugs seriously, it fails to tackle the fundamental problems that facilitate the drug issues in the EU – that, of course, being the borderless Schengen area.</p>
      <p sl="en">A Europe without borders not only facilitates the free movement of drugs, but also the free movement of weapons, terrorists, and illegal migrants. If the EU wishes to take the protection of its citizens seriously, it must dismantle Schengen, and it must dismantle it straight away.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, είναι γεγονός ότι τα ναρκωτικά αποτελούν μια μάστιγα της σύγχρονης κοινωνίας, γι’ αυτό όλα τα κράτη, τόσο σε εθνικό όσο και σε διεθνές επίπεδο, προσπαθούν να καθορίσουν τις ναρκωτικές ουσίες, να τις εντοπίσουν, να περιορίσουν τη διακίνησή τους, να περιορίσουν τον εθισμό των νέων από αυτές και να επιβάλουν ποινές στους διακινητές και τους εμπόρους. Δυστυχώς, με όλα αυτά τα μέτρα αντιμετωπίζονται μόνο οι συνέπειες της παράνομης διακινήσεως των ναρκωτικών. Εάν θέλουμε να αντιμετωπίσουμε στη βάση του και αποφασιστικά το πρόβλημα, θα πρέπει τα κράτη να ενισχύσουν το θεσμό της οικογενείας. Αυτό θα συντελέσει ώστε να διαπαιδαγωγηθούν σωστά τα παιδιά, μέσα σε ένα υγιές περιβάλλον, να μην έχουν ψυχολογικά προβλήματα και να μην αισθάνονται την ανάγκη να καταφύγουν στους τεχνητούς παραδείσους των ναρκωτικών. Πρέπει τα σχολεία να πληροφορούν τους νέους για τις καταστρεπτικές συνέπειες της χρήσεως των ναρκωτικών. Επίσης, το κράτος πρέπει να φροντίσει να εξαλείψει την ανεργία των νέων, για να μην αναγκάζονται αυτοί να εθίζονται στα ναρκωτικά και να γίνονται υποχείρια των διακινητών και των εμπόρων. Τέλος, τα κράτη αλλά και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, ως διεθνής οργανισμός, οφείλουν να προστατεύσουν τη ζωή των πολιτών τους και να συγκρουστούν με τα συμφέροντα των διεθνών καρτέλ ναρκωτικών, όσο ισχυρά και αν είναι αυτά, και να επιβάλουν εξοντωτικές ποινές στους διακινητές και τους εμπόρους.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="124847" name="Elena Gentile" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, siamo di fronte a uno dei drammi del nostro tempo: l'uso e la dipendenza da sostanze psicotrope che minacciano la salute e la vita di milioni di persone. Questo tema incrocia il dramma esistenziale di giovani e adulti, ne minaccia l'equilibrio mentale, diventa occasione di malaffare e di traffici illeciti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il numero di sostanze è vertiginosamente in crescita e quindi mi pare non più rinviabile la decisione di rafforzare, rendendolo anche più capillare, il sistema di controllo e di allarme, accompagnando ai sistemi di controllo la ricerca sugli effetti e sugli esiti del sempre più frequente utilizzo anche di mix di sostanze.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine, e torno ancora su questo tema, la commercializzazione via internet di sostanze psicoattive dovrebbe essere tassativamente vietata, perché è accessibile a tutti e perché è anche, forse, più a buon mercato.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, psihoaktivne tvari i njihovi prekursori nikada se nisu proizvodili i globalno distribuirali većom brzinom nego danas. Veća dostupnost znanja i modernih tehnologija uza sve svoje pozitivne učinke donijela je i zloporabe poput primjene u proizvodnji i raspačavanju droga. Mi te zloporabe moramo zaustaviti, ali ne ograničavanjem dostupnosti znanja i tehnologije nego upravo suprotno, koristeći ih u razvijanju pametnih i učinkovitih politika te naprednih sustava za borbu protiv organiziranog kriminala.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ovaj prijedlog koji je danas pred nama iznimno je kvalitetan jer uspostavlja primjeren i učinkovit okvir za rano otkrivanje, brzo prijavljivanje i eliminaciju novih psihoaktivnih tvari s europskog tržišta, a da pri tom ne ugrožava princip supsidijarnosti. Ovakav konstruktivan pristup trebali bismo primijeniti i u bilateralnim odnosima s trećim zemljama, koje često predstavljaju izvorište novih psihoaktivnih tvari i njihovih prekursora, kako bismo zaustavili ovo zlo već na njegovom izvorištu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-0000" speaker_id="99650" name="Tim Aker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, for the past 50 years, governments have thrown billions, even trillions, of dollars, pounds and even euros at the so-called war on drugs, and all it has resulted in is more ways for the drug traffickers and drug cartels to put different substances on the streets. And now we get these psychoactive substances. In my constituency, you go down some streets and you find these little gas canisters on the street.</p>
      <p sl="en">Legislation like this – legislation like any in the war on drugs – is always reactive. You’re trying to put the toothpaste back in the tube: you’re trying to stop something that is already happening, and by the time you have stopped it another substance is on the street, another legal high.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unless you recognise and look at the social problems behind it, unless you realise that throwing more money, more money and more money at the war on drugs is not working, unless new ways are found, then you are just going to be wasting taxpayers’ money that could be spent on healthcare, education or defence, or on combating the problems and the criminality associated with drugs, but not necessarily addressing the drug problem itself.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η αντιαπαγορευτική πολιτική έχει χρεοκοπήσει και μόνο από το ότι στην Ολλανδία και την Τσεχία η χρήση κάνναβης ξεπερνά το 50% στους μαθητές, ακόμα και ηλικίας 13 ετών, ενώ στην Ελλάδα είναι μόλις 9% σύμφωνα με το Ευρωπαϊκό Κέντρο Παρακολούθησης. Οι πακτωλοί των μονοπωλιακών ομίλων για την προώθηση της αντιαπαγορευτικής εκστρατείας μαρτυρούν την επιδίωξη να πειστεί ο λαός ότι, όχι μόνο δεν κάνουν κακό τα ναρκωτικά, αλλά έχουν και θεραπευτικές ιδιότητες. Μάλιστα, χωρίς επίσημες έρευνες για χρησιμότητα και παρενέργειες. Η κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ με τη λεγόμενη «φαρμακευτική κάνναβη» ως Δούρειο Ίππο στοχεύει στην Ελλάδα στη νομιμοποίηση και απελευθέρωση των ναρκωτικών. Η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση προτείνει τώρα νέο «βάλε-βγάλε» από τις λίστες παράνομων ουσιών, που κρύβει παζάρι μεγαλοσυμφερόντων. Τα δε μέτρα συντονισμού μηχανισμών καταστολής είναι η άλλη όψη της αδιέξοδης ευρωενωσιακής πολιτικής των κυβερνήσεων. Τα ναρκωτικά δεν είναι ελεύθερη επιλογή. Είναι καταναγκασμός της ταξικής, εκμεταλλευτικής κοινωνίας που πρέπει να ανατραπεί. Όχι σε όλα τα ναρκωτικά. Ζωή ολόκληρη, όχι με δόσεις.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-0000" speaker_id="124861" name="Caterina Chinnici" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, ringrazio i colleghi relatori dei due dossier che oggi si discutono, con i quali si aggiorna il quadro legislativo europeo sulla lotta alla droga, criminalizzando il commercio illegale delle nuove sostanze psicoattive e psicotrope.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'assoggettamento del traffico illecito di tali nuove sostanze a disposizioni di diritto penale costituisce certo un deterrente, finalizzato anche a porre dei limiti alla disponibilità e al consumo di sostanze talvolta estremamente pericolose per la salute dei nostri giovani.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia, accanto agli interventi repressivi, è necessario predisporre misure di prevenzione e informazione proprio sugli effetti dannosi derivanti dall'uso delle nuove sostanze psicoattive. Occorre, quindi, porre in essere azioni coordinate fra gli Stati membri per armonizzare le legislazioni sostanziali nazionali e, naturalmente, così come giustamente sostenuto dalla proposta di regolamento, per garantire il più rapido scambio di informazioni sulle nuove sostanze che potrebbero essere classificate come psicoattive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ringrazio i relatori del pacchetto sulle droghe. Le nuove sostanze psicoattive sono un fenomeno relativamente nuovo e l'Europa è stata la prima a muoversi in tal senso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia, oggi il fenomeno va considerato come un fenomeno globale ed è necessario rispondere rapidamente alle nuove sfide con nuove misure. Sicuramente non possiamo accontentarci del silenzio che c'è stato finora; non è accettabile il silenzio rispetto ad alcuni eventi internazionali, come la riunione ministeriale alle Nazioni Unite del 2019 per valutare se la comunità internazionale ha eliminato o ridotto sensibilmente la coltivazione, la domanda, la produzione, il traffico e il riciclaggio dovuti agli stupefacenti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non possiamo ignorare la società, che ci chiede di discutere apertamente e senza tabù sui derivati della cannabis, sostanza che impegna le nostre forze dell'ordine per l'80 % delle sue risorse. Tra l'altro, la legalizzazione della cannabis permetterebbe di sottrarre alla criminalità organizzata un mercato che genera un volume d'affari di 9,3 miliardi l'anno. Troppo spesso sono state anche sottovalutate le importanti proprietà farmacologiche di questa sostanza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ritengo pertanto opportuno l'avvio di un dibattito aperto nei prossimi mesi in seno al Parlamento sul ruolo dell'Unione in sede ONU e sulla necessità di dare alla cannabis uno statuto che sia più al passo con i tempi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, dragi colegi, așa cum a rezultat din dezbaterea de până acum, era nevoie să venim cu o asemenea propunere. Comisia e foarte bine că a venit cu o asemenea propunere. Eu cred că datele statistice motivează acest lucru. În ultimii zece ani, s-a înregistrat o creștere masivă a noilor substanțe psihoactive atât la nivel lor global, cât și în Europa. Și, din păcate, nu există un semn de încetinire. În ultimii cinci ani, s-au descoperit 70 % din substanțele noi puse în circulație pe piață.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este clar nevoie ca Uniunea Europeană să acționeze în ceea ce privește noile substanțe psihoactive. Statele membre, în mod individual, nu pot controla problemele cauzate de răspândirea noilor substanțe. Acțiunile naționale necoordonate în acest domeniu pot produce efecte negative de domino, cum ar fi deplasarea substanțelor nocive dintr-un stat membru în alt stat. Grupurile infracționale ar putea profita de această situație și cel mai grav este că aici sunt atrași tinerii. Tinerii cad cel mai ușor în capcană. Este nevoie, evident, de o mai bună colaborare, de schimb de informații între Observatorul European pentru Droguri, Europol și Agenția Europeană pentru Medicamente, dar este nevoie și de o preocupare pentru educația tinerilor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, negli ultimi cinque anni è stato registrato un aumento senza precedenti del numero, del tipo e della disponibilità di nuove sostanze psicoattive in Europa, con oltre 100 nuovi stupefacenti identificati per la prima volta. L'Organizzazione mondiale della sanità afferma che le nuove sostanze psicoattive disponibili in Europa sono particolarmente pericolose per tossicità, interazione con altre sostanze e influenza sui processi mentali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il rapido aumento delle nuove sostanze psicoattive costituisce una nuova sfida per la definizione di una politica di lotta efficace contro l'uso di tali sostanze, in cui l'Unione europea deve essere in prima linea, sia attraverso l'azione di coordinamento di Europol sia attraverso il sistema di allarme rapido dell'UE, strumento essenziale perché in grado di consentire alle autorità nazionali di individuare le nuove sostanze e di agire prontamente per intercettarle e toglierle dal mercato.</p>
      <p sl="en">È necessario dunque uno sforzo comune delle istituzioni europee, uno sforzo economico, logistico e politico, affinché le autorità nazionali e comunitarie siano dotate di strumenti adeguati per combattere la diffusione e lo sviluppo dei nuovi stupefacenti, sempre più difficili da individuare e purtroppo sempre più pericolosi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, uvijek i svugdje, ali zaista uvijek i svugdje, činit ću sve da se droga makne, da droga nestane jer ona, ne treba puno ponavljati, koliko je zlo za čovječanstvo, koliko je zlo pogotovo za mlade. Nažalost, imam i loših iskustava. Neki su mi poznanici, znanci otišli zbog predoziranja. Ali, imam i pozitivnih iskustava. Iskustvo Istre na jednoj nižoj razini, ne na svjetskoj, ne na europskoj, ne na nacionalnoj, može pomoći jer ima dobrih primjera borbe proziv zloupotrebe droge, koordinirane akcije represivnih organa, ali i edukativnih, obrazovnih institucija, kao i zdravstvenih institucija kada već imamo ovisnike. Iskreni razgovori s ovisnicima mogu pomoći, ali na nama je da pokušamo sve ovo što se dešava efikasno sprečavati jer rapidni rast droga na žalost je nešto čemu danas svjedočimo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="124985" name="Luke Ming Flanagan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is fairly obvious that, if there was no prohibition on the consumption of cannabis, the synthetic forms of cannabis would disappear from the market in the same way that the demand for melted—down boot polish plummeted after the repeal of prohibition of alcohol in the US. The choice we must make is that of allowing access to a relatively benign plant, which has had many, many studies carried out on it, or leave our young people to the mercy of a legal, untested cocktail of chemicals.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Ireland alone, in the region of 100 000 people have a criminal record for possession of cannabis. It prevents them from travelling, from parenting and from access to decent employment. The law, rather than the drug, destroys their lives. This is the main reason why young people take these dangerous cocktails of drugs. The alternative is to face a life of ruin for taking a safer substance called cannabis.</p>
      <p sl="en">The war on drugs is a war on people. It must end. Start it by legalising cannabis now.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="125072" name="Ελευθέριος Συναδινός" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η έκθεση είναι μεν ευπρόσδεκτη, αλλά τα αποτελέσματά της όψιμα και ελλιπή. Δεδηλωμένη επιδίωξη αποτελεί μια απελευθερωμένη από τα ναρκωτικά κοινωνία, όχι η χαλαρή παθητική προσέγγιση με θεωρητικά μέτρα μείωσης των επιβλαβών συνεπειών της χρήσης. Η βραδύτητα απόκρισης, η αντικατάσταση ελεγχομένων ουσιών με νομότυπες, μη ελεγχόμενες εναλλακτικές ουσίες και οι πρακτικώς κατασταλτικοί στόχοι μιας περιεκτικής αντιναρκωτικής πολιτικής επιβάλλουν την ενιαία, γενική και ευέλικτη διεύρυνση των ορισμών. Απαιτούνται η προληπτική, έγκυρη ενημέρωση των πολιτών, η υποστηρικτική αντιμετώπιση των χρηστών ως ασθενείς και η αυστηρή εφαρμογή ποινικών μέτρων σε όλα τα στάδια μέχρι τη διάθεση. Επιπλέον, πρέπει να υιοθετηθεί ο απόλυτος περιορισμός κάθε ουσίας ως προς την παραγωγή, την οποιαδήποτε διακίνηση και την κατοχή με πρόθεση διάθεσης, ώστε να καταναλωθεί για ψυχοτρόπες ιδιότητές της με ελάχιστες κατάλληλες εξαιρέσεις στη βάση ήδη εφαρμοσμένων προγραμμάτων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, once again I would like to express my thanks to the European Parliament, and in particular to our two rapporteurs for their constructive work over the past year on this very important topic.</p>
      <p sl="en">As has been said today, we need a strong response to the phenomenon of the number of new drugs being detected at EU level. We need – and, again it is something we will work on – swift, strong action to protect Europeans, in particular our youth and those who are vulnerable in our societies, from the extremely dangerous threat of harmful new psychoactive substances.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proposed EU legislation will improve the speed of our action against these substances, enabling us to act even within weeks in the case of an immediate risk to public health. It also ensures that an effective process for exchange of information is in place, and that our European Drugs Agency has the competences and the resources to provide the relevant expert advice.</p>
      <p sl="en">A long process in Parliament and in the Council is coming to a successful end, but the fight against drugs does not end here. We have a lot of work ahead. We have taken some important steps but there is still much to do: firstly to protect our youth, as I have said, and also to support the victims and to prosecute the criminals.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission and I, personally, will stand by our Member States in tackling this sensitive issue. I count on your support and I am looking forward to an overwhelming majority for this important package in tomorrow’s vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="96806" name="Teresa Jiménez-Becerril Barrio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señor presidente, desde aquí hoy estamos lanzando un claro mensaje sobre la necesidad de penalizar las nuevas drogas psicotrópicas porque creo que 540 nuevas drogas al año no son algo que debamos menospreciar, porque la vida de nuestros jóvenes está en riesgo y es nuestro deber como legisladores no seguir ignorando esta gravísima amenaza. No podemos seguir en este limbo jurídico en el que hemos estado hasta ahora. Realmente, a mí, estar cinco años tramitando esto, me parece una vergüenza; yo creo que realmente tendríamos que haberlo hecho mucho más rápido. Finalmente, como ya he dicho y gracias a la Presidencia maltesa, hemos agilizado el trámite, pero nos ha costado sangre, sudor y lágrimas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que nuestros jóvenes y la amenaza y el riesgo que estas nuevas drogas psicotrópicas suponen para los jóvenes necesitaban mucha más agilidad. Por lo tanto, gracias a todos los parlamentarios, creo que hemos visto aquí que estamos todos en el mismo barco. Creo que es necesario penalizar estas drogas porque, aunque también se ha hablado de no penalizarlas, yo creo que no, yo creo que el problema que tienen estas drogas es la ignorancia sobre su peligrosidad —nuestros jóvenes no saben, porque no hay información sobre esto—; cuando empiecen a penalizarse se hará mucho más difícil el camino de los criminales, como ha dicho el comisario. Creo que tenemos que ser más rápidos que ellos. Por lo tanto, hoy hemos dado un gran paso, pero desde luego vamos a dar muchos más, y quiero dar las gracias al señor Boni, al comisario, a mis asistentes, a los asesores y a todos los que han trabajado durante estos cinco años para conseguir que mañana el resultado de esta votación sea favorable. Estoy segura de que así será, porque es lo que hemos visto hoy aquí.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127-0000" speaker_id="124896" name="Michał Boni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, again I would like to thank Teresa Jiménez and the shadow rapporteurs for their excellent cooperation. Commissioner, special thanks are due to the Commission because the Commission helped us to solve many problems, so thank you very much again.</p>
      <p sl="en">And thank you very much to all participants in this discussion because I think that it was very multi-dimensional. The debate focused on many issues but the goal is clear: to restrict access to new psychoactive substances and drugs and understand how important this cooperation among all institutions – the EMCDDA, Europol, Member States – is in order, on the one hand, to fight against criminal organisations and punish the sale, distribution and production of those substances and, on the other, to halt the spread of those substances all over Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second key point raised during the discussion is the problem of awareness. It would be a very good opportunity when we start implementation of the directive and the regulation for the EMCDDA to do more, in cooperation with all countries, to raise awareness about new psychoactive substances and drugs and make those issues much more understandable for all social groups, especially the younger generation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The last point is related to proper implementation, because having a good legislative framework and good cooperation is important, but we need to combine all such measures properly: legislation, cooperation between all institutions and awareness-raising.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się we wtorek 24 października 2017 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-5000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">It is estimated in official EU reports that in Europe there is a cocaine market of about 124 tonnes, worth about USD 34 billion, an increased use of narcotic drugs and higher health risks. It is clear that the criminal networks behind the illicit drug traffic demonstrate a resilient ability to adapt and diverge their modus operandi in order to make a widespread of drug use. In the cyclical search for drug supply and trafficking, criminal acts vary from funding with illicit capital to use of the latest technology to avoid being intercepted, and finally to money laundering.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, in order to combat illicit drug trafficking, the following actions are imperative: increase the criminal penalties; implement harsher laws for selling and buying drugs; and enhance international cooperation between authorities on drug trafficking, money laundering and tax evasion. I am confident that as we move forward by increasing international cooperation and by raising awareness of the health risks and legal consequences for the illicit drug trafficking, we will succeed in the field of illicit drug trafficking.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-7500" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – A kábítószerek világa egy gyorsan változó világ, mely egyre jobban veszélyezteti gyermekeink és fiataljaink testi és lelki egészségét. A drogkereskedők most már jelen vannak iskoláink környékén, ahol a fiatalok maguk egyre könnyebben juthatnak hozzá ezekhez a szerekhez. Integrált módon lehet csak fellépni a drog elleni küzdelemben: a megelőzés, a rehabilitáció, valamint a bűnüldözés is elengedhetetlen. Mindent meg kell tenni azért, hogy fiatalok, a tanárok és a szülők megfelelő felvilágosítást kapjanak. Továbbá elengedhetetlen, hogy a szintetikus szerek, amelyek talán a legmérgezőbbek, minél gyorsabban kerüljenek a tiltott drogok listájára. Minden elvesztett idő emberéletben mérhető ezen a területen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Legitimate measures to protect whistle-blowers acting in the public interest (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest krótka prezentacja sprawozdania sporządzonego przez Virginie Rozière w imieniu Komisji Prawnej w sprawie uzasadnionych środków ochrony sygnalistów działających w interesie publicznym podczas ujawniania poufnych informacji posiadanych przez przedsiębiorstwa i organy publiczne (2016/2224(INI)) (A8-0295/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="103845" name="Virginie Rozière" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteure">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, quand on présente un travail comme celui-là, il est d’usage de remercier les collègues pour le travail accompli. Je le ferais bien volontiers, mais je voulais commencer par remercier d’autres personnes. Dire merci à Antoine Deltour, merci à Raphaël Halet, merci à Irène Frachon, merci à Denis Robert, merci à tous ceux qui, un jour, font ce choix courageux qui est celui de parler. Cela n’est jamais un choix facile parce que, pour les lanceurs d’alerte, c’est faire le choix de la vérité, faire le choix de l’éthique, faire le choix de l’intérêt général, et c’est très souvent un choix qui se fait à ses propres risques et périls.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je voulais aussi souligner que c’est la première fois que ce Parlement adopte un texte sur la protection des lanceurs d’alerte. C’est assez surprenant, parce que d’autres institutions ont déjà adopté des résolutions sur ce sujet; je pense, en particulier, au Conseil de l’Europe, qui a adopté une résolution en 2014, qui fixe des objectifs ambitieux et élevés, objectifs sur lesquels d’ailleurs nous nous sommes basés dans nos travaux.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’ai parlé d’Antoine Deltour et de Raphaël Halet, et je voulais aussi souligner que, par contre, ce Parlement a souvent appelé à la protection des lanceurs d’alerte et que cela a souvent été dans le cadre des résolutions qui ont suivi l’affaire LuxLeaks. Je pense aux rapports des commissions spéciales TAXE 1 et TAXE 2.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, oui, nous avons remercié Antoine Deltour et Raphaël Halet, nous avons même remercié Antoine Deltour avec le prix du citoyen européen. Nous avons pris des mesures pour lutter contre l’évasion fiscale grâce à lui – grâce à eux –, mais aujourd’hui, Antoine Deltour et Raphaël Halet ont été condamnés à de la prison avec sursis. Alors, nous, nous avançons, nous travaillons et nous améliorons le quotidien des citoyens européens dans la lutte contre l’évasion fiscale, mais eux sont toujours condamnés.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est particulièrement important aujourd’hui que ce Parlement appelle à adopter un instrument pour protéger les lanceurs d’alerte en Europe. Dans ce texte, nous posons un cadre qui peut servir de base à une protection efficace. En particulier, nous proposons une définition large des lanceurs d’alerte, en considérant que nous ne devons pas nous attacher à une situation particulière – salariés, sous-traitants, consultants –, mais plutôt à la nature de l’information qui est révélée, et donc considérer qu’à partir du moment où un lanceur d’alerte divulgue une information sur des agissements contraires à l’intérêt général européen, à ce moment-là, il doit être protégé.</p>
      <p sl="en">Justement, quelle protection pour les lanceurs d’alerte? On sait que, très souvent, quand on parle, on est soumis à énormément de pression, voire à des représailles. Il s’agit donc de disposer clairement que ces représailles sont punissables pénalement et de veiller à ce qu’elles soient sanctionnées et à ce que le préjudice causé aux lanceurs d’alerte et à leur entourage soit pleinement réparé.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous souhaitons aussi que les lanceurs d’alerte puissent faire l’objet d’un soutien judiciaire financier lorsque c’est nécessaire. Nous voyons que, dans plusieurs cas, ils doivent faire face à des conditions de vie extrêmement dégradées, un travail perdu, une maison vendue, des ressources réduites au minimum. C’est pourquoi nous devons pouvoir également apporter un soutien financier dans certains cas, mais également une aide psychologique, parce que c’est à chaque fois une épreuve de se confronter à des organisations qui, elles, ont énormément de moyens – énormément de moyens d’action et de moyens de pression. Cette nécessité de rééquilibrer le rapport de forces, nous voulons aussi qu’elle soit prise en compte lorsqu’un lanceur d’alerte salarié fait l’objet de mesures à l’intérieur de son entreprise, pour qu’il appartienne bien à l’employeur d’apporter les garanties sur le fait qu’il ne s’agit pas là de représailles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous faisons une proposition importante: nous voulons que soient mises en place des autorités indépendantes pour accueillir, aider et conseiller les lanceurs d’alerte. Nous l’avons dit, ils sont souvent en situation de fragilité et livrés à eux-mêmes face à des organisations puissantes et, donc, ce réseau d’autorités indépendantes, avec une autorité indépendante européenne qui pourrait assurer la coordination et une voie de recours pour les lanceurs d’alerte, nous semble particulièrement important.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je veux prendre pour exemple un cas dont nous allons également discuter cette semaine, mais qui est d’une autre nature. Je pense à toutes ces personnes qui ont été confrontées aux dommages provoqués par le glyphosate. Je pense à Mme Grataloup, en particulier, qui a essayé d’alerter la compagnie Monsanto des méfaits, qui a essayé d’alerter les autorités nationales et qui n’a pas été entendue. C’est pour cela qu’une autorité indépendante chargée d’accueillir les lanceurs d’alerte serait un pas important.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais je voudrais aussi souligner, pour le coup, une tentative assez méprisable de certains collègues de l’autre côté de cet hémicycle, qui, la main sur le cœur, prétendent vouloir protéger les lanceurs d’alerte, mais qui, dans le même temps, voudraient dans ce rapport leur enlever toute possibilité d’avoir recours à la presse.</p>
      <p sl="en">Or, il est évident que c’est précisément dans les cas les plus problématiques, dans les cas les plus lourds, dans les cas les plus graves – on parle de corruption, on parle de malversations –, qu’il est nécessaire d’alerter la presse; ce sont les cas dans lesquels les lanceurs d’alerte sont les plus exposés. Quel sens cela aurait-il de vouloir supprimer la protection des lanceurs d’alerte justement pour ces cas les plus graves qui nécessitent de s’adresser directement à la presse? Ce n’est ni plus ni moins que nier le droit des citoyens à une information de qualité et supprimer les sources du journalisme d’investigation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je trouve particulièrement regrettable que, alors que nous allons rendre hommage au courage de Daphne Caruana Galizia, demain à midi, certains collègues essaient d’empêcher les lanceurs d’alerte de s’adresser directement à la presse. J’espère que tout le monde saura voir clair dans leur jeu et dans les votes de demain midi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já souhlasím s tím, aby byl legislativní rámec, tedy zákonná ochrana oznamovatelů, a to zejména na národní úrovni. Tyto osoby, whistleblowers, tedy oznamovatelé, kteří se rozhodnou zveřejnit důvěrné informace o nezákonném jednání, pomáhají bojovat proti podvodům, korupci a daňovým únikům.</p>
      <p sl="en">Při prosazování regulace na evropské úrovni ale doporučuji, abychom byli velmi obezřetní. Například v oblasti anonymity bychom měli hovořit spíše o důvěrnosti, kdy identita bude známa, ale pouze dozorčím orgánům. Rovněž nesouhlasím se vznikem fondů na podporu whistleblowers, které by se plnily právě z toho, co se jejich činností získá. Tuto souvislost považuji za velmi nebezpečnou. Zkrátka, právo na ochranu oznamovatelů je důležité a je třeba při evropském rámci respektovat národní rámec a velmi citlivý přístup.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, whistle—blowers are essential for protecting the public interest, saving public money and ensuring transparency and integrity in public life. In the light of recent scandals, and particularly following last week’s assassination of Maltese journalist Daphne Caruana Galizia, it is crucial that we adopt an EU-wide protection plan. When protecting whistle—blowers, we also protect journalists and their sources, we protect NGOs and freedom of speech, and we protect the truth.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am proud that my group has played such an important role in promoting EU action for the protection of whistle—blowers, and I want to thank my colleague, Virginie Rozière, for her work on the report. Transparency, democracy, free press and high ethical standards – both in public and private organisations – are the values that we protect when we protect whistle—blowers. We need to stand strong on these, especially when faced with attempts to dilute the substance of the report by some other groups in this House, namely the EPP. We in the European Parliament should lead the way on greater transparency, not pull the curtains shut or close the door.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, σε μια φάση που πραγματικά η Ευρώπη έχει εκατομμύρια ανέργους, που έχουμε εκατομμύρια φτωχούς και ταυτόχρονα τεράστιο δημόσιο χρέος, είναι βέβαιο ότι θα πρέπει να αντιμετωπιστεί με αποφασιστικότητα η φοροδιαφυγή, η φοροαποφυγή και, φυσικά, η διαφθορά. Και στην πάλη αυτή, σε αυτόν τον αγώνα, σημαντικό ρόλο παίζουν οι καταγγέλλοντες, οι οποίοι είτε εργάζονται στον δημόσιο είτε στον ιδιωτικό τομέα, και αποκαλύπτουν πραγματικά τα σκάνδαλα τα οποία συμβαίνουν. Πρέπει, λοιπόν, να υπάρξει μια προστασία για αυτούς τους ανθρώπους και επίσης να δοθεί η δυνατότητα να μπορούν να προσέρχονται αυθορμήτως. Αλλά, αν ξέρουν ότι θα τιμωρηθούν, προφανώς θα είναι πολύ δύσκολο να έχουμε τους καταγγέλλοντες. Είναι σημαντικό ότι είχαμε τη λίστα Φαλτσιάνι, αυτό που ονομάζεται στην Ελλάδα λίστα Λαγκάρντ, που αποκάλυψε τεράστια φοροδιαφυγή, η οποία έχει συμβεί και στην Ελλάδα. Προστασία, λοιπόν, των καταγγελόντων χάριν του δημοσίου συμφέροντος και για αυτό θα πρέπει να υιοθετήσουμε έναν ευρύ ορισμό της έννοιας του καταγγέλλοντος, να λαμβάνουμε υπόψη κυρίως το είδος της πληροφορίας και, φυσικά, να υπάρχει και προστασία τους, ακόμη και οικονομική στήριξη, αν θέλουμε πραγματικά οι καταγγέλλοντες να προσέρχονται και να αποκαλύπτουν αυτά τα οποία συμβαίνουν σε βάρος του δημοσίου συμφέροντος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, zviždači i zviždačice, i te kako trebaju i zaslužuju našu kompletnu zaštitu. Želim ovom prilikom zahvaliti se izvjestiteljici i svima koji su radili na ovom sjajnom dokumentu jer nam je on trebao već i ranije. Europski parlament uglavnom ne zaostaje kada su u pitanju teme javnosti, slobode, demokracije. Možda smo u ovom trenutku u ovoj materiji nešto malo zaostali, ali vjerujem da možemo i te kako napraviti brz i jasan napredak. Ovaj dokument nam upravo to i omogućava.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sjećam se nekih primjera iz Hrvatske, vrlo famozan jedan primjer, jedne zviždačice vezano za najveću tadašnju hrvatsku kompaniju INA-u, industriju nafte, i znam što je sve prolazila i u kakvoj je situaciji sve bila, a sve je to činjeno u javnom interesu. Zato u tom kontekstu želim snažno podržati sve namjere koje imamo jer sam siguran da će se mnogo toga lakše otkriti ako Parlament potpuno jasno stane na stranu onih koji nam žele samo dobro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="124985" name="Luke Ming Flanagan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is time for an end to the lip service when we come to talking about whistle-blowers. Everyone says they are wonderful; everyone says they are brave; everyone says they are exceptional. It’s only when we get to a situation where people don’t need to be brave to be whistle-blowers where it becomes normal to be a whistle-blower – then we can say that we have succeeded. At the moment, you have to be exceptional: if you become a whistle-blower in my country, you will be the one ending up digesting the whistle. You will end up unemployed; you will end up mentally destroyed. I have seen this on so many occasions. We have seen situations in my country where whistle-blowers in our police force have had false files and paedophilia charges put against them, since exposed. We have had members of our police force who have had rats hung on their door for exposing wrongdoing. We need to help these people. Either that, or we need to tell them, ‘keep quiet, otherwise your life will be destroyed’. Hopefully this will change it. A good start.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, da diversi anni il ruolo fondamentale svolto dagli informatori nella rivelazione di gravi violazioni dell'interesse pubblico è stato messo in evidenza da una serie di scandali in settori molto diversi, quali la tutela della sanità pubblica, l'ambiente e l'evasione fiscale.</p>
      <p sl="en">La protezione degli informatori rappresenta uno degli strumenti più importanti per salvaguardare l'interesse pubblico. Purtroppo le protezioni offerte, laddove esistenti, sono inadeguate o troppo frammentate per poter garantire un quadro coerente all'interno dell'Unione europea. Sono state sviluppate numerose norme internazionali in materia di protezione degli informatori, sulle quali dovrebbe quindi basarsi una normativa europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Conformemente a tali norme, la definizione di informatore dovrebbe essere sufficientemente ampia da coprire un numero massimo di situazioni e proteggere, in tal modo, i dipendenti del settore pubblico e privato, i consulenti e i lavoratori autonomi. Anche il caso della giornalista e blogger Daphne Caruana Galizia, che era stata denominata la "donna Wikileaks", ci obblighi a fare tutto ciò che possiamo per proteggere gli informatori che lavorano per portare alla luce condotte sbagliate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139-0000" speaker_id="124942" name="Molly Scott Cato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as Commissioner Moscovici told our committee last week, the European Parliament is leading the EU institutions in fighting tax avoidance and money laundering, but we would never have been able to do this without the work of Antoine Deltour: the LuxLeaks whistle-blower whose courage led to the setting up of a series of special tax committees. Daphne Caruana Galizia, the Maltese journalist who was killed by a car bomb last week, gave evidence to our committee about the tax affairs of the rich and powerful in Malta. These two brave people gave us the information we needed to challenge the corrupt and self-serving behaviour of the global plutocracy, behaviour that is shaking the very foundations of our democracy as people lose faith that the system works for them. One was found guilty and barely avoided jail. The other was viciously murdered.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is the sort of courage it takes to be a whistle-blower in a world without protective legislation. How much corruption remains hidden because those who know about it are too afraid to come forward? The legislation that Parliament proposes today would offer whistle-blowers the protection they need.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="124861" name="Caterina Chinnici" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, le rivelazioni di Panama Papers, Swiss Leaks e Lux Leaks sono soltanto gli ultimi grandi scandali che hanno messo in luce sistemi di evasione fiscale, di frode transnazionale, di corruzione, resi noti grazie all'iniziativa coraggiosa di coloro che hanno sentito il dovere di denunciare condotte criminose, volte a danneggiare la collettività.</p>
      <p sl="en">Al Parlamento europeo credo vada riconosciuto il merito di aver acceso i riflettori su un tema così delicato e attuale, mettendo in evidenza anche le differenze tra i sistemi nazionali degli Stati membri, in alcuni dei quali gli informatori non sono protetti o, talvolta, sono criminalizzati per l'azione svolta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ringrazio l'onorevole Rozière che, con il suo lavoro, ha evidenziato come sia ormai necessario un quadro normativo che preveda standard minimi per armonizzare il trattamento di tali casi e per tutelare gli informatori, attraverso l'istituzione di specifiche norme giuridiche, così da riconoscerne il ruolo fondamentale nell'interesse pubblico.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Fabio Massimo Castaldo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, parliamo di tutela dei whistle-blower, degli informatori, e quindi parliamo di lotta vera contro la corruzione, lotta vera per la trasparenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma, al di là delle parole, la realtà dei fatti ci racconta un sistema disomogeneo di norme, che varia da paese a paese: in questo momento nell'Unione europea ci sono paesi che hanno messo istituti veramente forti, veramente adeguati a quella che è la sfida, altri in cui addirittura gli informatori vengono criminalizzati, e ancor di più bisogna dire che questa tutela deve essere non solo formale ma anche sostanziale.</p>
      <p sl="en">È quindi necessario garantire la possibilità, anche per gli informatori anonimi, di poter operare, è quindi necessario metterli al riparo da ogni forma di ritorsione da parte dei datori di lavoro e delle istituzioni presso cui lavorano, e per questo, a mio modo di vedere, è fondamentale arrivare a un'inversione dell'onere della prova. In caso di demansionamenti, in caso di comportamenti potenzialmente discriminatori, sono coloro che li hanno effettuati che devono dimostrare la propria buona fede e non l'informatore, al contrario, che deve dimostrare che ha subito un torto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oltre a questo, forse bisognerebbe pensare anche a dei fondi per andare a ovviare alle conseguenze economiche. Questo è quello che noi dobbiamo fare se veramente vogliamo parlare di tutela dei whistle-blower, altrimenti al coraggio delle loro parole noi faremo seguire solamente il silenzio della nostra indifferenza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="132366" name="Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, meitä on järkyttänyt maltalaisen rohkean journalistin viikko sitten tapahtunut murha. Hän paljasti väärinkäytöksiä, korruptiota ja rikoksia. Tämä tapaus on ääriesimerkki siitä, kuinka väärinkäytösten ilmoittajien voi käydä, minkälaisia riskejä he ottavat ja miksi heitä pitää suojella.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mietintö sisältää paljon hyvää, kuten anonyymit ilmoituskanavat ja taloudellisen tuen väärinkäytösten ilmoittajille. On itsestään selvää, että pienten, keskisuurten ja suurten yritysten toimintaedellytysten pitää olla tasapuolisia sisämarkkinoilla, on kysymys sitten verotuksesta, julkisista hankinnoista tai ympäristönormien noudattamisesta. Tarvitsemme selkeää lainsäädäntöä sellaisten henkilöiden turvaksi, jotka paljastavat näiden yritysten ja yhteisöjen väärinkäytöksiä ja rikoksia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, zviždači imaju veliku važnost za svako društvo jer je riječ o ljudima koji ugrožavaju vlastitu dobrobit kako bi iznijeli skrivene informacije od javnog interesa. Za takvu im požrtvovnost društvo prečesto ne izražava zahvalnost u onolikoj mjeri u kojoj zaslužuju i dozvoljava da budu marginalizirani.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zaštita zviždača nameće se stoga kao nužnost želimo li ohrabriti građane da bez zadrške i straha otkrivaju informacije od javnog interesa. Prije svega ovdje mislim na kvalitetan zakonski okvir na nacionalnoj razini koji bi trebale usvojiti sve države članice.</p>
      <p sl="en">No, moram naglasiti kako apsolutna zakonska zaštita zviždača kakvu zazivaju izvjestiteljica i dio kolega jednostavno nije moguća. Kad bismo drugu stranu, onu koja se smatra oštećenom, potpuno onemogućili u traženju pravde pred sudom, de facto bismo ozakonili zloporabu položaja, klevetu i svjesno kršenje ugovora.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nisu svi slučajevi isti i ne bi bilo mudro skupno na njih primjenjivati posebna pravila. O tomu mogu li se ona primijeniti na konkretan slučaj zviždača ipak treba odlučivati sud.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, τόσο στον δημόσιο τομέα όσο και στις μεγάλες επιχειρήσεις, υπάρχουν ορισμένα άτομα τα οποία εκμεταλλεύονται τη θέση τους και προβαίνουν σε παράνομες δραστηριότητες, όπως απάτες, φοροδιαφυγές, παράνομο πλουτισμό και άλλες ατασθαλίες, δημιουργώντας έτσι και συντηρώντας την γενικότερης μορφής διαφθορά. Αντιδρώντας σε αυτήν την απαράδεκτη κατάσταση, ορισμένοι έντιμοι πολίτες καταγγέλλουν όποιες παράνομες δραστηριότητες υποπίπτουν στην αντίληψή τους. Δυστυχώς, πολλές φορές οι άνθρωποι αυτοί πέφτουν θύματα της εντιμότητος και του θάρρος τους, διότι διώκονται από τις εργασίες τους, απειλείται η ζωή τους, η ζωή των μελών της οικογενείας τους, πολλές φορές χάνουν και τη ζωή τους και, γενικώς, υποφέρουν. Επειδή, με τις δραστηριότητες αυτές, οι άνθρωποι αυτοί βοηθούν το κράτος να λειτουργήσει, οφείλει το κράτος να τους προστατεύσει και να μεθόδευσει και να θεσμοθετήσει διαδικασίες οι οποίες θα συμβάλουν στην ενίσχυση της προθυμίας τους να καταγγέλλουν αυτές τις παράνομες ενέργειες. Εδώ όμως πρέπει να προσέξουμε να μην υποθάλψουμε περιπτώσεις ψευδούς καταμηνύσεως και αντεκδικήσεως. Δεν θέλουμε καταδότες, θέλουμε ανθρώπους οι οποίοι θα καταγγέλλουν παράνομες δραστηριότητες, ούτως ώστε να λειτουργεί σωστά το κράτος με τις αρχές της χρηστής διοικήσεως και του κράτους δικαίου.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, once again I would like to express my thanks to the rapporteur for this report, which is an important contribution to our debate. The Commission strongly believes that protecting those who raise the alarm helps detect serious violations of the law which would otherwise be difficult to identify. Whistle—blowing is an upstream component of the chain of actions necessary for an effective enforcement of the law and the safeguarding of the public interest.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me underline that we should protect responsible whistle—blowing which genuinely seeks to protect the public interest. It is essential to safeguard the rights and interests of entities affected by whistle—blower reports, such as their right of defence. The question is how best to achieve this objective, and how we can contribute at EU level. As you know, the Commission is currently finalising its assessment of the scope of such EU action. Our open public consultation conducted this year attracted a lot of interest. We received some 5700 replies, of which around 200 were from stakeholder organisations. The full results are available online, but let me underline that respondents were overwhelmingly in favour of protecting whistle—blowers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Asked specifically in which areas the European Union should support Member States to better protect whistle—blowers, the top four areas they cited were: the fight against fraud and corruption, the fight against tax evasion and avoidance, the protection of the environment and the protection of public health and safety. To feed our assessment, we have also commissioned an external study. We are carrying out a detailed mapping of the legal situation across the European Union, including through targeted consultations with national authorities and other stakeholders.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will consider further actions in the first part of 2018. In this context, your report is very timely, and the solutions proposed will be taken into account in our work.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się we wtorek 24 października 2017 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-2500" speaker_id="124898" name="Julia Pitera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Ochrona sygnalistów wymaga przemyślanego i odpowiedzialnego określenia ram, w jakich osoba informująca o nieprawidłowościach ma być chroniona przepisami prawa. Przekroczenie tych ram może prowadzić do zdegenerowania systemu i stworzenia narzędzi, które mogłyby posłużyć władzy o ciągotach autorytarnych do walki ze swoimi wrogami politycznymi. Pojawiające się co i raz koncepcje, by przenieść na oskarżanego o nadużycia obowiązek udowadniania swojej niewinności, zamiast domagać się od oskarżającego przedstawienia wiarygodnych dowodów świadczących jednoznacznie o winie, jest właśnie takim narzędziem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podobnie jak postulat utworzenia powszechnie dostępnych stron internetowych, pozwalających każdemu na anonimowe oskarżanie dowolnej osoby bez ponoszenia odpowiedzialności za ewentualnie wyrządzone krzywdy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Również dziennikarze powinni nadal pozostawać chronieni przez prawo prasowe – nie powinien przysługiwać im status sygnalisty. Prawo prasowe bowiem pozwala, a nawet nakazuje dziennikarzom chronienie swoich informatorów, ale jednocześnie wymaga od nich rzetelnego sprawdzania pochodzących z takiego źródła informacji. W przeciwnym razie dziennikarstwo mogłoby się przemienić w arenę walki rozmaitych środowisk pomiędzy sobą. Tak więc dziennikarzom nie powinien przynależeć status sygnalisty.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bądźmy więc rozważni, aby demonstrując wyborcom bezkompromisową wolę walki o uczciwość, nie wylać dziecka z kąpielą. By stworzony system ochrony sygnalistów realnie służył wspólnemu interesowi publicznemu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-5000" speaker_id="33989" name="Daciana Octavia Sârbu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – În ultimii ani, denunțătorii din interiorul instituțiilor publice sau al companiilor au contribuit la dezvăluirea multor fraude sau comportamente ilegale. Însă este nevoie ca denunțătorii sa fie protejați de posibile abuzuri. Din păcate, protecția oferită, în cazul în care există, este încă foarte insuficientă și prea fragmentată pentru a crea un cadru coerent în Uniunea Europeană. Trebuie să fie asigurată protecția confidențialității și ar trebui să fie introdusă o inversare a sarcinii probei; în același timp, ar trebui introduse dispoziții privind sprijinul financiar, psihologic, precum și privind despăgubirea prejudiciului. Însă este elementar să fie bine definit denunțul, astfel încât persoane care vor răzbunări personale sau promovări să nu se folosească de acest instrument în scopuri lipsite de etică.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-7500" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">par écrit. – Les lanceurs d’alerte sont essentiels dans une société démocratique; pourtant ils sont souvent menacés par les procédures judiciaires ainsi que par des représailles sur leur lieu de travail. Les législations nationales sont différentes d'un pays à l'autre et souvent inadaptées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous exigeons de la Commission européenne une proposition de législation afin d'assurer la protection des lanceurs d'alerte à l'échelle européenne et ce, d'ici la fin de l'année. Le paradoxe aujourd'hui, c'est de constater que les lanceurs d'alerte sont victimes de menaces, de persécutions et de poursuites judiciaires alors que, dans le même temps, ceux qui sont dénoncés sont relativement protégés. Les lanceurs d'alerte sont les sentinelles de notre époque, et quand ils servent l'intérêt général, ils doivent être protégés convenablement.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. Minimum income policies as a tool for fighting poverty (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-149-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest krótka prezentacja sprawozdania sporządzonego przez Laurę Ageę w imieniu Komisji Zatrudnienia i Spraw Socjalnych w sprawie polityki gwarantowanego minimalnego dochodu jako narzędzia do zwalczania ubóstwa (2016/2270(INI)) (A8-0292/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-0000" speaker_id="124811" name="Laura Agea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatrice. – Signor Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, cittadini, oggi è chiaro a tutti che la povertà è un problema europeo, causato proprio dalle politiche che questa Unione europea ha perpetrato per anni.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'ultima speranza per mettere un freno all'emergenza della povertà è la volontà da parte di tutti i paesi di adottare un reddito minimo che restituisca vita e dignità ai quasi 120 milioni di cittadini europei che non riescono più ad arrivare alla fine del mese e lottano per sopravvivere.</p>
      <p sl="en">Con questo documento l'Europa non potrà più girarsi dall'altra parte con indifferenza quando si parla della sofferenza dei suoi cittadini. L'Europa non deve più restare sorda di fronte alle richieste di aiuto che le famiglie e le imprese le rivolgono da anni. La Commissione europea affronti senza indugio la questione del reddito minimo, presentando quanto prima la proposta di una direttiva vincolante.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oggi, secondo l'Osservatorio sociale europeo, diverse forme di sostegno al reddito esistono già in 26 Stati membri, e con rammarico devo aggiungere che nel mio paese non esiste un reddito minimo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi vogliamo che l'Europa intervenga immediatamente con un quadro comune di norme che permetta l'armonizzazione dei diversi regimi vigenti con criteri di accesso comuni e validi per tutti come, ad esempio, basare il calcolo del reddito da erogare sulla soglia di povertà, che Eurostat fissa al 60 % del reddito medio nazionale. Non esistono cittadini di serie B, tutti devono poter beneficiare allo stesso modo dei regimi di reddito minimo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le parole non bastano più, bisogna mettere a disposizione le linee di bilancio del Fondo sociale europeo e del Programma europeo per l'occupazione e l'innovazione sociale per aiutare gli Stati membri a implementare regimi di reddito minimo. Si tratta di un approccio strategico e di visione, che consenta una vera e propria integrazione sociale. Non si tratta solo di soldi: i cittadini non chiedono elemosina, ma politiche di dignità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se si trovano i soldi per salvare le banche, tanto più pretendo che si trovino risorse per i figli di quest'Europa che è vittima, troppo spesso, di interessi scellerati. Questo nostro continente deve ritrovare il suo volto umano, assicurando assistenza sanitaria, alloggio, istruzione e dignità attraverso politiche economiche espansive a beneficio di tutti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vorrei concludere ringraziando il Commissario e i colleghi relatori, ma anche dicendo che questo lavoro, questo documento, porta la mia firma, porta la firma del Movimento 5 Stelle, ma racchiude i nomi di tutti i 120 milioni di cittadini europei per i quali è stato scritto. Il nostro impegno, la nostra dedizione e il nostro lavoro sono stati, sono e saranno sempre rivolti ai cittadini.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já nemůžu odolat, abych nereagovala na výzvu paní zpravodajky. Já jen chci upozornit, že Evropská unie nemůže nahradit rozhodování parlamentů a vlád členských států. Přesto univerzální minimální příjem je již v mnoha zemích realitou, jak ona sama přiznala, byť se třeba jmenuje jinak, například životní minimum, jako máme v České republice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je ale otázkou, zda má existovat nějaký minimální příjem definovaný na evropské úrovni. Já osobně s tím nesouhlasím, stejně tak jako nesouhlasím s definováním minimální mzdy na úrovni Evropské unie. Přijaté znění této zprávy je ale akceptovatelné, protože pouze vybízí všechny státy, aby zvážily nějakou formu minimálního příjmu. Osobně jsem proti tomu, abychom ve zprávě zmiňovali možnost směrnice Evropské unie o minimálním příjmu, a nesouhlasím s výzvou k založení fondu Evropské unie. Byla by to utopie a falešný slib voličům, který by Evropský parlament měl odmítnout.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, i dati sulla povertà nell'Unione europea destano molta preoccupazione, dati che le politiche di austerità di questi anni hanno acuito: 119 milioni di persone dell'Unione europea, circa il 25 % della popolazione totale, sono a rischio di povertà ed esclusione sociale, e a questi dati vanno aggiunti gli elevati tassi di disoccupazione, soprattutto giovanile.</p>
      <p sl="en">Una delle mie prime iniziative da parlamentare europeo è stata quella di interrogare la Commissione sulla grave condizione di milioni di cittadini europei che non riescono a soddisfare le proprie necessità primarie. Il reddito minimo di cittadinanza è una possibilità, anche se declinata con sfumature differenti nei vari Stati membri.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europa deve saper costruire un sistema comune di welfare fondato sulla centralità e sul protagonismo di ogni cittadino europeo. È doveroso lanciare una strategia integrata di lotta alla povertà, basata su indicatori oggettivi e con una tempistica di realizzazione precisa, per far sì che siano rispettati gli obiettivi di Europa 2020.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η λιτότητα, η βίαιη δημοσιονομική προσαρμογή έχουν πραγματικά οδηγήσει τεράστια τμήματα του πληθυσμού όλης της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης στη φτώχεια και στην ανεργία. Έχουμε πάνω από 119 εκατομμύρια άτομα τα οποία βρίσκονται σε κίνδυνο φτώχειας στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, δηλαδή περίπου το 25% του συνολικού πληθυσμού. Η ανεργία κυρίως πλήττει τους νέους και αυτό συμβαίνει σε όλον τον ευρωπαϊκό νότο, με την Ελλάδα να αναδεικνύεται πρωταθλήτρια στην ανεργία των νέων. Το 40% του ελληνικού πληθυσμού ζει κάτω από το όριο της φτώχειας λόγω των μνημονίων τα οποία έχει επιβάλει η τρόικα που συνεχίζει τη φορομπηχτική πολιτική και ταυτόχρονα οδηγεί τους έλληνες πολίτες μακριά από τα σπίτια τους, μια και τα κόκκινα δάνεια έχουν σαν αποτέλεσμα πλέον η τρόικα να επιβάλλει ηλεκτρονικούς πλειστηριασμούς και τα κοράκια να αρπάζουν τα σπίτια των Ελλήνων. Απαιτείται, λοιπόν, ένα σύστημα ελάχιστου εισοδήματος, απαιτείται ένας ελάχιστος ευρωπαϊκός μισθός, μπορεί να υπάρξει χρηματοδότηση μέσα από το Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινωνικό Ταμείο και μια οδηγία που να επιβάλλει υποχρεωτικά το σύστημα του ελάχιστου εγγυημένου εισοδήματος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. Quiero apoyar la aprobación de un marco europeo que establezca las condiciones de una renta mínima a nivel europeo y que anime a los Estados a entender que este gasto es una inversión. Es la mejor respuesta conocida, después de un empleo digno y de calidad, para rescatar a las personas de la marginalidad, evitar las terribles secuelas personales que produce el desempleo, proporcionar una plataforma sólida para su reinserción laboral y combatir la pobreza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los datos hablan por sí solos: en el País Vasco creemos en la Europa social. Hemos hecho un esfuerzo sostenido e intenso. La renta de inserción que funciona en Euskadi, que no alcanza el 5 % de la población estatal, atiende al 20 % de los perceptores y supone casi cerca del 40 % del dinero que se gasta en este concepto en el Estado. Así, nuestra tasa de riesgo de pobreza no alcanza el 9 %, frente al 22,3 % que se registra en nuestro Estado miembro, y los mecanismos de inserción influyen decisivamente también en nuestros índices de paro, igualmente los más bajos del Estado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este es el camino.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, falar de políticas de rendimento mínimo é falar das verdadeiras causas que a justificam; é falar das razões por que vivem hoje na pobreza 125 milhões de pessoas na União Europeia, que produz 20 % do PIB mundial; é falar das razões por que são crescentes as desigualdades económicas e sociais, os níveis de exploração laboral ou a precariedade.</p>
      <p sl="en">A resposta é clara: é na matriz capitalista da União Europeia e das políticas que têm promovido que estão as causas que justificam a necessidade destes instrumentos – instrumentos transitórios que são necessários, mas que não respondem às causas de fundo. Essas combatem-se com ruturas reais, com os constrangimentos que as políticas da UE impõem aos Estados e impedem políticas de efetiva redistribuição da riqueza, a promoção do trabalho digno com direitos, os avanços de acordos de contratação coletiva, o aumento real de salários, o combate às desigualdades ou a garantia de serviços públicos, gratuitos e de qualidade, de saúde, segurança social e educação – enfim, políticas progressistas de desenvolvimento que deem resposta às necessidades dos trabalhadores e dos povos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-0000" speaker_id="188624" name="Wajid Khan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we have a minimum wage in the United Kingdom. It is called a minimum wage, but it is less than the minimum amount a person can live on. Its spending value is lower now than it was nine years ago. In the UK, more than seven million people in working families protected by the so—called minimum wage live in poverty. The latest figures show that 1.1 million people in the UK are using food banks, over a quarter of whom are in work.</p>
      <p sl="en">Only a real living wage will truly tackle in—work poverty. A living wage is a fundamental issue of social justice. It is the most basic economic protection there is. It is a guarantee by each state to its citizens that their work will earn them enough to live off. The introduction of the minimum wage across all EU states is welcome, but it is my sincere hope that we will set our sights on making a minimum wage a living wage.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η εσφαλμένη οικονομική πολιτική που εφήρμοσε η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση την τελευταία δεκαετία υπήρξε αιτία εκατομμύρια Ευρωπαίων, κυρίως στις χώρες του Νότου, να ζουν αυτή τη στιγμή είτε στα όρια της φτώχειας είτε μέσα στη φτώχεια και την ανεργία, κυρίως των νέων. Για αυτό, για να αντιμετωπιστεί αυτή η απαράδεκτη κατάσταση, πρέπει να καθιερωθεί ένα ελάχιστο εγγυημένο εισόδημα σε όλες τις χώρες της Ευρώπης, ούτως ώστε να πάψει ο Ευρωπαίος να ζει εξαθλιωμένος. Στα πλαίσια αυτά, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση οφείλει να αφήσει την κακεντρεχή και πέραν πάσης λογικής πολιτική της εφαρμογής των μνημονίων στην Ελλάδα, η οποία έχει οδηγήσει στην εξαθλίωση το μεγαλύτερο μέρος του πληθυσμού της χώρας. Είναι εντελώς υποκριτικό να συζητούμε εδώ για την καθιέρωση ενός ελαχίστου εγγυημένου εισοδήματος του Ευρωπαίου πολίτη και, από την άλλη πλευρά, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση να βοηθάει τη Γερμανία να υφαρπάσσει τον επίγειο θαλάσσιο και υποθαλάσσιο πλούτο της χώρας. Είναι μια απαράδεκτη κατάσταση η οποία πρέπει οπωσδήποτε να λήξει.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-0000" speaker_id="103488" name="Sergio Gutiérrez Prieto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, hemos trabajado mucho y duramente para hacer este informe y por eso quiero dar la enhorabuena a la ponente, a mi compañera Laura Agea. Pero hemos trabajado mucho para solicitar tener un consenso, para solicitar a la Comisión Europea una directiva sobre rentas mínimas. Una propuesta, en definitiva, que cubra los huecos que hemos descubierto que existen tras la dureza de la crisis económica en nuestro modelo social, en nuestro Estado del bienestar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hemos de crear un nuevo sistema que proteja a las personas que después de más de dos años en el desempleo pierden su prestación y, por lo tanto, se quedan en los arcenes de la salida de la crisis, se quedan en los porcentajes de personas en riesgo de exclusión social.</p>
      <p sl="en">Queremos una directiva que obligue a los Estados miembros a crear este sistema de rentas mínimas; que les obligue a dar una cuantía por encima del 60 % de la renta disponible de las familias de cada Estado miembro; que también incorpore políticas de inserción laboral y, por lo tanto, que haga, desde la iniciativa, desde la política, una sociedad más justa y más decente para la inmensa mayoría de los ciudadanos que esperan de esta Europa algo más que lamentos y algo más que porcentajes, en este caso de personas que viven en el umbral de la pobreza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a introdução e o reforço das políticas de rendimento mínimo, se devidamente combinados com outras medidas e políticas relativas ao mercado social e laboral, podem ser uma forma de combater a pobreza e promover a inclusão social e o acesso ao mercado de trabalho. Creio ainda que os regimes de rendimento mínimo podem também atuar como estabilizadores macroeconómicos automáticos na reação aos choques económicos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em 2015, 23,7% da população e 12,5% dos trabalhadores com mais de 18 anos na União Europeia estavam em risco de pobreza e de exclusão social.</p>
      <p sl="en">Caros colegas, a Europa é uma das regiões mais prósperas do mundo, mas estes dados mostram uma crua e dura realidade que urge combater. O Observatório Social Europeu tem vindo a referir que 26 Estados-Membros dispõem já de regimes de apoio ao rendimento, subsistindo, porém, muitas diferenças entre os Estados-Membros relativamente ao tratamento das políticas de rendimento mínimo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por tudo isto, expresso a minha concordância com este relatório, que insta, designadamente, todos os Estados-Membros a introduzirem regimes de rendimento mínimo adequados, como última rede de proteção social, como forma de lutar contra a pobreza e assegurar uma existência digna a todos aqueles que não dispõem de recursos suficientes, e propõe que a Comissão pondere a criação de um Fundo Europeu adequado, numa base temporária, que funcione como um instrumento da política de coesão e de sociedade europeia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-0000" speaker_id="125090" name="Σωτήριος Ζαριανόπουλος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το ελάχιστο εγγυημένο εισόδημα, αυτό το καμάρι της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και όλων των κομμάτων ― φιλελεύθερων, σοσιαλδημοκρατών, ακροδεξιών και φασιστών ― των οπορτουνιστών που το στηρίζουν, αποτελεί κορυφαίο δείγμα υποκρισίας για δήθεν κοινωνική ευαισθησία. Το λαϊκό εισόδημα, ρημαγμένο από απολύσεις, μειώσεις μισθών, συντάξεων, επιδομάτων, άγρια φοροεπιδρομή, χρηματοδοτεί αυτό το δίχτυ δήθεν ασφαλείας για ελεημοσύνη στις πιο ακραίες περιπτώσεις εξαθλίωσης και αποτροπή της έκρηξής τους. Μοιράζει δηλαδή τη φτώχεια μεταξύ φτωχών και ακόμα φτωχότερων με άθικτα τα κέρδη των μονοπωλίων. Αυτή η δήθεν ασφάλεια πλασάρεται επίσης στους εργαζόμενους για να ανεχθούν περαιτέρω μειώσεις μισθών, κατάργηση των συλλογικών συμβάσεων εργασίας ― βλέπε Γαλλία του Μακρόν, Ελλάδα του ΣΥΡΙΖΑ κ.λπ. Οι εργαζόμενοι να απορρίψουν αυτόν το Δούρειο Ίππο για τα τελευταία δικαιώματά τους. Να αρνηθούν το μικρότερο κακό που αποδεικνύεται πάντα μεγαλύτερο. Με οργάνωση και πάλη, να διεκδικήσουν αυξημένα επιδόματα ανεργίας για όλους τους ανέργους, σε όλη τη διάρκεια της ανεργίας, υπογραφή συλλογικών συμβάσεων εργασίας με αναπλήρωση των απωλειών και μισθούς που να καλύπτουν τις ανάγκες των εργαζόμενων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, ideju o minimalnom dohotku kao negativnom porezu na dohodak koji bi zamijenio sve druge socijalne transfere i drastično smanjio administraciju ekonomska ljevica sve češće zloupotrebljava.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cilj zajamčenog minimalnog dohotka, kako ga je zamislio Milton Friedman, nije uvođenje još jedne socijalne mjere na račun produktivnog dijela stanovništva, već upravo suprotno – pojednostavljenje socijalnog sustava i to na način da država svima, a ne samo nekima, osigura osnovne uvjete za život dok bi za sve ostale trebalo raditi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Budući da se zaposlenjem ne bi gubilo pravo na minimalni dohodak kao što se danas u pravilu gubi na različite socijalne mjere, ljudi bi imali veći motiv tražiti posao kako bi dodatno zaradili. S druge strane, oni koji žele volontirati i baviti se humanitarnim radom imali bi više vremena za takve aktivnosti jer osnovni dohodak ipak imaju zajamčen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nažalost, u ovom se izvješću radi o nečemu sasvim drugome i ne bih ga mogla podržati čak i kad ne bi opasno narušavalo princip supsidijarnosti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to express my thanks to Ms Agea for this comprehensive report, which looks into minimum income policies to address poverty.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are now clear signs that Europe is recovering from the crisis. 2017 is the first year since 2008 when all European economies are expected to grow. The recovery is also reflected in the employment and social situation in Europe. Employment has reached the highest number ever recorded: 232 million in 2016. Unemployment rates are back to the pre-crisis level: 7.7% in August 2017. The number of people at risk of poverty and social exclusion decreased in more than half of the Member States in 2015 and is back to its pre-crisis level of 23.7%. However, we cannot be complacent, as thousands of our citizens – including people with jobs – are at risk of poverty and social exclusion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, I welcome your report as it highlights this challenge. Poverty and inequality are not only detrimental to social cohesion, but also to sustainable economic growth. Addressing these challenges is at the core of the European Semester and the European pillar of social rights. The pillar includes, as key principles, the provision of adequate minimum income schemes, essential services and employment activation. In line with the active inclusion approach, all Member States currently have some form of minimum income scheme. However, their design and implementation vary greatly. Moreover, as the report also points out, income support should be accompanied by access to services and activation, such as lifelong learning, for workers, the unemployed and vulnerable social groups.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Semester has proved to be an effective framework to monitor and provide guidance to Member States in this area. The pillar will further strengthen these efforts by introducing a new social scoreboard. Moreover, we are currently working with the Member States on a benchmarking framework for minimum incomes. The Commission is also promoting mutual learning and the exchange of good practices among Member States, for instance within the Social Protection Committee, or by supporting the European Minimum Income Network, which aims at the progressive realisation of adequate and accessible minimum income schemes in Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 24 October 2017.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-0625" speaker_id="124812" name="Fabio Massimo Castaldo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – La crisi economica e i processi di globalizzazione sono all'origine di una sempre maggiore divaricazione tra ricchi e poveri, con una classe media europea che negli ultimi anni è sempre più scivolata verso l'indigenza. È quindi assolutamente prioritario che una forte rete di protezione venga messa in campo a livello europeo e il reddito di cittadinanza costituisce in questo senso una misura atta a ridare dignità ai tanti che si trovano oggi in estrema difficoltà. Si tratta di una battaglia che il M5S da sempre porta avanti in Italia, ma una direttiva europea in questo senso costituirebbe un importante intervento di giustizia sociale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-1250" speaker_id="26837" name="Λευτέρης Χριστοφόρου" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">γραπτώς. – Η οικονομική κρίση άφησε μόνιμα στίγματα στην ευρωπαϊκή αγορά εργασίας με σημαντικό αντίκτυπο στον κοινωνικό ιστό. Τόσο τα ευρωπαϊκά θεσμικά όργανα όσο και οι εθνικές κυβερνήσεις έλαβαν και λαμβάνουν μέτρα για την μείωση των ποσοστών της φτώχειας και της ανεργίας. Η παρούσα έκθεση για το ελάχιστο εγγυημένο εισόδημα θέτει ως στόχο να παράσχει πρακτική καθοδήγηση ως προς τον τρόπο ταυτόχρονης παρέμβασης, αφενός, για την άμβλυνση του κοινωνικού αντίκτυπου της οικονομικής κρίσης και, αφετέρου, για την προώθηση ενεργών πολιτικών που αποσκοπούν στη δημιουργία θέσεων απασχόλησης και στη διασφάλιση βιώσιμης ανάπτυξης. Η Κύπρος ήδη εφαρμόζει με επιτυχία μέτρα για την υποστήριξη του ελάχιστου εγγυημένου εισοδήματος με στόχο την παροχή ενός δικτύου κοινωνικής ασφαλείας για τα άτομα που διατρέχουν τον κίνδυνο της φτώχειας. Συγκεντρώνοντας και εξορθολογίζοντας τους διαθέσιμους πόρους, μέσα από το ελάχιστο εγγυημένο εισόδημα η κυβέρνηση δημιούργησε ένα αποτελεσματικό δίχτυ κοινωνικής προστασίας, ενισχύοντας χιλιάδες Κύπριους που το είχαν ανάγκη και που προηγουμένως δεν είχαν καμία στήριξη από το κράτος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-2500" speaker_id="95281" name="Viorica Dăncilă" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Măsurile de austeritate care au dominat politica economică europeană din ultimii ani au dus la recesiune economică, creșterea ratei șomajului și reducerea posibilităților de a găsi un loc de muncă pentru mulți cetățeni europeni. Consider că statele membre și Comisia au nevoie de cifre actualizate privind venitul și condițiile de viață din țările UE, care să țină cont și de specificitățile naționale, pentru a pune în aplicare un buget de referință și un venit minim la nivel european, utilizate pentru a combate mai bine sărăcia și a testa robustețea nivelului venitului minim și a pragului amintit, dar respectând totodată principiul subsidiarității.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ca atare, consider benefică propunerea raportorului referitoare la elaborarea unui concept la nivel european privind obiectivele comune pentru sistemele naționale de venit minim, pentru a crea condiții egale între statele membre. Pentru acesta ar fi utilă realizarea de către Comisie a unei evaluări a impactului sistemelor de venit minim în Uniunea Europeană, cu monitorizare și raportare periodică în perspectiva unor acțiuni viitoare. În plus, atunci când sunt vizate sistemele de venit minim, statele membre trebuie să ia în considerare pragul de risc de sărăcie stabilit de Eurostat la 60% din venitul mediu național echivalat disponibil (după transferurile sociale), împreună cu alți indicatori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-3125" speaker_id="124895" name="Krzysztof Hetman" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Zmniejszanie nierówności jest jednym z nadrzędnych celów Unii Europejskiej, zapisanym w traktatach. Dlatego też, mimo iż polityka społeczna pozostaje kompetencją państw członkowskich, także na poziomie unijnym należy podejmować zadania, które mają doprowadzić do większej spójności społecznej i podniesienia poziomu życia obywateli.</p>
      <p sl="en">Propozycja ustanowienia dochodu minimalnego jest koncepcją, która zasługuje na uwagę, jednak należy mieć świadomość, iż różnice gospodarcze w systemach społecznych i prawnych między państwami członkowskimi sprawiają, iż niemożliwe byłoby wprowadzenie go na poziomie ogólnounijnym. Dlatego też mam wątpliwości co do wprowadzenia dyrektywy ramowej w sprawie dochodu minimalnego. Uważam ponadto, że osoby dotknięte ubóstwem i wykluczone z rynku pracy muszą przede wszystkim zyskać wsparcie w integracji społecznej, a także aktywizacji zawodowej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-3750" speaker_id="125021" name="Agnes Jongerius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftelijk. – "De sociale kloof in Europa neemt toe. Tussen jong en oud. Tussen zuid en noord. Armoedebestrijding is een verwaarloosd kind geworden". Dat waren mijn woorden twee jaar geleden. Ik vroeg toen om concrete voorstellen om de armoede te bestrijden. Ik ben blij dat wij vandaag een voorstel bespreken waarop wij sinds de crisis van 2008 wachten, namelijk een eerste stap richting een bestaansminimum voor alle Europeanen. Een goede zaak, want naar mijn mening moet iedereen in Europa kunnen rekenen op een fatsoenlijk bestaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dit voorstel wordt ook gerefereerd aan een (onvoorwaardelijk) basisinkomen. Ik ben daar op voorhand geen voorstander van. Van iedereen mag namelijk verwacht worden dat er naar vermogen wordt bijgedragen aan het betaalbaar houden van collectieve voorzieningen voor mensen die bijvoorbeeld te maken hebben met ziekte of tegenslag. Uiteraard laat ik mij graag van het tegendeel overtuigen. Ik ben benieuwd naar de uitkomsten van de experimenten met een basisinkomen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Veel Europeanen leven nog altijd in armoede. Dat kunnen wij niet accepteren. Het wordt tijd dat wij dit "verwaarloosde kind" bij de hand nemen en wat doen. Het garanderen van een fatsoenlijk bestaan in elke lidstaat is daarbij een goede eerste stap.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-4375" speaker_id="124751" name="Dominique Martin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">par écrit. – Si la lutte contre la pauvreté doit être un des objectifs les plus importants en Europe qui, rappelons-le, peine à se relever de la crise et des politiques d’austérité imposées par l'Union européenne, et ce malgré une reprise économique certaine, cela ne doit pas se faire au sacrifice de la souveraineté des États membres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Or ce rapport a pour objectif d'instaurer un revenu minimum européen qui serait à la fois financé par les États membres (via le Fonds social européen) mais géré par les institutions européennes. Aussi, nous n’acceptons pas que les formes nationales de revenu minimum (comme le RSA en France) puissent être remplacées par un instrument supranational dont la France n'aura plus le contrôle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-5000" speaker_id="124722" name="Csaba Molnár" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. –Lesújtó képet fest a magyar minimálbér európai összehasonlításban. Majdnem mindenhol magasabb a minimálbér Európában, mint a magyar. Több tízezer forinttal keresnek többet a szlovákok, a horvátok és a lengyelek is. A németek háromszor, de még a szlovénok is kétszer annyit kapnak, mint a magyarok. A helyzet súlyosságát tovább fokozza, hogy Magyarországon 4 millióan élnek szegénységben, és majdnem 7 millióan élnek egyik napról a másikra, nulla megtakarítással. Egy német, vagy egy dán autószerelő ugyanazért a munkáért háromszor annyit keres, mint egy magyar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Európai uniós minimálbért kell ezért meghatározni, amellyel ugrásszerűen növelhetnénk a magyar dolgozók munkabérét. Ha van uniós szinten garantált európai minimum jövedelem, drámaian javíthatunk a magyarok életszínvonalán, nem kellene többet azon aggódniuk, hogy kijönnek-e a hónap végéig. Ugyanakkor a minimumjövedelem biztosíthatná azt is, hogy egyenlő munkáért egyenlő bért fizessenek. Nem ér többet egy szlovák, vagy egy lengyel munkája, mint a magyaroké.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-7500" speaker_id="96847" name="Claudiu Ciprian Tănăsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Sărăcia și excluderea socială, ale căror cauze și durată nu depind de voința persoanelor care se confruntă cu acestea, constituie înjosiri ale demnității umane și încălcări ale drepturilor fundamentale ale omului. Conform Eurostat, în 2016, în cele 28 de state membre din Uniunea Europeană, 23,4 % din populație, respectiv 117,5 milioane de persoane, erau supuse riscului de sărăcie și excluziune socială, un nivel aproape similar cu cel de dinaintea crizei (2008).</p>
      <p sl="en">Este cunoscut faptul că un obiectiv al Strategiei Europa 2020 este scoaterea din categoria celor expuși sărăciei și excluziunii sociale în UE a cel puțin 20 de milioane de persoane până în 2020. Cu toate acestea, organizațiile internaționale (FMI) au impus, în cazul unor state membre, politici de austeritate bugetară extrem de restrictive, prin care obligă la reduceri substanțiale ale cheltuielilor în domenii fundamentale, cum ar fi educația, sănătatea, justiția, cultura și ajutoarele și serviciile sociale. Astfel de opțiuni politice au dus la o creștere accentuată a sărăciei și a excluziunii sociale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ca atare, suntem de acord cu faptul că doar o economie prosperă, cu o rată de șomaj scăzută, cu sisteme de venit minim reprezintă cel mai eficient instrument pentru combaterea sărăciei.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Control of spending and monitoring of EU Youth Guarantee schemes cost-effectiveness (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-168-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Derek Vaughan, on behalf of the Committee on Budgetary Control, on control of spending and monitoring of EU Youth Guarantee schemes’ cost-effectiveness (2016/2242(INI)) (A8—0296/2017).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169-0000" speaker_id="96918" name="Derek Vaughan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, youth unemployment has been one of the scandals of our time. Some of the youth unemployment rates in some Member States have been an absolute disgrace. Therefore, I am pleased that the EU has done its part to tackle this scandal through the Youth Guarantee Scheme and the Youth Employment Initiative. Between 2013 and 2017 youth unemployment has come down from 23.8% to 16.6%.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am pleased that the EU has put his money where its mouth is. I am pleased we have put more money into the programmes to allow us to tackle this issue. I am also pleased that the programme was front-loaded and pre-financing was increased in order to tackle the problem when it was at its worst. I am also pleased that the EU has now agreed to extend the Youth Employment Initiative up until at least 2020. So all that is good.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, more needs to be done. The programmes got off to a slow start. They were introduced quickly. Many Member States did not have the capacity or the structures to put in place the programmes, and it therefore got off to a slow start and youth unemployment still remains high. It is currently around 18%.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, I would urge Member States not to use EU funds to replace their own funds and programmes, but I would urge Member States to use their own funds to tackle youth unemployment, and not just rely on funds coming from the European Union. I would also urge Member States, companies and trainers to ensure they are offering a good-quality opportunity to young people and not just use them as cheap labour, as we have seen so often in the past.</p>
      <p sl="en">On implementation and monitoring, because after all this is a Committee on Budgetary Control report, I want to say I am concerned that there is sparse data on the output and results of the programmes. Better systems need to be put in place so that the results can be properly measured. We need to know how effective and efficient these programmes are. I would also like to see better market analysis so relevant opportunities can be offered to young people. We want opportunities which would benefit young people, but also benefit the economy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, hopefully we will see an evaluation coming from the Commission soon on these important programmes. This will allow us to make adjustments to improve implementation of these programmes even further. As I said at the start, these programmes have been worthwhile. They have made a huge difference but there is still much to do.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, nezaměstnanost mladých je velmi vážné téma, je tedy naší povinností se tím zabývat. Podle nejaktuálnějších statistik Eurostatu se nezaměstnanost výrazně snížila. V srpnu 2017 bylo mladých do 25 let v Evropské unii 16,7 %, a to je skutečně pokles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Věřím, že k tomu přispělo také právě čerpání z Evropského sociálního fondu, které pomohlo nalézt práci mnoha mladým nezaměstnaným. Je ale alarmující, že třeba v Řecku, ve Španělsku, v Itálii stále ta procenta dosahují čtyřiceti, třiceti procent. Nezaměstnanost mladých má obrovské negativní dopady na ekonomiku, ale i na samotné mladé lidi. Samozřejmě, hrozí zde jejich frustrace, radikalizace a každý mladý člověk, který nemůže nalézt práci, nás musí zajímat. Proto podporuji pokračování a zefektivnění těchto záruk za mladé.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, youth unemployment is a particularly worrying phenomenon. From the perspective of the wider economy it can have long-lasting effects on productivity and growth. From the perspective of individuals it can have the effect of excluding young people from the labour market for an extended period of time, which in turn can affect their job prospects for life.</p>
      <p sl="en">Considering that youth unemployment in the EU reached an alarming high of 23.8% in 2013, I am convinced that we were right to prioritise this particular segment of the labour market. I also believe that the recent fall in unemployment rates was due in part to the Youth Guarantee, its success depending on national factors such as implementation capacity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Although reduced, the youth unemployment rate still remains a concern that needs our particular attention. At the same time, however, we should not lose sight of the issue of general unemployment and the structural reforms needed to efficiently deal with it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, nell'ambito del piano europeo per la lotta alla disoccupazione giovanile, la "Garanzia per i giovani" ha l'obiettivo di finanziare politiche attive di orientamento, formazione e inserimento nel mercato del lavoro per i giovani inattivi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si tratta dunque di obiettivi fondamentali, considerando che il tasso di disoccupazione medio nell'Unione europea è del 17,8 %, con picchi del 45 % in Grecia, del 41,5 % in Spagna e del 35 % in Italia. La Corte dei conti europea, nella relazione sull'impatto delle politiche europee sulla disoccupazione giovanile, ha tuttavia evidenziato che in molti paesi il programma non ha assicurato l'effettivo inserimento dei giovani nel mondo del lavoro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda l'Italia, già in passato ho segnalato la persistenza di criticità in talune regioni, con ritardi medi nei pagamenti intorno ai 64 giorni, anche se il dato che preoccupa di più è però quello sull'efficacia complessiva del programma, ossia l'impatto sulla disoccupazione giovanile nei singoli Stati. A fronte del 64 % in Irlanda e del 90 % in Francia, in Italia solo il 31 % dei giovani coinvolti ha trovato un'occupazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vanno dunque definite strategie chiare e adeguate per correggere …</p>
      <a text="(Il Presidente interrompe l'oratore.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, τα ποσοστά ανεργίας των νέων είναι τεράστια στην Ευρώπη, αλλά κυρίως στον ευρωπαϊκό Νότο. Πρωταθλήτρια, δυστυχώς, είναι η Ελλάδα με 45% κι αυτό κυρίως λόγω των μνημονιακών πολιτικών που έχουν επιβληθεί. Φυσικά υπάρχει και μετανάστευση των νέων. Πεντακόσιες χιλιάδες νέοι από την Ελλάδα έχουν αναγκαστεί, ακριβώς λόγω της σκληρής μνημονιακής πολιτικής, να μεταναστεύσουν. Είναι δεδομένο ότι χρειάζεται στήριξη του προγράμματος «Εγγυήσεις για τη νεολαία», καθώς επίσης και «Πρωτοβουλία για την απασχόληση των νέων». Οι «Εγγυήσεις για τη νεολαία» απαιτούν 50 δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ. Τι ποσά όμως διατίθενται, κύριε Αβραμόπουλε; Ψίχουλα. Απαιτούνται πολύ μεγαλύτερα ποσά, αν θέλουμε να αντιμετωπίσουμε πραγματικά τα προβλήματα της ανεργίας των νέων κι όλα αυτά σε μια φάση που ο κύριος Draghi έχει μέχρι στιγμής δαπανήσει 1,7 τρισεκατομμύρια ευρώ στην ποσοτική χαλάρωση. Επομένως, απαιτούνται τεράστια ποσά για να αντιμετωπιστεί η ανεργία των νέων και φυσικά εγκατάλειψη της πολιτικής της λιτότητας και της βίαιης δημοσιονομικής προσαρμογής.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, program Jamstvo za mlade dao je određene rezultate, pogotovo u državama članicama koje su se teško oporavljale od krize i u kojima je nezaposlenost mladih godinama bila na rekordnoj razini.</p>
      <p sl="en">Izvjestitelj je dobro prepoznao izazove s kojima se program danas susreće, a rješenje bi moglo biti u prilagodbi preporučenih mjera lokalnom kontekstu uz veće uključivanje predstavnika poslodavaca i obrazovnih institucija s velikim lokalnim ili regionalnim utjecajem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Smatram kako Jamstvo za mlade ima budućnost, ali pozivi na dodatna izdvajanja iz nacionalnih proračuna mogli bi se pokazati kontraproduktivnima. Budemo li poslodavcima uzimali više novca kroz poreze kako bismo financirali ovaj program, smanjit ćemo njihovu sposobnost rasta i zapošljavanja i tako ograničiti uspješnost samog programa. Nemojmo upasti u tu zamku.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-0000" speaker_id="124815" name="Arne Gericke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen, liebe Kollegen! Thema EU-Jugendstrategie: Was haben wir dazu für tolle Sonntagsreden gehört. Leider sieht die Realität anders aus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Folgendes hatte Europa versprochen: Die Jugendgarantie stellt sicher, dass allen jungen Menschen ohne Arbeit binnen vier Monaten eine Arbeitsstelle oder ein Praktikumsplatz beschafft wird. Dafür investieren wir insgesamt 6,5 Mrd. Euro. Wären wir hier kein Parlament, sondern ein Unternehmen, hätten viele von uns die Kündigung in der Hand.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das sagt der Europäische Rechnungshof dazu, ich zitiere: „Mitte 2016 waren in der EU vier Millionen junger Menschen arbeitslos. Die politischen Entscheidungsträger sollten dafür sorgen, dass keine Erwartungen geweckt werden, die nicht erfüllt werden können.“</p>
      <p sl="en">Als siebenfacher Vater erinnere ich immer gern an das achte Gebot: Du sollst nicht lügen. Mein Wunsch: Seien wir ehrlich zu den Leuten, dann steigt auch die Glaubwürdigkeit unserer Politik! Europa kann vieles, aber nicht alles lösen. Vielleicht erreichen wir sogar mehr, wenn wir weniger versprechen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-0000" speaker_id="125214" name="Bronis Ropė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gerbiamas Pirmininke, jaunimo nedarbas yra senas reiškinys. Ir dalis Europos Sąjungos valstybių narių jau daugelį metų susiduria su nepaprastai aukštu jo lygiu. Tai kelia ne tik dideles socialines problemas, bet yra ir labai nuostolinga ekonomiškai. Lietuvoje dėl nedirbančių, nesimokančių ir mokyklose nedalyvaujančių jaunų žmonių 2008 m. buvo prarandama 0,7 proc. BVP, o jau 2011 m. – 1,1 proc.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todėl labai svarbus yra Europos Sąjungos jaunimo garantinių iniciatyvų išlaidų kontrolė ir nuolatinė ekonominė vaisingumo stebėsena, savavališkai teikiant rekomendacijas ir konsultacijas kiekvienai paramos gavėjų grupei, kartu nustatant ir valstybės narės finansinio indėlio dalį. Manau, vieningai sutariama, kad jaunimo nedarbo mažinimo projektai, net ir trumpalaikiai, yra veiksmingi. Tyrimai rodo, jog trumpalaikis jaunimo užimtumas kur kas padidina tikimybę susirasti darbo ateityje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-0000" speaker_id="124778" name="Marco Valli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, nel mio paese la disoccupazione giovanile arriva quasi al 37 %, secondo gli ultimi dati, e la disoccupazione giovanile in Sicilia, una regione che abbiamo visitato proprio per controllare come venivano spesi i fondi della Garanzia per i giovani, arriva a un vergognoso 57 %. Capite come siano dati impressionanti e la cosa più impressionante, che ci ha impressionato e ha impressionato anche la Corte dei conti europea, è che la politica in questa regione non è stata in grado di mettere insieme un sistema di pagamenti efficiente. I giovani sono andati molto spesso a lavorare e hanno ricevuto i pagamenti dopo mesi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa è una vergogna, una vergogna che si può ribaltare, assolutamente, mandando via certi partiti. E assolutamente bisogna anche invertire, però, le politiche di austerità, perché capite che se non aiutiamo anche le imprese a creare domanda e a creare posti di lavoro duraturi non riusciremo mai a uscire da questo circolo vizioso della crisi. Quindi, da una parte liberiamoci dai partiti e dall'altra liberiamoci dall'austerità per creare domanda e posti di lavoro duraturi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, προκαλούν οι πανηγυρισμοί της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και της κυβέρνησης ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ για τη δήθεν πτώση της ανεργίας. Με ταχυδακτυλουργίες βαφτίζουν ανέργους ως μη ενεργά αναζητούντες εργασία. Μια ώρα απασχόλησης, και χωρίς αμοιβή ακόμα, αρκεί για να θεωρηθεί κάποιος εργαζόμενος, η δε εκ περιτροπής εργασία αυθαίρετα εξαιρείται της μερικής απασχόλησης. Και στην Ελλάδα, με πρωτιά στην ανεργία, το «εγγύηση για τη νεολαία» σημαίνει ολιγόμηνο διάλειμμα από την ανεργία, με 300-400 ευρώ, χωρίς συνταξιοδοτική ασφάλιση, επιδοτώντας την εργοδοσία. Ανακύκλωση δηλαδή πάμφθηνων αναλώσιμων εργατών για τους επιχειρηματικούς ομίλους, σε αντικατάσταση κιόλας παλιότερων που στέλνονται στην ανεργία. Αυτή είναι η προϋπόθεση για την καπιταλιστική ανάκαμψη, που θα πληρώσουν πανάκριβα οι εργαζόμενοι με βίο αβίωτο, είτε έχουν είτε δεν έχουν δουλειά. Κανένας άνεργος χωρίς κάλυψη, επίδομα για όλο το διάστημα της ανεργίας, σε ύψος που να μπορούν να ζήσουν οι άνεργοι με τις οικογένειές τους. Μόνη απάντηση είναι η οργάνωση της εργατικής λαϊκής πάλης, για να μπουν εμπόδια στην καπιταλιστική εργασιακή γαλέρα. Να δυναμώσει και πάλι …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Dimitris Avramopoulos" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, providing young people with better opportunities has been a top priority for the Commission. I therefore welcome Mr Vaughan’s report, which comes at the right time.</p>
      <p sl="en">Four years into the launch of the Youth Guarantee and the Youth Employment Initiative (YEI), our efforts are now paying off. The Youth Guarantee has been an important policy driver to improve the transition of young people from education to work. Setting it up was not easy. It required commitment and political support from Member States and building new partnerships, as well as significant reforms of labour market, education and training policies.</p>
      <p sl="en">But these efforts are now bearing fruit. Since its launch, around 18 million young people have registered and 11 million have received an offer. The youth unemployment rate decreased from a peak of 24% in January 2013 to 16.7% in August 2017. There are now two million fewer young unemployed in the European Union, and one million fewer young people who are not in employment, education or training – the so—called NEETs. The improving macroeconomic context certainly played a role, but young people have managed better on the labour market thanks to the Youth Guarantee. Public employment services have expanded their services and developed new approaches towards the hard—to—reach. Apprenticeship and traineeship reforms have taken place in many countries. The Youth Employment Initiative has directly helped at least 1.6 million young people to receive a job, training or further education.</p>
      <p sl="en">As your report rightly points out, there are still challenges. We take due note of the European Court of Auditors’ Special Report on the impact of these two projects on youth employment. The Youth Guarantee has done a lot to shift the focus to early intervention and not registered needs, and to ensure a new focus on outreach. But addressing young people in more vulnerable situations, who face multiple barriers, remains a challenge. We are committed to helping Member States by providing financial support and policy advice to ensure that all young people can have access to these opportunities. Through the Employment and Social Innovation (EaSI) Programme we are, for example, supporting outreach and awareness—raising projects in four Member States and providing mutual learning opportunities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Your report stresses the importance of cooperation between all partners as a crucial part of achieving this goal. Indeed, public employment services, education providers, social partners and youth organisations need to be involved so that we can reach out effectively to all young people and ensure that measures are sustainable and of high quality. Adequate investment is of course a prerequisite for achieving this.</p>
      <p sl="en">Many of the measures of the Youth Guarantee would not have occurred without the European Union’s financial support, namely the Youth Employment Initiative and the European Social Fund. In some Member States, the Youth Employment Initiative is funding the vast majority of youth guarantee measures and has been instrumental in setting up schemes. Despite a slow start, implementation of the Youth Employment Initiative sped up between 2015 and 2016: the number of young people supported by the Youth Employment Initiative tripled. The recently agreed increase of the Youth Employment Initiative’s budget by EUR 2.14 billion will help to continue this effort, but I fully agree with you that Member States also need to invest in youth employment in order to effectively implement Youth Guarantee schemes and really reach all young people.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards monitoring requirements on the progress of the YEI, we have been providing guidance and requesting feedback from the Member States on data collection and monitoring. The provision of guidance will continue on a regular and ad—hoc basis. Collecting relevant information and feedback on the results on the ground is essential in order for us to be able to report on the achievement of the Youth Employment Initiative. To facilitate this dissemination of the Youth Guarantee’s results, on 26 October we are organising a Youth Guarantee Learning Forum. This will bring together Youth Guarantee policy coordinators from Member States and YEI managing authorities to disseminate good practices, take stock of the lessons learned so far and come up with proposals for the future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place on Tuesday, 24 October 2017.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-1250" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">par écrit. – Malgré son léger reflux, le chômage des jeunes reste, avec 18,8 % en 2016, à un niveau inacceptable. Il n’est, en outre, que le versant le plus visible d’une précarisation massive de la jeunesse européenne, qui hypothèque l’avenir de toute une génération et déstabilise l’équilibre socioéconomique des États concernés à travers les recettes fiscales et les systèmes de retraite, mais aussi la natalité, qui a lourdement chuté en France.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’austérité imposée par la Commission rend illusoire tout investissement de 50,4 milliards d’euros annuels nécessaire au fonctionnement de la « Garantie pour la Jeunesse », instituée en 2013. En outre, l’absence d’une définition d’« offre de qualité » laisse la porte ouverte aux dérives associées aux mécanismes d’aide publique à l’emploi, de l’effet d’aubaine aux emplois sans perspectives. Ainsi, il est illusoire de penser que seul un mécanisme de soutien public permettrait aux quatre millions de jeunes Européens de sortir de l’ornière.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est impératif de traiter les causes du chômage des jeunes: d’une part, les lacunes de la formation secondaire et professionnelle et, d’autre part, la pression sur les coûts de personnel pesant sur les entreprises, soumises à une concurrence internationale impitoyable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-2500" speaker_id="96781" name="Danuta Jazłowiecka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – W swoim sprawozdaniu Trybunał Obrachunkowy wykazał, że we wdrażaniu unijnych programów gwarancji dla młodzieży poczyniono niewielkie postępy. Wystarczy wspomnieć, iż w całej Unii bezrobotnych jest ponad 4 miliony osób poniżej 25. roku życia. W niektórych państwach członkowskich bez pracy pozostaje aż jedna czwarta osób młodych.</p>
      <p sl="en">W przypadku gwarancji dla młodzieży kontrolerzy Trybunału Obrachunkowego ustalili, że podstawowym źródłem niepowodzenia był brak strategii zawierających jasne cele pośrednie i końcowe. W wielu państwach członkowskich nawet nie została wystarczająco precyzyjnie określona grupa docelowa. Tym samym utrudnione było dotarcie do wszystkich osób potrzebujących oferty zatrudnienia, dalszego kształcenia lub praktyki zawodowej. Często też nie zbierano danych umożliwiających pomiar realizacji zgłoszonych rezultatów. Funkcjonowanie programów nie spełniło oczekiwań Komisji, ale przede wszystkim zawiodło osoby młode znajdujące się w trudnej sytuacji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Konieczne jest więc wyciągnięcie wniosków z dotychczasowej praktyki i zastanowienie się nad tym, jak podnieść efektywność tych programów. Na pewno należy dokonać całościowego przeglądu kosztów związanych z gwarancjami dla młodzieży i dostosować programy do dostępnych środków finansowych. Ponadto Komisja powinna zadbać o to, aby państwa członkowskie uzasadniały, w jaki sposób finansowane przez Unię działania na rzecz zatrudnienia młodzieży będą odpowiadać na istniejące potrzeby. Zmiany te powinny zostać szybko dokonane, ponieważ nie możemy pozwolić sobie na zmarnowanie kolejnych lat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-5000" speaker_id="124726" name="Henna Virkkunen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – Vaikka Euroopan unionin työttömyysaste on nyt alhaisimmillaan sitten vuoden 2008, pitkittynyt talouskriisi näkyy vielä liian monen nuoren elämässä ja tulevaisuuden mahdollisuuksissa. Paras vastaus nuorisotyöttömyyteen on osaaminen ja koulutus. Koulutus ehkäisee työttömyyttä tehokkaimmin. Kaikissa Euroopan unionin jäsenmaissa on edelleen parannettava sekä perusopetuksen laatua että jatkokoulutusmahdollisuuksia. Kyse on koko Euroopan kasvusta ja tulevaisuuden kilpailukyvystä. Meillä on ratkottavana yhteisiä haasteita, kuten työvoiman ikääntyminen, ammattitaidon puutteet, teknologian kehitys ja globaali kilpailu. Lisääntynyt kansainvälinen kilpailu sekä digitalisaation ja robotisaation eteneminen tarkoittaa isoja muutoksia työelämässä. Koulutuksen on tarjottava jokaiselle nuorelle riittävä perusosaaminen ja valmiudet, mutta vähintään yhtä tärkeää on mahdollistaa osaamisen päivittäminen työuran aikana. On tärkeää, ettei yksikään nuori jää tyhjän päälle, vaan pääsee nopeasti kiinni oppimiseen tai työhön. Nuorisotakuun ja nuorisotyöttömyyden vähentämisen toteutumiseksi tarvitaan vielä monissa maissa jäykkien koulutusjärjestelmien ja työmarkkinoiden uudistuksia. Jäsenmailta tarvitaan tehokkuutta nuorisotakuutoimissa ja niiden seurannassa. Investoiminen nuoriin ja koulutukseen on avain Euroopan parempaan tulevaisuuteen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-184-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance (Rule 163). I would like to underline the word ‘one’, so please respect the time limit and I will try to be strict.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-185-0000" speaker_id="28394" name="Dariusz Rosati" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Ostatni rok ujawnił skalę ingerencji służb Federacji Rosyjskiej w przebieg demokratycznych wyborów w wielu krajach członkowskich Unii Europejskiej. Ostatni przykład mieliśmy w ubiegłym tygodniu w Republice Czeskiej. Federacja Rosyjska wykorzystuje wielojęzyczne kanały telewizyjne, ośrodki analityczne, a także angażuje trolle i komputery zombie do prowadzenia dezinformacji i propagandy politycznej obliczonej na dyskredytowanie Unii Europejskiej, podważanie jej jedności i niszczenie współpracy między poszczególnymi krajami. Jednocześnie wspiera partie populistyczne i nacjonalistyczne. Moim zdaniem nie możemy pozostać obojętni wobec tej ukrytej agresji, która godzi w naszą wspólnotę, i dlatego chciałbym prosić Komisję o dokonanie gruntownej analizy tego zjawiska i zaproponowanie skutecznych narzędzi i sposobu przeciwdziałania tym niebezpiecznym praktykom Federacji Rosyjskiej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-0000" speaker_id="124691" name="Κώστας Μαυρίδης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, πρόσφατα συζητούσαμε για το μέλλον της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και ο κύριος Juncker εξήγγειλε τη σύσταση Ευρωπαϊκής Εποπτικής Αρχής για τη συμμόρφωση των κρατών μελών γύρω από θέματα ευρωπαϊκής νομοθεσίας και ιδιαίτερα την εφαρμογή δικαστικών αποφάσεων για να εξαλειφθεί το κοινωνικό ντάμπινγκ και πολύ σωστά το εξήγγειλε. Ωστόσο, εγώ, κύριε Πρόεδρε, θέλω να εγείρω ένα τεράστιο θέμα που αφορά ευρωπαϊκές αποφάσεις, ευρωπαϊκών δικαστηρίων γύρω από θεμελιακά ζητήματα, όπως είναι η προστασία της ιδιωτικής περιουσίας, η οποία παραβιάζεται στο κατεχόμενο βόρειο μέρος της Κύπρου και ευρωπαίοι πολίτες, ανάμεσά τους και εγώ, δεν μπορούμε να απολαύσουμε την περιουσία μας, η οποία βρίσκεται σε έδαφος της Κυπριακής Δημοκρατίας, εντός της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, αλλά είναι υπό κατοχή των τουρκικών στρατευμάτων. Δεν θα έπρεπε η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση να προστατεύσει τα θεμελιώδη δικαιώματα των ευρωπαίων πολιτών στην Κύπρο;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-187-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, κύριε Αβραμόπουλε, σας μεταφέρω την κραυγή αγωνίας και διαμαρτυρίας των κατοίκων της Σάμου και των υπολοίπων νησιών του Αιγαίου που δεν αντέχουν πλέον άλλους πρόσφυγες και παράνομους μετανάστες. Χθες, Κυριακή 21 Οκτωβρίου παραβρέθηκα στη Σάμο και μίλησα σε μια πολυπληθή συγκέντρωση των κατοίκων, οι οποίοι απαιτούν την αποσυμφόρηση του νησιού, την αποσυμφόρηση του «hotspot», όπου στοιβάζονται πάνω από 4.000 πρόσφυγες και παράνομοι μετανάστες, ενώ οι διαθέσιμες θέσεις φιλοξενίας στο «hotspot» δεν ξεπερνούν τις 800. Στη συγκέντρωση συμμετείχαν και αρκετοί από τους εγκλωβισμένους πρόσφυγες που ζητούν να πάνε σε άλλες χώρες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης. Κύριε Αβραμόπουλε, είναι αναγκαία η λήψη μέτρων αποσυμφόρησης των νησιών του Αιγαίου. Να εφαρμοστεί η απόφαση του Συμβουλίου Επικρατείας για την προώθηση των παρανόμων μεταναστών. Τέλος, πρέπει να συνεχιστεί το πρόγραμμα μετεγκαταστάσεων από Ελλάδα σε άλλες χώρες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, δεδομένου ότι το προηγούμενο εκτελέστηκε μόνο κατά το 1/3. Είναι χαρακτηριστικό ότι, από τους 17.209 που έπρεπε να φύγουν από την Ελλάδα για τη Γερμανία, έχουν φύγει μόνο 4.447 άτομα …</p>
      <a text="(Ο Πρόεδρος διακόπτει τον ομιλητή.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188-0000" speaker_id="112753" name="Jozo Radoš" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, u tijeku je usvajanje paketa čiste energije u tijelima Europske unije, uključujući i Europski parlament. Mnoga su područja energetske politike u kojima se očekuju inovacije, i bez tih inovacija zapravo neće moći biti ni postignuti ciljevi koji su postavljeni u okviru te energetske politike. Ja bih samo želio ukazati na neke od tih područja kao što su, recimo, nova biogoriva, kao što su nove tehnike skladištenja energije, uključujući i baterije, i kao što su to novi materijali na području energetske učinkovitosti zgrada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ali, ono što želim posebno napomenuti i pozvati Komisiju da razvije posebne sektorske politike, na primjer na području transporta u okviru novih inovacija na području čiste energije, i još nešto što želim posebno naglasiti, a to je potreba da se ruralna područja ne izostave i da se ta šansa iskoristi s novim tehnologijama i da se smanji razvijenost na području sjeverne Europske unije.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-0000" speaker_id="125049" name="Maria Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, garantir o acesso da população a água potável e segura passa por agir face aos riscos e às ameaças de poluição das águas. Hoje, quero chamar a atenção da Comissão Europeia no sentido de abrir uma investigação independente sobre os resíduos perigosos que se estão a enterrar na antiga mina de Touro para determinar se estão a ser tratados corretamente e, assim, evitar a poluição das águas do rio Ulla e da ria de Arousa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fotos como estas mostram e fazem suspeitar que, possivelmente, os resíduos que se estão a enterrar nesta antiga mina não tenham o tratamento adequado. Por outro lado, quero chamar também a atenção para o perigo que o glifosato constitui para as águas e instar a Comissão Europeia a proibir definitivamente este herbicida.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0000" speaker_id="124932" name="Josep-Maria Terricabras" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. Hoy hablo para expresar rechazo y estupefacción.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rechazo. El Gobierno español conduce su campaña anticatalana por unos caminos que pueden coincidir con el delito de odio, no solo por denunciar y encarcelar a dirigentes sociales de trayectoria limpia, pacífica, ejemplar, sino por anunciar que va a eliminar completamente la autonomía de Cataluña.</p>
      <p sl="en">El Gobierno puede estar en desacuerdo con el proyecto separatista, pero no puede, si es democrático, anular las decisiones de los ciudadanos catalanes que, democráticamente y por mayoría absoluta, han elegido a sus parlamentarios y a su Gobierno. Solo elimina la democracia quien se inspira en principios autoritarios y dictatoriales. Después de Franco, es la primera vez que ocurre en España.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y estupefacción. ¿Cómo es posible que la democrática Europa apruebe métodos autoritarios en España cuando los denuncia acertadamente en otros países?</p>
      <p sl="en">Soy diputado europeo y me avergüenza que mi Parlamento no se haya levantado aún decididamente frente a tanta indignidad. ¿Es eso diálogo? ¿Eso es lo que quiere Europa?</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo estoy trabajando por una Europa distinta; la que veo ahora, cada día me gusta menos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-191-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io voglio denunciare in questa casa, in questa Aula dei cittadini europei, l'ennesima truffa nei confronti della democrazia che si sta verificando nel mio paese, in Italia.</p>
      <p sl="en">In pratica, a pochi mesi dalle elezioni nazionali la maggioranza, che in Parlamento è stata eletta con una legge incostituzionale, sta cambiando le regole del gioco e lo sta facendo per tenere fuori l'unica forza di opposizione reale che c'è stata, ossia il Movimento 5 Stelle. Lo sta facendo utilizzando l'istituto della "fiducia", così come aveva fatto Benito Mussolini nel 1923 con la legge Acerbo, ossia la fiducia sulla legge elettorale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questo è un appello che faccio a voi, colleghi: è bene che se ne parli negli altri paesi, perché è una vergogna per la democrazia ed è qualcosa su cui chiediamo il vostro aiuto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-192-0000" speaker_id="125090" name="Σωτήριος Ζαριανόπουλος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, στην Ελλάδα, εφτά χρόνια μετά και τρία μνημόνια ανεργίας, μειώσεων μισθών, συντάξεων, επιδομάτων, ελαστική απασχόληση, άγρια φορολεηλασία, η πλειοψηφία του λαού αδυνατεί να πληρώσει δάνεια και φόρους. Η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και η Ευρωπαϊκή Κεντρική Τράπεζα, το Διεθνές Νομισματικό Ταμείο και η κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ στην αξιολόγηση του τρίτου μνημονίου συμφώνησαν για μια ακόμα κεφαλαιακή ενίσχυση των τραπεζών, ρευστοποιώντας τα κόκκινα δάνεια για να δοθούν νέα σε βιώσιμες, δηλαδή μεγάλες επιχειρήσεις, εξαφανίζοντας αυτοαπασχολούμενους και μικρές και πολύ μικρές επιχειρήσεις από την αγορά. Ήδη κατάσχονται χιλιάδες τραπεζικοί λογαριασμοί μισθοσυντήρητων, συνταξιούχων και αυτοαπασχολούμενων, επισπεύδονται χιλιάδες ηλεκτρονικοί πλέον πλειστηριασμοί λαϊκών κατοικιών ή η πώληση δανείων στα κοράκια των κερδοσκοπικών funds. Ουσιαστικά, καμιά προστασία δεν προβλέπεται ούτε καν για την πρώτη κατοικία, τον μισθό και τη σύνταξη. Η κλοπή της λαϊκής περιουσίας είναι τεράστια. Οι λαϊκές κινητοποιήσεις με αίτημα «νομοθέτηση τώρα απαγόρευσης πλειστηριασμών της πρώτης κατοικίας, της κατάσχεσης μισθού και σύνταξης, διαγραφή τόκων και κούρεμα και πάγωμα δανείων» να δυναμώσουν με σύνθημα «κάτω τα χέρια από τα σπίτια και τον ιδρώτα του λαού».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-193-0000" speaker_id="124929" name="Ivan Štefanec" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážený pán predseda. Denne cestujú tisíce našich občanov za prácou, vzdelaním, či turistikou do iných členských štátov. Mnoho z nich na to využíva leteckú prepravu. Títo občania musia mať za každých okolností istotu, že doletia bezpečne, načas a bez zbytočných výdavkov do svojho cieľa a naspäť. Nemôžeme akceptovať, aby letecké spoločnosti neinformovali o dlhodobo plánovanom rušení letov včas. Nemôžeme akceptovať, aby cestujúcim odmietali preplácať škody, ktoré im vlastnou vinou spôsobili. A nemôže akceptovať také situácie, že ľudia zostávajú zaseknutí na letisku v cudzej krajine, bez prostriedkov a bez informácií v ich rodnom jazyku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dámy a páni, pri dôraze na leteckú bezpečnosť a spoľahlivosť leteckej prepravy nám musí predovšetkým záležať na právach ľudí, ktorí ju používajú. Verím preto, že tak, ako tento týždeň budeme diskutovať o neakceptovateľnom zneužívaní postavenia veľkých spoločností voči menšej a lacnejšej konkurencii, budeme mať diskusiu veľmi skoro aj o výraznom zlepšení práv cestujúcich v leteckej doprave lebo naozaj je to … (prerušené predsedajúcim z dôvodu uplynutia časového limitu)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážený pán predseda. Minulý týždeň sme si pripomenuli Svetový deň boja proti chudobe. Chcela by som v tejto súvislosti pripomenúť dva dôležité fakty.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po prvé, stratégia Európa 2020 je v boji s chudobou neúčinná, tak ako kedysi Lisabonská stratégia. Čo je horšie, stále viac ľudí ohrozuje chudoba napriek tomu, že majú prácu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po druhé, prah chudoby je v každom členskom štáte iný. Vo Francúzsku alebo Nemecku sa za chudobného považuje človek s príjmom nižším ako tisíc euro mesačne. To je viac, ako mediánový príjem väčšiny občanov až v dvanástich členských štátoch.</p>
      <p sl="en">Európa musí začať brať boj proti chudobe vážne. Príjmy takmer polovice jej občanov totiž nedosahujú ani hranicu chudoby v Nemecku a Francúzsku. Kým sa to nezmení, nikdy nad populistami nezvíťazíme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-195-0000" speaker_id="125046" name="Jonás Fernández" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, hoy quiero trasladar aquí la grave situación de discriminación que sufre la región de Extremadura como consecuencia de la paralización de la línea de ferrocarril de alta capacidad y electrificada que se estaba planeando. Paralizar esta línea que une además Madrid con Lisboa con vistas al objetivo de mejorar el mercado único en el conjunto de la Unión es una mala decisión y espero que de ahora en adelante la Comisión y el conjunto de instituciones europeas ayuden a la puesta en marcha inmediata de esta línea central.</p>
      <p sl="en">También querría, en relación con este asunto, destacar la necesidad de poner en marcha —para ello es necesaria la sensibilidad de la Comisión—, para Asturias, Galicia y Castilla y León, la conexión ferroviaria de los puertos marítimos de Vigo, La Coruña, Gijón y Avilés—, a fin de poder cerrar un bucle de comunicaciones en el conjunto del noroeste español. En los últimos años hemos hecho grandes avances en infraestructuras, pero necesitamos muchos más.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-196-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, my constituents are alarmed at the threat to Coleman’s mustard factory after the announcement that Britvic, who share the same site, are closing their operations. Coleman’s mustard is Norfolk through and through, and Norwich is where the jobs must stay. The 200-year-old larder staple is quintessentially East Anglian, made in Norwich with English mustard seeds from Norfolk, Cambridgeshire and Lincolnshire, and it is enjoyed across the world. The decline of manufacturing jobs is not written in stone, and 10 000 people have already signed the EDP petition to say that we do not want to see much-needed jobs that are vital for the Norwich economy lost, and we do not want to see the 200-year Norwich and Coleman’s link severed. So my message is clear: Norwich does not just have a fiery condiment: we have fiery campaigners too. So, Unilever, please come up with plans and reassurances that really cut the mustard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Panie i Panowie Posłowie! Trzy miliony ludzi w Rumunii – to jest ogromna liczba jak na dwudziestomilionowy kraj – podpisało wniosek o przeprowadzenie referendum w obronie naturalnego ustroju rodziny opartego na małżeństwie i rodzicielstwie. To jest wspaniały przykład odradzania się społeczeństwa obywatelskiego, poczucia odpowiedzialności za dobro wspólne, odbudowy opinii chrześcijańskiej po dziesięcioleciach udręk komunizmu. Niestety ta wspaniała inicjatywa spotkała się z atakami również w tym parlamencie. Trudno w to uwierzyć, ale odezwały się głosy wzywające władze rumuńskie do przeszkodzenia w przeprowadzeniu tego referendum. To jest niestety kolejny bardzo groźny sygnał świadczący o narastaniu tego dryfu totalitarnego w naszych instytucjach, w strukturach władzy europejskiej. W tej sytuacji naszych rumuńskich przyjaciół trzeba zapewnić o jednym: nie jesteście sami, dobro zwycięży, jesteśmy z wami.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the ongoing elections in Kosovo and Macedonia and in the other Western Balkan countries clearly show that these countries are actually solving their serious problems in a serious way. Quite recently, we had the constitutional crisis in Macedonia and actually they solved it. On the other hand, we, the European Union, are not doing much more than talking. If you look at the money we are giving these countries you will find that the Member States that are receiving money are receiving EUR 3000 per capita. In the Western Balkans the best case figure is EUR 300, and in the worst case the figure is EUR 4 per capita, in Bosnia-Herzegovina. This is actually shameful. If we want enlargement, and if these countries are seriously doing something towards enlargement, then we have to play our part as well and increase that financial help.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-199-0000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last week Ireland was hit by Storm Ophelia. Homes, farms, businesses roads, schools even sports stadiums fell victim to massive structural damage. Unfortunately, lives were also lost. Government politicians have been quick to call for applications to the European Solidarity Fund, although they are aware that the threshold has not been reached for this third consecutive catastrophic storm. One reason for this is that, in 2015, the threshold for Ireland to apply for Solidarity Funds was EUR 803 million. This year, however, the threshold is EUR 1.2 billion. The story is the same for the regional thresholds based on GDP: Irish regions have seen leaps of between EUR 58 million and EUR 333 million in the amount of damage they must incur to apply for funds between 2015 and 2017. This is a result of distorted GDP figures famously described as ‘leprechaun economics’, and we now need to cut out those figures. On the EU side, too, there is a need to review the Solidarity Fund, as it discriminates against rural and peripheral regions. It is harder for regions to meet the threshold if they have poorer infrastructure to begin with.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-0000" speaker_id="124988" name="Deirdre Clune" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, every year 1.4 million Europeans develop some form of dementia, and the World Health Organisation estimates that 6.4 million people in the European Union are currently living with dementia, either the most common cause of dementia or Alzheimer’s disease.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is no cure to halt or treat the disease but there are treatments that delay progression or alleviate the symptoms. Emphasis is now being placed on the standard of care, ensuring dignity for those who have dementia, ascribing to a rights-based approach. There is also a gender dimension to dementia, with Alzheimer’s disease mainly affecting women, and women play an important role in caring.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think much more could, and should, be done at EU level to coordinate the research – into both care and prevention – that is being carried out at Member State level. We can improve diagnosis and post-diagnostic services if we foster dementia-friendly communities. I would suggest establishing an EU coordinator to ensure that this issue is addressed at the highest level, because a lot of information is not being shared across Member States.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-0000" speaker_id="28141" name="Lívia Járóka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Nemcsak a fiatalkori munkanélküliség kapcsán, hanem – ahogy Madame Záborská is már említette – a szegénység elleni küzdelem kapcsán is nagyon fontos, hogy előre tekintsünk a most, november 5. és 7. között Lisszabonban megrendezendő „Digitális summit”-ra, aminek kapcsán azért kértem szót, mert nagyon fontosnak tartom, hogy a fiatalok, és köztük is a legszegényebbek digitális tudásának mélyítésével hangsúlyosan javítsunk az integráción, a mély belső európai integráción.</p>
      <p sl="en">Például Magyarországon a diákok 94%-ának van okostelefonja, és az EU megteremthetné, és már meg is teremtette 2019-ig, hogy a széles sávú, gyors internet még a legutolsó kis faluban is elérhető legyen, az utolsó gettókban is. Ideje, hogy az EU kifejlesszen olyan mobil alkalmazást, amelynek segítségével a legszegényebbek közül, a fiatalok közül igenis valós deszegregáció indulhat meg azzal, hogy a szolgáltatásokat ezekre a területekre visszük, mobil alkalmazások segítségével, a gyerekek kezébe. Nagyon fontos, hogy ne csak az oktatásban, hanem az egészségügyi megelőzésben is, a képzésekben, a munkahelyteremtésben játsszanak ezek szerepet a fiataloknál.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is an honour to speak for the first time in this Parliament as its newest Member, and in doing so let me first pay tribute to my predecessor, Glenis Willmott, who made a distinguished contribution to this Parliament, my Group and indeed my party.</p>
      <p sl="en">I speak today on an issue that should unite this Parliament: the issue of mental health. This is our first plenary since World Mental Health Day and, as we see the impact of austerity bite, we see mental health services such as those in the UK stretched to breaking point. It is time for our Member States and their governments, and indeed this European Union, to redouble our efforts to improve that situation, to secure parity of esteem between mental health and physical health and to eradicate mental health stigma and discrimination.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our job as parliamentarians is to be a voice for those who cannot be heard. On this issue, that task is more important than ever. Together, we can address this challenge and make sure those people who need a voice on this issue have many voices in this Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Mr Palmer, welcome to this House. It is good to have you with us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-204-0000" speaker_id="4545" name="Catherine Stihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as we live in an ever more deeply interconnected world, we rely more on online services. And it is not just our laptops or gadgets which are connected, it is public institutions, governments and our very own homes.</p>
      <p sl="en">However we make sure we stay safe in this online realm, and that our personal or government data is not hacked into and our democratic processes are not tampered with, I believe the cybersecurity package presented by the Commission last month takes the right approach to ensure we have a concrete European response to potential cybersecurity threats.</p>
      <p sl="en">International and operational cooperation amongst Member States is key, and can only be achieved by bridging the divides between the internal and external, the public and private and the civil and military that exist within our Member States and the EU. The creation of EU cybersecurity standards and certification frameworks will help businesses and citizens to understand when products are cybersecure and improve trust in digital services.</p>
      <p sl="en">The interconnected world we live in is exhilarating, but it also poses potential challenges to every single one of us. I hope that this proposal will be debated thoroughly in this House.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-205-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, Hrvatska ispunjava svoje posljednje zadatke kako bi ušla u Schengensko područje. Koliko je to značajno za naše gospodarstvo pogotovo za turizam, podsjetit ću kako su u Istri na graničnim prijelazima u šestom mjesecu bile kilometarske kolone zato što Hrvatska nije članica Schengena. Zato pozivam Komisiju da učini sve, pa i nebirokratske mjere uz snažnu političku podršku da Hrvatska čim prije uđe u Schengensko područje, jer će to dodatno doprinijeti stabilizaciji stanja na zapadnom Balkanu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Također, Hrvatska u ovom trenutku vrši prave ispravne pripreme za Eurozonu, za ulazak u Eurozonu, za proces ulaska u Eurozonu. I tu očekujem od Komisije snažnu podršku za našu zemlju, jer Hrvatska zaslužuje ući i u Schengensko područje i u Eurozonu. Učinite sve i političkim metodama da se taj problem čim prije razriješi za našu zemlju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-206-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, de acordo com notícias vindas a público, a Comissão Europeia terá anunciado, na semana passada, a suspensão do terceiro pilar da União Bancária. Surpresa das surpresas, não terá havido consenso ao nível do Conselho relativamente a uma proposta que era já, ela própria, um recuo relativamente à tão propagandeada criação de um sistema comum de garantia de depósitos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Era evidente, há muito tempo, que o Sistema de Garantia de Depósitos era a cenoura com que o pau da usurpação da soberania nacional, da centralização e da concentração bancária vinha acompanhado. Este é um desenvolvimento que não surpreende. Mesmo que o terceiro pilar tivesse avançado, isso não alteraria a natureza do projeto da União Bancária.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mas aos que, ingenuamente, olharam para a cenoura e aos que deliberadamente com ela acenaram, aos que caucionaram o ataque às soberanias nacionais na supervisão e intervenção sobre os respetivos sistemas bancários, aos que assim defenderam a concentração monopolista à escala europeia, dizendo que o prémio de consolação seria aquilo que agora caiu por terra, impõe-se a pergunta: estão disponíveis para mudar de posição?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-207-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, as eleições regionais venezuelanas, de 15 de outubro, cujo resultado Nicolas Maduro proclamou como uma vitória arrasadora, constituíram mais um triste episódio do longo processo de erosão da democracia naquele país.</p>
      <p sl="en">Primeiro, assistimos a uma campanha eleitoral em que o oficialismo instrumentalizou vergonhosamente os meios de comunicação social públicos para favorecer os seus candidatos. Depois, após a votação, foram inúmeras as irregularidades denunciadas, incluindo mudanças de última hora e sem notificação pública de assembleias de voto ou ainda votos forçados em troca de alimentos.</p>
      <p sl="en">O regime exige agora que os governantes eleitos prestem juramento perante a fraudulenta Assembleia Nacional Constituinte. Um ato eleitoral que deveria ter sido realizado no ano passado foi transformado, pelo PSUV, num plebiscito à sua ruinosa governação, que condicionará as eleições presidenciais de 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta nova farsa e o preocupante impacto da crise humanitária devem fazer-nos aumentar a pressão contra o regime de Maduro e, por isso, repito que, face à gravidade desta crise política e humanitária, se torna urgente que a União adote medidas individuais e seletivas contra os seus responsáveis, incluindo pelos eventuais crimes contra a humanidade, segundo as palavras do Alto-Comissário para os Direitos Humanos da ONU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-208-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Miközben az elmúlt időszakban a gyűlöletbeszéd elleni fellépés az online térben okoz komoly nehézségeket a hatóságoknak világszerte, Romániában a nyomtatott lapokban és az audiovizuális médiában váltak rendszeressé az országban élő magyar kisebbség elleni uszító üzenetek. Ezek a magyarokat becsmérlő, a tényeket semmibe vevő és az etnikai gyűlöletet feltüzelő üzenetek büntetlenül hangozhatnak el a román médiában, széles körben ismert televíziós műsorvezetők, újságírók vagy akár a tudományos élet ismert személyiségeinek szájából. A jelenség ma már a politikai életre is rányomja a bélyegét, gyakorlatilag megbénítva a többség és a kisebbség közötti – amúgy is akadozó és részleges – párbeszédet.</p>
      <p sl="en">A társadalmi hatások egyértelműek, felmérések szerint a magyar kisebbség elutasítottsága növekedőben, a román politikai elit körében pedig senki sem emeli fel a szavát a jelenséggel szemben. Jövőre szeretné Románia fennállásának 100 éves évfordulóját ünnepelni, és ebben az országban száz éve élő másfél millió magyar felé azonban eddig csak kioktató vagy egyenesen ellenséges üzenetek érkeztek.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-209-0000" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Father Shay Cullen is an Irish priest working with vulnerable children in the Philippines since the early 1970s. In his experience, sex offenders travel from the European Union and beyond to the Philippines to abuse children, and he has many, many horrific cases which he is dealing with. He has called on my country, Ireland, and other countries in Europe to stop convicted child sex offenders traveling abroad, by taking their passports from them or preventing them from getting a passport. There is a precedent in this – Australia passed legislation in July to stop registered sex offenders from traveling by removing their passports.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should heed the words of this priest – he knows what he is talking about. As we protect, or try to protect, our children in our own countries, the least we could do is afford the same level of protection to children elsewhere. Where we know a sex offender is convicted in our Member State, we should stop them traveling to do their evil deeds elsewhere.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-210-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, pesce spada con cadmio e metalli pesanti in eccesso, integratori e cibi dietetici con ingredienti e novel food non autorizzati, arachidi dalla Cina e peperoncini dall'India contaminati da aflatossine cancerogene, peperoni provenienti dalla Turchia con pesticidi oltre i limiti: questi sono solo alcuni dei prodotti più pericolosi per la salute elencati da Coldiretti, la maggiore associazione di rappresentanza dell'agricoltura in Italia.</p>
      <p sl="en">I dati emergono da un dossier redatto sulla base dell'ultima relazione sul sistema di allerta rapido europeo, che registra gli allarmi per rischi alimentari verificatisi a causa di residui chimici, micotossine, metalli pesanti, inquinanti microbiologici, diossine, additivi e coloranti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Occorrono maggiori garanzie per i consumatori europei, non possiamo affidarci unicamente al sistema di allerta europeo. L'Europa deve fare molto di più in termini di tracciabilità, etichettatura e trasparenza per impedire che prodotti potenzialmente pericolosi per la salute giungano sulle tavole di milioni di consumatori europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-211-0000" speaker_id="96847" name="Claudiu Ciprian Tănăsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule Președinte, dragi colegi, anul trecut, în 7 iulie, aici, la Strasbourg, lansam către dumneavoastră propunerea ca în condițiile post-Brexit să facem împreună un prim pas spre consolidarea unei Europe omogene, a celor 27, prin regândirea distribuției în teritoriu a instituțiilor Uniunii. La acel moment, v-am făcut cunoscută intenția mea de a declanșa și a susține relocarea de la Londra la București a Agenției Europene pentru Medicamente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Azi vin în fața dumneavoastră și vă spun: colegii mei din guvernul României au pregătit una dintre cele mai bune oferte pentru relocarea EMA. Vă invit atât pe dumneavoastră, cât și pe factorii de decizie în chestiunea relocării EMA să priviți cu obiectivitate oferta României și, împreună, să ajungem la soluția corectă de relocare a agenției, al cărei loc poate fi la București. Relocarea în România a EMA ar putea fi primul semnal real privind coeziunea Uniunii Europene, dar și un semnal politic la fel de ferm în direcția combaterii ideii că membrii Uniunii Europene sunt egali doar pe hârtie. Relocarea EMA nu este doar un act administrativ generat de rezultatul Brexitului, ci este, în primul rând, o decizie cu o largă încărcătură politică, ale cărei consecințe se vor vedea ulterior.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-212-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, over the past months the level of violence across the Oromo and Ogaden regions of Ethiopia has hugely increased. Human rights groups continue to raise concerns over the use of excessive and unnecessary force by the state in response to peaceful protests. These developments take place after years of human rights violations by the state against Ogadeni, Somali and Oromo groups, including arrests and systemic violence against women, documented by the Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organisation (UNPO). The recent outbreaks of cholera in the country have increased the uncertainty of the situation. I am ashamed that the European Union has not yet made a statement on this worrying situation. As Ethiopia’s long-standing partner, the European Union should express its concern over the growing unrest and address the human rights abuses being perpetrated against minorities. Ethiopia is a crucial actor for security in East Africa. There must be a democratic and inclusive dialogue among groups in Ethiopia in order to de-escalate the tensions and bring about lasting peace and stability.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213-0000" speaker_id="96735" name="Patrick Le Hyaric" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, depuis 2010, ce qui devait être un plan de sauvetage de la Grèce s'est transformé en une succession de diktats économiques au nom du service d'une dette, dont on savait depuis le début qu'elle était insoutenable. Or, voici que nous apprenons que ces plans d'aide – aux conséquences catastrophiques pour le peuple grec – ont été l'occasion d'une lucrative opération pour la Banque centrale européenne, lui rapportant 7,8 milliards d'euros de dividendes et de rachat d'obligations à prix cassés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette somme considérable doit être rendue sans condition au trésor grec, sans quoi les opérations de la Banque centrale ne sauraient être autre chose que de la spéculation et un instrument de punition collective.</p>
      <p sl="en">D’autre part, la Grèce étant sortie depuis septembre de la procédure de déficit excessif, il est grand temps que l'Eurogroupe tienne ses engagements de novembre 2012 en matière de restructuration de la dette grecque. Ceci est une nécessité. Il faut rendre l'argent aux Grecs!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-214-0000" speaker_id="185974" name="Jordi Solé" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente. La de hoy es la séptima noche de Jordi Sánchez y Jordi Cuixart en la cárcel: siete días y siete noches privados de su libertad, acusados de algo que no han hecho. Prisioneros políticos en plena Unión Europea del siglo XXI, porque no están en la cárcel por lo que han hecho, sino por lo que representan y lo que piensan y, mientras tanto, ilustres corruptos campan a sus anchas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si la verdad y la justicia importaran, estarían libres. Pero, ¿cómo va a importar la verdad si hasta el ministro español de Asuntos Exteriores afirma, con toda la desfachatez del mundo, que muchas de las imágenes de la violencia policial del 1 de octubre son falsas? Lo único que les importa es castigar a un país que ha osado votar, que ha osado ejercer el derecho a la autodeterminación a pesar de los porrazos. Y si para castigar tienen que poner en peligro la democracia y modelar a su antojo el Estado de Derecho, ningún problema: lo hacen tranquilamente, amparados como están por su nacionalismo de Estado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y a Europa, ¿le importa la verdad? ¿Le importan los derechos fundamentales o solo le importan en países lejanos y situaciones distantes?</p>
      <a text="(El Presidente retira la palabra al orador)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-215-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ στην Ελλάδα, όσο και αν προκλητικά επιχείρησε να εμφανίσει την κυβέρνηση Trump από λύκο σε πρόβατο, ανέλαβε μεγάλες και επικίνδυνες δεσμεύσεις με την επίσκεψη Τσίπρα στις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες. Χρονική επέκταση και αναβάθμιση της Σούδας και άλλων βάσεων, ώστε να υπηρετήσουν πιο αποτελεσματικά τα ιμπεριαλιστικά σχέδια, εξοπλισμοί 2,4 δισεκατομμυρίων για νατοϊκές ανάγκες, ενώ κανένας δεν μπορεί να εφησυχάζει από τις κυβερνητικές δηλώσεις για τα πυρηνικά. Η προώθηση των συμφερόντων των μονοπωλίων των Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών με επενδύσεις πατάει στα αποκαΐδια των εργατικών λαϊκών δικαιωμάτων. Η γεωστρατηγική αναβάθμιση των συμφερόντων της ελληνικής αστικής τάξης που χαιρετίζουν κυβέρνηση και όλα τα αστικά κόμματα εδραιώνει σε βάρος του λαού την Ελλάδα ως ορμητήριο ιμπεριαλιστικών επεμβάσεων και πολέμων. Ανάγκη αποτελεί να ενταθεί η καθημερινή λαϊκή πάλη για να καταδικαστούν οι νέες, ακόμα πιο επικίνδυνες συμφωνίες της κυβέρνησης ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ με τις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες σε ρήξη με την εξουσία του κεφαλαίου και με τους ιμπεριαλιστικούς οργανισμούς, όπως το ΝΑΤΟ και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-216-0000" speaker_id="124706" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Colleagues, the list has been completed. That concludes the item.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Agenda of the next sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
