<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20180611.EN" lang="en" date="2018-06-11" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro ripresa la sessione del Parlamento europeo interrotta giovedì 31 maggio 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Statement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="El presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Quiero, al principio de este Pleno, mandar un mensaje de solidaridad con Guatemala. Hemos visto imágenes terribles sobre el volcán en erupción. El drama ha empezado la semana pasada y el volcán sigue todavía activo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las autoridades de Guatemala han anunciado que la cifra de muertos supera las cien personas. El número de desaparecidos es también muy elevado. Casi dos millones de personas se han visto afectadas por el volcán, lo que es más del 10 % de la población total del país.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sé que los satélites de Copérnico están siendo utilizados para ayudar en los rescates. También está llegando ayuda humanitaria por parte de la Unión Europea; pero, por encima de todo, quiero expresar, en nombre del Parlamento Europeo, nuestro afecto y apoyo al pueblo de Guatemala en estos momentos tan difíciles.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Announcement by the President">
    <intervention id="1-010-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Lo scorso 31 maggio il tribunale dell'Unione europea ha annullato due decisioni dell'Ufficio di presidenza del Parlamento europeo, con le quali si irrogava una sanzione all'eurodeputato Korwin-Mikke per le dichiarazioni rilasciate nel corso di due sessioni plenarie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nella sessione del 7 giugno 2016, l'onorevole aveva definito i migranti "spazzatura umana che non ha voglia di lavorare". Nella seduta del 1° marzo 2017, durante la discussione sul divario retributivo tra uomini e donne, l'onorevole Korwin-Mikke aveva sostenuto "che le donne dovrebbero guadagnare meno degli uomini in quanto più deboli, più piccole e meno intelligenti".</p>
      <p sl="en">Rispetto le decisioni dei tribunali. Tuttavia, credo fermamente che sia mio dovere, sempre, sanzionare chi afferma che le donne sono esseri inferiori.</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">Non rinuncerò mai a difendere l'uguaglianza tra donne e uomini. Lo devo a tutte le donne che, a prezzo di enormi sacrifici, hanno conquistato nei secoli i loro diritti e che, nonostante questo, rimangono ancora oggi vittime di discriminazioni e violenze in ogni paese dell'Unione europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ho chiesto al Servizio giuridico del Parlamento di valutare la possibilità di presentare ricorso contro la decisione presso la Corte di giustizia. Ne discuteremo, anche questa sera, all'Ufficio di presidenza.</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">Lo devo a mia madre, che non c'è più, ma anche a mia moglie, a mia figlia e a tutte quante voi.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Negotiations ahead of Parliament's first reading (Rule 69c): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Corrigendum (Rule 231): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Major interpellations (Rule 130b) (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Action taken on Parliament’s positions and resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-020-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il progetto definitivo di ordine del giorno, fissato dalla Conferenza dei presidenti, ai sensi dell'articolo 149 del regolamento, nella riunione di giovedì 7 giugno 2018, è stato distribuito. Sono state presentate le seguenti proposte di modifica:</p>
      <p sl="en">Lunedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Non sono proposte modifiche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Martedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Il gruppo GUE ha chiesto che il titolo della dichiarazione del vicepresidente della Commissione/alto rappresentante dell'Unione per gli affari esteri e la politica di sicurezza sui "Territori georgiani occupati a dieci anni dall'invasione russa" sia modificato in "Regioni separatiste della Georgia a dieci anni dalla guerra con la Russia".</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-0000" speaker_id="96646" name="Helmut Scholz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I guess we are all still under the impression of the G7 controversial messages, decisions and developments, and therefore I think we should stick to the historical rules, to the facts. Therefore, I would propose, on behalf of our Group, that we change the title of the debate on Tuesday to the new version. I will read it out: ‘Georgia’s breakaway regions ten years after the war with Russia’. This is much closer to the facts which happened – and what are the facts? How we can deal with the responsibility of the European Union in contributing to finding solutions to this very complicated and controversial situation should be the matter of the debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-022-0000" speaker_id="28353" name="Anna Elżbieta Fotyga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the security situation in Georgia has frequently been debated in the Subcommittee on Security and Defence. We were usually in agreement that the territories of South Ossetia and Abkhazia were not voluntarily breaking away from Georgia, but that the situation in these regions is due to high pressure from their neighbour, namely the Russian Federation. Georgia did not declare war on those territories or any other, particularly Russia. It was a Russian invasion of the integral territories of Georgia. Therefore I am against.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Passiamo ora alle proposte di modifica per la giornata di mercoledì.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mercoledì</p>
      <p sl="en">Il gruppo dei Verdi ha proposto di aggiungere come secondo punto all'ordine del giorno del pomeriggio le dichiarazioni del Consiglio e della Commissione sulla "Situazione dopo la chiusura dei porti del Mediterraneo, le emergenze umanitarie e la solidarietà nell'Unione europea".</p>
      <p sl="en">La discussione dovrebbe concludersi con una risoluzione da votare a luglio.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, d’abord je voudrais vous dire que je suis fier de faire partie d’un Parlement qui a su, en décembre dernier, trouver une large majorité pour réformer le système de Dublin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense que si les solutions que nous avons adoptées ici devenaient réalité, nous ne serions pas dans la situation dans laquelle nous nous trouvons aujourd’hui – une situation où un navire avec plus de 600 personnes à bord, dont plus de 130 mineurs, est ballotté d’un endroit à l’autre de la Méditerranée parce que deux pays ont décidé de lui fermer leurs ports, en violation, d’ailleurs, de leurs obligations légales. Alors, je comprends la frustration de l’Italie, de Malte, de la Grèce, de la Bulgarie ou encore de l’Espagne, que trop souvent la règle de Dublin laisse seuls pour faire face au défi de l’immigration. C’est évident, nous ne pouvons pas les laisser seuls. Ceci dit, cela n’excuse pas ce qui est en train de se passer et nous pensons qu’il faut mettre ce point à l’ordre du jour.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons tenté de trouver un titre de compromis. Je comprends bien que nos collègues socialistes, ne voulant pas se désolidariser du Premier ministre maltais, voudraient qu’on ne parle pas de fermeture des ports – ce qui, à la limite, ne me pose pas de problème, même si c’est bien cela l’élément déclencheur –, alors on pourrait reformuler le titre. Je vais le dire en anglais puisque c’est le titre que nous avons trouvé:</p>
      <p sl="en">‘Council and Commission statement on humanitarian emergencies in the Mediterranean and solidarity in the European Union.’</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous pourrions être d’accord avec ce titre de compromis, j’espère qu’il pourra trouver une large majorité au sein de cette assemblée.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-028-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Lamberts?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-029-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">onsieur le Président, on m’informe que la commission des libertés publiques prépare une résolution sur un sujet tout à fait connexe qui sera à l’ordre du jour du mois de juillet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense qu’on peut donc se passer d’une résolution à ce stade et se contenter d’un débat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="124737" name="Maria João Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the real solution for the situation we have is for the next European Council to endorse the reform of the Dublin system, as we in the European Parliament endorsed it with a clear majority. This is the real solution. In the meantime, it is important to highlight that in the face of the conservative xenophobic behaviour of the Italian Government, we now have a bold position coming from a Socialist government: the newly elected government in Spain. That is why we, the S&amp;D Group, would like to have a debate on the Council and Commission statements on humanitarian emergencies in the Mediterranean. This is exactly our purpose, and we would also like to add ‘solidarity in the European Union’ in the title. We do not need a resolution, because good work is being undertaken in Libya on how exactly to deal with this situation.</p>
      <a text="(Interjection from the floor: ‘That is exactly what I said.’)"/>
      <p sl="en">Yes, you changed your minds at the right time. Thank you again for joining something that we shall get a majority for in this Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="97058" name="Guy Verhofstadt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, I ask myself why we have to wait until Wednesday. We have a European Council debate tomorrow. This European Council debate will be about migration, so I am telling you that I am going to intervene about this scandal tomorrow. I am not going to wait until Wednesday, because the Commission and the Council will be there.</p>
      <p sl="de">So my request to you is that we don’t wait until Wednesday and that we add it to the debate on the European Council tomorrow, as it will be one of the points. In my proposal, Mrs Rodrigues, it’s not a question of pointing the finger at one or other country and saying: ‘Oh how good we are when the socialists are in the government; how bad we are …’. I think in Malta you are in the government, aren’t you? So don’t start this little political game on the backbone of migrants. I don’t like it and nobody likes it.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="de">My request is very simple: please, Mr President, put it as an additional point tomorrow with the Commission and the Council. I think the scandal is so great that we cannot wait for a separate debate on Wednesday afternoon.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="21817" name="Mario Borghezio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ENF. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, nulla quaestio da parte nostra che si discuta su questo argomento. Vorrei solo, sommessamente, osservare che sono quasi dieci anni che da questi banchi chiediamo di riformulare queste regole e di non lasciare l'Italia da sola.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'è voluto il gesto coraggioso di un governo che, come ha sottolineato il vicepresidente del Consiglio Di Maio, si è preoccupato, anzitutto, della situazione e dell'emergenza sanitaria e umanitaria. Io vorrei sapere quali dei vostri paesi fa altrettanto nel Mediterraneo, e ringrazio la Spagna, per aver, con un gesto coraggioso, risolto in extremis questo governo, mentre il resto dell'Europa ci lasciava da soli, come sempre! Povera Italia! È cambiata: la pacchia è finita! È cambiata l'aria!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Onorevole Borghezio, quindi, se ho capito bene, stava esprimendo la sua posizione a favore di un dibattito sull'argomento?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-0000" speaker_id="21817" name="Mario Borghezio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ENF. – Più esattamente, non ci opponiamo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="124810" name="Barbara Spinelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo GUE/NGL. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io vorrei spiegare perché sono favorevole a una discussione a parte sulla questione degli sbarchi. So benissimo che alle radici delle decisioni italiane c'è una persistente mancanza di solidarietà europea, a cominciare dalla paralisi dei negoziati su Dublino IV, ma la legge internazionale fissa priorità ineludibili: prima viene il dovere di disimbarcare centinaia di migranti in condizioni di sofferenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'inviato speciale dell'ONU Vincent Cochetel chiede al governo italiano lo sbarco immediato e il rispetto di un imperativo umanitario urgente e aggiunge che questioni più vaste concernenti la suddivisione di responsabilità nell'Unione potranno essere discusse più tardi tra gli Stati membri. In questione sono le priorità, e dunque ben venga un dibattito sulla crisi umanitaria dei migranti in Italia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Le Président" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur Verhofstadt, si j’ai bien compris, vous demandez d’ajouter dans le débat de demain, une ligne avec un titre: «le titre ajouté au débat de demain».</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur le texte, vous êtes d’accord? Sur le titre du débat? Vous êtes d’accord avec les socialistes? Alors il faut décider si nous le faisons demain ou mercredi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur Lamberts, s’il-vous-plait.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, je comprends la logique de la proposition du collègue Verhofstadt. L’avantage est qu’il n’y a pas d’attente, puisque cela se passe demain matin, mais l’inconvénient est qu’il y a de nombreux sujets à l’ordre du jour du Conseil. Je pense notamment à l’avenir de l’Union économique et monétaire, au Brexit ou encore à la question migratoire. Nous craignons que le point dont nous voulons discuter ici soit dilué dans un débat qui parlera de plein de choses et que tout cela ne soit finalement très clair.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc a priori nous sommes … (interruption inaudible) est-ce que je peux encore parler? (Le Président interrompt l’orateur) Notre option privilégiée est un débat séparé et, en solution de repli, s’il n’y a pas de majorité pour cette option, on rajoute en effet le titre au … (Le Président retire la parole à l’orateur).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Le Président" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">J’ai bien compris. M. Verhofstadt soutient qu’il faut faire tout de suite le débat et l’insérer dans les débats de demain.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous, vous dites que c’est mieux d’avoir un débat séparé, après-demain, car le sujet est très important.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="124737" name="Maria João Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in fact I have exactly the same argument, which is that European Council will deal with this and, of course, will make the point. But there are many other points for the next European Council, therefore we’d like to keep this proposal of a separate debate on this refugee case, along with the debate – a proper debate – in the European Council tomorrow.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Le Président" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il faut voter et décider si le débat aura lieu demain ou mercredi. Je commence avec la proposition de M. Lamberts, qui est aussi celle de Mme Rodrigues.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, κατ’ αρχάς δεν αποφασίσαμε εάν θέλουμε να γίνει αυτή η συζήτηση. Εσείς θέτετε δύο ζητήματα: αν η συζήτηση θα εγγραφεί στη ημερήσια διάταξη της αυριανής συνεδρίασης ή στην ημερήσια διάταξη της μεθαυριανής συνεδρίασης. Κατ’ αρχάς πρέπει να ψηφίσουμε αν θέλουμε να γίνει αυτή η συζήτηση, γιατί κάποιοι εδώ θέλουν να απαξιώσουν το δικαίωμα της κυβέρνησης της Ιταλίας να απαγορεύσει σε κάποιες ΜΚΟ να μεταφέρουν λαθραία μετανάστες στην Ιταλία. Θεωρώ λοιπόν ότι πρώτα πρέπει να ψηφίσουμε εάν θέλουμε να γίνει αυτή η συζήτηση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">(rivolgendosi all'onorevole Fountoulis) Sono due proposte differenti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prima voteremo la proposta degli onorevoli Lamberts e Rodrigues. Se uno non vuole il dibattito, vota contro. Non è una scelta tra un giorno e un altro. Si può votare contro la proposta Lamberts-Rodrigues. Poi si voterà la proposta dell'onorevole Verhofstadt. Se entrambe le proposte vengono bocciate non si farà il dibattito.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi: se viene approvata la proposta Lamberts-Rodrigues si farà dopodomani; se viene bocciata e poi viene approvata quella dell'onorevole Verhofstadt, si farà domani; se viene bocciata anche quest'ultima, non si fa né domani né dopodomani.</p>
      <p sl="en">Passiamo alla votazione della proposta Rodrigues-Lamberts.</p>
      <a text="(Il Parlamento accoglie la richiesta)"/>
      <p sl="en">Giovedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Non sono proposte modifiche.</p>
      <a text="(L'ordine dei lavori è così fissato)"/>
      <a text="(La seduta è sospesa per pochi istanti)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Clearing obligation, reporting requirements, risk-mitigation techniques and trade repositories (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Președintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este dezbaterea privind raportul lui Werner Langen, în numele Comisiei pentru afaceri economice și monetare, referitor la propunerea de regulament al Parlamentului European și al Consiliului de modificare a Regulamentului (UE) nr. 648/2012 în ceea ce privește obligația de compensare, suspendarea obligației de compensare, cerințele de raportare, tehnicile de atenuare a riscurilor pentru contractele derivate extrabursiere care nu sunt compensate de o contraparte centrală, înregistrarea și supravegherea registrelor centrale de tranzacții și cerințele aplicabile registrelor centrale de tranzacții (COM(2017)0208 - C8-0147/2017 - 2017/0090(COD)) (A8-0181/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="1928" name="Werner Langen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Herr Präsident! Ich habe eine laute Stimme, wäre aber trotzdem dankbar, wenn die Lärmkulisse etwas kleiner wäre.</p>
      <a text="(Der Präsident ruft zur Ruhe im Saal auf.)"/>
      <p sl="en">Wir beraten heute, zehn Jahre nach dem Beginn der Finanzmarktkrise und fünf Jahre nach der Verabschiedung von EMIR, der Europäischen Marktinfrastruktur-Verordnung, über Vorschläge, die die Kommission gemacht hat, um dieses wichtige Instrument zur Bewältigung der Finanzmarktkrise und zur Abmilderung der Risiken an die Erfordernisse und die Erfahrungen der vergangenen Jahre anzupassen. Seit 2012 ist EMIR in Kraft. Die letzte internationale Vereinbarung mit den USA auf der Grundlage des Dodd-Frank Act ist am 17. Februar 2017 in Kraft getreten, sodass wir hier weltweit vergleichbare äquivalente Vorschriften haben. Die Anpassung ergibt sich durch die Erfahrungen insbesondere mit kleineren Marktteilnehmern, mit nichtfinanziellen Marktteilnehmern, die natürlich ein weitaus geringeres Risiko haben als die großen Akteure am Markt, und deshalb haben wir die Meldepflichten vereinfacht. Die Kommission hat das vorgeschlagen, wir haben es etwas modifiziert. Wir haben die Berichtspflichten mit einer klaren Haftung versehen. Wir wollen nichtfinanzielle kleine Gegenparteien weitgehend freistellen, und wir haben Ungereimtheiten der ersten Verordnung ausbügeln wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der zuständige Wirtschaftsausschuss hat den Vorschlag auf der Grundlage der ausgehandelten Kompromisse mit den anderen Fraktionen mit 46 Stimmen bei 5 Gegenstimmen und 4 Enthaltungen angenommen. Das ist eine sehr gute Grundlage, um nach dem Votum des Parlaments in Verhandlungen mit dem Rat zu treten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte gleichzeitig auch drei Ratspräsidentschaften Dank sagen: der estnischen, die relativ früh angefangen hat, den Vorschlag zu beraten, der bulgarischen, die ihn weiterentwickelt hat, und wir werden die Verhandlungen, so hoffe ich, in wenigen Runden mit der österreichischen Ratspräsidentschaft vollenden können und damit ein modernes Regelwerk beschließen, das geeignet ist, die Risikominderung im Bereich der Derivate deutlich zu verbessern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zur Erinnerung: Im Jahre 2009 war das Nennvolumen der weltweiten Derivate 720 Billionen US-Dollar; das war damals exakt das Zwölffache des Weltsozialprodukts aller 7,5 Milliarden Menschen. Das Volumen ist leicht gesunken, vor allen Dingen sind die Risikowerte deutlich verbessert worden. Wir haben Vorschriften und Vorschläge gemacht, die über die der Kommission hinausgehen, die der Ausschuss gebilligt hat. Wir haben einen wirklich strittigen Punkt auch im Parlament diskutiert, den wir auch mit dem Rat weiterdiskutieren werden: das ist die Verlängerung der Befreiung von der Clearingpflicht für Pensionsfonds, die OTC-Derivate zur Reduktion von Anlagerisiken nutzen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nun haben wir die Ausnahme bisher viermal verlängert, die Kommission hat erneut drei Jahre und am Ende zwei Jahre vorgeschlagen. Wenn man bedenkt, dass das Volumen in den Pensionsfonds in der Europäischen Union immerhin 3,6 Millionen Euro beträgt, dann ist das ein gewaltiger Batzen. Ich bin dem Kommissar, dem Vizepräsidenten Dombrovskis ausdrücklich dankbar, dass er zu dieser Frage eine Runde eingerichtet hat, die die Debatte führt, einen runden Tisch, der Lösungsvorschläge erarbeitet. Und das Parlament möchte diese Fristen verlängern, jedenfalls keine dauerhafte Ausnahme. Und deshalb, Herr Dombrovskis, sind wir äußerst dankbar. Ich habe das Protokoll der ersten Runde gelesen, und dort haben auch die Stakeholder gesagt: Jawohl, wir halten eine Lösung für machbar.</p>
      <p sl="en">In diesem Sinne möchte ich mich bei allen Beteiligten – den Schattenberichterstattern, der Kommission, den Akteuren am Markt – für ihre guten Beiträge bedanken. Ich hoffe, dass diese Änderung morgen mit einem klaren Votum des Plenums verabschiedet werden kann.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all I would like to thank the rapporteur and the shadows for the excellent work they put into preparing the committee report.</p>
      <p sl="en">Your vote tomorrow concerns the first of the two proposals we put forward on the European Market Infrastructure Regulation, or EMIR, in 2017. This proposal is about simplifying EMIR, reducing costs and burdens where possible without calling into question the core objectives of EMIR: financial stability, risk mitigation and transparency.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proposal is part of the Commission’s Regulatory Fitness and Performance programme. It emphasises the need for cost reduction and a simplification. The need to revise some of EMIR’s requirements became evident from the responses we got to the Commission’s general call for evidence on financial services legislation in 2016.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our proposal is technical but important. Its savings potential is big. The estimated cost reductions are up to EUR 6.9 billion in fixed or one-off costs, and up to EUR 2.6 billion in annual operational costs. Our proposal includes a more professional clearing obligation for non-financial firms: it exempts the smallest financial counterparties from the clearing obligation altogether; it introduces a new mechanism to suspend clearing in exceptional circumstances; it incentivises clearing and improves access to it; and it simplifies reporting requirements, in particular for businesses without compromising the quality of data.</p>
      <p sl="en">Companies, market participants, regulators and supervisors all agree on the need for this proposal and largely support it. I am very pleased that the debate and the vote takes place now as the adoption of the proposal is urgent.</p>
      <p sl="en">As Mr Langen outlined, pension funds currently benefit from an exemption from central clearing which expires very soon. Without legislative change this exemption cannot continue, but we still need this exemption for a limited time. While the market has progressed, it has not yet adopted viable solutions for pension funds to centrally clear their derivatives.</p>
      <p sl="en">In recent months the Commission has brought together all stakeholders to discuss progress towards a clearing solution for pension funds, and last week I hosted a high-level meeting with those stakeholders and I was happy that some of you joined us for this. I was glad to see that industry stakeholders all committed to design and implement a solution. We need a bit of time to put this commitment into practice, but let me be clear, we are not giving a carte blanche. Progress during this extended exemption period must be monitored, and the Commission will set up a monitoring group for this purpose.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, let me highlight again that the purpose of this proposal is to introduce some targeted amendments to simplify and to make EMIR requirements more proportionate. But these amendments need to uphold the fundamental objectives of EMIR. For example, when it comes to reducing requirements to report or exchange bilateral margins for derivatives: if we go too far, supervisors will no longer be able to supervise and monitor over-the-counter derivatives and mitigate systemic risks.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must keep in mind that this piece of legislation is one of the cornerstones of the new system we put in place after the crisis in agreement with the G20. It’s our collective responsibility to ensure that it remains effective.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="118658" name="Brian Hayes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I want to congratulate my colleague, Mr Werner Langen, for his report. It is a very sensible approach and there is strong support in the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs (ECON) for this report. In particular, the rapporteur’s proposal to extend the intra-group exemption to a global basis and to introduce full, single-sided reporting for non-financial corporations is welcomed. This will significantly reduce costs for most small companies, which can then be reinvested in the real economy.</p>
      <p sl="en">When the Commission published their proposal last May, the idea was to eliminate disproportionate costs and burdens on small companies and to simplify rules without compromising financial stability. The Parliament has taken this approach and has stuck to the argument produced by the Commission. By applying single—sided reporting as opposed to the current dual-sided regime, it would bring Europe in line with other jurisdictions and make the EU more attractive destination for corporate treasury functions, which is an important aspect.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parliament’s position reduces the proposed three-plus—two—year exemption for pension funds to comply with the clearing obligations to two—plus—one—year exemption, with very small pension funds exempted. I understand the compromises that were reached on behalf of my colleague and his colleagues in ECON, but at the end of the day we do need to be careful about this. Whether European pension funds will be able to comply with the requirements over a very short period of time is a serious issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">I was the rapporteur for the IORP II Directive; I am aware that pension funds are fundamentally different to other financial entities when it comes to clearing, as they have a long—term investment profile and low liquidity needs. We really need to be sure that pension funds will be able to manage a new clearing obligation in such a short space of time, especially given the difficult position that many pension funds find themselves in right now with the low interest rate environment and the difficulty of making returns for existing members and beneficiaries. We have to find a solution to this; I like the idea of a round table. The exemption cannot continue forever but we need to be cautious in how we respond to the pension issue.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="124840" name="Jakob von Weizsäcker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would first like to thank the rapporteur, Werner Langen, and all shadow rapporteurs for the excellent spirit of cooperation that produced a good report, building on a sensible Commission proposal to streamline EMIR in a number of areas. It has been our priority, in working on this file, to safeguard financial stability and to expand central clearing, while allowing some simplification in areas where reduction of requirements has little influence on systemic risk and helps to reduce cost.</p>
      <p sl="en">A notable improvement is the introduction of a specific clearing threshold for financial counterparties. However, perhaps most notable in this report – and it has been mentioned by previous speakers – are the credible arrangements to bring pension funds into the scope of the clearing obligation somewhat sooner than was envisaged, against the backdrop of a number of extensions that have already taken place. Here I am particularly grateful to the Vice—President for having invited me, among others, to the round table that you organised with stakeholders – not least in view of the realism of the two-plus-one solution that we are envisaging.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I am confident that it is absolutely possible to implement the necessary steps, especially for bigger pension funds, within the timeframes that we have put forward. Indeed, on 16 May a large majority in the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs (ECON) voted for those particular deadlines. This measure stands to improve financial stability – that is bringing in pension funds and the safety of pensions – while giving all stakeholders enough time to prepare. I am looking forward to continuing our work in the forthcoming trialogues and would be delighted if this House were to vote with a large majority to enter into interinstitutional negotiations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="124897" name="Stanisław Ożóg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Dzięki decyzji o włączeniu rozporządzenia EMIR do systemu REFIT udało się stwierdzić, że w niektórych obszarach EMIR wygeneruje nieproporcjonalnie wysokie koszty i obciążenia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dzisiaj dzięki pracy pana sprawozdawcy i kontrsprawozdawców mamy do zaoferowania propozycje, które w konkretny sposób upraszczają przepisy EMIR oraz zwiększają ich przejrzystość bez wzrostu ryzyka dla stabilności finansowej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Delegacja Prawa i Sprawiedliwości zdecydowanie popiera obecny projekt również w kwestii najbardziej nas dzielącej chyba, czyli kompromisu co do tymczasowego wyłączenia z obowiązku rozliczania systemów programów emerytalnych, zarówno w odniesieniu do tych dużych, jak i małych. Wierzymy, że obecna propozycja pozwoli uniknąć małym kontrahentom finansowym kosztów operacyjnych, według szacunku może być to nawet rzędu 1,5 mld euro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gratuluję Panie Pośle Sprawozdawco, przyjmiemy dobry dokument.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="124707" name="Petr Ježek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, the original EMIR entered into force in 2012 and it is rightly considered the gold standard worldwide, but since the entry into force of EMIR it has been possible to identify areas where further attention is needed, or indeed where there is a risk of duplicative requirements which can add costs for firms dealing in derivatives. In particular, it is right that we are streamlining the reporting requirements by moving toward single-sided reporting. It is also positive that there will be exemptions for intra-group transactions and the removal of the backloading obligation. Furthermore, it is made clear in the EP report that data quality is more important than quantity.</p>
      <p sl="de">We must also must bear in mind the practical aspects of implementation of EMIR. Through the EMIR REFIT, we have been able to identify areas which can be further streamlined in the regulation. For example, an exemption for certain small financial counterparties from the clearing obligation, and it will now be possible for the Commission to suspend the clearing obligation in cases of instability in the markets.</p>
      <p sl="de">Finally, I am glad that the rapporteur has included a proposal to bridge the limbo period for pension funds. We must ensure that the pension funds are able to continue to make use of the exemption in the period between August of this year and the entry into force of the EMIR REFIT Regulation. This will be one of the key priorities for my Group as we move towards our negotiations with the Council. My thanks to the rapporteur and to the shadows.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, after the financial crisis, when the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EMIR) was put in place, it resulted – and we welcomed that – not only in more transparency on the derivatives market, but also in more central clearing, which is a welcome development. There is still progress to be made, and the first positive aspect of the text that we are going to adopt is that we insist that central clearing should go up; the share of the market that should be centrally cleared cannot go down, it has to go up.</p>
      <p sl="en">Second, this idea of having more conservative methods to decide whether small financial counterparties are below the clearing threshold is also welcome. On these pension funds: I remember the study carried out by the European Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA) showing how badly pension funds were funded. When pension funds have to resort not only to derivatives, but to over-the-counter derivatives to run their business, then something is probably badly wrong. They made promises that they cannot possibly hold. I do not think that this is a reason to exclude them from the obligation of central clearing. The two—plus—one is welcome, and they cannot complain about that; they have to run their businesses in a sustainable way.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are going to vote on this report, but I would finish by saying this: Warren Buffett mentioned these derivatives as weapons of mass financial destruction. This was not by chance. These products are used in such volumes that they dwarf the real economy. 30 or 40 years ago, we had a working economy and we did not have this mass of derivatives. There are probably a lot of these derivatives that are unneeded and dangerous, and this is still a work in progress. Secondly, central clearing houses are becoming ‘too big to fail’ institution. They are systemic, and we should better regulate on how we deal with them in case of crisis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as we all know – and indeed as the G20 leaders themselves acknowledged in Pittsburgh – derivatives were at the very heart of the global financial crisis. When we’re talking about the regulation of a market worth more than USD 500 trillion, we need to get it right. EMIR, the post-crisis framework for the regulation of over-the-counter derivatives, has its problems certainly, but it is a crucial instrument for ensuring financial stability.</p>
      <p sl="en">This review proposal bends over backwards in my view to meet the demands of the industry, an industry – let’s not forget – that just a decade ago brought our economies and societies to the brink of collapse. I share the concerns that this move reflects a more general effort by this House to roll back and unpick the financial regulations put in place after the crisis. The weakening of regulations may be targeted at the smaller market participants, but the nature of this market is that it is a chain of interdependencies that promotes risk volatility. We have a responsibility as legislators to ensure that the derivatives industry is bound by strict and high standard regulations on transparency, reporting and clearing, and this Parliament, I fear, is failing to meet that responsibility with the report in front of us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="124967" name="David Coburn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I suppose that it’s a positive thing in revising regulations on OTC derivatives – the trend is to make reporting requirements slightly less complicated and burden slightly fewer firms with them. Even these modest changes will, by the Commission’s own estimates, save billions of pounds every year. But how many more billions could be saved by scrapping the attempt to micromanage the markets completely? The volume of data collected is so vast that there is no way to analyse it in a timely fashion, if at all. And what will the regulators do once the data tells them that the OTC horse has bolted? Close the stable door? All that will be achieved is to discover that a white elephant preceded the horse.</p>
      <p sl="en">And if proof were needed that the EU has not learnt the lesson of the euro crisis and wants to let sleeping dogs lie, look no further than the Italian banks, dramatically increasing their use of securitisation – the same financial engineering as in the American sub-prime bubble. Who can forget that? Certainly not those who lost their homes. Italian banks have been falling over themselves to bundle up packages of their non-performing loans, wrap them up as CDOs, and sell them to other banks at a pace almost twice that seen last year. 25 billion – I repeat, 25 billion – has been sold like this in the first half of 2018, with some senior tranches guaranteed by – guess who? – the Italian Government.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is simply making the debt contagious all over again: a wolf in sheep’s clothing. All it does is create a new debt death-loop between Italian banks and their government. Italy’s debt still stands at 132% of GDP, and over 150% of GDP if you include TARGET2 liabilities. Unable to devalue its currency, public debt is like a snake eating its own tail. I can tell you: bolting horses, white elephants, sleeping dogs – a financial dog’s dinner, ladies and gentlemen, a financial dog’s dinner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="1922" name="Thomas Mann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Nach Herrn Coburn zu reden, ist immer ein Vergnügen, weil seine schlichte Sprache zwar ankommt, aber weit weg von Inhalten ist. Das Kernziel von EMIR ist die Stärkung der Stabilität der Finanzmärkte in der EU durch höhere Anforderungen bei Meldung und bei der Transparenz. Der Bericht der EU-Kommission kam zu dem Schluss, dass vor allem bei den nichtfinanziellen Gegenparteien hohe Hürden abgebaut werden müssen. Die Reformvorschläge beabsichtigen eine verbesserte, möglichst effiziente Verwendung der Mittel. Zahlreiche Industrie- und Finanzunternehmen sind unmittelbar von EMIR betroffen. Die Absicherung der Geschäftsrisiken durch Reporting-Pflichten verursacht Kosten. Ja, richtig aber ist, sie dort zu senken, wo die Finanzstabilität nicht geschwächt wird, um auf diese Weise unverhältnismäßig hohen Mehraufwand zu unterbinden, etwa die doppelte Mehrheit. Sie sollte beim finanziellen Unternehmen verbleiben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mit breiter Mehrheit haben wir den ausgezeichneten Bericht meines Kollegen Werner Langen unterstützt. Ich bin ihm ausgesprochen dankbar dafür, dass wir heute, lieber Werner, darüber debattieren, bevor solche Verhandlungen im Trilog geführt werden. Das nenne ich absolute Möglichkeit an demokratischer Partizipation. Er schlägt vor, die deutlichen Verbesserungen bei den Berichtspflichten zu unterstützen – in der Risikovorsorge, beim Bürokratieabbau. Auch wird der Aspekt der bislang nicht geregelten Risikobewertung von Pensionsfonds angegangen – sein Stichwort war „Runder Tisch“, wirklich als eine große Chance für gemeinsame Ergebnisse. Wir stehen zu diesen Schritten eines modernen Regelwerkes für mehr Stabilität auf den Finanzmärkten. Lieber Werner, herzlichen Dank – ein Bericht, der eine riesengroße Chance hat, breite Mehrheitsunterstützung zu bekommen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, je soutiens la proposition EMIR REFIT, à savoir la révision du règlement sur l'infrastructure du marché européen au titre du programme pour une réglementation affûtée et performante, qui révise le règlement original EMIR de 2012 en simplifiant certaines règles pour les contreparties financières et non financières sur le marché des dérivés, le rendant plus proportionnel et, je cite, plus simple, plus léger, plus efficace et moins coûteux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout en soulignant que la proposition EMIR REFIT apporte plusieurs améliorations, notamment en ce qui concerne la suspension de la compensation et le calcul du seuil de compensation ainsi que le traitement des régimes de retraite, je considère que les régimes de retraite devraient être encouragés à mettre en œuvre des solutions et des compensations centralisées en temps opportun.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, je voudrais saluer, en particulier, l’objectif de la proposition de préserver la stabilité financière et d’élargir la compensation centrale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="190519" name="Caroline Nagtegaal" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, een goede, eerlijke en betrouwbare pensioenvoorziening is een van de pijlers van onze moderne welvaartstaat. Dat gaat verder dan alleen maar een overheid die na de pensioengerechtigde leeftijd een uitkering geeft. Dat betekent namelijk ook dat burgers zelf geld inleggen voor een goed inkomen op hun oude dag.</p>
      <p sl="en">De verantwoordelijkheid van de overheid bestaat erin te zorgen voor een goed stelsel waarbij zo veel mogelijk geld dat voor het pensioen bestemd is, daar ook daadwerkelijk terechtkomt. Onnodig geld aan de administratieve strijkstok laten hangen zonder voor een efficiënte oplossing zorgen, is juist niet hoe het moet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik betreur dan ook oprecht dat de rapporteur, samen met het onderhandelingsteam, ervoor heeft gekozen om de pensioenfondsen en de clearinghuizen maar twee jaar te geven om een oplossing te vinden voor de clearingverplichting. Om het namelijk goed te doen is er meer tijd nodig. Die tijd niet nemen, zal er helaas toe leiden dat een goede, deugdelijke en eerlijke pensioenvoorziening in het gedrang komt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik ben dan ook blij dat dit slechts een parlementspositie is: niet het eindpunt, maar een tussenstap in het uiteindelijke akkoord van het Parlement met de Raad. Ik hoop en verwacht eigenlijk ook dat in de trialoogonderhandelingen over deze wetgeving de misser van dit Parlement uiteindelijk wordt gerepareerd. Dank u wel.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Nie mam zastrzeżeń do sprawozdania, do pracy wykonanej przez kolegę Langego, natomiast zwrócę uwagę na dwa elementy, które mnie niepokoją. Otóż cały czas coraz lepiej radzimy sobie z kryzysami, które miały miejsce, i potrafimy zastosować określone procedury, aby uprzedzić ewentualny kryzys, który znamy z przeszłości. Natomiast bardzo słabo funkcjonujemy, jeżeli chodzi o antycypowanie kryzysów z użyciem innych narzędzi, innych technik, innych sposobów.</p>
      <p sl="en">I muszę powiedzieć, że ochrona funduszy emerytalnych w tej materii powinna być przedmiotem naszej szczególnej troski i powinniśmy pamiętać także o tych pojedynczych sygnałach, które pojawiają się już w chwili obecnej, a nawet o przenoszeniu indywidualnymi decyzjami części zasobów emerytalnych, np. poprzez ich lokowanie w kryptowalutach. Według mojej oceny musimy mieć więcej wyobraźni i szybciej wyprzedzać sytuacje kryzysowe, które mogą się zdarzyć.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we have done important work to make the derivatives market safe and efficient, and this file continues our work. I would like to use this opportunity to thank the European Parliament, and in particular the rapporteur, Mr Werner Langen, and the shadow rapporteurs, but also the Committee Chair, Mr Roberto Gualtieri, for their excellent work on this file.</p>
      <p sl="en">I very much look forward to working further on this file and I would finish by reiterating the hope expressed by Werner Langen that we will be able to conclude this file after a few rounds within the Austrian Presidency.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="1928" name="Werner Langen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Herr Präsident! Ich möchte ebenfalls allen Rednern für ihre positiven Beiträge danken. Mit der Kommission und den Mitarbeitern haben wir seit 2010 die Debatte geführt. Sie war intensiv, sie war kontrovers, sie war mehr oder weniger der Benchmark, die europäische Regelung weltweit. Und wir sind jetzt, nach den Erfahrungen von fünf Jahren, in der Lage, das anzupassen. Das ist eigentlich der richtige Weg, um Kosten zu sparen, wie der Kommissar gesagt hat, um Vereinfachung zu erreichen, Bürokratie abzubauen und die Risikobewertung für kleinere Marktteilnehmer neu zu gewichten. Das ist die Hauptsache.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das zweite wichtige Thema sind die Pensionsfonds. Ich habe nochmal nachgeschaut: Den größten Anteil an OTC-Derivaten haben die Pensionsfonds in Italien mit 1,8 Billionen Euro, dann kommen die Niederlande mit 1,2 Billionen und dann mehrere andere Mitgliedstaaten mit kleineren Beträgen. Insgesamt hat die Kommission ja Vorschläge gemacht, nicht nur im Rahmen des REFIT-Programms, sondern auch zur location policy – der Bericht von Frau Hübner, der bereits in den Verhandlungen ist –, und wir haben die Aufsicht verstärkt durch den Vorschlag, die ESMA stärker zu beteiligen und die EZB dort einzubeziehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein geschlossenes Paket, von dem ich hoffe, dass wir es relativ schnell zu Ende bringen können, damit keine Übergangszeiten ohne Regelung entstehen, wie der Kollege Ježek gesagt hat. Insofern möchte ich mich ausdrücklich bedanken. Ich glaube, es ist und war richtig, dass wir ein so wichtiges Thema der Finanzmarktregulierung nicht nur im Ausschuss, sondern auch im Plenum debattieren und im Endeffekt darüber abstimmen, sodass jeder Kollege die Möglichkeit hat, sich durch die internen Beratungen zu informieren und zu beteiligen. Vielen Dank an alle!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Președintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dezbaterea a fost închisă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votul va avea loc marți, 12 iunie 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Common rules in the field of civil aviation and European Union Aviation Safety Agency (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-065-0000" speaker_id="33984" name="Președintele" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Următorul punct de pe ordinea de zi este dezbaterea privind raportul lui Marian-Jean Marinescu, în numele Comisiei pentru transport și turism, referitor la propunerea de regulament al Parlamentului European și al Consiliului privind normele comune în domeniul aviației civile și de înființare a Agenției Uniunii Europene pentru Siguranța Aviației, precum și de abrogare a Regulamentului (CE) nr. 216/2008 al Parlamentului European și al Consiliului (COM(2015)0613 - C8-0389/2015 - 2015/0277(COD)) (A8-0364/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Domnule președinte, doamna comisar, stimați colegi, discutăm astăzi despre un regulament extrem de important pentru industria aviatică, un regulament care stabilește toate normele de certificare pentru toate categoriile pe care le are în domeniul de aplicare. Cred că rezultatul negocierilor este echilibrat, ține cont atât de pasageri, cât și de toate componentele industriei: transportatori, producători, muncitori, personal, management de trafic, administrație. Se propun reguli pentru asigurarea siguranței aeriene, dar și pentru asigurarea flexibilității necesare în producția de avioane și echipamente, necesară în contextul progresului rapid al tehnologiilor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regulamentul se referă pentru prima dată la toate componentele industriei, simplificând în acest fel activitatea administrației și a beneficiarilor. Se precizează foarte clar competențele AESA și competențele autorităților naționale. Elaborarea specificațiilor de certificare se bazează pe principiul evaluării nivelului de risc. DG MOVE este obligată să updateze toată legislația secundară, datorită acestui principiu, într-o perioadă de cinci ani. Acest principiu va permite, de exemplu, adaptarea normelor la diversele categorii de avioane în funcție de complexitate și utilitate și va permite zborul cross-border al avioanelor de mici dimensiuni. Se introduc în premieră reguli referitoare la securitate și, în special, la securitatea cibernetică. Este inclus, de asemenea, un mecanism european de avertizare pentru survolarea zonelor de conflict. Se asigură libertatea de decizie a beneficiarilor privind autoritatea de certificare și, în același timp, posibilitatea transferului de responsabilitate în cazul în care activitatea unei autorități pune în pericol siguranța pasagerilor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comisia are o responsabilitate viitoare destul de importantă în elaborarea legislației secundare, care acoperă aspecte extrem de importante pentru siguranța pasagerilor și dezvoltarea industriei, accesul rapid la datele de zbor în cazul zborurilor în dificultate, asigurarea controlului de trafic în cazul întreruperilor neprevăzute, integrarea în traficul aerian a aparatelor de zbor fără pilot. Acest ultim punct este extrem de important. Industria dronelor se dezvoltă foarte mult în ultima perioadă. Este nevoie de norme pentru asigurarea nu numai a siguranței zborurilor, dar și a vieții private și a securității. Este evident că, în perioada următoare, numărul mare de drone și numărul de aplicații pentru aceste drone vor crea destul de multe probleme din acest punct de vedere și este nevoie de niște reguli foarte clare în această direcție.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parlamentul așteaptă oricum cu mare interes această legislație secundară. Vreau să mulțumesc raportorilor din umbră, raportorilor grupurilor politice, pentru că am lucrat foarte bine împreună. Mulțumesc și doamnei comisar pentru sprijinul acordat și mulțumesc președinției Estoniei pentru efortul mare pe care l-a făcut pentru a ajunge la acest acord.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-067-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Violeta Bulc" is_mep="False" mode="written" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank you for all the work that you have put into this file and for the continued support of Parliament, especially Mr Marinescu and his colleagues from the Committee on Transport and Tourism (TRAN), for the Commission’s proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parliament has played a major role in these negotiations. Now it is for plenary to confirm the compromise text that has been reached with Council last December. This will contribute to our common strategic objective of achieving a deeper and fairer internal market while fostering innovation, with a strong positive impact on jobs and growth.</p>
      <p sl="en">A safe and competitive European aviation industry needs an effective and balanced legislation such as the one which you will vote on tomorrow. This new regulation is also a centrepiece of the Commission’s 2015 aviation strategy for Europe, ensuring safe, secure and environmentally-friendly aviation for EU citizens. It does so through a better use of resources, the enforcement of risk- and performance-based requirements, and by eliminating unnecessary administrative burdens.</p>
      <p sl="en">In practical terms, we are changing the certification process to be more tuned in for innovation, which means shortening time-to-market and keeping our industry more competitive. This regulation closes the existing gap in the regulatory system and introduces effective, cooperative safety management processes. Importantly, it includes a system of pooling and sharing of resources between the Member States and EASA and establishes better governance for our aviation agency.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allow me to underline other key benefits of the new regulation. It takes into account new technologies and market developments to ensure that they are efficiently integrated into the aviation system as well as subject to effective and proportionate oversights. This is in particular the case for the safe operation of drones, with new provisions regarding registration of drones and drones’ operations. I wish to thank again Parliament, and particularly Mr Marinescu, for the strong support on this important topic. It is worth pointing out that we are going to get, for the first time EU-wide, a regulatory framework for drones.</p>
      <p sl="en">This regulation also takes into account the interdependencies between aviation safety and aviation security. In the future, EASA will play a role in aviation security, including cybersecurity, and contribute upon request with its expertise to the implementation of rules in this area.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another very important point for Parliament was the establishment of an oversight support mechanism. This objective has been achieved. This new mechanism will represent an important instrument for a high and uniform aviation safety in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me finally mention that the Commission has prepared a declaration concerning the Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS), as previously announced during the negotiations. The declaration should be attached to the plenary minutes and transmitted to the Council.</p>
      <p sl="en">With your positive vote tomorrow, the new EASA Regulation could enter into force in the second half of this year. The Commission is ready for this and has already started to prepare the implementation of this new regulation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commission Statement</p>
      <p sl="en">In the view of the Commission, services consisting of the emission of signals by satellites of core constellations of global navigation satellite systems (GNSS), such as the system established under the Galileo programme and other similar systems, are as such not to be considered as air traffic management and air navigation services (ATM/ANS) as defined in Article 3, read in conjunction with the corresponding recital, of new Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on common rules in the field of civil aviation and establishing a European Union Aviation Safety Agency and repealing Regulation (EC) No 216/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council. This view is based, in particular, on the fact that those signals are not primarily or exclusively emitted for the purpose of air navigation, but are used for that purpose only through services that augment those signals, which are expressly covered by the definition of ATM/ANS.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="96754" name="Wim van de Camp" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de PPE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, ik dank de rapporteur en de commissaris voor de inleidende opmerkingen. Maar ik denk dat een speciaal woord van dank vandaag past aan mijn partijgenoot Marian Marinescu. Dit was een heel pittig dossier en hij heeft met de schaduwrapporteurs verschillende moeilijke discussies tot een goed einde gebracht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Veiligheid in de luchtvaart is een van de belangrijkste thema's die het Europees Parlement hier vandaag kan behandelen. Op 17 mei ben ik zelf, samen met collega Marinescu en andere EP-leden, nog op bezoek geweest bij EASA in Keulen. Ik ben onder de indruk van de huidige taakopvatting van het agentschap en meer nog van de taken die het in de toekomst zal krijgen.</p>
      <p sl="en">EASA heeft ook internationaal een hele goede naam. Het gaat immers niet alleen om de EU maar ook om de relaties met de VS, China en Zuid-Amerika inzake luchtvaartveiligheid. Ik denk dat wij als Europees Parlement trots mogen zijn dat wij een dergelijk agentschap hebben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu komt er een taakuitbreiding. Het zal niet alleen meer gaan over vliegtuigen en certificering, maar ook over drones en binnenkort ook over de apparatuur op vliegvelden. Dat zijn allemaal onderwerpen die de luchtvaartveiligheid compleet maken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Interessant wordt natuurlijk de vraag: "Blijft het Verenigd Koninkrijk of niet?". Het VK kan natuurlijk niet alleen doorgaan met luchtvaartveiligheid. We zullen dus moeten zien hoe een en ander zich ontwikkelt. Dank u zeer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="124888" name="Gabriele Preuß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Sie alle fliegen als Mitglieder dieses Hauses wahrscheinlich deutlich häufiger als der EU- Durchschnittsbürger. Haben Sie sich aber schon einmal Gedanken darüber gemacht, wie fit und gesund beziehungsweise ausgeruht Pilot und Crew sind? Wie viele Flugstunden der Pilot vorweisen kann oder ob er die Kosten seiner Ausbildung noch abfliegen muss, egal ob er müde oder krank ist? Dass wir heute entspannter als je zuvor ins Flugzeug steigen, hat auch damit zu tun, dass es nie so sicher war zu fliegen wie heute. Und nirgendwo ist es sicherer als hier bei uns in der EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daher lohnt es sich, ab und zu hinter die Kulissen zu schauen und sich immer wieder klarzumachen, dass das Niveau an Sicherheit und Service, welches wir genießen, keine Selbstverständlichkeit ist. In der Luftfahrt setzt sich mit einiger Verzögerung zunehmend etwas durch, das wir aus anderen Verkehrssektoren wie Schifffahrt und Straßentransport kennen: Profitmacherei auf Kosten der Arbeitnehmer. Das führt langfristig immer zu schlechteren Dienstleistungen, und – davon sind wir überzeugt – das ist nicht gut für die Sicherheit. Denn Sicherheit ist eine schwierige und detailreiche Arbeit, nicht nur im technischen Bereich. Wer im Bereich Flugsicherheit tätig ist, muss seine Aufgaben frei von unternehmerischem Druck ausüben können, muss optimal aus- und fortgebildet werden und selbstverständlich alle wichtigen Informationen erhalten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Um dem besorgniserregenden Trend des Sozialdumpings entgegenzutreten, haben wir den Artikel 76a der neuen EASA-Verordnung durchgesetzt. Die EASA wird nun die Möglichkeit haben, sich windige Geschäftskonstruktionen, in denen keiner mehr nachvollziehen kann, wer eigentlich zuständig ist, unter dem Aspekt der eindeutigen Verantwortlichkeit anzuschauen. Das gleiche gilt für Beschäftigungsmodelle, bei denen Piloten quasi dazu gedrängt werden, permanent zu fliegen und auf Teufel komm raus die Kosten zu senken. Darüber hinaus bin ich davon überzeugt, dass wir die richtigen Weichen für unsere Luftfahrt gestellt haben. Wir brauchen mehr internationale Präsenz der EASA, um die Sicherheit weltweit zu verbessern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es waren wirklich denkwürdige Verhandlungen, die wir geführt haben, und daher möchte ich Herrn Marinescu als Berichterstatter und der Kommission ganz herzlich danken, dass wir so einen ausgewogenen Bericht zur Abstimmung stellen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-0000" speaker_id="117477" name="Mark Demesmaeker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Collega's, we nemen hier niet alleen een beslissing voor de ontwerpers, de producenten en de operatoren van luchtvaartuigen, maar voor alle Europese burgers.</p>
      <p sl="en">De zomervakantie staat voor de deur. Vele vakantiegangers stappen binnenkort weer op het vliegtuig richting hun favoriete reisbestemming en die willen dat op een veilige en comfortabele manier doen. Misschien gaan anderen deze zomer wel over tot de aankoop van hun eerste drone of zorgt een Europese ondernemer voor de volgende innovatie in de sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Steeds meer mensen raken betrokken bij de luchtvaart en de cijfers tonen dat ook. In 2035 zullen 14,4 miljoen passagiersvluchten worden uitgevoerd in Europa. Dat is 50 % meer dan in 2012. Die steile vlucht zien we ook in de dronesector, die de komende twintig jaar 100 000 jobs zal creëren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Een goede zaak voor de economie, de werkgelegenheid en de concurrentiekracht van de Europese Unie. Maar laten we natuurlijk ook de veiligheid van de passagiers en de impact op de mens en het milieu niet uit het oog verliezen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vandaag zetten we alvast een belangrijke stap in de goede richting. We omarmen beloftevolle innovaties, maar zorgen ook voor het noodzakelijke veiligheidskader. Proportionaliteit, minder administratieve rompslomp en realiteitszin staan daarbij centraal. Op die manier faciliteren we innovatieve ideeën en besparen we de recreatieve luchtvaart een hoop kopzorgen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarnaast zorgen we inderdaad ook voor specifieke regels voor drones. Een essentiële stap om deze onbemande toestellen op een veilige manier in ons luchtruim te integreren. Net zoals voor andere toestellen zullen producenten en operatoren in de toekomst aandacht moeten hebben voor veiligheid, privacy en bescherming van persoonsgegevens. Een maatregel die zowel de gebruikers van drones als de mensen op de grond ten goede komt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot vraag ik het Europees Agentschap voor de veiligheid van de luchtvaart om zijn goede werking voort te zetten en zijn nieuwe takenpakket plichtsbewust uit te voeren.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="125022" name="Matthijs van Miltenburg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ALDE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, Europa bereikt weer een nieuwe mijlpaal om vliegen nog veiliger te maken: met nieuwe Europese regels voor het gebruik en de registratie van drones, met nieuwe kansen om de specifieke kennis van luchtvaartinspecteurs overal in Europa in te zetten, en met nieuwe taken voor het Agentschap voor de veiligheid van de luchtvaart (EASA), om in te kunnen grijpen als de veiligheid van de luchtvaart in het geding is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar nieuwe regels, nieuwe kansen en nieuwe taken vragen om samenwerking tussen EASA en verschillende autoriteiten in de Europese lidstaten. Zo ben ik verheugd dat er een Europees systeem komt om Europese luchtvaartmaatschappijen te waarschuwen voor gevaarlijke vliegroutes. Rampen als die met vlucht MH17 kunnen op die manier in de toekomst mogelijk worden voorkomen. Maar dat vergt een goed samenspel tussen nationale inlichtingendiensten, luchtvaartautoriteiten, de Europese Commissie en EASA. Inlichtingendiensten gaan informatie verzamelen en delen over risico's bij het vliegen over conflictgebieden. Gezamenlijke risicoanalyses worden opgesteld, zodat EASA de Europese luchtvaartsector tijdig kan waarschuwen voor gevaar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, dat vraagt om onderling vertrouwen en samenwerking. Dat vergt dat papieren regels worden omgezet in werkbare oplossingen. Ik roep de lidstaten dan ook op om eensgezind en krachtig samen te gaan werken met EASA en de Europese Commissie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Morgen brengen we de nieuwe EASA-verordening in stemming, maar de veiligheid vraagt vandaag en elke komende dag om actie. Want met de veiligheid van passagiers mag niet gesold worden. Nooit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="96868" name="Karima Delli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, merci Madame la Commissaire et merci à notre rapporteur, M. Marinescu. Parfois, ce n’est pas facile de trouver des accords, mais nous y sommes arrivés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je dois vous dire que nous avons en Europe l’un des espaces aériens les plus performants du monde en matière de sécurité et c’est grâce à l’EASA, c’est grâce à l’harmonisation européenne des normes de l’aviation civile, que nous avons aujourd’hui ce ciel unique européen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais l’aérien est un secteur qui est en pleine mutation et qui doit s’adapter. D’un côté, des mutations technologiques, avec l’arrivée en masse des drones. Il est vrai que nous – les Verts – avions demandé un contrôle des drones dès 250 grammes, une immatriculation européenne et un permis de conduire pour tous les utilisateurs. Nous avons eu moins, mais les catégories de drones les plus dangereuses semblent au moins bien encadrées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous resterons quand même très vigilants sur les actes délégués à venir et les retours d’expérience du programme U-space mené par SESAR, pour bien comprendre comment le trafic aérien des drones peut être géré d’une manière qui soit à 100 % sûre et sans nuisance.</p>
      <p sl="en">De l’autre côté, l’aérien vit des mutations sociales. Ce secteur est très exposé aux emplois précaires dans des modèles comme les low-cost ou certaines compagnies régulières. Nous dénonçons depuis longtemps certaines pratiques autorisées en Europe, comme les contrats zéro heure, le «pay-to-fly» ou les statuts de faux indépendants. La législation, enfin, fait le lien entre sécurité et conditions sociales des travailleurs de l’aérien pour que plus jamais un drame comme celui de la Germanwings ne puisse arriver.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, nous vivons aussi une accélération du trafic: + 50 % d’ici 2030, x 3 d’ici 2050, les prévisions montrent une accélération du secteur complètement incompatible avec les accords sur le climat et c’est là où l’EASA a une plus-value, puisqu’elle a des compétences environnementales, pour que des progrès soient faits en matière d’allègement des matériaux, d’utilisation d’hydrocarbures et d’électrification des sols. C’est pourquoi nous voterons demain en faveur de votre rapport, M. Marinescu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-0000" speaker_id="124736" name="Merja Kyllönen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr Chairman, dear colleagues, my greatest thanks to my dear colleague, Marian-Jean Marinescu. It was tough, but there was very good cooperation with all of us shadow rapporteurs. I like that we find stricter social, physical and psychological health standards for the personnel and that we have also included environmental and climate protection in the annexes to this regulation, as are social standards. Ground handling could be stricter, but it’s a compromise. Regarding higher civil risk with drone operations, it is very important that we use this time for this area. I’m totally happy to support this work which we are doing together.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-0000" speaker_id="124842" name="Daniela Aiuto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, innanzitutto volevo ringraziare l'onorevole Marinescu per l'impegno profuso per portare avanti questo impegnativo dossier.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi accogliamo con favore molti aspetti positivi contenuti all'interno del testo, relativi alle procedure di certificazione dei requisiti di aeronavigabilità, delle condizioni di volo, della sicurezza, delle componenti, dei requisiti ambientali e degli aeroporti. Assolutamente importante è anche la previsione di licenze per i piloti e i controllori del traffico aereo e di attestati per gli equipaggi di cabina con relativa idoneità sanitaria.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per la prima volta avremo un quadro regolatorio europeo per le norme sui droni, assolutamente necessario e impellente. Sicuramente ci sono un po' di perplessità, perché ci sarà un impegno notevole per rendere performante un ente unico che accentra poteri e competenze. Quindi su questo noi monitoreremo, così come monitoreremo con attenzione anche sul rilascio dei numerosi atti implementativi, che in un settore così delicato come quello della sicurezza aerea potranno fare la differenza in positivo o in negativo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, χιλιάδες πτήσεις πραγματοποιούνται καθημερινά στον ουρανό των κρατών μελών της Ενώσεως με εκατομμύρια επιβάτες. Η σημασία των πτήσεων αυτών, είτε επιβατικών είτε εμπορικών, για τις οικονομίες των χωρών είναι τεράστια και φυσικά αναντικατάστατη. Πρέπει όμως να διασφαλίσουμε ότι όλες αυτές οι διαδρομές θα γίνονται με το μέγιστο δυνατό επίπεδο ασφαλείας τόσο για τους επιβάτες όσο και για τα πληρώματα των αεροσκαφών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πρέπει να τονίσω πως είμαι ξεκάθαρα υπέρ του συντονισμού των διαφόρων υπηρεσιών πολιτικής αεροπορίας των κρατών, καθώς ο συντονισμός αυτός μπορεί να σώσει ζωές. Συνεπώς βλέπω θετικά την ίδρυση ενός πανευρωπαϊκού οργανισμού που θα συντονίζει τους αντίστοιχους εθνικούς. Όμως αυτός θα πρέπει να έχει καθαρά συντονιστικό ρόλο και σε καμία περίπτωση δεν θα πρέπει να είναι αρμόδιος για τον ίδιο τον έλεγχο των εναέριων χώρων, καθώς αυτοί αποτελούν τμήμα της επικράτειας του κάθε κράτους μέλους και η παραχώρηση του ελέγχου συνιστά ξεκάθαρη παραχώρηση εθνικής κυριαρχίας. Ειδικά δε σε περιπτώσεις όπως η Ελλάδα, όπου η Τουρκία αμφισβητεί την κυριαρχία της χώρας μου, η παραχώρηση του ελέγχου θα οδηγούσε μαθηματικά σε απώλεια εθνικής επικράτειας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Τέλος, σχετικά με τα μη επανδρωμένα αεροσκάφη: αν και είναι γεγονός πως πρέπει να δημιουργηθεί ένα ρυθμιστικό πλαίσιο, εντούτοις το προτεινόμενο πλαίσιο είναι εκτός πραγματικότητας, γιατί τα drones δεν είναι μόνο παιχνίδια και εργαλεία, αλλά και πολεμικές μηχανές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="96791" name="Elżbieta Katarzyna Łukacijewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Jak pokazują prognozy, w przeciągu najbliższych 20 lat ruch powietrzny zwiększy się o 50 procent w stosunku do dzisiejszego poziomu. Dlatego oczywiście nadrzędnym celem staje się bezpieczeństwo pasażerów, którego nie można zwiększyć bez inwestycji w innowacje i nowe technologie. Nie da się osiągnąć długotrwałego postępu, nie biorąc pod uwagę megatrendów w branży rozwoju technologii dronów, współpracy z sektorem kosmicznym czy satelitarnymi systemami nawigacji. Kluczowe jest zapewnienie firmom właściwych warunków do prowadzenia dalszych badań w zakresie innowacji oraz udoskonalenia istniejących już technologii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlatego z zadowoleniem przyjmuję zapisy dotyczące współpracy z przemysłem w tej dziedzinie. Ważne jest, że w sprawozdaniu znalazły się przepisy udoskonalające przeloty nad strefami konfliktów zbrojnych oraz że ustanowiono ramy prawne w odniesieniu do bezpiecznego korzystania z dronów. Jasne przepisy pozwolą firmom zaangażowanym w produkcję dronów spokojnie przygotowywać strategie i plany rozwoju na najbliższe lata, a, jak wskazują dane, tylko w tym sektorze będzie zatrudnionych w przyszłości około 100 tysięcy osób.</p>
      <p sl="en">Propozycje, o której dzisiaj mówimy, przewidują lepsze wykorzystanie dostępnych zasobów, lepszą certyfikację, a także, co bardzo ważne, zwiększenie konkurencyjności europejskiego sektora lotniczego. Z pewnością niełatwo było pogodzić wszystkie oczekiwania, a zwłaszcza zwiększenie bezpieczeństwa pasażerów z ochroną danych osobowych. Dlatego tym bardziej gratuluję posłowi sprawozdawcy, a także wszystkim osobom, które prowadziły to dossier i przyczyniły się do uzyskania jak najlepszych propozycji i rozwiązań.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="124803" name="Isabella De Monte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signora Commissario, finalmente dopo due anni di negoziati abbiamo l'opportunità di votare questo importante regolamento. La sicurezza nel campo dell’aviazione è di vitale importanza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mantenere sempre aggiornata la lista nera delle compagnie aeree però non basta. Evitare che le stesse possano volare nei cieli europei grazie al wet lease è una vera vittoria. Anche le condizioni dei piloti e dei membri dell'equipaggio di alcune compagnie low cost possono influire sulla sicurezza del volo e per questo motivo ritengo importante che tali aspetti vengano presi in considerazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infine, mi compiaccio del nuovo ruolo dell'agenzia e della possibilità della stessa di aprire uffici regionali in paesi terzi per fornire sostegno alle attività di certificazione e per lavorare su aspetti tecnici. Questo nuovo ruolo internazionale aiuterà a promuovere l'industria europea dell'aviazione e gli altri standard europei in materia di sicurezza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-0000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wenn wir morgen darüber abstimmen – und wir sollten alle dafür sein –, dann haben wir eine gute neue Regelung für die Sicherheit in Europas Luftraum. Die EASA hat vorher schon sehr gute Arbeit geleistet und hat jetzt eben wirklich eine aktualisierte Aufgabe bekommen, die auch noch teilweise erweitert ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte nur mal fünf Punkte benennen. Das eine ist – das ist nur eine Kleinigkeit, die war mir aber wichtig –, dass man durchaus eben auch im Annex Ausnahmen hat: bei Einsitzern bis 300 Kilogramm, bei Zweisitzern bis 450 Kilogramm, damit eben teilweise auch die bürokratische Belastung geringer ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wichtig ist aber vor allen Dingen: Wir haben eine Regulierung für Drohnen – das ist ganz entscheidend. Es gibt immer mehr unbemannte Flugobjekte, die müssen jetzt registriert sein. Das muss also national ausgetauscht sein, es muss digital verfügbar sein – sehr, sehr wichtig. Wir versuchen, die bürokratischen Belastungen zu reduzieren, das ist eine kleine Sache.</p>
      <p sl="en">Weiter ist aber ganz wichtig, dass die militärischen Überflugzonen geregelt sind. Und mir als Deutscher ganz wichtig nach dem Absturz der Germanwings-Maschine: Es kann nicht sein, dass ein Pilot lebensmüde ist und andere Leute in den Tod reißt. Auch dafür haben wir jetzt Dinge vorgesehen, die in Zukunft etwas in dieser Richtung verhindern können. Und darum freue ich mich auf die Abstimmung morgen, die positiv sein wird.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, a complexidade e o alcance do Regulamento não alteram, antes prosseguem os objetivos de sempre: o estabelecimento de um maior grau de harmonização das regras comuns do domínio da aviação ao nível da UE, o aprofundamento do céu único europeu, o agravamento da liberalização do sector do transporte e navegação aérea, com consequentes fenómenos de concentração.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma liberalização que, em nome da rentabilidade financeira, tem posto em causa direitos laborais, promovendo a precarização generalizada das relações laborais no sector, mas que tem aberto portas também para a degradação da qualidade dos serviços e até dos níveis de segurança de operação e manutenção.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nessa estratégia, integra-se a Agência Europeia de Segurança na Aviação, um símbolo do assalto à soberania estratégica dos povos, com a transferência de competências dos Estados para a União Europeia. O que se deve aprofundar e desenvolver é a cooperação entre Estados através das suas autoridades nacionais, salvaguardando a soberania de cada país e o respeito pelos direitos dos trabalhadores e dos utentes de serviços.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="23693" name="Alojz Peterle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spoštovana gospa komisarka, dragi kolegi, jaz pozdravljam rezultat trialoga z velikim veseljem tudi v imenu mojih kolegov pilotov, ki so veseli, da je zakonodaja bila – oziroma, da je evropska zveza pozorna na njihove potrebe, na razvoj.</p>
      <p sl="en">V tem smislu je prišlo do pomembne prilagoditve in dvig maksimalne vzletne mase za ultralahka letala pomeni resnično korak naprej in to pomeni tudi nove obete za razvoj tega zelo hitro razvijajočega se sektorja evropskega letalstva, tudi kar zadeva inovacije.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-0000" speaker_id="96784" name="Janusz Zemke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Dzisiejsza dyskusja dotyczy przepisów, które mają nam zapewnić bezpieczeństwo za 15 lat. Rozmawiamy tu zatem o wyzwaniach, jakie wystąpią w przyszłości. Najważniejsze wyzwanie, przed którym staniemy, to duży przyrost ruchu lotniczego. Przewiduje się, że za 15 lat w skali roku będziemy mieli aż 15 milionów lotów. To będzie oznaczało ogrom nowych problemów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jednak w tym rozporządzeniu porusza się też dwie inne kwestie, które budzą moje zastrzeżenia, bo wydaje mi się, że propozycje są tu zbyt ogólnikowe. Pierwszy problem to narastające ryzyko kolizji samolotów z bezzałogowymi statkami powietrznymi. Podkreślę jeszcze raz: propozycje w tej materii są chyba jednak zbyt ogólnikowe. Drugi problem, o którym jest jeszcze mniej w tym akcie, to konieczność zwiększenia odporności na możliwość ataków cybernetycznych. Te ataki będą i trzeba się na to przygotować.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="28331" name="Jaromír Kohlíček" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, civilní letecký provoz zemí Evropské unie a USA tvoří v současné době více než 60 % světového civilního letectví. Agentura EASA poměrně spolehlivě plní úkoly, kvůli kterým byla vytvořena. Je logické, že v průběhu let se v leteckém průmyslu objevily nové jevy a že v době, kdy se dynamicky rozvíjí letecká doprava, je nezbytné, aby na stav reagovaly i nové úkoly agentury.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tato novelizace zahrnuje např. novou kapitolu týkající se řízení bezpečnosti letectví. Pro rozvoj lehkých letadel, tedy ultralightů a LSA, je pozitivním momentem kompromis dosažený u jejich parametrů. Přesto věřím, že dříve nebo později přejdeme k jiným definicím užitečného zatížení. Již řadu let probíhají bouřlivé diskuse na téma definice pro činnosti leteckých modelářů na jedné straně a na straně druhé regulace v oboru bezpilotních letadel, takzvaných dronů.</p>
      <p sl="en">Současný tvar nařízení považuji za dobrý kompromis. Jako u každého kompromisu ovšem samozřejmě vidím možnosti zlepšení. Přesto budu hlasovat pro jeho přijetí v předkládané formě bez zásadních změn.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="26837" name="Λευτέρης Χριστοφόρου" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, χαιρετίζουμε την ίδρυση Οργανισμού Αεροπορικής Ασφάλειας της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και στηρίζουμε τη δέσμη μέτρων για ισχυροποίηση της ασφάλειας των αεροπορικών μεταφορών. Ως προς τούτο οφείλουμε εύφημη μνεία εις τον αγαπητό συνάδελφο Marian-Jean Marinescu, ο οποίος πραγματικά δημιούργησε αυτό το πολύ ορθό και ισχυρό πλαίσιο. Όπως ορθά τόνισε και εκείνος, θέλουμε ισχυροποιημένη αεροπορική ασφάλεια των αεροπορικών μεταφορών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Μέσα σε αυτό το πνεύμα όμως οφείλω να τονίσω ότι υπάρχει μία χώρα, η Τουρκία, η οποία συνεχίζει να παραβιάζει τους διεθνείς κανόνες αεροπλοΐας σε βαθμό που πραγματικά δημιουργεί προβλήματα και για την ασφάλεια. Οφείλω να επισημάνω στο Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο αλλά και στην Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή ότι η Τουρκία με πολιτικά και πολεμικά αεροσκάφη παραβιάζει διαρκώς τον εναέριο χώρο και το FIR της Κυπριακής Δημοκρατίας. Οφείλω να τονίσω στον υπερθετικό βαθμό ότι τουρκικές αεροπορικές εταιρείες συνεχίζουν να βρίσκονται παράνομα στο παράνομο αεροδρόμιο της Τύμπου, να το χρησιμοποιούν και να μην εφαρμόζουν κανέναν κανόνα αεροπλοΐας με ό, τι αυτό συνεπάγεται για την ασφάλεια.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πέραν τούτου πρέπει να υπογραμμιστεί ότι η Τουρκία παραβιάζει συλλήβδην όλους αυτούς τους κανόνες που εμείς θέλουμε να θωρακίσουμε. Κυρία Επίτροπε, γνωρίζετε πολύ καλά ότι η Τουρκία δεν εφάρμοσε και δεν υλοποίησε το Πρωτόκολλο της Άγκυρας και αυτή τη στιγμή απαγορεύει σε ευρωπαϊκά αεροσκάφη, αεροσκάφη της Κυπριακής Δημοκρατίας, να διέρχονται από τον εναέριο χώρο της Τουρκίας, καθώς και πλοία με κυπριακή σημαία, με ευρωπαϊκή σημαία, να προσαράζουν στα τουρκικά λιμάνια. Αυτό είναι απαράδεκτο και αναμένουμε από εσάς μια ξεκάθαρη απάντηση. Μέσα σε αυτά τα πλαίσια τι θα κάνει η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή για να επιλυθεί αυτό το ζήτημα και να δοθούν πραγματικές απαντήσεις όσον αφορά την Τουρκία;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamnă comisar, stimați colegi, eu cred că am avut o propunere necesară din partea Comisiei, propunerea unui nou regulament. Vreau să-l felicit și eu pe raportor și pe raportori și pe toți colegii din TRAN care și-au adus contribuția. Cred că se înscrie această propunere de regulament și acest raport pe care mâine îl vom vota - sunt sigură că va trece la vot - în strategia de îmbunătățire a competitivității sectorului aviației al Uniunii Europene.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am citit cu atenție propunerea Comisiei și raportul. S-a ținut cont de toate părțile interesate. Comisia a prezentat un rezultat al consultării. Cred că s-au atins toate subiectele. Consider că este necesar să avem un sistem de certificare și de supraveghere unic în Uniunea Europeană.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este foarte important, doamna comisar, ce veți face, agenția vă sprijină în monitorizarea aplicării acestui regulament în statele membre și cred că aici este cheia succesului acestui regulament. De asemenea, așa cum spunea și domnul Marinescu, raportorul, este foarte important cu ce veniți, cu legislația ulterioară, pentru că regulamentul trebuie să răspundă la două lucruri extrem de importante: siguranța pasagerilor și protecția mediului.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-0000" speaker_id="125016" name="Claudia Schmidt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Vor zehn Jahren haben wir nicht gewusst, was ein Smartphone alles kann. Wir haben nicht gewusst, dass die Flüchtlinge sich auf Flüchtlingsrouten damit verständigen. Wir haben nicht geahnt, dass sechs nordafrikanische Diktaturen wegen dieses Smartphones fallen, und wir haben nicht gewusst, dass wir ein Drittel unserer Wachzeit mit diesem Telefon verbringen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Warum sage ich das? Wir beschließen morgen eine Gesetzgebung für Drohnen. Drohnen werden ein game changer sein. Wir wissen nicht, wie sich die Geschichte mit den Drohnen entwickeln wird, aber wir haben einen mutigen Schritt getan – und das sage ich ganz bewusst, wo ich doch sonst öfter mal etwas kritisiere, was im legislativen Bereich ist: Wir beschließen morgen eine einheitliche europäische Zulassung für die Drohnen, und wir beschließen auch, dass die Drohnenführer eine einheitliche europäische Ausbildung haben. Das ist wunderbar. Und wir geben den Mitgliedstaaten die Möglichkeit, subsidiär zu agieren – die entscheiden nämlich, wann, wieso, wo diese Drohnen dann auch fliegen dürfen und wer das Ganze kontrolliert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das ist eine Vorgangsweise, die wirklich wichtig ist für alle Europäer und auch für das Ansehen Europas in der ganzen Welt. Ich begrüße das außerordentlich und freue mich – denn so muss Europa!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Przedmiotem mojego zainteresowania czy też troski jest bezpieczeństwo. Bezpieczeństwo nie tylko tych, którzy latają, ale także tych, którzy na ziemi mogą być przedmiotem ataków ze strony właśnie pojazdów latających.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przypomnę, że cztery lata temu, będąc zwolennikiem tworzenia centralnego rejestru pasażerów, byłem, z pewną grupą oczywiście, w mniejszości. Ataki terrorystyczne zmieniły te proporcje. Trzy lata temu udało mi się przekonać Podkomisję Bezpieczeństwa i Obrony, aby objęła swoimi kompetencjami także systemy satelitarne Galileo i Copernicus. Także wówczas postulowałem zmianę kryteriów wagowych, jeżeli chodzi o drony.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dziś mogę powiedzieć z dużą satysfakcją, że wiele tych elementów, które były przedmiotem naszej troski, zostało w sprawozdaniu kolegi Marinescu uwzględnionych, ale chcę dopowiedzieć – jesteśmy 5 lat spóźnieni, jeżeli chodzi o regulacje europejskie. Musimy zwracać uwagę na konieczność rozwijania systemów identyfikacji obiektów latających, zwłaszcza tych małych, ale także rozwijać możliwości ich neutralizacji. To dziś jest podstawowe wyzwanie instytucji europejskich.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Violeta Bulc" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank honourable Members for this very positive and engaging debate. I have taken good note of your comments. I believe that we have a common understanding in considering this compromise as the right answer to the need to maintain a high level of civil aviation safety under the current challenges of growing traffic, while ensuring the competitiveness of European aviation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Before I conclude, allow me to make some comments on the topics that you raised. First, on social conditions, this topic has not been forgotten during negotiations. There are indeed new provisions in the regulation to make sure that interdependencies between social and safety aspects are adequately addressed by EASA. Let me also inform you that the Commission will continue to work on this during the year. In the second part of the year, we intend to issue reports on social issues in the aviation sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the question of oversight, let me say that the proposal includes a balanced and effective oversight support mechanism. This mechanism enhances the cooperative nature of the oversight system in Europe. It is driven by a clear timeline and planning of the activities and reserves the possibility to take further measures to ensure safety if necessary.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will make another comment on safety itself. Let me stress again that in Europe we have one of the highest – if not the highest – level of aviation safety, and it continues to improve year after year. This is clear evidence that the single European aviation market functions well and thus in no way compromises safety. On the contrary.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will make one quick comment on drones. EASA will ensure the safe coexistence of commercial aviation and drone activity for professional or recreational use. This implies, among others, an adequate design and use of our air space. The agency is already working on those issues, including in urban areas through the so—called urban aviation space or ‘U-Space’ as we normally call it. I have to say that this is a very important EU innovation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Before concluding, allow me to draw your attention to another crucial piece of legislation for the future of European aviation on which the European Parliament will be called upon to play a major role in the coming months, namely our proposal of safeguarding competition in air aviation, better known as the revision of Regulation 868. It is a priority to equip Europe with an efficient and credible instrument for the benefit of our industry, passengers and regions. Please bear in mind that the Council, under the Bulgarian Presidency, reached a general approach on this topic. I know that discussions with the Council will not be easy but, thanks to your support, I am confident that we will succeed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Domnule președinte, repet mulțumirile mele adresate colegilor pentru această colaborare foarte, foarte bună, doamnei președintă, pentru că a stat în permanență cu noi la negocieri. Doamnă comisar, trebuie să îmi exprim regretul privind declarația referitoare la Galileo - nu era necesară, după părerea mea, pentru că rezolvasem subiectul în textul regulamentului. Sper ca această declarație să nu pună în umbră performanțele sistemului Galileo, care este un sistem extrem de important.</p>
      <p sl="en">Repet rugămintea mea: aveți o responsabilitate foarte mare în ceea ce privește viitorul acestui regulament prin legislația secundară. Sunt foarte multe lucruri pe care puteți să le rezolvați prin această legislație, lucruri care sunt așteptate de industrie și sunt așteptate - unele dintre ele - foarte mult de pasageri, pentru că, până la urmă, pasagerul este cel mai important în această industrie și trebuie să avem foarte mare grijă de el.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner, tomorrow we shall vote on EASA. It is a very important step forward, but you know very well that it is not enough. We also need the Single European Sky. We need a new regulation; we need to unblock the negotiations for SES II+. For sure, Ms Karima Delli will be very happy, because the Single European Sky will bring a decrease in emissions without any effort and without any cost, only political, and this is not a big cost. I know that you can do it. It is in your power to discuss this with the Ministers and to convince them to start negotiations with Parliament on SES II+.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί αύριο,Τρίτη 12 Ιουνίου 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. CO2 emissions from and fuel consumption of new heavy-duty vehicles (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-095-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Το επόμενο σημείο στην ημερήσια διάταξη είναι η έκθεση του κυρίου Damiano Zoffoli, εξ ονόματος της Επιτροπής Περιβάλλοντος, Δημόσιας Υγείας και Ασφάλειας των Τροφίμων, σχετικά με τις εκπομπές CO2 και την κατανάλωση καυσίμου από τα νέα βαρέα οχήματα (COM(2017)0279 - C8-0168/2017 - 2017/0111(COD)) (A8-0010/2018)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="131051" name="Damiano Zoffoli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la proposta di regolamento in esame colma una grave lacuna: la mancanza, ad oggi, di un sistema di monitoraggio, comunicazione e verifica dei dati sulle emissioni di anidride carbonica e dei consumi di carburante dei mezzi pesanti immatricolati e immessi sul mercato dell'Unione europea. Manca una banca dati comune contenente tutti i dati di monitoraggio degli Stati membri. Questi dati, ad ora, non erano né certificati, né monitorati, né comunicati in maniera oggettiva e comparabile, come avviene invece per automobili e furgoni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa mancanza di informazioni ha determinato innanzitutto una ridotta concorrenza fra i costruttori europei di veicoli pesanti, con scarsi stimoli all'innovazione e all'implementazione di tecnologie efficienti dal punto di vista energetico. Ha determinato inoltre l'impossibilità degli operatori di trasporto, che sono principalmente piccole e medie imprese, oltre 500 000, di scegliere i veicoli più efficienti in termini di consumo di carburante e di risparmiare quindi sui costi del carburante stesso, costi che rappresentano un terzo dei costi di esercizio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Inoltre, questa mancanza di informazione ha rappresentato un freno all'azione a livello nazionale di Unione europea in materia di riduzione delle emissioni dei veicoli pesanti, tenendo conto che il 25 % delle emissioni di CO2 del settore dei trasporti su strada proviene da camion, autobus e pullman, responsabili del 5 % delle emissioni totali. Una percentuale peraltro destinata ad aumentare, in assenza di interventi, fino si stima al 10 %, quindi raddoppia addirittura al 2030.</p>
      <p sl="en">Grazie a questo regolamento, nell'arco di due anni, sul sito dell'Agenzia europea dell'Ambiente saranno disponibili i dati sulle emissioni di anidride carbonica e sui consumi di tutte le categorie di mezzi pesanti di nuova produzione. La proposta della Commissione europea era già un buon punto di partenza e il lavoro di confronto con i colleghi della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare e con la Presidenza bulgara del Consiglio e la stessa Commissione ci ha permesso di raggiungere un compromesso ancora più ambizioso.</p>
      <p sl="en">In particolare, abbiamo migliorato la quantità e la qualità delle informazioni che saranno rese pubbliche, aumentando la trasparenza, per esempio per quel che riguarda le prestazioni dei motori. Le uniche eccezioni riguarderanno i casi giustificati dalla necessità di proteggere dati privati sensibili e assicurare una leale concorrenza fra i costruttori. Abbiamo poi inserito con le verifiche obbligatorie, la previsione delle relative sanzioni amministrative, previsione che era assente nella proposta dalla Commissione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un altro dei punti qualificanti su cui abbiamo insistito come Parlamento riguarda l'inserimento del risultato dei test su strada nella pubblicazione annuale dei dati per comparare i dati Vector misurati in laboratorio con le emissioni in condizioni reali di guida. Ora si può procedere a fissare standard obbligatori sulle emissioni di CO2, che già esistono per le auto e furgoni, anche per tutti i mezzi pesanti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mi auguro che questo avvenga in tempi non troppo lunghi, sulla base della proposta di regolamento già licenziata dalla Commissione. Grazie a questo regolamento, avremo nelle nostre città aria più pulita e i nostri sindaci avranno a disposizione autobus verdi per i trasporti scolastici.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europa è movimento. L'Europa è in movimento verso un'economia più competitiva e a basse emissioni di anidride carbonica rispetto alla situazione attuale che vede il settore dei trasporti dipendere ancora per il 94 % dal petrolio. Oggi facciamo un altro passo in avanti nella direzione di una nuova alleanza fra industria e ambiente, un'alleanza capace di creare nuova e buona occupazione. Facciamo un passo in avanti verso un modello di sviluppo più intelligente e rispettoso della salute e della qualità della vita delle persone.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Violeta Bulc" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, I am glad we are meeting today to finalise the adoption of the Regulation on monitoring and reporting of CO2 emissions from heavy-duty vehicles. This is the first piece of legislation on CO2 emissions from lorries, buses and coaches. A swift agreement on this Regulation has been possible, thanks to the constructive efforts and spirit of compromise of the negotiators from both institutions. The agreement strikes a good balance between the need for transparency and the need to protect commercially-sensitive data, ensuring a robust and reliable monitoring and reporting system.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank the rapporteur, Mr Zoffoli, and his team and congratulate them on the quick result. This regulation is a crucial instrument to close the current knowledge gap on the CO2 emissions and fuel consumption from heavy-duty vehicles put on the European Union market. The information made available with the publication of the reported data will be especially important for transport operators. In addition, the regulation paves the way for the CO2 emissions standards for lorries proposed by the Commission last month, which will need to rely on the data reported for its compliance processes. The support and steering of the rapporteur, Mr Zoffoli, as well as the active engagement of all shadow rapporteurs really paved the way to this good result.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament has strongly contributed to the final shape of the legal text. I would like to offer you two major examples: the introduction of administrative fines if manufacturers do not report the data or if the data reported deviates from their type-approval values, and the extension of the monitoring system to the results of future on-road verification tests. The Commission invites you to support this motion and continue the work with a swift negotiation of the CO2 emissions standards for lorries already on the table at both the European Parliament and the Council.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-0000" speaker_id="1927" name="Peter Liese" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ganz herzlichen Dank an Herrn Zoffoli und alle anderen, die mitgeholfen haben, zu diesem Ergebnis zu kommen! Für unsere Fraktion war das Christofer Fjellner, der heute leider entschuldigt ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, jetzt sind wir uns einig. Das war bei der Abstimmung im Ausschuss und auch in der ersten Lesung im Plenum nicht der Fall. Die EVP-Fraktion war unzufrieden, weil die Regelungen den Schutz des geistigen Eigentums nicht ausreichend berücksichtigten. Wir hatten nach dem Mandat des Umweltausschusses die Sorge, dass die Daten dann doch in die Hände von anderen Herstellern kommen und diese anderen Hersteller außerhalb Europas, zum Beispiel in China, daraus Vorteile ziehen. Das kann nicht der Sinn von europäischer Gesetzgebung sein, dass wir Konkurrenz in China und anderswo unterstützen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zum Glück ist das dann im Trilog durch den Rat geändert worden, und deswegen können wir zustimmen. Das Ziel ist wichtig. Um das Pariser Klimaschutzabkommen umzusetzen, müssen wir alle Potenziale nutzen. Die gibt es nicht nur bei Pkw und leichten Nutzfahrzeugen, sondern auch bei schweren Nutzfahrzeugen. Wir werden zum Beispiel in der Debatte um die Gesetzgebung – konkret beim Bericht Dalli und den anderen Berichten – dann sehen, dass das 40 %-Ziel schon durchaus ambitioniert ist, wenn es an die Umsetzung geht. Deswegen müssen wir da genau überlegen und schauen, wie wir dann zum Ziel kommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Für uns ist es in all diesen Fragen wichtig, dass man nicht pauschal reduziert, sondern auch mal schaut, was transportiert wird. Miriam Dalli hat ihren Berichtsentwurf für die leichten Nutzfahrzeuge und für Pkw schon vorgelegt. Da ist völlig unabhängig von der Frage, wie groß ein Auto ist und was damit transportiert wird, ein gleiches Kriterium angesetzt; das Gewichtskriterium wird ersatzlos gestrichen. Es kann aber nicht sein, dass man, wenn man eine Familie mit sechs Personen transportiert, die gleichen Reduktionsziele hat, wie wenn man nur einen Zweisitzer fährt. Da muss man nochmal nachschärfen, damit wir uns in diesem Verfahren ein bisschen früher einig sind und nicht erst nach den Verhandlungen mit dem Rat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-0000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel Schaldemose" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">for S&amp;D-Gruppen. – Hr. formand! Tusind tak til ordfører Zoffoli for en fremragende betænkning og et rigtigt godt resultat. Hvorfor er dette så et godt resultat? Jo, jeg tror, at de fleste af os har prøvet at køre en tur på motorvejene i EU, og der ser vi den ene lastbil efter den anden køre på vejene. Der er simpelthen så mange lastbiler, og det er sådan set godt for vores handel, men det er ikke særligt godt for klimaet, hvis vores lastbiler og andre tunge køretøjer bliver ved med at udlede så meget CO2, som de gøre. Cirka en fjerdedel af al den CO2, der kommer fra transportsektoren, kommer fra lastbiler og andre tunge køretøjer. Det har vi brug for at få gjort noget ved.</p>
      <p sl="en">Den lovgivning, vi nu skal til at stemme om, er lige præcis et skridt i den rigtige retning. Det er den første lovgivning, som kommer til at medvirke til, at vi overvåger og får afrapporteret lastbilers og andre tunge køretøjers CO2-udledning. Det er helt afgørende for, at vi kan få at se, hvordan det ser ud, og få skabt en konkurrencesituation på EU’s indre marked. Vi har brug for, at dem, der producerer lastbilerne, sørger for, at de bliver mere miljøvenlige, og en af de måder, vi kan gøre det på, er ved at sikre, at vi ved, hvor meget de udleder, og hvor meget brændstof de bruger. Vi mener i den socialdemokratiske gruppe ikke, at det er nok, men at vi skal videre endnu. Men denne lovgivning er trods alt et skridt i den rigtige retning, så vi hilser det varmt velkomment, at vi nu får en lovgivning, som gør, at vi kan gøre det her. Det er også læren fra dieselgate: Vi ved, at der er brug for mere gennemsigtighed i disse data. Hvis vi har den gennemsigtighed i dataene, så ved vi også, at vi kan lægge pres på for at få skabt en udvikling, så vi kan få nogen renere og bedre køretøjer.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi er også rigtig glade for, at det er lykkedes at få givet EU-Kommissionen redskaber, så de kan udskrive bøder, hvis producenterne ikke får givet de informationer, de skal give. Igen fordi vi ved, det er så vigtigt - denne gennemsigtighed i vores data er et afgørende redskab til at sikre, at vi får en mere klimavenlig transportsektor. Til sidst er det også vigtigt at sige tak for, at vi nu også får mulighed for at gennemføre test på vejene. Vi ved, at det ikke er nok at teste vores tunge køretøjer i laboratorierne. De skal også testes ude på vejene, så vi ved, om de overholder de regler, vi får. Så tusind tak til Zoffoli for et rigtigt godt resultat, og dette er et skridt i den rigtige retning for at gøre EU mere miljøvenlig og for at efterleve Parisaftalens målsætninger.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="124874" name="Bolesław G. Piecha" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Pani Komisarz! Na wstępie chciałbym podziękować posłowi sprawozdawcy za dobrze i solidnie wykonaną pracę. Wiemy z danych z 2014 r., że emisja gazów cieplarnianych z ciężkich pojazdów drogowych to 5% całkowitej emisji gazów cieplarnianych w Unii Europejskiej, aż 20% emisji gazów cieplarnianych całego transportu (morskiego, lotniczego i oczywiście drogowego) i 25%, czyli jedna czwarta, emisji CO2 z transportu drogowego.</p>
      <p sl="en">Grupa ECR uważa, że należy ustanowić odpowiedni system certyfikacji i monitoringu oraz wprowadzić odpowiednio wysokie standardy dotyczące ciężkich pojazdów drogowych. Istotnym jest, aby rozporządzenie wyszczególniało różne punkty, które zobowiązują producentów do monitorowania i konsekwentnego raportowania określonych informacji, tzw. parametrów monitorujących (przypomnę, że w ponad 70 obszarach te dane nie są do dzisiaj zharmonizowane). Musimy wziąć pod uwagę bardzo szczegółowe parametry techniczne, dotyczące skrzyni biegów, mocy silnika czy wreszcie zużycia paliwa. Takie szczegółowe podejście jest konieczne do ścisłej współpracy z różnymi organizacjami międzynarodowymi, aby efektywnie przyczynić się do monitorowania i raportowania emisji CO2 przez ciężkie pojazdy drogowe, a następnie móc wyciągać odpowiednie wnioski i konsekwencje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Grupa ECR uważa, że zaproponowane rozporządzenie bardzo ściśle wiąże się z regułami przede wszystkim przejrzystości, lecz także dostępu do informacji. Przypomnę, że naszym zdaniem informacje powinny być jawne i – nie ukrywam – również publiczne. Bardzo zależy nam na utrzymaniu kompromisu, który brałby pod uwagę dobrze znane nam obawy dotyczące z jednej strony ochrony środowiska, a z drugiej strony własności intelektualnej i międzynarodowych aspektów konkurencyjności. Ostatecznie ECR uważa, że zaproponowany kształt rozporządzenia jest satysfakcjonujący.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="114268" name="Nils Torvalds" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för ALDE-gruppen. – Herr talman! Ett stort tack till föredraganden Zoffoli för ett gott arbete med den här frågan. Det har funnits många underligheter i europeisk bilpolitik. Man mäter inte de verkliga avgaserna eller tillåter att man fifflar lite med utrustningen. Till raden av underligheter hör den fråga vi nu talar om: för lastbilar, tung transport, har det inte funnits regler överhuvudtaget.</p>
      <p sl="en">När den här diskussionen började utgick man ifrån att parlamentets krav på en mer miljövänlig politik egentligen bara var ett sätt att förhindra bilindustrins framfart. Så småningom har bilindustrin lärt sig – det tog visserligen alldeles onödigt lång tid – att man genom att motsätta sig en reglering av de olika bilsektorerna egentligen försatte sig i en mycket besvärlig situation, det vill säga man blev teknologiskt på efterkälken och överlämnade en stor del av initiativet åt konkurrenter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu håller vi som bäst på med slutfasen av vårt arbete att åstadkomma de praktiska reglerna för hur det här ska se ut för personbilar. Nästa steg på den vägen, utgående från de förslag vi har fått från kommissionen, blir att ta hand också om tunga transporter. Det kommer att vara speciellt intressant av den orsaken att vi vet att det sätt på vilket vi ska fördela bördan mellan till exempel jordbruket och tunga transporter kan ställa jordbruket inför allvarliga utmaningar. Jordbrukets produktivitet är naturligtvis mycket lägre om vi inte sköter om att den tunga transporten tar sin andel av Paris-kraven, genom COP21. I så fall försätter vi jordbruket samtidigt i en sämre situation. Vi har alltså tagit ett stort steg framåt. Vi kan ta ännu större steg i framtiden och det kommer också att vara nödvändigt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="96868" name="Karima Delli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, si on compte sur les routes européennes, on trouve seulement 5 % de camions parmi tous les véhicules en circulation. Et pourtant, ces camions produisent environ 25 %, soit un quart, des émissions de gaz à effet de serre du transport routier dans l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est plus que temps qu’on en finisse avec ce déséquilibre si l’on veut respecter un jour les engagements de la COP 21 pour sauver le climat et la planète, mais aussi pour que les citoyens puissent respirer.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mettre en place une surveillance en matière d’émissions de CO2 et de consommation de carburant des camions, c’est une bonne nouvelle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jusqu’à récemment, les émissions de CO2 et la consommation de carburant des poids lourds n’étaient ni signalées, ni surveillées de manière objective et comparable dans l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Désormais, les entreprises opératrices de transport pourront choisir les véhicules les moins consommateurs et émetteurs: cela permettra de dépenser moins et de polluer moins.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ne nous arrêtons pas là, le secteur routier de marchandises doit faire plus et mieux pour réduire ses émissions de gaz à effet de serre.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’étape que nous franchissons aujourd’hui, évidemment, est nécessaire, mais elle doit surtout servir de base pour le futur proche, c’est-à-dire pour établir des limites d’émission de CO2 obligatoires pour tous les camions dans l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Commission a fait des propositions dans ce sens récemment en vue d’une réelle décarbonisation complète du secteur d’ici 2050. J’ose espérer que, là aussi, nous serons au rendez-vous, mes chers collègues, pour donner plus de force, de concret et d’ambition à cette proposition afin que le secteur routier de marchandises émette 50 % de gaz à effet de serre en moins d’ici 2030 et plus en 2050.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc, si on y tient, alors nous avons une chance de respecter nos accords, notamment de la COP 21, parce que nous dansons tous sur le même volcan face aux dérèglements climatiques, donc saisissons cette opportunité.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-0000" speaker_id="124736" name="Merja Kyllönen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">GUE/NGL-ryhmän puolesta. – Arvoisa puhemies, hyvät kollegat, erityiskiitos kollega Zoffolille ja koko neuvottelutiimille ja tietysti myös komission ja neuvoston joukkueelle yhteisestä lopputulemasta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Raskaan liikenteen polttoaineenkulutuksen ja hiilidioksidipäästöjen luotettava seuranta on ollut ennen tätä lakiehdotusta hakusessa. Nyt meillä on mahdollisuus saada tietoa sekä polttoaineen kulutuksesta että hiilidioksidipäästöistä. Kun tämä vielä yhdistetään kunnalliseen tyyppihyväksyntään ja ajonaikaisiin todellisiin päästöihin, voimme todeta, että meillä on työkaluja ilmastonmuutoksen torjumiseen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rahoitus on mielestäni avain niihin parhaisiin keinoihin, miten saavutamme ilmastotavoitteet. Toivoisinkin, että EU-liikennerahoituksen kriteeriksi pystyttäisiin asettamaan arviointi, jossa katsottaisiin, miten hankkeet edistävät päästövähennystavoitteiden saavuttamista, ja rahoitusta kohdennettaisiin ensisijaisesti tällaisiin hankkeisiin, joissa päästövähennykset ovat riittävän korkeita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="124779" name="Eleonora Evi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, fino a ieri non avevamo dati sulle emissioni e neanche sul consumo del carburante. Oggi, finalmente, con questo regolamento introduciamo un monitoraggio e una comunicazione dei dati sulle emissioni di CO2 e sul consumo di carburante dei veicoli pesanti nuovi. Di questo mi rallegro e faccio i miei complimenti al relatore per aver guidato il Parlamento nelle negoziazioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questo regolamento va a colmare una lacuna, perché finalmente la comparazione dei dati ricavati grazie al software di simulazione Vector e raccolti nel registro pubblico che viene istituito permetterà alle piccole e medie imprese e alle amministrazioni pubbliche di compiere delle scelte di acquisto informate, orientandole – si spera appunto – verso dei modelli che generano i maggiori risparmi di carburante e non solo, ovviamente si parla anche di emissioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono particolarmente soddisfatta anche dell'accordo raggiunto nei negoziati interistituzionali per quanto riguarda la trasparenza e la pubblicità dei dati raccolti, soprattutto per quanto riguarda le prestazioni dei motori dei veicoli pesanti e dei cicli di prova. Era uno dei nostri emendamenti, che inizialmente il Parlamento non aveva sostenuto, ma fortunatamente nell'accordo finale questo aspetto è contemplato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non dimentichiamoci però che la battaglia più importante si giocherà nei prossimi mesi, con la definizione dei target di riduzione di CO2 per questi veicoli che sono responsabili da soli del 30 % delle emissioni complessive del traffico stradale con preoccupanti proiezioni di crescita.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chiudo dicendo che dobbiamo ascoltare le imprese e gli autotrasportatori virtuosi, che già oggi ci chiedono di tagliare le emissioni almeno del 24 % già dal 2025 e di spingere con decisione verso l'elettrificazione dei veicoli pesanti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-0000" speaker_id="124765" name="Joëlle Mélin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, c’est en partant du constat que les émissions de gaz à effet de serre proviennent à 38 % du transport routier que la Commission présentait en 2017 un système de surveillance et de communication des données relatives aux émissions de CO2 des véhicules utilitaires lourds neufs. Ce faisant, la Commission prend le risque d’être incohérente.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, parallèlement à ce souhait de baisse des émissions de CO2 ayant conduit la France à promouvoir le moteur diesel, ce qui lui permet d’afficher des émissions de CO2 plus de 10 % inférieure à la moyenne européenne, la Commission, elle, s’est lancée dans la chasse au diesel au profit de l’essence. Or, force est de constater que les moteurs essence, consommant davantage que les moteurs diesel, émettent in fine 25 % de CO2 de plus que les moteurs diesel. C’est donc un cercle vicieux et les constructeurs ne savent plus à quoi s’en tenir. D’un côté, la chasse au CO2, de l’autre, la chasse au diesel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Une fois de plus, il s’agira d’une écologie punitive, avec des amendes administratives qui iront directement dans les poches de l’Europe, qui va venir frapper l’industrie des poids lourds au détriment d’une politique encourageant les bonnes pratiques en matière d’écoconduite et d’accompagnement des constructeurs et équipementiers vers des objectifs environnementaux viables économiquement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette proposition de la Commission est d’autant plus déraisonnable qu’elle ne prend absolument pas en compte la réalité du processus de fabrication et d’utilisation des camions. En effet, les constructeurs fabriquent des châssis nus qui sont ensuite destinés à différents types de transport selon la caisse sous la remorque choisie pour l’utilisation finale. Les données du constructeur deviennent ainsi des données d’usine inutilisables et de facto inutiles, mais qui viendront effectivement faire grimper la facture du produit fini.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors la seule option dont disposent les constructeurs actuellement est de se tourner vers les carburants alternatifs émettant moins de CO2, comme le GNL ou l’électricité. C’est ce que font déjà de nombreux constructeurs; mais les technocrates à l’origine de ce texte oublient simplement que ces différents types de carburant, s’ils sont adaptés à certains trajets courts, sont – à ce jour et pour un certain temps encore – relativement inutilisables sur des trajets de longue durée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors dans ce contexte, il serait plutôt dans l’intérêt de la Commission de s’atteler à encourager le développement de points de recharge et de distribution de carburants alternatifs avant de venir s’attaquer aux constructeurs qui se contentent de répondre à une demande d’un type précis de véhicule et correspondant aux besoins et aux possibilités actuelles.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="96754" name="Wim van de Camp" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, dank u zeer. In Nederland hebben wij het prachtige spreekwoord: "zonder transport staat alles stil". Het wegtransport in de Europese Unie is een economische factor van groot belang. Onze economie draait nog steeds voor een heel groot gedeelte op wegtransport. Als je kijkt naar de discussies over het mobiliteitspakket deze week, dan weet je dat wegtransport voor de Europese economie zeer belangrijk is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar wij hebben allemaal in december 2015 COP21 ondertekend en wij willen dat ook de transportsector schoner wordt. Dat mag niet te lang duren. In dat opzicht ben ik het met mevrouw Bulc eens. Tegelijkertijd brengen schone vrachtauto's ook innovatie met zich mee. Het is helemaal niet zo slecht dat de politiek hier en daar een duwtje geeft om die innovatie te versnellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dat opzicht vraag ik nog even aandacht voor de stad. Als ik het goed heb begrepen, vallen ook onze bussen onder deze zware voertuigen, en vervuiling door bussen is echt een heel groot thema in verschillende steden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot, Voorzitter, ben ik blij dat men in de trialoog ook het debat over de gegevens en industriële eigendom heeft kunnen oplossen. De Europese industrie was, denk ik, terecht bang dat al te grote inzage in de gegevens tot industrieel stelen zou kunnen leiden. Ik heb begrepen dat dat in de trialoog tot een goed einde is gebracht.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-0000" speaker_id="185619" name="Tiemo Wölken" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Tatsächlich stellen wir uns hier im Europäischen Parlament ja fast täglich die Frage, wie wir es denn hinbekommen wollen, dass wir als Europäische Union die Pariser Klimaziele einhalten. Wir wissen, wie wichtig es sein wird, dass wir die Paris-Ziele erreichen, und anders als transatlantische Partner sind wir davon überzeugt, dass dieses Agreement dafür sorgen wird, dass wir in Europa unseren fairen Anteil an der Reduktion der Treibhausgase tragen werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das bedeutet aber auch, dass wir uns anschauen müssen, was an Treibhausgasemissionen in dem Verkehrssektor der Lkw emittiert wird. Wir wissen, dass 5 % aller Treibhausgasemissionen in Europa aus dem Sektor der Nutzfahrzeuge kommen, und deswegen ist es doch niemandem zu erklären – den Bürgerinnen und Bürgern nicht, aber auch den Unternehmen nicht, die Lkw kaufen –, dass die CO2-Emissionen noch nicht überwacht wurden, noch nicht zertifiziert wurden. Es ist daher an der Zeit, und es ist richtig – und deswegen möchte ich meinem Kollegen Damiano auch danken, dass er diese Verhandlungen so gut geführt hat –, dass wir endlich einen Vorschlag auf dem Tisch haben, der dafür sorgen wird, dass wir in diesem so wichtigen Bereich Transparenz bekommen. Es ist gut, dass wir Sanktionen in dieses Papier hineinverhandelt haben, sodass wir Hersteller, die sich nicht an die Transparenzpflichten halten, auch in die Pflicht nehmen, sanktionieren können, denn wir alle arbeiten ja Tag für Tag daran, dass CO2-Emissionen reduziert werden, und das müssen auch die Hersteller von schweren Lkw tun.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist auch wichtig, dass wir den Käufern von Lkw die Möglichkeit geben, ihre Kaufentscheidung daran zu orientieren, wie viel CO2 ein Lkw ausstößt. Denn wir sehen immer noch, dass der Lkw-Verkehr innerhalb der Europäischen Union zunimmt, dass der Verkehr der Güter auf der Schiene hingegen abnimmt, obwohl der Verkehr auf der Schiene sehr viel klimafreundlicher wäre. Insofern ist diese Regel, ist dieser Vorschlag auch ein Ansatz, mehr Transparenz und mehr Marktgerechtigkeit zu schaffen und mehr Güter von der Straße auf die Schiene zu bekommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein letzter Punkt: Wir alle wissen, dass Hersteller von Verbrennungsmotoren dazu neigen, unsere Vorgaben zu umgehen. Deswegen ist es ein großer Erfolg, ein wichtiger Schritt, dass wir Tests eingeführt haben, die die realen Emissionen messen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Insgesamt glaube ich, dass dieses Paket ein guter und wichtiger Schritt für die Bürgerinnen und Bürger ist.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-0000" speaker_id="96870" name="Gesine Meissner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, liebe Frau Kommissarin! Zunächst mal herzlichen Dank an den Berichterstatter: Das ist wirklich ein gutes Gesetz geworden. Ich könnte mich ja, lieber Tiemo Wölken, sofort anschließen und sagen, ich stimme dir voll zu. Darum geht es hier aber nicht, ich soll ja meine eigene Rede halten. Es ist tatsächlich so: Wenn es auch nur 5 % der CO2 Emissionen sind, die die Lkw und die schweren Nutzfahrzeuge ausstoßen – es sind 25 % vom Straßenverkehr, und wir müssen dringend etwas verbessern. Wir brauchen eben auch viel Verkehr, die Verbraucher wollen Produkte kaufen, die müssen transportiert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es kann aber wirklich nicht sein, dass wir noch keine Standards hatten. Darum ist es unwahrscheinlich wichtig, dass wir tatsächlich jetzt erstmals Standards für diese Emissionen und für die Effizienzmessung haben. Es ist doch verrückt: die USA, China – sogar China! –, Japan, Kanada, die haben das alle und wir noch nicht. Das messen wir jetzt im realen Straßenverkehr. Das ist auch eine ganz wichtige Geschichte, dass wir das jetzt so machen und nicht irgendwo im Labor. Und wir veröffentlichen die Daten – da ist mir besonders wichtig, dass wir sensible Daten und geistiges Eigentum schützen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber insgesamt sind wir in einer sehr guten Richtung unterwegs für die Karbonisierung des Transports. Was wir jetzt haben, ist gut für die Umwelt, gut für die Transparenz und bringt uns weiter nach vorne.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="106202" name="Julia Reid" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this report states that global warming is a real problem requiring clear and courageous decision—making, and yet there has been no discernible increase in global temperature since the late 1990s, despite an increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide. It would appear that initial climate models have been too pessimistic, with empirical data temperatures diverging from those forecast 10 years ago and climate scientists now admitting that previous forecasting models had exaggerated the amount by which temperatures would rise.</p>
      <p sl="en">What we are experiencing is a relatively inactive sun. Sunspot activity has been decreasing since 1996, with the sun being completely blank for 25% of last year, and to date, 2018 appears to be no different. In fact, solar scientists are predicting another Maunder Minimum. In my opinion, it would be best to adopt a wait and see attitude rather than to continue with current unilateral EU energy and climate policies that are profoundly damaging to the European economy, causing industry closures and job losses.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="125016" name="Claudia Schmidt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, geschätzte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Es ist natürlich überhaupt keine Frage: Wir haben Handlungsbedarf! Ich bin, wie wahrscheinlich jeder hier, gespannt, wie sich gerade die aktuellen Ereignisse bei Daimler weiterentwickeln werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nimmt man das Lkw-Kartell noch zur Volkswagen-Geschichte dazu, dann muss man feststellen, dass die Branche absolut Regeln und Kontrollen braucht. Strengere Regeln und Überprüfungen sind nötig, nicht nur aufgrund des eingeschränkten Vertrauens, sondern auch, damit wir überprüfen können, wie unsere Entscheidungen in der Praxis funktionieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bezweifle ausdrücklich, dass Steuern auf Treibstoffe auch nur einen Funken CO2 eingespart haben. Straßenverkehr wird dadurch nur teurer für die Nutzer und für die Konsumenten. Ich glaube aus vollem Herzen: Die Mehrheit dieses Hauses und Europas teilt das gleiche Ziel. Die Umweltbelastung soll sinken, der Sektor soll seinen Beitrag zum Klimaschutz leisten, und wir sollten – auch aus geopolitischen Überlegungen heraus – weg vom Erdöl. Synthetische Treibstoffe schonen dabei nicht nur die Umwelt, sondern sie reduzieren unsere Abhängigkeit und holen die Wertschöpfungskette zurück nach Europa. Die Batterien lösen dieses Problem nicht, sondern schaffen eigentlich neue.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte daher warnen, angesichts der aktuellen Ereignisse nachzugeben und den Fokus ausschließlich auf die Straße und den Verbrennungsmotor zu richten. Wenn man Lkw verpflichtet, pro Kilometer eine gewisse Abgabe wegen Lärms, Schadstoffen und CO2-Emissionen zu zahlen, dann hilft das weder Mensch noch Tier noch der Umwelt. Lediglich der Finanzminister freut sich. Weiterentwicklung von Motoren- und Abgastechnologie hilft, wie die Euro-Normen eindrucksvoll bewiesen haben. Die Kosten können nicht einfach auf den Konsumenten überwälzt werden, sondern man drängt die Hersteller in die richtige Richtung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noch einmal gesagt: Es braucht Überwachung, aber den Öko-Ablasshandel brauchen wir ganz sicher nicht.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="124739" name="Carlos Zorrinho" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, o aquecimento global tem que ser combatido com decisões claras e corajosas.</p>
      <p sl="en">A União Europeia fixou uma meta vinculativa e ambiciosa de, pelo menos, 40 % de redução das emissões de gases com efeito de estufa em todos os setores da economia até 2030 e é óbvio que, para cumprir este objetivo, o setor dos transportes tem um contributo muito importante e, em particular, os transportes de pesados, dado que um quarto das emissões de CO2 é devido a este tipo de transporte rodoviários.</p>
      <p sl="en">As emissões de CO2 e o consumo de combustível dos veículos pesados novos, colocados na União Europeia, não é, como todos sabemos, objeto de certificação, nem de vigilância, nem de comunicação dos dados, como já acontece, de forma contrária, com os veículos ligeiros de passageiros e comerciais.</p>
      <p sl="en">E por isso esta proposta de regulamento é bem-vinda, porque corrige uma lacuna. Só com dados robustos e fiáveis se pode fazer boa legislação. Tenho—me, aliás, batido por isso, como relator-sombra, no grupo que está neste momento a trabalhar nos trílogos das negociações do regulamento da governação da União da Energia. Uma abordagem integrada de todos os setores para podermos atingir os objetivos pretendidos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nesta proposta, são estabelecidos requisitos precisos em matéria de vigilância e comunicação das emissões, o que vai permitir a constituição de uma base de dados, algo muito positivo, transparente, gerida pela Agência Europeia do Ambiente e importante será também o relatório anual da Comissão Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este regulamento integra-se na Estratégia Europeia de Mobilidade Hipocarbónica e é um passo importante para a descarbonização dos transportes, mas não podemos perder de vista, como já foi aqui dito, que, num futuro tão breve quanto possível, temos que ter modelos limpos e inteligentes de mobilidade e que esses modelos limpos e inteligentes de mobilidade também têm que ser aplicados aos veículos pesados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta é, aliás, mais uma área em que, em nome da saúde, da sustentabilidade e da competitividade da indústria europeia, a União Europeia tem que reassumir um papel de liderança à escala global. Muito obrigado.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="96791" name="Elżbieta Katarzyna Łukacijewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Ambitne cele, kolejny krok Unii Europejskiej w kierunku gospodarki niskoemisyjnej. Jak wiemy, samochody ciężarowe to 5 % pojazdów na drogach, ale 25 % zanieczyszczeń i emisji dwutlenku węgla. Dlatego nie możemy nie reagować, nie działać, bo mówimy o zdrowiu i życiu ludzkim, i olbrzymich kosztach z tym związanych. Patrząc na poziomy ograniczeń, musimy zastosować takie progi, aby one były możliwe do osiągnięcia. Również pomiary, kontrole i testy muszą być rzetelne, aby z jednej strony wyeliminować z rynku nieuczciwe podmioty, ale z drugiej strony, aby wyeliminować sytuacje, taką jaka miała miejsce z aferą Diesel Gate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rozwój gospodarczy, wszyscy wiemy, że wymaga zwiększenia zapotrzebowania na transport drogowy i siłą rzeczy związane są z tym emisje CO2, więc oczywiście przejście na inną formę silników, napędów jest bardzo istotne, bardzo ważne, ale patrząc na te ograniczenia, nie zapominajmy, że to są również miejsca pracy, to są również koszty dla konsumentów. Myślę, że wszyscy zrobiły dużo, aby tych kosztów nie przerzucać na naszych wyborców. To jest bardzo istotne, ale też ważne jest, aby ci, którzy produkują silniki spalinowe czy części do silników spalinowych, firmy czy podmioty, które tworzą tysiące miejsc pracy, aby mieli czas na zmianę technologii i ochronę miejsc pracy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przy tym wszystkim, Pani Komisarz mam jedno pytanie, co zrobimy z samochodami, które będą przyjeżdżały spoza Unii Europejskiej, z Bułgarii, z przepraszam z Białorusi, Ukrainy, jeżeli nie spełniają norm, czy będą wpuszczane do Europy, bo inaczej nasze ograniczenia, jeżeli zaleją nas samochody, które nie spełniają norm, nie zdadzą żadnego egzaminu, nie osiągniemy żadnych ograniczeń emisji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="124890" name="Adam Szejnfeld" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Rozmawiamy oczywiście na bardzo ważny temat, dlatego że wiąże się on z ochroną klimatu i powietrza, a to jest niezwykle istotne w dzisiejszych czasach. Ma to wpływ na zdrowie ludzi, ale gdy mówimy o ludziach, to musimy pamiętać także o tych, którzy pracują w fabrykach, gdzie produkuje się pojazdy, i w przedsiębiorstwach wykorzystujących te pojazdy. Chcę przez to powiedzieć, że należy zachować pewną równowagę między potrzebami a możliwościami.</p>
      <p sl="en">Istotne jest też, żebyśmy poziom oczekiwanej redukcji CO2 i wszystkich innych szkodliwych dla powietrza i naszego zdrowia składników podnosili wprost proporcjonalnie do postępu technicznego. Bo oczywiście bardzo łatwo na pstryknięcie palców wymyślić sobie, że do tego i tego roku należy obniżyć emisje o 15%, 30%, 50%, 70% – tak sobie można rzucać – natomiast pozostaje pytanie, czy jest to technicznie możliwe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlatego też apelowałbym, żeby równolegle do tego rodzaju projektów Komisja przewidywała również działania wspierające naukę, badania i rozwój w kierunku tworzenia nowych rozwiązań technicznych i technologicznych, które ułatwią osiąganie tych celów.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-0000" speaker_id="124803" name="Isabella De Monte" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signora Commissario, vorrei innanzitutto ringraziare il collega Damiano Zoffoli, per la commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare, e il collega Nicola Caputo, per la commissione per i trasporti e il turismo, per il loro lavoro su questo importante dossier.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il settore dei trasporti contribuisce in maniera significativa al totale delle emissioni nell'Unione europea e i veicoli pesanti giocano un ruolo predominante. Gli obiettivi che l'Europa si è prefissata per quanto riguarda la riduzione delle emissioni sono ambiziosi e credo che questi saranno difficili però da raggiungere se non siamo in grado di monitorare e confrontare i dati relativi ai veicoli pesanti, cosi come già facciamo per le auto e i veicoli leggeri.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se vogliamo ridurre le emissioni di gas ad effetto serra nei trasporti su strada del 60 % entro il 2050, dobbiamo dotarci di un sistema di monitoraggio delle emissioni e dei consumi anche per i veicoli pesanti. Del resto, ciò è proposto dalla strategia europea 2016 per una mobilità a basse emissioni. Finalmente, anche per tali veicoli quindi sarà possibile avere dati affidabili, sia relativi ai consumi di carburante sia relativi alle emissioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dopo lo scandalo Dieselgate, infatti, è sempre più necessario raccogliere e diffondere dati sulle emissioni reali di guida, e non quelli calcolati in laboratorio. I dati raccolti saranno gestiti in una banca dati dall'Agenzia dell'ambiente, ma mai come ora sono convinta che vi sia bisogno anche di un'agenzia per il trasporto stradale, la quale potrebbe non solo assicurare che tali informazioni siano accessibili al pubblico, ma altresì che dati sensibili e commerciali siano protetti.</p>
      <p sl="en">La cosa più importante, comunque, è l'effetto per i cittadini, che vogliamo possano respirare un'aria più pulita, con indubbi benefici per la salute, ma ci sarà un effetto positivo anche per gli autotrasportatori, che avranno risparmi sui consumi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I’m glad I made it, just in from Strasbourg, three and a half hours on the bus, so it’s good to make my speaking time. I am pleased to support this proposal, which looks to put in place an EU-wide system for monitoring and reporting of CO2 emissions and fuel consumption for manufacturers’ heavy-duty vehicles, or HGVs. As part of this mandatory system, the findings would be cross-checked against new vehicle registration data as provided by Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">At present, HGVs account for approximately a quarter of the EU’s CO2 emissions from road transport – a very high sum. It is anticipated that this will increase significantly, along with growing levels of road transport in the coming years, unfortunately. Thus it is imperative that we take action as soon as possible to ensure a sizeable reduction in new HGV CO2 emissions in the 2020-2030 period.</p>
      <p sl="en">The primary aspects of the proposal include introducing administrative fines where there is infringement in clearly-defined cases; making public certain data reported under the regulation, including air drag value in a range format; provisions to monitor and report results of on-road verification tests; measures to verify and correct other measures adopted by implementing acts. These are all important inclusions, and I think they will certainly help the situation. I am encouraged by this proposal and the opportunities it will create, as well as enabling fleet buyers to make more informed purchase decisions in order to boost competition between manufacturers and stimulate fuel efficiency and lower emissions in the freight sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">We depend heavily on innovation to sufficiently reduce our transport emissions, and I am certain there is a great potential to make significant strides forward in this regard. We will need to make real cuts in transport by 2030 if we are to comply with the commitments on the recently adopted effort-sharing regulation, and as rapporteur for the renewable energy file which we are completing, hopefully, this week, I think this is a positive step.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="28126" name="Christofer Fjellner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Jag vill passa på att tacka föredragande Zoffoli och även kommissionen och det bulgariska ordförandeskapet för ett gott samarbete här. Jag har ju själv varit ansvarig för frågan i EPP-gruppen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Utan lastbilen stannar Europa. Vi klarar oss helt enkelt inte utan den, och det är därför vi måste göra det vi kan för att bekämpa utsläppen från lastbilarna. De står för en betydande del av utsläppen. Bara i Sverige till exempel står vägtrafiken för ungefär 30 procent av utsläppen och lastbilarna för 20 procent av den andelen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det sprids en myt om att lastbilar inte blir mer och mer effektiva. Det är inte sant; de blir mer effektiva. Bara i Sverige minskade utsläppen från tunga lastbilar med 11 procent förra året. Det inte så konstigt; den som köper en lastbil vill framför allt ha en lastbil som är bränslesnål, för det är den största kostnaden när du köper lastbil. Marknadskrafterna fungerar här väldigt bra för att hjälpa miljön. Problemet är bara att det inte minskar snabbt nog, och det är det vi måste göra något åt. Det är därför vi nu har en lagstiftning som ska se till att vi mäter koldioxidutsläppen från våra tunga lastbilar på ett bättre sätt, och snart ska vi tillsammans även hitta en lagstiftning för att begränsa utsläppen från de tunga lastbilarna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Den stora frågan vi har debatterat här, och haft konflikter om, är ju vilken information som ska bli offentlig. Jag har haft en viktig princip om att den information som tillverkarna ska vara tvungna att offentliggöra om sina produkter är den information som vi behöver för att mäta utsläppen, men vissa här verkar ha principen att all information om allt möjligt ska bli tillgänglig för alla. Nästan som om målet vore att våra produkter ska kopieras av andra. Europa är världsledande när det gäller att producera lastbilar och så ska det förbli, men då ska vi exportera miljövänliga lastbilar, inte känslig information om hur vi producerar våra lastbilar. Det är därför jag tycker att den avvägning vi har gjort här – att se till att vi publicerar information som minskar utsläppen, inte som gör att andra kan kopiera våra lastbilar – är det som är viktigt. För gör vi det, då exporterar vi känslig information, vi exporterar jobb och tillväxt från Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Dzisiejsza sesja w Strasburgu to trzy tematy: po pierwsze instrumenty finansowe, zagrożenia przede wszystkim dla ewentualnych kryzysów, drony, zagrożenia w ruchu pasażerskim; ale także dla tych, którzy funkcjonują na ziemi, i oczywiście CO2, czyli sprzęt ciężki. Co łączy te tematy? Przede wszystkim pogoń, niezwykle trudna reakcja Parlamentu Europejskiego, Komisji na zjawiska, które na tej sali wszyscy identycznie oceniają.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niech pewną ilustracją do tego będzie moja obserwacja sprzed zaledwie dwóch tygodni. Duża, wielka ciężarówka, chłodnia, z dwiema funkcjonującymi sprężarkami, z włączonymi silnikami przy przedszkolu rozładowuje, krótko mówiąc towar. Dzieci, które przechodzą do tego przedszkola, wdychają te spaliny, które jak zwróciłem uwagę, funkcjonowały prawie przez godzinę. Z mojego punktu widzenia właśnie takie obserwacje, takie obrazki powinny nas lepiej i mocniej mobilizować do tego, żeby szybciej wdrażać takie przepisy, nad jakimi dzisiaj debatujemy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamna comisar, stimați colegi, sigur, ne lipsea acest sistem de monitorizare și de măsurare a emisiilor, dar și a consumului de combustibil pentru vehiculele grele. Eu vreau să felicit Comisia pentru că s-a ținut de cuvânt. În 2017 în pachetul pentru mobilitate spuneați, doamna comisar, că în prima jumătate a anului 2018 veți veni cu o propunere. Este foarte bine. Vreau să felicit și raportorii și colegii care au lucrat. Avem nevoie de măsurarea emisiilor, până la urmă, sigur, avem interesul siguranței, dar și al protecției mediului.</p>
      <p sl="en">Însă am două îngrijorări și vă rog, doamnă comisar, să țineți cont de ele, au mai ridicat colegii acest lucru. În primul rând, ce facem dacă îi protejăm totuși pe constructorii de vehicule grele din Europa față de importurile din celelalte state, să fie supuse acelorași teste și verificări. Și, în al doilea rând, sigur că trebuie să ținem cont de cum pot să țină constructorii ritmul în construcția de noi autovehicule cu emisii scăzute pentru a nu bloca construcția de mașini și a nu bloca, până la urmă, transportul rutier.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sper să se țină cont de acest lucru și, sigur, sper că veți monitoriza corect transportul în toate statele membre și că va fi un sistem echitabil cu protecția datelor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Violeta Bulc" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you for this debate which confirms the importance to act on CO2 emissions from heavy-duty vehicles. Together we can be proud of the result of our joint effort to agree on this new piece of legislation. But before I conclude, allow me to respond to some of your comments.</p>
      <p sl="en">On transparency of data: the agreed text strikes the right balance between the need for increased transparency in the heavy-duty vehicle market and the need to protect commercially sensitive information. This approached, agreed for the publication, does strike such a balance considering the high influence of this parameter to the fuel consumption performance and hence CO2 emissions of vehicles. Of course I am referring to the air-drag values.</p>
      <p sl="en">On in-service conformity tests, this provision has the objective of ensuring that consumers get what they pay for and that the cars that are produced are as clean as the ones that are tested.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission had already included this provision in the context of the type approval reform, and the European Parliament had strongly backed this position during trilogues. Unfortunately, the final compromise for type approval did not manage to keep this provision. This is why we included it again in this legislation. Hopefully this time we will succeed.</p>
      <p sl="en">On alternative fuels, the Commission issued, in its second mobility package last November, a detailed action plan to accelerate the deployment of alternative fuels infrastructure throughout the EU. This also includes fast charging points for electrical vehicles, and the Commission dedicated EUR 450 million of cofinancing in its November 2017 CEF call to support these efforts. So the projects are now in the deployment phase.</p>
      <p sl="en">On diesel cars the Commission sees a need for accelerating the uptake of zero and low-emission vehicles in an effort to improve air quality and lower CO2 emissions, while following an approach of technological neutrality. While the proposal will speed up the market uptake of zero and low-emission vehicles, accelerating innovation and reaching economies of scale, the change in the fleet composition will be gradual. It is expected that at least 80% of new car fleets in 2030 will contain an internal combustion engine.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I do hope that additional innovation will be introduced, for use in combustion engines to qualify for at least low-emission vehicles.</p>
      <p sl="en">On imported vehicles: there is no doubt that all vehicles placed on the European market are subject to the same standards, either being manufactured here in Europe or imported from third countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, let me again stress the benefits of addressing HDV emissions, very quickly. First, transport operators, mainly SMEs, will save money at the pump. Second, we will keep and create new jobs here in Europe, up to 25 000 more jobs in 2025 are estimated. Third, we will invest and innovate here in Europe. Fourth, we will use and import less oil. And fifth, we will fight against climate change and improve the air we breathe, in particular in EU cities.</p>
      <p sl="en">So, as a next step, the Commission counts on the co-legislators to replicate the success of this file when negotiating the CO2 emissions standards for lorries.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="131051" name="Damiano Zoffoli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, solo pochi minuti per ringraziare tutti gli intervenuti. Mi pare che ci sia un ampio consenso sulla proposta di regolamento. Un ringraziamento per la proficua collaborazione va al Commissario Cañete, con cui ci siamo intesi, abbiamo discusso e abbiamo trovato un giusto punto di equilibrio, a tutta la struttura della DG Clima, alla Presidenza bulgara e naturalmente ai colleghi relatori ombra della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo dimostrato che si può fare presto e bene. Si può fare, si può fare presto e bene. I tempi sono importanti e, in un tempo ragionevole, il risultato di oggi mi pare soddisfacente per tutti i cittadini europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-0000" speaker_id="124891" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się we wtorek 12 czerwca 2018 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-5000" speaker_id="90110" name="Carolina Punset" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – El transporte es el responsable de una cuarta parte de emisiones de GEI de la UE. Desde 2013, y a pesar de las advertencias de la comunidad científica, las emisiones de este sector no paran de crecer, amenazando el cumplimiento de los objetivos del Acuerdo de París sobre el clima. Al no estar sujeto al comercio de emisiones, son los Estados los que tienen que desarrollar políticas en el transporte para la reducción de emisiones, pero poco o nada puede hacerse con unas economías enormemente condicionadas por la industria del automóvil, de las que depende hasta el 10 % del PIB. Así, el sector sigue produciendo vehículos contaminantes, con un modelo más que amortizado, y no se plantea cambios ni siquiera ante una elevada demanda real de vehículos eléctricos, hasta tal punto que empresas de reparto alemanas han tenido que fabricarse sus propios furgones. Sin penalizaciones en Europa por falsear las emisiones y con Gobiernos y Comisión amedrentados ante la pérdida de empleo o deslocalización, se aleja incluso el cumplimiento de los objetivos menos ambiciosos. De nada servirán las nuevas medidas adoptadas para emisiones de motores de combustión sin una verdadera apuesta por la electrificación del transporte de mercancías en todo su sentido.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-7500" speaker_id="96847" name="Claudiu Ciprian Tănăsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Economia circulară cu emisii scăzute de dioxid de carbon reprezintă un obiectiv major al UE. Atingerea acestui obiectiv este susținută de un plan de investiții care vizează reindustrializarea Europei pe baza unor noi modele de afaceri și tehnologii de vârf. Așa cum se cunoaște, în vederea tranziției către o energie curată pentru toți europenii, UE și-a stabilit obiective ambițioase de reducere a emisiilor până în 2030, la care trebuie să contribuie și sectorul transporturilor. Însă, până în prezent, emisiile de CO2 și consumul de combustibil al vehiculelor grele noi introduse pe piața UE nu au fost certificate și nici nu sunt monitorizate și raportate, ceea ce generează o barieră în calea instituirii de politici de reducere a emisiilor de gaze cu efect de seră în sectorul vehiculelor grele.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prin urmare, sistemul de monitorizare și de raportare pentru noile vehicule grele propus la nivelul Uniunii, va contribui la crearea unei piețe pe deplin transparentă a vehiculelor grele noi, care le va permite cumpărătorilor să ia cele mai bune decizii de cumpărare în cunoștință de cauză, oferind producătorilor un stimulent mai puternic de a inova și de a dezvolta vehicule mai eficiente din punct de vedere energetic.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Modernisation of education in the EU (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="124891" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dziennego jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Krystynę Łybacką w imieniu Komisji Kultury i Edukacji w sprawie modernizacji edukacji w UE (2017/2224(INI)) (A8-0173/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127-0000" speaker_id="124883" name="Krystyna Łybacka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">sprawozdawczyni. – Panie Przewodniczący! Przede wszystkim chcę bardzo gorąco podziękować wszystkim osobom zaangażowanym w powstanie tego sprawozdania. Dziękuję kontrsprawozdawcom za doskonałą współpracę, dziękuję Komisji Zatrudnienia i Komisji Praw Kobiet za ich cenne opinie, dziękuję Panu Komisarzowi za aktywną współpracę i Komisji za liczne komunikaty. Specjalne podziękowania kieruję do ekspertów z dziedziny edukacji, nauczycieli, studentów, uczniów i organizacji pozarządowych za ich bezcenne uwagi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pracując nad sprawozdaniem, przyjęłam trzy główne założenia. Po pierwsze, tradycyjne miejsce zdobywania wiedzy, czyli szkoła, jest dziś zastąpione wieloma innymi dostępnymi źródłami. Współczesne technologie uwolniły edukację, tworząc przestrzeń edukacyjną. Ogromnym wyzwaniem dla nas jest stworzenie szkoły jako najciekawszego miejsca tej przestrzeni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Po drugie, doceniamy rolę szkolnictwa zawodowego, podkreślamy w sprawozdaniu konieczność utworzenia zestawu kluczowych kompetencji, umiejętności, ale przypominamy, że rolą systemów edukacji jest wykształcenie wielowymiarowego człowieka realizującego się nie tylko zawodowo, ale także kulturowo, społecznie i obywatelsko.</p>
      <p sl="en">I wreszcie po trzecie, uważamy, że warunkiem koniecznym wszelkiego rozwoju jest ustanowienie paktu cywilizacyjnego opartego na dobrze finansowanych wysokiej jakości systemach edukacji. Dlatego postulujemy zarówno zwiększenie nakładów, jak i uzyskanie większej synergii pomiędzy funduszami strukturalnymi, funduszami inwestycyjnymi a edukacją.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sprawozdanie rozpatruje wszystkie poziomy edukacji. Podkreślamy znaczenie edukacji przedszkolnej i wczesnoszkolnej. Wspieramy ustanowienie europejskich ram kształcenia przedszkolnego, aby zadbać o holistyczny rozwój dziecka. Szkoły widzimy jako centra krytycznego i twórczego myślenia. To oczywiście wymaga zmiany paradygmatu kształcenia, odejścia od werbalnego przekazu i mechanicznego zapamiętywania na rzecz rozumienia, dyskusji, rozwiązywania problemów, ale także indywidualizacji procesu kształcenia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szkolnictwo wyższe pełni kluczową rolę w rozwoju potencjału intelektualnego i konkurencyjności gospodarki europejskiej. Z dużym zainteresowaniem przyjmujemy zapowiedź utworzenia europejskiego obszaru edukacji, ale podkreślamy, że musi być on skorelowany z europejską przestrzenią szkolnictwa wyższego i z europejskim obszarem badawczym, aby wzmocnić trójkąt wiedzy i uzyskać u absolwentów postawy proinnowacyjne. Wspieramy również utworzenie europejskiej sieci uniwersytetów, zakładając jednak, że powinna to być oddolna inicjatywa samych uczelni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie będzie żadnych zmian w edukacji bez nauczycieli, dlatego zwracamy uwagę na konieczność pozyskania silnie zmotywowanych, doskonale wykształconych i mentalnie przygotowanych nauczycieli. Wymaga to jednak zarówno zmiany sposobu ich kształcenia, jak i ogromnej troski o podniesienie ich statusu zawodowego i materialnego. Z dużym zainteresowaniem przyjęliśmy zapowiedź utworzenia Europejskiej Akademii Nauczyciela, szczególnie po ewidentnym sukcesie styczniowego szczytu edukacyjnego. Pamiętajmy o słowach brytyjskiego pedagoga Johna Dewey’a: „Jeśli uczymy tak, jak uczyliśmy wczoraj, zabieramy naszym dzieciom jutro”.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-0000" speaker_id="124889" name="Agnieszka Kozłowska-Rajewicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autorka projektu opinii Komisji Zatrudnienia i Spraw Socjalnych. – Panie Przewodniczący! Przede wszystkim chciałabym pogratulować pani poseł Krystynie Łybackiej znakomitego sprawozdania. Ja jestem odpowiedzialna za przygotowanie opinii Komisji Zatrudnienia i Spraw Socjalnych i w tej opinii podkreślamy, że edukacja wysokiej jakości jest prawem każdego Europejczyka, a cele edukacji wykraczają daleko poza przygotowanie absolwentów do odnalezienia się na rynku pracy, choć ten cel w postaci rynku pracy jest oczywiście bardzo istotny.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zauważamy też, że digitalizacja i automatyzacja rynku pracy zmieniają rodzaj potrzebnych na rynku umiejętności. Zwiększa się zapotrzebowanie na zaawansowane umiejętności i zawody, w tym umiejętności cyfrowe, matematyczne, inżynieryjne, a zmniejsza na proste prace niewymagające kwalifikacji. Ten fakt państwa członkowskie powinny w końcu uwzględnić w swoich politykach edukacyjnych, które muszą skutecznie zwalczać zjawisko wtórnego analfabetyzmu i porzucania nauki, a także lepiej kształcić studentów szkół wyższych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podkreślamy również, że na rynku pracy rośnie zapotrzebowanie na umiejętności miękkie, które wymagają kształcenia praktycznego, otwartego, powiązanego z otoczeniem, oraz że kluczem do dobrej jakości edukacji są nauczyciele, jakość ich wykształcenia oraz wolność w wyborze programu i metod nauczania.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Tibor Navracsics" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, Madam Łybacka, I’m very pleased to have this debate with you today. You underline in your report the crucial role of education in shaping the future of Europe. I couldn’t agree more. The transformation of our societies and economies creates changing education realities that need urgent responses if we want to offer bright futures to all our young people. In fact, over the last year or so the topic of education has visibly moved up on the EU’s agenda.</p>
      <p sl="en">In March 2017, the Rome Declaration called for a Union where young people receive the best education and training and can study and find jobs across the continent. In November last year, EU leaders debated education at the Gothenburg Social Summit and adopted conclusions on the topic at the December European Council.</p>
      <p sl="en">With this mandate, the Commission has recently outlined its vision for a European education area where people can move freely to study, learn and train, and where we can offer high quality and innovative education for all our citizens. I thank you for your explicit support for the European education area.</p>
      <p sl="en">This project is based on three objectives. Firstly, to promote cross-border mobility and cooperation in education and training. Secondly, to remove unjustified obstacles that make it difficult to learn, train or work abroad. Our aim is to make the free movement of learners possible and to create a genuine European learning space. Thirdly, to support Member States in making their education and training systems more inclusive and innovative and to base them on the idea of lifelong learning.</p>
      <p sl="en">On 22 May 2018, we proposed a second set of concrete steps towards turning the vision of a European education area into reality following a first batch of proposals we tabled in January. In May, the Commission presented three proposals for Council recommendations.</p>
      <p sl="en">First, a recommendation on the automatic mutual recognition of higher education and upper secondary education diplomas and the outcomes of learning periods abroad. I firmly believe that we can only succeed in building a strong European identity if young people are free to study and learn in another EU country, unimpeded by administrative hurdles. Let us remove the recognition obstacle, at least inside the EU, once and for all.</p>
      <p sl="en">Second, we want a comprehensive approach to the teaching and learning of languages. Our societies, our economy and the European project itself depend on our citizens being able to communicate with each other. Alas, multilingualism is far from being a reality in the EU. It is high time we stepped up our efforts to be a truly multilingual Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Third, high-quality early childhood education and care systems. Evidence shows that if learning opportunities are missed at an early age, it takes much greater efforts to make up the deficit later. The Commission proposal aims to create a quality framework for early childhood education and care with the aim of giving all children the best possible start in life.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have outlined some key initiatives in support of the European education area. Let me mention just some them. First, the European universities. These will boost cross-border cooperation between higher education institutions. Higher education institutions which share the same vision and values will develop long-term institutional strategies for top quality education, research and innovation. The Commission aims to launch pilot projects in 2019 and 2020 under the Erasmus+ programme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Second, the European student card will simplify learning mobility by reducing administrative burdens and costs for students and educational institutions. The aim is to make it available to all Erasmus students by 2021 as a visible symbol of European student identity.</p>
      <p sl="en">Third, with the graduate tracking initiative, we have launched the first ever European survey of graduates in eight pilot countries, with initial results expected by the end of 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">All these initiatives build on the first proposals on the European education area we put forward in January. Back then, the Commission had launched an ambitious digital education action plan. This promotes digitalisation and innovation-driven approaches in education. A new European framework of key competences reminds us that we have to invest more in developing basic and digital skills, civic competencies and entrepreneurial attitudes, and we have to encourage more young people to study science, technology, engineering and mathematics.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the Council recommendation on promoting common values, inclusive education and the European dimension of teaching was also tabled in January and adopted by ministers in May. Never before has the EU said so clearly how important it is to promote our common values, to create a sense of belonging, to teach about the functioning values and origins of the European Union and, most importantly, to learn about the cultural and historical diversity of Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madam Łybacka your excellent report and its constructive recommendations come at just the right moment. On 30 May, we presented our proposals for the future Erasmus programme, which will continue to play a key role in delivering the objectives of the European education area.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me take this opportunity to warmly thank this House for your unwavering support for an ambitious Erasmus programme post 2020, with an increased budget that is proportionate to the size of our ambition. I agree that we need to make the programme more inclusive and accessible. Our proposal will allow 12 million people, more than ever before, to participate in different types of exchanges while reaching out to more people of all social backgrounds. In order to reach new groups of learners, the Commission proposes to increase support for school pupil mobility, mobility of learners in vocational education and training, and youth mobility.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, the Commission wants to provide more flexible formats for learning mobility, such as short-term and group activities and virtual mobility. We also want to make it easier for smaller and grassroots organisations to take part, in particular community-based organisations that work with disadvantaged learners of all ages.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank you, Madam Łybacka, for your excellent cooperation in drawing up this report. All of you are a key partner for us in supporting Member States in improving and modernising Europe’s education systems.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spravodajkyňa Výboru pre práva žien a rodovú rovnosť požiadaného o stanovisko. – Vážený pán predsedajúci, európske vzdelávanie sa musí usilovať predovšetkým o rozvoj uvažovania a premýšľania. Táto veta zo správy kolegyne Łybackej by mala byť vytesaná do kameňa. S mnohými návrhmi v správe súhlasím, ale rovnako ako navrhovateľka stanoviska vo výbore FEMM, pani Šojdrová, s niektorými som sa nestotožnila.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podporujem dôraz na učiteľov a ich odmeny vrátane problému feminizácie školstva, či otázky rovnakých príležitostí pre chlapcov a dievčatá a motiváciu dievčat pre niektoré odbory. Správa tiež kladie dôraz na tak potrebnú mediálnu gramotnosť, ktorá je najlepším dlhodobým prostriedkom, ako bojovať proti falošným správam a dezinformáciám a zvyšovať bezpečnosť detí na internete.</p>
      <p sl="en">V tejto správe teda správne vyzývame Komisiu a členské štáty, aby vytvorili zvláštne opatrenia na podporu projektov mediálnej a digitálnej gramotnosti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="124712" name="Andrea Bocskor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a PPE képviselőcsoport nevében. – Elnök Úr! Először is szeretném megköszönni Krystyna Łybackának a kiváló együttműködést a jelentés elkészítése során, egy nagyon jó és tartalmas jelentés született, gratulálok az elvégzett munkához. A jelentés hangsúlyozza az oktatás fontosságát, gazdasági és társadalmi szempontjait a megváltozott információs társadalomban. A fiatalkori munkanélküliség mértéke több tagországban továbbra is aggasztó, azonban a tudás és a képzettség még mindig a legnagyobb érték, a diplomások körében még mindig kisebb a munkanélküliek aránya, mint a képesítés nélküliek között.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ezért fontos, hogy a tagállamok a jelenlegi kihívásoknak megfelelően beruházzanak az oktatási rendszerek és infrastruktúra minőségének javításába, aktualizálják a tanterveket, hogy a diákok hasznos, alkalmazható és gyakorlatias tudást szerezhessenek. A jelentés hangsúlyozza a szakképzés és a duális képzés fontosságát, az oktatási intézmények és tartalmak összehangolását a munka világával, a munkaerőpiaci és jelenkori szükségletekkel, illetve a szakmunka presztízsének a növelését.</p>
      <p sl="en">Örülök annak, hogy a jelentésbe bekerült a nemzeti kisebbségek anyanyelvű oktatásának témaköre is, hisz az anyanyelv használatának joga az oktatás folyamatában a kisebbségek számára létkérdés. A jelentés kimondja, hogy a tagállamoknak nagyobb erőfeszítést kell tenniük annak érdekében, hogy az őshonos kisebbségekhez tartozó tanulók hozzáférjenek az oktatás valamennyi szintjéhez anyanyelvükön, és a kisebbségi nyelveken oktató intézmények kiemelt támogatásban részesüljenek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az ajánlásokba bekerültek a kulcskompetenciák teljes körének elsajátítása, mint az idegen nyelvek, digitális készségek, valamint a vállalkozói készségek, és nem utolsó sorban az egész életen át tartó tanulásnak a kompetenciája. A jelentés kiemelt figyelmet szentel a pedagógusoknak: a tagállamoknak ösztönözni kell a fiatalokat, hogy a pedagógiai szakmát válasszák, hogy újra vonzóvá és presztízsessé váljon a tanári szakma, és ebben a pedagógusképzésnek van kiemelt szerepe. A magyarországi jó példát követve, a jelentés ajánlásai közé bekerült, hogy a tagállamok tegyenek nagyobb erőfeszítést a korai, és kisgyermekkori oktatás hozzáféréséhez, tehát a tagállamok több óvodai és bölcsődei helyet biztosítsanak, főleg a hátrányos helyzetű családok gyermekei számára.</p>
      <p sl="en">A magyar kormány 2010-től számos kezdeményezést indított a kisgyermekkori nevelés és közoktatás területén, ingyenes iskolai étkeztetést, tankönyveket biztosít a diákok számára. Ez jó példa a korai felzárkóztatásra, amire sok államban szükség lenne. Remélem, a tisztelt Ház nagy többséggel fogja megszavazni ezt a jelentést!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">от името на групата S&amp;D. – Уважаеми г-н Наврачич, Подкрепих доклада на Кристина Либацка, защото смятам, че модернизирането на образованието е нещо, което не можем да продължаваме да отлагаме. Живеем във време, в което новите технологии и дигитализацията се развиват с бързи темпове и образователните системи трябва да бъдат в крак с тези развития. В противен случай нашите учебни заведения ще продължават да произвеждат бъдещи безработни и кадри, които не владеят уменията на ХХІ век.</p>
      <p sl="en">Когато говорим за модернизиране на образованието, това не трябва да се разбира като обновяване само на материалната база на учебните заведения и закупуване на модерна техника. Важно е да сме в крак с новите технологии, но те не гарантират на подрастващите, че ще могат да усвоят по-добре знания, умения и компетентности. Резултатите от международното изследване „Пиза“ показват, че наличието на модерна дигитална инфраструктура не повишава резултатите на учениците и това не е изненадващо.</p>
      <p sl="en">Проблемът с функционалната грамотност е добре познат и на българската система. Нашите ученици биват затрупани с огромни количества теоретични знания, което е за сметка на стимулирането на критично мислене. Нужен е холистичен подход, подход, който да взима под внимание и нуждите на нашите учители, защото без тях нито една реформа не може да бъде успешна. Отношението към тях е показателно за отношението към цялата образователна система.</p>
      <p sl="en">Повишаването на техните възнаграждения няма да реши проблемите с магическа пръчка. Те трябва да имат повече автономия и достъп до възможности за професионално развитие. За тази цел, обаче, не трябва да се разчита само на възможностите, предоставени от европейските програми. Не можем да очакваме от Брюксел да реши всичките ни проблеми. Нужна е национална политика в сферата на образованието. За съжаление у нас такава липсва, други са управленските приоритети в България. Жалкото е, че потърпевшите ще бъдат нашите деца.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="124794" name="Remo Sernagiotto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ECR. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, grazie ai colleghi ma soprattutto grazie alla relatrice che ci ha permesso di lavorare con serenità su un tema così importante: la modernizzazione dell'educazione. Noi crediamo di aver centrato quei punti che erano necessari, ma sono necessari nei paesi, nei nostri paesi, perché siamo paesi e siamo Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io credo che questa modernizzazione, che guarda con interesse le competenze linguistiche, guarda con grande interesse le competenze digitali e le competenze mediatiche, considerando che il contenitore scuola non è l'unico luogo dove si possono formare le persone, e guarda anche alla formazione permanente e all'istruzione permanente, sia il centro di tutto il nostro ragionamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voi sapete che come gruppo dell'ECR abbiamo presentato degli emendamenti e abbiamo cofirmato molti emendamenti su un tema a noi molto caro: la libertà e la scelta educativa, la famiglia – quella grande risorsa che forse per un periodo ci siamo dimenticati – e la comunità, capaci di partecipare in modo attivo.</p>
      <p sl="en">È chiaro che di fronte alla possibilità di insegnanti che possono formarsi e proporsi costantemente, non sotto il profilo della capacità di essere insegnanti e della capacità economica, ma di quella di partecipazione attiva, sono centrali nella formazione e nello sviluppo della nostra comunità. Ecco perché io credo che quando noi diciamo che la libertà e la scelta educativa competono alla famiglia, vuol dire che competono alla comunità. Non parlo delle comunità nazionali, ma oggi parlo della Comunità europea, che forse è la strada migliore per evitare quello che vediamo quotidianamente e quello che abbiamo visto soprattutto negli ultimi anni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allora, un grande impegno dell'Europa e questa è una relazione – grazie alla relatrice e a tutti quelli che hanno partecipato – importante e che guarda al futuro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor presidente, el paradigma de desarrollo que hemos elegido para mantener nuestras señas de identidad como Unión, para mantener nuestro liderazgo mundial y nuestro modelo social, se basa en un crecimiento sostenible, inteligente e integrador. Estas tres características se fabrican con conocimiento y valores. Por eso necesitan el respaldo de un sistema educativo flexible, en permanente transformación y centrado en ofrecer a las personas la formación que van a necesitar para incorporarse a la vida adulta en las mejores condiciones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que hay que subrayar más que todas las mejoras en materia educativa que exijamos a lo institucional, a lo público, solo funcionarán si asumimos lo que nos toca a cada uno como ciudadanos, como progenitores. No podemos dar por supuesto que cumplimos, y no hacerlo nos deslegitima para exigir nada a maestros, a profesores y al sistema en el que trabajan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Necesitamos una educación en igualdad. Sin estereotipos. Necesitamos capacitación digital, dominio del lenguaje visual, capacidad para desarrollar el pensamiento crítico y creativo y hábito para trabajar en equipo, combinando capacidades, aptitudes y conocimiento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tenemos que enseñar la diversidad como una fuente de valor que hay que respetar. Y, por supuesto, fomentar el pluralismo y la solidaridad. Porque esta es la base del crecimiento integrador que es la base de la estabilidad y la justicia social.</p>
      <p sl="en">El reto de alcanzar estos objetivos requiere invertir, para empezar, en las y los profesionales del ramo, revisar las herramientas que les ofrecemos para formarse y adaptarse a los cambios. Y ofrecerles la tecnología no como un fin sino como una herramienta al servicio de una profesión, de una inteligencia que nunca podrá ser artificial. Organizar todo el sistema pensando en la igualdad de oportunidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso estoy plenamente de acuerdo con extender el principio en que se basa el espacio europeo de educación superior al resto de los niveles educativos. Esa es la base del espacio educativo europeo al que se refiere este informe: facilitar la movilidad, el reconocimiento mutuo. Fomentar los intercambios de personas, profesores y estudiantes, y de buenas prácticas. Creo que este proceso permitiría avanzar hacia un concepto que necesitamos: el de talento europeo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="4550" name="Jill Evans" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur and express our support for this report. Quality education creates active and engaged citizens and increases the employability and mobility of young people, as well as contributing to building the economy as a whole.</p>
      <p sl="en">The modernisation of education systems across Europe is a pressing need, and one that must address deep structural challenges. It is the responsibility of Member States and devolved governments – such as we have in Wales, where full powers over education are devolved – to implement reforms, but the EU can assist their efforts. This report presents excellent recommendations on how to do that.</p>
      <p sl="en">One point that I especially welcome, and one that has been mentioned by several colleagues, is the importance given to the teacher as a guarantor of quality teaching. Earlier this year, I went with some others here on a study visit to Finland. Teachers there are highly trained and highly respected. To become a teacher, candidates must have passed at least a master’s degree, and many students try to be accepted on training courses for teachers and fail. It was clear that the status of teachers within society also changed the view of the value of education itself.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I am very glad that this report calls for measures to raise the status of the teacher. With the creation of the European Education Area under way, this is a crucial period where cooperation across the EU must be a priority. I hope that Wales, the country that I represent, will play its full part in these developments, and I will work towards that aim.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-0000" speaker_id="26851" name="Νικόλαος Χουντής" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Κύριε Επίτροπε, σήμερα στον τομέα της παιδείας, ως αποτέλεσμα των αντιλαϊκών και αντικοινωνικών πολιτικών που εφαρμόζονταν και εφαρμόζονται στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση αλλά και στα κράτη μέλη, παρατηρούμε τα εξής: γενική υποβάθμιση των πολιτικών εκπαίδευσης και υποχρηματοδότηση της δημόσιας παιδείας, συρρίκνωση των εργασιακών δικαιωμάτων των δασκάλων και των καθηγητών, αύξηση του ποσοστού των κοινωνικά αποκλεισμένων πολιτών και διόγκωση του φαινομένου του brain drain από την Ελλάδα και τις άλλες χώρες του Νότου, προώθηση του ατομικισμού σε βάρος της συλλογικής συνείδησης, εκπαιδευτικά συστήματα με κυρίαρχο σκοπό την εξυπηρέτηση των αναγκών της αγοράς εργασίας, συμμετέχοντες γεμάτους άγχος και ανησυχία λόγω της πολύ δύσκολης κατάστασης που θα αντιμετωπίσουν μετά τις σπουδές.</p>
      <p sl="en">Αυτές οι πολιτικές στο πλαίσιο των νεοφιλελεύθερων πολιτικών και των πολιτικών λιτότητας στοχεύουν στη δημιουργία ακόμα μεγαλύτερων ανισοτήτων και στην ακόμα μεγαλύτερη συγκέντρωση του πλούτου στα χέρια ολίγων. Ο εκσυγχρονισμός της εκπαίδευσης, για να είναι προς το συμφέρον των πολλών, πρέπει να έχει ως απαραίτητες προϋποθέσεις: γενναία αύξηση των δημόσιων δαπανών για τις πολιτικές εκπαίδευσης, εξασφάλιση πρόσβασης για όλους σε όλες τις βαθμίδες της εκπαίδευσης, εκπαιδευτικά συστήματα με επίκεντρο τους μαθητές και σπουδαστές και όχι τις επιταγές των αγορών και ενίσχυση των πολιτικών για την καταπολέμηση της ανεργίας των νέων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="124831" name="Isabella Adinolfi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario vorrei ringraziare la relatrice e i colleghi per l'ottimo lavoro svolto. Il testo finale rappresenta un buon compromesso politico su un tema che è cruciale per il futuro della nostra società, quello della modernizzazione dell'istruzione in Europa, dove il tasso di analfabetismo funzionale registra ancora un livello drammaticamente alto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono principalmente tre gli aspetti delle raccomandazioni rivolte alla Commissione e agli Stati membri che vorrei sottolineare in questa sede. Il primo riguarda il ruolo fondamentale degli investimenti pubblici. Senza un sistema di istruzione e formazione di qualità e all'avanguardia, infatti, non ci può essere un reale cambiamento che oggi, come non mai, è necessario per affrontare al meglio le sfide che il mondo globalizzato, gli avanzamenti tecnologici e le crisi economica e politica pongono.</p>
      <p sl="en">Di pari passo con gli investimenti pubblici va anche la lotta al precariato degli insegnanti, che sono i pilastri del sistema, ai quali vanno garantite condizioni di lavoro dignitose che non mortifichino più la loro decisiva attività che accompagna gli studenti dalla scuola preprimaria fino all'università e che garantisce che si formino cittadini critici e consapevoli.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il terzo aspetto, infine, concerne l'incremento di politiche di alfabetizzazione funzionale e mediatica. Si tratta di un aspetto di cui troppo poco si parla e che invece è cruciale. Sono convinta che serva una risposta comune nonché un serio piano di medio e lungo periodo e il testo approvato, a questo proposito, affronta la questione in modo appropriato, delineando delle buone soluzioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voglio chiudere dicendo che l'aspetto che mi rende maggiormente orgogliosa del lavoro svolto è il riconoscimento del diritto all'istruzione come diritto umano fondamentale, che va garantito a tutti, specialmente a coloro che si trovano in situazioni di difficoltà o di svantaggio, come per esempio i disabili o le persone che provengono da background difficili. Vorrei, cari colleghi, che a tutti fosse chiaro che nessuno deve rimanere indietro. Veramente nessuno.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, en 2000, la stratégie de Lisbonne prétendait hisser l’Union européenne au rang d’espace le plus compétitif, dynamique et basé sur la connaissance. Quatorze ans plus tard, la Commission fixait à 2020 l’âge d’or auquel 40 % d’une génération se verraient dotés d’un diplôme du supérieur et 85 % maîtriseraient les savoirs fondamentaux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las, les classements internationaux se suivent et se ressemblent et les chiffres sont têtus. Ainsi, le classement QS, publié le 6 juin dernier, ravale la première université d’Europe continentale – en excluant la Suisse – à la 50e place en se fondant sur l’opinion de quelque 42 000 employeurs. On peut certes s’insurger contre les critères utilisés, un peu comme face à la défaite d’un grand sportif – il est de bon ton de maudire la météo, la fraîcheur du gazon ou la partialité de l’arbitre. Reste que des tests Pisa, qui voient certaines régions européennes rivaliser avec des pays en développement, au délabrement de notre recherche, dont témoigne l’exode massif des chercheurs, tout confirme que, dans une concurrence mondiale féroce, l’Europe semble avoir rendu les armes. Comment pourrait-il en être autrement alors qu’à coup de lignes directrices, l’Union européenne n’a de cesse d’abreuver les États membres de lubies pédagogiques éculées sapant les fondements des traditions nationales séculaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense au totem des nouvelles technologies à l’école, alors que, de l’OCDE à l’Académie américaine de pédiatrie, tous reconnaissent désormais leur effet délétère sur les résultats scolaires et la santé mentale. Sans parler de la surconsommation de contenus en ligne pornographiques et violents ou des risques associés au cyber-harcèlement, dont les conséquences sur le développement psychique, émotionnel et affectif des jeunes sont parfois irréversibles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense également au mépris pour la hiérarchie entre le professeur et l’élève, qui résonne d’un écho cruel à l’heure où la peur est devenue un compagnon familier pour tant d’enseignants des banlieues perdues de la République française.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais le plus frappant est la contradiction flagrante entre l’aspiration à l’excellence et à la diversité. Ainsi, alors que plus de 15 % des chefs d’établissements défavorisés en France et en Belgique considèrent la diversité d’origine comme un obstacle à l’apprentissage, l’arrivée d’un nombre exponentiel de migrants dans les systèmes scolaires exsangues sera d’autant plus calamiteuse qu’elle n’a pour corollaire aucun effort d’assimilation, l’exigence de maîtrise de la langue cédant le pas à celle du multilinguisme. Les enseignants sont désormais enjoints d’encourager chez l’élève migrant la connaissance de sa langue maternelle. Il est loin le temps où venus des confins de Pologne ou d’Italie, des cohortes d’immigrés sacrifiaient leur langue et leur identité sur l’autel d’une nouvelle patrie porteuse d’espoir et de promotion sociale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Entre fracture scolaire et identitaire, l’école inclusive rêvée par Bruxelles sèmera les ferments du nivellement par le bas, du communautarisme et de la division.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Ubolewacie Państwo, że brakuje w wielu dziedzinach wykształconych specjalistów. Deklarujecie, że troską Unii jest to, żeby edukacja nadążała za potrzebami rynku pracy, a nie produkowała bezrobotnych. No i cóż w związku z tym w tej rezolucji proponujemy? No oczywiście zwalczanie stereotypów dotyczących płci, LGBT, zdrowie reprodukcyjne i seksualne, co wiemy, co to w waszej nowomowie oznacza, ale to jest najlepsze, pkt. 35, włączenie do programów szkolnych, nauczania i treści edukacyjnych wiedzy o historii emancypacji kobiet, w szczególności praw wyborczych dla kobiet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie wiem, z jakiej planety nadaje do nas autor tego tekstu, ale: Halo, tutaj Ziemia. Tutaj na Ziemi nie pytamy ludzi na rozmowach kwalifikacyjnych, co wiedzą o emancypacji kobiet i w szczególności o historii praw wyborczych. Tutaj pytamy o kompetencje. To nie jest żadna wiedza, to jest wasza propaganda, wasza lewicowa hagiografia, którą chcecie wtłaczać na siłę ludziom, którzy w wielu przypadkach nie będą podzielali waszych poglądów.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Edukacja wymaga modernizacji. Zaczynam od tego stwierdzenia, bo samo sprawozdanie brzmi „w sprawie modernizacji edukacji”. Tak, jakby to była kwestia otwarta. Nie, ona jest w sprawozdaniu przesądzona, po to abyśmy mogli być konkurencyjni, mogli być bogatsi, mogli być sprawniejsi i mieli pokolenie, które samo się realizuje – musi być modernizacja systemów edukacyjnych, samej edukacji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie wiem, czy jest to najbardziej adekwatne pojęcie, najbardziej właściwe słowo, ale bez wątpienia edukacja odpowiada na kluczowe wyzwania, nie tylko Europy, nie tylko społeczeństwa Europy, ale także świata. Trzeba pamiętać, że niedawno debatując tu na posiedzeniu właśnie Parlamentu w Strasburgu, mówiliśmy, że blisko 30 procent młodych ludzi do 25 roku życia jest albo bez pracy, albo bez edukacji, albo bez jednego i drugiego razem. To jest wyzwanie dla nas wszystkich, jak dojść do tej sytuacji, o której mówi sprawozdawczyni? No przede wszystkim łącząc programy modernizacyjne w tych grupach, które są wymienione w samym sprawozdaniu, to jest szkolnictwo wyższe, to są sami nauczyciele, to jest umiejętność także wykorzystywania zmian cywilizacyjnych, czyli także technologii, ale to także badania naukowe, jak i również lepsze reagowanie na zmieniające się potrzeby rynku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bardzo się cieszę, że podjęliśmy temat kluczowy z punktu widzenia wyzwań. To, co dla mnie jest najistotniejsze, to żeby te modele edukacyjne nie były wciśnięte w zbyt silną twardą matrycę – tak powinno być w naukach ścisłych, ale w humanistyce, w programach internetowych, tam, gdzie potrzeba jest kreatywności i twórczości, potrzeba także większej swobody.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="124788" name="Luigi Morgano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, mi associo ai complimenti già espressi per l'eccellente relazione della collega Krystyna Łybacka. La sua relazione di iniziativa è sicuramente una delle più importanti di questa legislatura per il tema che affronta. Le cose che hanno detto i colleghi e anche il Commissario danno ragione a questa mia affermazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">I cambiamenti in corso li conosciamo. Si tratta di prendere questi cambiamenti non come problemi, ma come sfide, e di affrontarli con un approccio davvero globale, coinvolgendo tutta la politica dell'istruzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se vogliamo creare uno Spazio europeo dell'istruzione e della formazione, nel rispetto del principio di sussidiarietà, è irrinunciabile un'istruzione universale di alta qualità. Questo però deve diventare anche una reale priorità politica degli Stati membri. È altresì fondamentale fornire un forte sostegno finanziario ad ogni livello, quindi alle scuole di ogni ordine e grado, sia pubbliche che private no profit, nella consapevolezza che investire nell'istruzione non è solo e non può essere solo un imperativo economico, ma che in un mondo peraltro globalizzato è uno dei fattori essenziali per il pieno sviluppo di ogni persona, in tutte le sue dimensioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">È giusto quindi, da un lato, ribadire i fondamentali, il diritto alla libertà di scelta educativa dei genitori, garantire a tutti i cittadini dell'Unione l'apprendimento delle competenze di base, comprese ovviamente quelle digitali, la parità di accesso a un'istruzione inclusiva e di qualità e anche come ascensore sociale e, dall'altro lato, porre l'accento sulle componenti invece cosiddette di modernizzazione, che riassumo brevemente: risorse didattiche e metodi di insegnamento che utilizzino le nuove opportunità, il tema dei disabili, fin dall'infanzia e non solo chi è stato trattato come elemento essenziale, il cosiddetto triangolo della conoscenza e il miglioramento del legame tra ricerca e insegnamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ci sarebbero varie cose da aggiungere. Mi permetto di concludere ricordando la centralità della figura dell'insegnante che deve essere da un lato garante e pietra angolare per il cambiamento del sistema di istruzione. Credo però che quello che è già emerso oggi dice di una forte volontà di tutto il Parlamento di procedere per la propria strada per arrivare ad una conclusione il più condivisa possibile.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="124815" name="Arne Gericke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Es geht um die Modernisierung der Bildung! Ich darf der Kollegin für den hervorragenden Bericht danken – wohl wissend, dass Bildungspolitik in nationaler, für uns in Deutschland sogar in regionaler Hand ist. Und dort soll sie auch bleiben. Das nur als Randnotiz an all die linken und liberalen Kollegen, die nun schon wieder meinen, Europa könnte nach allem greifen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich sage ihnen: „Schuster, bleib bei deinen Leisten!“ und danke schon mal allen Dolmetschern, deren hervorragende Bildung es möglich macht, dieses geflügelte Wort binnen Sekunden in dreiundzwanzig Sprachen zu dolmetschen – danke schön! Und gleichzeitig, Vorsicht: Verlieren wir uns nicht im Wolkenkuckucksheim, wir, die wir über den Bericht abstimmen und gleichzeitig im Büro, im Saal modernste Technik haben! Das ist nicht unbedingt die Realität an Europas Schulen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moderner Unterricht, auch der digitale, funktioniert nur im gegebenen Rahmen. Hinzu kommt: Eine Maschine allein macht keine Bildung. Nehmen wir unsere Lehrkräfte mit, bilden wir sie fort, überfordern wir sie nicht mit Schnapsideen à la Digi-Doro die in jedem Hausmeister den Programmierer sieht und am liebsten im Flugtaxi zur Schule düst. Bleiben wir mit beiden Beinen auf dem Boden! Das sage ich hier auch im Namen aller Bürgermeister. Ideen kosten nichts, ihre Umsetzung sehr wohl! Das müssen die Kommunen schultern, und dafür brauchen sie volle Unterstützung von Bund, Land und Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Ungdomsarbetslösheten är ett av de största problemen vi har i alla europeiska samhällen. Ungdomarna hör till dem som har drabbats hårdast av den finansiella och ekonomiska krisen och har fallit ut först från arbetsmarknaden med sina tillfälliga kontrakt. De har drabbats mest av det sociala utanförskapet och nu börjar de till och med att rösta på de partier som vi inte vill se i våra samhällen. Anledningen till det är väldigt ofta att de har bristfällig utbildning som inte tillåter att de får fäste på arbetsmarknaden, och det är enligt Pisa-studien alldeles drastiskt: en av fem ungdomar har svårigheter att läsa och förstå text. Därför är det nödvändigt att vi åtminstone tar tag i problemet på europeisk nivå och försöker hjälpa nationalstaterna att göra någonting åt det, även om de är de som måste göra det. Annars kommer vi att förlora en hel generation och det har vi inte råd med.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-0000" speaker_id="125193" name="Eleonora Forenza" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, esprimo soddisfazione per questa relazione che riporta la parola modernizzazione al suo corretto significato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io vengo da un paese, l'Italia, in cui la parola modernizzazione associata a educazione ha avuto il sapore di un incubo negli ultimi vent'anni: le tre "i" di Letizia Moratti, per non parlare della buona scuola di Matteo Renzi. Modernizzazione ha significato distruzione del sistema pubblico di istruzione, ha significato dequalificazione degli insegnanti, ha significato tagli alla spesa pubblica per la scuola e la scuola come educazione allo sfruttamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Io credo che invece occorra parlare di modernizzazione dell'istruzione, esattamente appunto come educazione alla sessualità, come educazione alle differenze, e utilizzare una prospettiva di genere in tutte le materie di insegnamento. Occorre rimettere gli insegnanti al centro della scuola, come sta facendo ad esempio la LIP, la legge di iniziativa popolare per le scuola. Occorre finanziare un sistema d'istruzione libero, gratuito, laico e di massa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-145-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, despite ever-faster changes in economic and social life, one truth has remained constant over the years: quality education is as crucial as ever for the well-being of individuals and for society as a whole. Providing for it is one of the best investments a society can make.</p>
      <p sl="en">Member States are primarily responsible for their education, and there are wide disparities among them. According to a recent World Bank document, Romania’s education system is failing: 40% of Romanian students are functionally illiterate, and one in five children drop out of school. Adding to this, the skills of the workforce have not kept up with the increasing sophistication of the economy and the switch in exports from labour-intensive to high-technology sectors.</p>
      <p sl="en">To advance from situations such as this, Member States will need EU support to drive reforms in their social and education systems. I am hopeful that through pushes from the Semester process, and with instruments such as the ESF and the SRSP, we will be able to move on together. In this drive, it is essential that we insist on education systems that are truly inclusive and accessible to all people, irrespective of their social, ethnic or linguistic background.</p>
      <p sl="en">I fully agree with the report’s recommendation for Member States to ensure access to mother-tongue education at all levels for pupils from autochthonous minorities. The EU used to request this before accession; it should continue to do so today, especially because we see that many Member States currently pursue policies in full contradiction of their pre-accession promises.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-0000" speaker_id="125112" name="Γιώργος Γραμματικάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, σήμερα συζητάμε για το μέλλον της παιδείας και για το πώς μπορεί η Ευρώπη να ενισχύσει τον υποστηρικτικό της ρόλο. Χαίρομαι πολύ γιατί η συνάδελφός μου κυρία Łybacka στην Επιτροπή Πολιτισμού και Παιδείας είδε με βάθος και τόλμη τα προβλήματα της παιδείας και έδωσε τις σωστές κατευθύνσεις για το μέγιστο αυτό ευρωπαϊκό θέμα.</p>
      <p sl="en">Πέρα από τα συνηθισμένα αλλά σημαντικά θέματα, όπως είναι η στενότερη συνεργασία των Πανεπιστημίων αλλά και η κινητικότητα καθηγητών και σπουδαστών, θα μου επιτρέψετε να δώσω ιδιαίτερη έμφαση στους στόχους χρηματοδότησης που πρέπει να ανέρχεται τουλάχιστον στο 5% του ΑΕΠ των κρατών μελών μέχρι το 2025. Η Ευρώπη χρειάζεται τον στόχο αυτό αν θέλουμε να μιλήσουμε σοβαρά για τη σύγκλιση και για την οικονομική ανάπτυξη παντού χωρίς αποκλεισμούς. Τα στοιχεία μπορούν να εξηγήσουν πολύ πειστικά γιατί χρειάζεται ο στόχος αυτός: από τη Ρουμανία που δαπανά μόνο το 3% και την Ελλάδα που μόλις ξεπερνάει το 4% – και αυτό με επιφυλάξεις – είναι τεράστια η απόσταση μέχρι το 6,5% του Βελγίου και το 7% της Δανίας και συγχαίρω τις χώρες αυτές.</p>
      <p sl="en">Είναι λοιπόν σαφές ότι σε μια ενιαία αγορά οι ισορροπίες αυτές πλήττουν τους πιο αδύναμους. Καθώς η συζήτηση για τον επόμενο πολυετή προϋπολογισμό της Ένωσης έχει ξεκινήσει, πρέπει να διεκδικήσουμε τα επενδυτικά εργαλεία της επόμενης περιόδου, τα οποία πρέπει να είναι επαρκώς προσανατολισμένα στον μέγιστο στόχο της παιδείας. Πολύ σωστά η εισηγήτρια δίνει έμφαση και ιδιαίτερη προσοχή στην προσχολική αγωγή. Στα σχολεία τα προγράμματα πρέπει να εστιάσουν στις ανάγκες του μαθητή και όχι του δασκάλου. Επίσης είναι αξιόλογη η πρόταση της εισηγήτριας, την οποία και στηρίζω, για τη δημιουργία ενός ευρωπαϊκού δικτύου πανεπιστημίων, ώστε να καταστεί ο ευρωπαϊκός χώρος εκπαίδευσης καινοτόμος, ζωτικός και ελκυστικός, όπως αρμόζει στη σωστή παιδεία.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="124689" name="Νεοκλής Συλικιώτης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, χαιρετίζουμε την προσέγγιση της έκθεσης, η οποία αντιλαμβάνεται τα σχολεία ως αυτόνομα κέντρα τόνωσης της κριτικής και δημιουργικής σκέψης και προώθησης των δημοκρατικών αξιών και της ενεργού συμμετοχής στα κοινά. Είναι θέση μας πως η εκπαίδευση πρέπει να παραμένει ευθύνη του κράτους και να είναι ανθρωποκεντρική. Το σχολείο θα πρέπει να παραμείνει ένα θεμελιώδες μαθησιακό περιβάλλον ανάπτυξης των δυνατοτήτων των νέων, που θα παρέχει ίσες ευκαιρίες και εξίσωση των δυνατοτήτων επιτυχίας για όλα τα παιδιά και τους νέους.</p>
      <p sl="en">Την ίδια ώρα πρέπει να προστατευτεί η εκπαίδευση από την επιβολή των κανόνων της αγοράς και των συμφερόντων των πολυεθνικών εταιρειών που θεσμοθετούν την επισφάλεια στην εργασία και προωθούν τη διάλυση των εργασιακών σχέσεων. Απάντηση στην τεράστια ανεργία των νέων παραμένει η ρήξη με τις νεοφιλελεύθερες πολιτικές. Χρειαζόμαστε αύξηση των δαπανών για την παιδεία και αύξηση των δημόσιων επενδύσεων οι οποίες θα εντάσσουν τους νέους απόφοιτους ομαλά στον κόσμο της εργασίας και θα τους διασφαλίζουν αξιοπρεπείς θέσεις εργασίας με πλήρη εργασιακά δικαιώματα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-0000" speaker_id="124930" name="Pál Csáky" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök úr, biztos úr! Az oktatás unióbeli korszerűsítésének kérdését nagyon fontos dokumentumnak tartom, és egyértelműen támogatom. Látnunk kell, hogy az oktatás felkarolása, az oktatásügyi kihívások prioritásként kezelése egy olyan pillér, amelyre Európa versenyképessége a jövőben is épülhet. A dokumentum alaptéziseivel teljesen azonosulni tudok. Ezek a következők: a minőségi oktatás szükségességének hangsúlyozása, az ehhez szükséges feltételek megteremtése és összehangolása uniós és tagállami szinten, a felsőoktatási intézmények közötti együttműködés különböző elemeinek támogatása, a nyelvi és intézményi kompetenciák növelésének lehetősége, az egész életen át való tanulás fontosságának hangsúlyozása, valamint számos modern és innovatív elem bevonása az oktatási folyamatokba.</p>
      <p sl="en">Örülök annak is, hogy a dokumentum odafigyel a kisebbségek soraiból származó diákok anyanyelven történő oktatására is. Ez az elem azért is fontos, mert ebben az évben ez már a második dokumentum, amely a kisebbségek oktatásával is hangsúlyosan foglalkozik az Európai Parlament szintjén. Emlékeztetni szeretnék rá, hogy az Európai Parlament idén február hetedikén megszavazta „a kisebbségek védelme és hátrányos megkülönböztetésük tiltása az EU tagállamaiban” című határozatot, amely szintén hangsúlyozza, hogy a kisebbségek védelme európai szintű felelősség is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Méltányolom, hogy az egyébként nagyon komplex felépítésű jelentés támogatja a regionális és kisebbségi nyelvek oktatásának és használatának előmozdítását is. Mivel magam is egy őshonos európai kisebbségi közösségből jövök, tudom, hogy ez kiemelten fontos, és remélem, hogy országom, Szlovákia is megfogadja majd ennek a dokumentumnak az ajánlásait, a kisebbségi intézmények és a kisebbségi pedagógusok plusz anyagi támogatására is.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-0000" speaker_id="125099" name="Liliana Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, o nosso compromisso neste relatório - desde já os parabéns à minha colega - é o compromisso com o desenvolvimento do raciocínio, da reflexão e da curiosidade científica dos nossos jovens.</p>
      <p sl="en">É um compromisso com orientação para a vida profissional tendo como horizonte a entrada no mundo do trabalho. É uma educação que defendemos, que se deve preocupar em informar a partir da realidade concreta da vida local, do país, mas também da comunidade internacional.</p>
      <p sl="en">A modernização da educação na Europa não pode ser induzida de fora. Ela consiste num processo de dentro, o que implica reflexão e crítica. A verdadeira inovação da educação não está em termos somente de “mais tecnologia”, mas está em sermos capazes de mudar as práticas pedagógicas e isto não se faz sem os professores. São eles que podem fazer da educação uma ferramenta de combate à discriminação, nomeadamente à de género.</p>
      <p sl="en">A educação foi quem mais pagou a crise. Por isso, o apoio financeiro público contínuo deve ser acrescido. Daí que não compreenda os cortes, os presentes cortes, no Fundo Social Europeu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Acima de tudo devemos garantir um ensino que seja livre, público e gratuito. Modernizar a educação é livrarmo-nos do modelo fabril e das linhas de montagem que marcaram a escola do século XIX. Sabemos que a escola ainda é, ou ainda pode ser, o lugar onde não se certificam apenas conhecimentos, mas posições de classe e de género.</p>
      <p sl="en">A igualdade não é, por isso, um tema menor na educação, é uma questão de justiça, é uma questão de democracia, é uma questão de liberdade. Se assumirmos que a escola pode ser um lugar de reprodução social, e isso acontece de facto, então estaremos em posição de perseguir aquilo que mais nos une: a igualdade de existir e de ser quem somos.</p>
      <p sl="en">É urgente a União Europeia repensar a educação. Essa modernização da educação europeia será tão mais célere quanto mais formos capazes de refletir sobre a função social da escola e sobre a democracia.</p>
      <a text="(A oradora aceita responder a uma pergunta formulada ao abrigo do procedimento “cartão azul” (artigo 162.º, n.º 8, do Regimento))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. – Mówiła Pani, że musimy pomóc dzieciom w przyszłości przygotować się do wejścia na rynek pracy, ale moje pytanie jest takie: a skąd Pani wie jakie umiejętności będą za 10 lat potrzebne ludziom do wejścia na rynek pracy? Czy ktokolwiek na tej sali to wie? I czy ktokolwiek z tych osób, które będą o tym decydować to wie? Skąd macie taką wiedzę? Nikt nie wie, co będzie za 10 lat potrzebne. I proszę nie mówić, że naszym celem jest równość, to Pani celem jest równość. Moim celem jest równouprawnienie. I edukacja nie ma prawa narzucać poglądów jednej strony sali drugiej stronie sali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-0000" speaker_id="125099" name="Liliana Rodrigues" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Resposta segundo o procedimento "cartão azul". – Senhor Deputado, lamento que não saiba quais são as competências que se espera para os jovens da União Europeia daqui a dez anos. Isso está muito bem plasmado, por exemplo, nos objetivos da OCDE e da própria União, e portanto não é difícil, através da educação profissional, imaginar quais serão as saídas de mercado de trabalho para os jovens europeus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em relação à questão que põe da igualdade, só quem não percebe de educação é que julga que a educação para os valores, nomeadamente a igualdade, não pode ser concebida na sala de aula.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-0000" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, jos haluamme vahvistaa ihmisten hyvinvointia Euroopassa, rakentaa vakaata yhteiskuntaa eri jäsenmaihin ja taata taloudellisesti menestyvän Euroopan, meidän tulee vahvistaa komission toimivaltaa ja kompetenssia ja yhteistä koordinaatiota koulutuspolitiikan alueella, koska tarvitsemme merkittävästi lisää resursseja ja lisää laatua koulutukseen. Tämä tarkoittaa, että on lähdettävä liikkeelle opettajien koulutuksesta. Peruskoulutuksen tasoa on nostettava kaikissa jäsenmaissa, kuten myös ammatillisen koulutuksen ja yliopistokoulutuksen tasoa, ja on lisättävä resursseja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tämä on kansainvälisestikin jatkuva juoksu, jossa on kirittävä tahtia, jotta pysyttäisiin kärjessä. Tämän ja myös yhteisten työmarkkinoiden toteuttamiseksi tarvitsemme nykyistä parempaa elinikäisen oppimisen mallia, parempaa koulutuksen harmonisaatiota ja myös mittarit eurooppalaiseen lukukauteen siitä, kuinka eri jäsenmaat ovat koulutuspolitiikassaan onnistuneet ja miten tähän on suunnattu resursseja.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am pleased that this report does not overlook the importance of early childhood education. The evidence is clear that access to high—quality pre-school and early years provision has a positive impact on educational progression and life chances, and that is why it is such a scandal that in the UK the Conservative Government has cut the Early Years budget by GBP 500 million, meaning the door is closing to hundreds of Sure Start children’s centres. Properly funded high-quality early years provision should be the bedrock of our education systems.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also need to see a continued focus on apprenticeships and vocational learning. Those routes are not second-class. They are as important for our economic competitiveness in the future as degrees and PhDs. On Friday, I was at Silverstone, the iconic home of British motor sports, but also the home of the Silverstone University Technical College, equipping young people with the skills and ambition to graduate to high-level apprenticeships at Formula 1 racing teams.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, this report rightly acknowledges that education is also about broadening horizons and encouraging a positive sense of global citizenship. De Montfort University in my constituency is a trailblazer in this, giving its students once in a lifetime opportunities to learn and engage with communities right across the world through its unique DMU Global programme. Let’s not ever forget in this Parliament, our national parliaments, or indeed in regional local government as well, that every young person everywhere has the right, regardless of their background, to achieve their full potential and their aspirations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="129256" name="Emilian Pavel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, dragi colegi, în primul rând aș dori să o felicit pe colega mea, doamna Lybacka, pentru acest raport excelent și pentru munca depusă. Alături de Noua agendă europeană pentru competențe, acest raport reprezintă o viziune completă asupra educației și formării în Europa. Da, stimate coleg, toate statele membre au competențe depline asupra implementării și dezvoltării sistemelor educaționale în țările lor. Însă cred că putem cădea cu toții de acord că un set de principii sănătoase și ancorate în realitate pentru o piață unică europeană sunt de mare folos. Susțin pe deplin prioritatea-cheie a Pilonului european al drepturilor sociale de a asigura o educație, o formare profesională și o învățare pe tot parcursul vieții incluzive și de înaltă calitate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Însă, ca membru al Comisiei pentru ocuparea forței de muncă și afaceri sociale, aș dori să subliniez faptul că formarea profesională nu a primit aceeași atenție și aceleași investiții ca educația superioară în multe state membre. De aceea, aș vrea, cu această ocazie, să atrag încă un semnal de alarmă pentru a remedia acest lucru de urgență. Mai mult, ca un mare susținător al sinergiilor între educația formală, non-formală și informală, rog statele membre să accelereze eforturile de a pune în aplicare Recomandarea Consiliului privind validarea învățării non-formale și informale până la finalul anului 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Susțin, de asemenea, crearea unui spațiu european al educației, dar și al unui spațiu al învățământului superior, astfel cum a fost prezentat la summitul social din Göteborg în anul 2017. Însă insist ca propunerile europene să stimuleze cooperarea și să evite orice clivaje interregionale. Nu în ultimul rând, vă rog să susțineți recunoașterea perioadelor de studiu în străinătate, așa cum am propus alături de mulți colegi din acest Parlament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-0000" speaker_id="96933" name="Milan Zver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Najprej zahvale in pa čestitke Krystyni Łybacki za tako dobro pripravljeno poročilo. Tudi sam sem v zadnjih letih v svojih poročilih, začenši z Mladi in mobilnost in drugimi, zelo poudarjal ta zelo ključen pomen, to je modernizacija evropskih izobraževalnih sistemov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vesel sem tudi, da vse bolj prihaja naprej spoznanje, da je kakovost izobraževanja ključna, ne samo pri ohranjanju in dvigovanju gospodarske rasti in drugih gospodarskih kazalcev, ampak tudi in predvsem za … ključna pri ohranjanju načina življenja – evropskega, njene kulture in pa vrednot. Vesel sem tudi, da evropske inštitucije polagajo zadnja leta veliko več pozornosti, tako z denarjem, izobraževanju – tako z denarjem kakor tudi z mehanizmi, ki vplivajo na modernizacijo izobraževalnih sistemov v državah članicah.</p>
      <p sl="en">In ne nazadnje veselim se že sodelovanja pri snovanju novega programa za leto 2021 do 2027.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, a future—proofed education system should ensure the right of people of all ages and backgrounds, including refugees and migrants, to access quality education in a variety of indoor and outdoor learning environments, in informal, non—formal and lifelong learning, and including subjects such as learning for sustainability, social entrepreneurship and media literacy. In a fast-changing world we are asked to equip learners with skills which do not yet exist, and that’s why transferable and social skills are absolutely key in order to encourage and develop lifelong learning.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also need a strong commitment to training the trainers. The education agenda must not only look at training future workers, but also future active, responsible and open citizens. I believe education must be part of a broader reflection on occupational literacy in the context of growing digitisation and robotisation of European societies. We must focus not only on economic growth, but on learners’ personal development, improved health and well-being, including sex and relationship education for healthy relationships.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, a modernização da educação não se faz de meras intenções e teorizações.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não é possível uma escola moderna com o desinvestimento público que os senhores impõem desde o semestre europeu e reformas estruturais orientadas para a privatização e a liquidação do ensino e resultando na dramática degradação do parque escolar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não é possível uma escola moderna onde se eclipsa a pedagogia enfiando 30 alunos por turma em nome da racionalização dos recursos financeiros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não é possível uma escola moderna no desprezo e desrespeito pelos professores sem as dezenas de milhares que em Portugal foram despedidos durante a troica que vocês impuseram ou fazendo desaparecer 9 anos, 4 meses e 2 dias de carreira para cumprir metas economicistas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma escola moderna só poderá existir alavancada na escola pública gratuita e de qualidade como garante da igualdade e da superação das barreiras económicas, a par do respeito pelos profissionais do sector e das suas condições laborais valorizando salários e reduzindo horários de trabalho.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η εκπαίδευση των νέων αποτελούσε ήδη από την αρχαιότητα βασική μέριμνα όλων των κρατών που ήθελαν να δημιουργήσουν μορφωμένους νέους, με ήθος και με δυνατότητες, ούτως ώστε να μπορέσουν να εξασφαλίσουν την επιβίωση του κράτους και του έθνους. Αυτή η ανάγκη υπάρχει και στη σημερινή εποχή. Βεβαίως έχουν μεταβληθεί οι απαιτήσεις και οι νέες απαιτήσεις επιβάλλουν και αλλαγή πολιτικής στο θέμα της εκπαιδεύσεως αλλά και βέβαια εκσυγχρονισμό της εκπαιδεύσεως.</p>
      <p sl="en">Βλέπουμε ότι λόγω της αυξήσεως των δαπανών και των διδάκτρων είναι πολύ περιορισμένη η δυνατότητα πρόσβασης των φοιτητών στην τριτοβάθμια εκπαίδευση σε όλη την Ευρώπη και κυρίως στη Νότιο Ευρώπη και στην Ελλάδα. Επίσης στην πράξη έχει απαξιωθεί οποιαδήποτε γνώση των νέων. Οι νέοι υποχρεούνται να επιλέξουν εργασίες διαφορετικές από τις σπουδές που έκαναν, να επιλέξουν θέσεις απασχόλησης με απαξιωτικές συνθήκες εργασίας και αποδοχές ή να μείνουν άνεργοι. Όλα αυτά πρέπει να αντιμετωπιστούν. Το κάθε κράτος οφείλει να μεθοδεύσει την εκπαίδευση των νέων του, να διαθέσει τα απαραίτητα κονδύλια και στο τέλος να υπάρξει και μια συνεργασία σε πανευρωπαϊκό επίπεδο. Αν δεν γίνει αυτό, κινδυνεύουμε να καταστρέψουμε και την παρούσα γενεά αλλά και τις επόμενες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="28141" name="Lívia Járóka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Úr! Meg szeretném dicsérni mind a jelentéstevőt, mind a Bizottságnak a hozzáállását, az elmúlt években volt előre mozdulás, hisz Európa jövőjének a munkásait legszegényebb családokból érkező gyerekek fogják adni, ezért a digitalizáció, a korai gyermekfejlesztés, amiről biztos úr beszélt, és a szolgáltatások kibővítése és a szegregáció megszüntetése mind a Bizottságnak a céljai közé tartozik, ez pedig nagyon-nagyon üdvözlendő. Ezekben a közösségekben a gyerekek nem beszélnek nyelveket, nem tudnak írni és olvasni még sokszor 15 éves korukban sem, és számolni sem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ezért Magyarországon olyan új programokat próbáltunk elindítani, amik igenis bent tartják a leszakadókat, és most már a kutatások azt mutatják 15 éves gyerekeknél, hogy hat-hét éves korban eltűnnek a különbözőségek, hogyha tényleg az az oktatási és bölcsőderendszer, amiről biztos úr és a Bizottság beszélt, megvalósul. Egyetlenegy pont van, amit még hozzá szeretnék tenni, ha megengedik, most a középiskolai oktatásnál, a duális képzésnél azt tapasztaljuk, hogy a cégeknek, akiknek ezek a gyerekek a munkásaik lesznek, sokkal inkább részt kell, hogy vegyenek mind a finanszírozás, mind a tehetséggondozásban.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-161-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, în primul rând și eu vreau să o felicit pe raportoare și pe Comisie. Este un subiect extrem de important. Cine poate contesta că educația nu are legătură cu societatea noastră, cu modernizarea societății, cu pacea, până la urmă, cu comportamentul cetățenilor în societate? De aceea, cred că trebuie să ne gândim - și știm că este subsidiaritate, dar trebuie să ne gândim și la nivel de Uniune Europeană - cum putem să modernizăm educația.</p>
      <p sl="en">Avem metode de multe ori învechite. Nu trebuie să ne mai bazăm pe memorare, trebuie să ne bazăm pe vocație, să identificăm încă din clasele primare ce abilități au copiii, să dezvoltăm dragostea pentru meserie și, sigur, trebuie să ne gândim la mediul rural, domnule comisar. Ce facem acolo? Pentru că profesorii nu prea merg în mediul rural, nu avem profesori, avem suplinitori, de fapt necalificați. Cum să facă educație la copii? Iar în facultate este deja târziu. Și mai este foarte important să ne gândim cum corelăm educația cu nevoia din economie, pentru că suntem într-o dezvoltare economică și trebuie să ținem cont de noile meserii de care avem nevoie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-162-0000" speaker_id="188906" name="Francis Zammit Dimech" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sur President, la qed nitkellmu fuq il-modernizzazzjoni tal-edukazzjoni, naħseb li għandna wkoll nirriflettu fuq ir-realtajiet li qed ngħixu fihom illum. Realtà importanti hu dwar il-metodu kif in-nies jikkomunikaw ma’ xulxin. In-nies qed jikkomunikaw iktar permezz tal-istampi, aktar metodi viżwali. U għalhekk illi jien ipproponejt rigward dan ir-rapport, li nagħmlu enfażi dwar il-ħiliet viżwali, jiġifieri li nitkellmu dwar il-litteriżmu viżwali, għaliex dan huwa kunċett li qed jingħata ħafna importanza, anke f’ċerti pajjiżi oħra bħall-Istati Uniti tal-Amerika u nemmen li huwa importanti fl-Ewropa wkoll.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qed insemmu wkoll l-edukazzjoni bikrija, hawnhekk mhux biss hemm bżonn edukazzjoni bikrija b’xejn imma li tkun ta’ kwalità, għaliex huma l-fażi ta’ formazzjoni. Għalliema, il-ħtieġa ta’ opportunitajiet, ta’ kundizzjonijiet adegwati, għaliex mingħajr għalliema lanqas biss ikollok edukazzjoni, aħseb u ara kemm ikollok il-modernizzazzjoni tagħha. U fl-aħħar nett, irridu ngħinu liż-żgħażagħ jagħmlu dak it-traġitt, anke mill-qasam vokazzjonali għal dak professjonali.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first I would like to congratulate the Commissioner for his good work in this area. It is obviously crucial for us. As everybody knows, education is the way to the future and, if we want to be competitive in Europe, we will have the highest standard of education in the world. As some speakers have said, we have to start with the young, but above all we must start with teachers. As a former teacher myself, I realise how important teaching is.</p>
      <p sl="en">One area where we need to put more emphasis is allowing teachers to have access to continuing professional development (CPD). There is not enough opportunity for them to do that on a professional basis, as distinct from a voluntary basis, and that will make a huge difference. As well as that, we have been putting emphasis in Ireland on the STEM subjects in recent times, and that needs to continue. We especially need to encourage girls into the STEM subjects, and bodies like the voluntary group, CoderDojo, are doing tremendous work to encourage people at a very young age with skills in that area to develop them. So education is the way to the future. The more we can do, the better.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Tibor Navracsics" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it was very good to hear during the debate that there was broad and strong consensus on the future of education. We share the same ideas and the same objectives. It is a very good starting point for a future collaboration. Digital skills, critical thinking, lifelong learning, skills—oriented education, the role of teachers in the future of education, the quality of education and the role of preschool education – these are the pillars of the future vision of education, and this is a very solid foundation for our future collaboration.</p>
      <p sl="en">This consensus bears fruit, because we have experienced a spectacular development at European level in education since 2014. Education is now at the top of the EU’s political agenda, and decision-makers and politicians share the ideas of the future European Education Area and the European Universities project. I thank you for your support. I really think that we have to continue this cooperation in the future. I thank Ms Łybacka for this report, and I look forward to working with you in the future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-0000" speaker_id="124883" name="Krystyna Łybacka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Edukacja to prawo podstawowe. Edukacja to klucz do wszelkiego rozwoju. Ale dzisiejsza dyskusja pokazała, że edukacja ma jeszcze jeden ogromny walor. Edukacja potrafi łączyć nas wszystkich niezależnie od różnic politycznych. Tak, ponieważ odpowiedzialność za wychowanie przyszłego pokolenia spoczywa na każdym z nas niezależnie, z jakiej jesteśmy opcji, niezależnie z jakiego pochodzimy kraju, przy oczywiście wolności edukacyjnej, przy zachowaniu wręcz indywidualnego procesu kształcenia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bardzo za tę dyskusję dziękuję. Dziękuję wszystkim koleżankom i kolegom. Dziękuję Panie Komisarzu za Pańską aktywność proedukacyjną. Bardzo dziękuję Komisji za tę dużą liczbę komunikatów i nam wszystkim życzę, aby europejscy nauczyciele odpowiedzieli tak jak w ostatnim badaniu nauczyciele chińscy na pytanie młodych ludzi: kim chcesz zostać w przyszłości? Odpowiedź pierwsza brzmiała: nauczycielem. A kim chciałbyś zostać gdybyś nie mógł zostać nauczycielem? Odpowiedź brzmiała: nauczycielem. A więc dbajmy o przyszłość edukacji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le débat est clos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le vote aura lieu mardi 12 juin 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Déclarations écrites (article 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-1250" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Pirmiausia, norėčiau pabrėžti, jog demografiniai ir socialiniai Europos iššūkiai, darbo rinkos reikalavimai, naujosios technologijos, asmeniniai prioritetai ir mokymosi poreikiai lemia švietimo pokyčių tendencijas. Svarbu, kad švietimo sistemos atsižvelgtų į šiuos veiksnius ne tik siekdamos pasiūlyti kokybiškų žinių, bet ir atitinkamų kompetencijų, įskaitant sėkmingo mokymosi visą gyvenimą įgūdžius. Technologijų plėtra ir globalizacijos procesai kelia naujų iššūkių. Jie taip pat apima švietimo sistemas. Švietimo sistemų užduotis informacinėje visuomenėje – ne tik žinių ir jų taikymo įgūdžių perdavimas, bet ir mokymas kurti žinias, kurios yra konkurencingumo ir piliečių gerovės šaltinis bei svarbiausias ekonominis išteklius. Pritariu Komisijos sumanymui sukurti Europos švietimo erdvę. Vis dėlto reikia pažymėti, kad ši erdvė turi derėti su iki šiol pasiektais Europos aukštojo mokslo erdvės ir Europos mokslinių tyrimų ir inovacijų erdvės rezultatais. Be to, Europos švietimo erdvei turi būti skirta tvirta politinė parama iš valstybių narių, kurių bendros pastangos suteiks naują paskatą švietimo plėtrai, kartu užtikrinant subsidiarumo principo laikymąsi, švietimo laisvę ir institucijų savarankiškumą. Taigi, ragina valstybes nares ir regionines valdžios institucijas daugiau investuoti į švietimą, panaudojant Europos Sąjungos struktūrinius ir investicinius fondus, tai pat teikti mokytojams ir mokyklų vadovams paramą šiuolaikinių technologijų srityje ir rengiant į mokinį orientuotus mokymo metodus, užtikrinančius aukštą švietimo kokybę, matuojamą sukauptomis žiniomis ir įgytais įgūdžiais, kūrybiškumu ir gebėjimu mokytis visą gyvenimą.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-2500" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I would like to reiterate the vital importance of education, not just for nowadays society but also for building a better future for the generations to come. Sustainable development cannot be reached without a solid educational base, adapted to the current framework in order to provide the necessary knowledge and skills to address the contemporary challenges. Digitalisation and common educational platforms have a huge potential, by contributing to the establishment of a modern education, more accessible, available and inclusive, but in order to benefit from their full potential, prevention programmes and awareness raising campaigns on the new issues of cyberbullying must be also integrated within this project. The European education area should be focused on achieving common goals, including ensuring quality education for all. I strongly believe that internal and external collaboration must be enhanced, and the rights of the most vulnerable groups must be promoted, including women’s and girls’ rights. Therefore, a notable increase in the founding of the ERASMUS + programme is essential in order to provide the same opportunities also to students from disfavoured environments and to include more students and teachers, which will result in a better inclusion and more qualified workforce at the European level.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-3750" speaker_id="135491" name="María Teresa Giménez Barbat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – No es posible afrontar los retos que se presentan a la Unión sin un sistema educativo mejor adaptado a un entorno global, cambiante y competitivo. Cuando hablamos de «modernizar» la educación, sin embargo, no nos referimos únicamente a un mejor uso de las nuevas oportunidades tecnológicas y digitales. También se trata de actualizar los métodos educativos de acuerdo con la mejor evidencia científica. Sabemos que las escuelas no son meras «cadenas de montaje» de resultados educativos, sino que las personas, sus habilidades y preferencias, cuentan. El sistema educativo no trabaja con materiales brutos y dóciles, sino con cerebros humanos diversos, moldeados por milenios de evolución biológica y expuestos a diferentes influencias sociales y culturales. Identificar tempranamente tanto el talento como las dificultades en el aprendizaje de los estudiantes, resulta crucial para conciliar igualdad y excelencia. En este sentido las diferencias individuales en las capacidades de los alumnos europeos deben ser estudiadas y tomadas en cuenta. La educación debe estar en el centro de la agenda política europea. Una educación de calidad es fundamental para el desarrollo de una Europa fuerte y unida, con una ciudadanía activa que participe en la construcción del proyecto europeo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-4375" speaker_id="98341" name="Ева Майдел" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">в писмена форма. – Приветствам доклада относно модернизирането на образованието в ЕС и смятам, че той е стъпка напред в гарантирането на качествено образование за всички европейци, но и в задаването на още по-амбициозни общи цели за системни промени на национално ниво. Образователните реформи, които трябва да отговорят не само на настоящето, но и на бъдещето, изискват политическа воля и силна обществена подкрепа – от съвместното им изготвяне до ефективното им прилагане с участието на всички заинтересовани страни.</p>
      <p sl="en">Често акцентираме върху ключовата роля на участието на всички заинтересовани страни, но аз бих отишла дори по-далеч – да насърчим създаването на Национални алианси за качествено образование на територията на ЕС. Такъв пример в България е неправителствената организация „Образование България 2030“ – застъпническо обединение на граждански, бизнес и публичен сектор, чиято мисия е повишаване качеството на образованието в страната до 2030 г. Мрежата от над 40 организации и експерти работи активно по постигането на измерими цели чрез мониторинг на напредъка по ключови индикатори, информиране на обществеността за предизвикателства и възможни решения и превръщането им в образователни политики чрез застъпничество. Подобни обединения са жизненоважни за модернизирането на образованието на национално ниво и за конструктивния и резултатен диалог между заинтересованите страни в общата визия за качествено образование за всички.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-5000" speaker_id="124793" name="Claudia Țapardel" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Education is a key element for fulfilling the economic potential, and a crucial factor for development in the information society. It is vital that education systems take into account the rising social and demographic challenges, as well as Europe’s requirements of the labour market, new technologies, personal preferences and educational needs, which are determining the current directions of changes in education. I strongly believe that in order to deliver high-quality knowledge, while ensuring adequate competences, it is necessary to adapt to these rapid changes. Data has shown that modern technologies can improve the interaction between teachers and students, making the teaching process more effective. This is why I fully endorse this report, which calls for a paradigm shift in teaching. I firmly believe the idea that learning by rote is obsolete and no longer responds to the current needs of society, and this is why it must be replaced by developing skills such as critical and analytical thinking. Moreover, I strongly support that EU Member States must invest at least 2% of their GDP in higher education and give priority to educational programmes, when in cooperation with regional authorities, use national and regional resources and allocate European structural funds.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Towards a sustainable and competitive European aquaculture sector (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-170-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour appelle la brève présentation du rapport de Carlos Iturgaiz, au nom de la commission de la pêche, intitulé «Vers un secteur européen de l’aquaculture durable et compétitif» 2017/2118(INI) (A8-0186/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-0000" speaker_id="28398" name="Carlos Iturgaiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, me gustaría dar las gracias a mis compañeros, en primer lugar, de la Comisión de Pesca por la aportación de todos ellos a este informe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señorías, la acuicultura en la Unión Europea proporciona productos sostenibles y de alta calidad al consumidor, y de nuestro sector europeo solo podemos estar orgullosos. Sin embargo, aunque la acuicultura mantiene a nivel mundial y desde hace medio siglo un ritmo de crecimiento sostenido, en la Unión Europea no acaba de desplegar todo su potencial.</p>
      <p sl="en">El crecimiento del sector tropieza a veces con varios problemas. Entre ellos, la falta de espacio marítimo disponible para sus actividades o los obstáculos administrativos, particularmente los derivados de los procedimientos para la concesión de licencias, o la competencia que existe en el mercado mundial, combinada con la insuficiente información al consumidor sobre productos de la acuicultura de terceros países, en cuanto a su calidad, huella ambiental, condiciones sociales, bienestar de los peces … o la mala imagen preconcebida que de la acuicultura tienen a veces los ciudadanos, etcétera, etcétera.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es cierto que las buenas iniciativas e intenciones abundan. La Comisión Europea publicó en el año 2009 un comunicado enfocado en construir un futuro sostenible para la acuicultura. Y en 2013 publicó otro sobre las directrices de estrategia para el desarrollo sostenible de la acuicultura en la Unión Europea. La nueva política pesquera común apunta también, entre otras cosas, a dar nuevos impulsos a la acuicultura en la Unión Europea, asignando para su difusión una financiación de 1,2 billones de euros para el periodo comprendido entre 2014 y 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, la implementación no se correspondía con las expectativas del sector, y el entusiasmo inicial pronto se transformó en decepción y en derrotismo. ¿Qué es lo que necesitamos hacer, entonces? Pues bien, las estrategias propuestas por la Comisión Europea continúan siendo muy relevantes en la actualidad. Debemos simplificar los procedimientos administrativos, asegurando el desarrollo sostenible y el crecimiento de la acuicultura a través de la planificación de la coordinación espacial, realzando las competencias de la acuicultura en la Unión Europea o promoviendo la igualdad de condiciones para los operadores de la Unión Europea y explotando sus ventajas competitivas. Y todo ello continúa siendo un desafío que se debe afrontar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un gran grupo de científicos consejeros han emitido recientemente, en una petición por el comisario Vella, un informe titulado «Alimentos de los océanos: ¿Cómo se puede obtener más comida y biomasa de los océanos sin privar a las futuras generaciones de sus beneficios?». Sus recomendaciones, señorías, son muy relevantes, y yo las comparto todas ellas por completo. Hay que integrar un paradigma —como dicen ellos— de cultura responsable sobre los alimentos del océano en las agendas generales de política a nivel de sistemas europeos y mundiales. Y también, como se dice en ese informe, hay que llevar el desarrollo de la maricultura en Europa a un nivel superior y más estratégico, mediante una estrategia política completa y coordinada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pues bien, en resumen: los problemas han sido identificados, el diagnóstico es bueno y las soluciones propuestas hasta el momento son muy relevantes. Lo que se necesita es un impulso político dentro de un contexto de respeto mutuo del papel de cada uno entre las instituciones de la Unión Europea y las administraciones locales y regionales de los Estados miembros. Así, las dosis necesarias de subsidiariedad para la gestión de la acuicultura en la Unión Europea deben mezclarse con una acción reforzada a nivel de la Unión Europea, estableciendo objetivos a nivel de esta Unión Europea, mientras se opta por objetivos regionalizados adaptados a las particularidades de cada rama de la acuicultura a nivel local y regional.</p>
      <p sl="en">Termino ya, señorías. No deberíamos olvidar que el Parlamento Europeo es, desde el año 2009, colegislador y que cualquier futura política tendrá que ser elaborada conjuntamente por el Consejo y el Parlamento Europeo. Y estoy particularmente orgulloso de estos logros. Termino diciendo que existen inminentes oportunidades y nombramientos que no debemos perdernos para poder dar a la acuicultura de agua salada y de agua dulce de la Unión Europea el sitio que merece. Y debemos también aprovechar la oportunidad que se nos brinda con este informe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I think this is a vital sector and it had great promise, as has been said by the rapporteur, until recently, when some issues rose and people aren’t as enthusiastic about it now. But the facts are that the growing demand for fish, both in Europe and worldwide, cannot be met by naturally-produced fish. In fact in some cases, the stock is going down, and that has to be managed properly. So aquaculture, managed properly and properly efficient, has a huge role to play. I’ve spoken to people in my own constituency and they’re concerned about lice in relation to aquaculture and its effect on other fish and so forth. So innovation and research has to be done, and then, as a result of that, we should be able to move, to have far more aquaculture than we have now, and that would help to meet the demand that’s there without impacting on other fish resources.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-0000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, quero começar por felicitar o meu colega Carlos Iturgaiz pelo relatório consistente que produziu e para as reflexões que aqui expôs. As atividades da economia azul, tal como a aquicultura, são, de facto, uma prioridade e o seu desenvolvimento deverá ser potenciado, em particular nas regiões ultraperiféricas da União Europeia muito dependentes do mar e onde a maior parte das vezes não está ainda desenvolvida.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nos Açores, de onde provenho, com os apoios dos fundos do FEAMP, estão a ser desenvolvidos projetos em aquicultura. Estes projetos estão a envolver os pescadores e pretende-se que seja uma atividade complementar à pesca, reduzindo-se desta forma a pressão sobre os recursos encontrando alternativas para os pescadores.</p>
      <p sl="en">A procura de proteínas provenientes do mar e o aumento da produção agrícola terá que ter em conta que não se deverá aumentar a pressão sobre os recursos selvagens. A produção da aquicultura não poderá ser sustentada no aumento cego da captura de recursos selvagens, como os pequenos pelágicos e o krill, que sirvam de alimento para a produção de espécies em aquicultura.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, o desenvolvimento da aquacultura comporta um potencial considerável ainda por explorar. Fazê-lo de forma sustentável exige um forte apoio à investigação científica e ao desenvolvimento tecnológico, uma exigência distante da realidade quotidiana dos laboratórios de Estado e das demais instituições públicas asfixiadas financeiramente.</p>
      <p sl="en">A diminuição da dependência face ao pescado selvagem para alimentação das espécies cultivadas, a melhoria do rendimento da atividade, o incremento da conversão alimentar, o cultivo de espécies autóctones, incluindo espécies de água doce, algas e espécies herbívoras, a par da diminuição dos impactos ambientais da atividade, são linhas a prosseguir no desenvolvimento da aquacultura.</p>
      <p sl="en">Os apoios ao investimento são igualmente bem-vindos e necessários. O desenvolvimento da aquacultura deve ser encarado numa lógica de complementaridade com a pesca, que deve salvaguardar especialmente a pesca de pequena escala, costeira e artesanal, e privilegiar as pequenas e médias empresas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Digo complementaridade e não substituição ou alternativa, nem sequer competição, como alguns parecem erradamente sugerir ou apontar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-0000" speaker_id="24942" name="Ana Miranda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, a complexidade administrativa e a falta de transparência dos processos de concessão de licenças de que fala o relatório Senhor Iturgaiz pode ser uma desculpa para implementar processos, desculpa da complementaridade, que substituam a pesca de pequena escala e mesmo a aquicultura sustentável.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu venho de um país, a Galiza, que vive de forma sustentável da pesca e que, além disso, tem competências próprias no interior das rias tanto em matéria de pescas como de cultivo do marisco e também na aquacultura. A complexidade administrativa de que fala o relatório, dificultado pelas exigências da sociedade, implica que o meu povo se levantou contra o plano galego da aquicultura que o partido do Senhor Iturgaiz queria impulsar e levantou-se porque ia substituir a nossa atividade produtiva e, portanto, não queremos grandes indústrias marinhas, mas sim uma pesca sustentável. Por isso votarei contra este relatório.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, děkuji za udělení slova. Já bych chtěl poděkovat zpravodaji za předložení velmi kvalitní zprávy. On ve své řeči několikrát zdůraznil odpovědnou akvakulturu. Ta zpráva obsahuje rovněž pojem jako udržitelnost a já si myslím, že to je pro naši budoucnost skutečně klíčové v jakémkoli odvětví, ale samozřejmě i v akvakultuře.</p>
      <p sl="en">Když vidíme průmyslový rybolov, který doslova drancuje naše oceány, a mnohé pobřežní oblasti už vlastně neobsahují žádný život, tak o to více je naše budoucnost a akvakultura důležitá. Potřebujeme podpořit inovace a výzkum, vědu v této oblasti a podporovat ji právě z evropských fondů.</p>
      <p sl="en">Myslím si, že to má vysoký potenciál a také se mi líbilo, pokud kolega zpravodaj zdůraznil i důležitost regionálních cílů právě v tomto tématu. Subsidiarita je nutná, ale podpora EU právě v těchto oblastech je skutečně klíčová pro naši budoucnost, to podtrhuji znovu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-0000" speaker_id="124711" name="Norbert Erdős" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Sajnos az akvakultúra ritkán kerül a politika középpontjába, pedig egy kiemelten fontos ágazat, hiszen már a jövőben egyre jobban pótolnia kell a tengeri halászati fogások szigorodása és csökkenése miatt kieső halmennyiséget. Az EU-nak ezért kiemelten támogatnia kellene mind a tengeri, mind az édesvízi akvakultúra ágazatot. A képviselőtársakkal együtt kérem biztos urat, hogy tegyen meg mindent, hogy 2020 után az uniós támogatások szintje a lehető legkisebb mértékben csökkenjen ezen a területen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szeretném felhívni a figyelmét, hogy az édesvízi akvakultúra teljesítménye az egész ágazat egyötödét teszi ki. Ezért úgy igazságos, ha az akvakultúrára szánt uniós támogatások egyötödét az édesvízi ágazat kapja meg. Továbbá, az édesvízi akvakultúra lényegében különbözik a tengeri akvakultúrától. Ebben az ágazatban az állománymegőrzés, a takarmányozás vagy a szaporodás teljesen más gyakorlatot igényel. Ezért a vonatkozó környezeti fenntarthatósági normáknak is megfelelően figyelembe kell venniük e különbségeket, külön szabályok kellenek az édesvízi haltenyésztésre. Közös sikerünk, hogy az Európai Parlament az Iturgaiz-jelentéssel támogatja ezeket a célkitűzéseket.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Tibor Navracsics" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, I would like to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Iturgaiz, and the Committee on Fisheries (PECH) for their work on this comprehensive report. I welcome the fact that your report recognises the importance of developing a sustainable and competitive European aquaculture sector. This report builds on the momentum of the ‘Food from the oceans’ report submitted by the Commission’s High Level Scientific Advice Mechanism. It highlights the fact that aquaculture can and must grow in the future to feed a planet with 10 billion inhabitants.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, let me recall that we have already done a lot to create a positive environment for the sustainable development of EU aquaculture. Together with Member States, industry and other stakeholders, the Commission first identified in 2013 the main barriers to growth for EU aquaculture and has been working since to help Member States address them and stimulate growth. The main blueprints for development are the Member States’ multi-annual strategic plans for aquaculture, on which they have made good progress, in particular by developing maritime spacial planning and reforming overly-complicated national laws. The Commission is currently undertaking a mid-term review of the EU’s and Member States’ progress on aquaculture since these plans were established. Our review will be finalised in mid-2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are meeting regularly with Member States in the context of the open method of coordination and with stakeholders through the Advisory Aquaculture Council. We have a constructive dialogue with the key players at national level and those involved in production. Your report gives this work an additional political impetus, especially through the links you have established with key players, such as regional authorities and developers, during its preparation. At the initiative of this House, the Commission is also starting a pilot project on trans-national producer organisations, which will hopefully foster cross-border cooperation and increase interactions within the sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am proud of the significant funding the EU invests in research and innovation: around EUR 20 million per year under Horizon 2020, as well as in communication to promote sustainable aquaculture in the EU. Under the current EMFF, EUR 1.2 billion, which is approximately 21% of the total EMFF budget, have been allocated directly to the promotion of aquaculture.</p>
      <p sl="en">Your report rightly stresses the need for imported aquaculture products to meet the same standards that EU operators must meet. Let me recall that imported aquaculture products are already subject to strict sanitary requirements and that the European Commission is carrying out regular inspections in third countries to control compliance with EU legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite the important successes we have already reached together thanks to hard work and commitment, we are fully aware that more has to be done. We need to see even more improvements at administrative level: more reduction of red tape when it comes to licensing new farms – a number of Member States have made clear moves in this direction. More need to follow, and a commitment to simplification and adequate support needs to be taken by the regional authorities who ultimately take the relevant decisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I share your opinion that support to innovation is needed, and we will support smart ideas and approaches that make the sector more sustainable and more competitive. One way we are working on this is through the launch of a Blue Bioeconomy Forum, which should be operational in the third quarter of 2018, and which will help identify a project pipeline, draft a roadmap for the development of the sector and find new markets and value chains.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are also working on a Blue Economy Investment Platform to support innovative business ideas in the blue economy that have reached the post-research stage, but are not yet ready for full-scale investment. This platform will help mobilise funding from both private and public resources, including the European Fund for Strategic Investment. And of course, there is continued support for aquaculture development in the current and the new EMFF, as well as funding for research through the Horizon 2020 programme.</p>
      <p sl="en">I’m looking forward to continuing to work with you on further promoting aquaculture and developing a competitive and sustainable aquaculture sector in the EU.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le débat est clos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le vote aura lieu mardi 12 juin 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Déclarations écrites (article 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-2500" speaker_id="124957" name="Mike Hookem" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">This report proposes greater harmonisation in aquaculture and bemoans the un-competitiveness of EU based producers blaming a lack of financial prospects and stability for a lack of growth. I would suggest that growth needs light touch local regulation rather than this proposal which is nothing short of a Soviet style five year plan. The EU is in-competent so should not try to coordinate this and the Commission should not oversee Member States plans. This is just duplication of bureaucracy not a blueprint for growth. The reason the sector is struggling is the existing level of EU regulation making it uncompetitive. The fact that there are two minority opinions is nothing less than a gooey mess. The larger Group obviously being miffed that somebody pointed out the ecological failings contained in the original report. As it happens, I largely support the second minority report as this highlights the destructive nature of battery-farmed fish on the local environment and the impact on inshore fisheries. There is a reason farmed fish have such a bad reputation with consumers! Finally, I can save the Commission some time by explaining what will happen after Brexit. The UK will put its house in order. Maybe you can copy us later?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-5000" speaker_id="191377" name="Maria Gabriela Zoană" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Constatăm că, în ultimii ani, sectorul european al acvaculturii stagnează, spre deosebire de acvacultura din alte zone care înregistrează o creștere constantă. O dovadă în acest sens este faptul că producția acvicolă din UE acoperă doar 10 % din cererea internă de pește, iar mai mult de jumătate din produsele de acest gen sunt importate din țări terțe. Consider că, pentru a reduce presiunea asupra locurilor de pescuit naturale, ar fi benefic ca UE să își mărească producția în sectorul acvaculturii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uniunea are nevoie, totodată, să dezvolte acvacultura de apă dulce și acvacultura interioară în ape împrejmuite, sectoare care reprezintă o oportunitate pentru îmbunătățirea securității alimentare și dezvoltarea zonelor rurale, furnizând locuri de muncă în zonele rurale cele mai sărace și având un rol ecologic în menținerea unor zone umede valoroase și în furnizarea unei game vaste de servicii ecosistemice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu în ultimul rând, este nevoie de simplificarea și armonizarea procedurii la nivel european de obținere a documentelor necesare acestei activități, pentru a încuraja investițiile în afaceri și a reduce astfel importurile din țări terțe.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. State of play of recreational fisheries in the EU (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-183-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour appelle la brève présentation du rapport de Norica Nicolaï, au nom de la commission de la pêche, sur l’état des lieux de la pêche de loisir dans l’Union européenne 2017/2120(INI) (A8-0191/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-184-0000" speaker_id="96825" name="Norica Nicolai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raportoare. – Doamna președintă, domnule comisar, este o bucurie pentru mine să prezint în plenul Parlamentului European primul raport dedicat pescuitului recreativ. Sigur, pescuitul recreativ este considerat un hobby, dar este un hobby care ține de patrimoniul cultural, de tradițiile multor comunități din zonele costiere și insulare. Este o activitate care are o influență economică din păcate ușor ignorată în politicile noastre comune de pescuit. Numai în ceea ce privește pescuitul recreativ marin, nouă milioane de oameni sunt implicați, iar impactul economic al acestei activități este de peste zece miliarde de euro anual. Iar în ceea ce privește pescuitul în ape dulci, care se întâmplă în marea majoritate a statelor europene, peste 25 de milioane de cetățeni europeni sunt implicați, iar industria aferentă acestei activități de pescuit o reprezintă circa 25 de miliarde de euro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sigur, este un domeniu care ține de subsidiaritate, dar este un domeniu care va avea un rol important în ceea ce numim noi „economia albastră” și în economia circulară. Din păcate, datele științifice în momentul de față sunt insuficiente pentru câteva specii de pește. Ele sunt prezente, dar este nevoie, pentru o definiție coerentă a acestei activități, să avem un suport științific solid. Și fac apel la Comisie să sprijine și să impulsioneze colectarea de date științifice cu privire la pescuitul recreativ în statele membre pentru a avea o viziune foarte clară asupra acestei activități, pentru a avea o definiție relativ unitară pe întreg teritoriul Uniunii Europene.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pescuitul recreativ este diferit în fiecare stat, așa cum spuneam, face parte dintr-un dat cultural al multor comunități, dar, adesea, pentru foarte multe comunități, este un pescuit de subzistență și unica sursă de hrană pentru comunitățile din zonele periferice în special. Activitatea economică care se poate desfășura și care poate aduce foarte multe locuri de muncă în Uniunea Europeană trebuie, de asemenea, susținută și fac apel la Comisia Europeană să includă pescuitul recreativ printre temele anului aferente proiectului EDEN pentru un turism sustenabil și să ne inițieze în fondul COSME proiecte pentru promovarea turismului generat de pescuitul recreativ. Este foarte important să dăm o șansă de diversificare a opțiunilor economice în comunitățile care sunt marginalizate și sunt dependente ca mediu înconjurător de acest tip de pescuit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cerem, de asemenea, Comisiei Europene ca, în baza definiției din 2013 a Consiliului Internațional pentru Exploatarea Apelor Maritime, să încercăm o definire clară a acestei activități în viitoarea politică de pescuit; cerem, de asemenea, un suport financiar pentru activitatea științifică de cercetare în domeniu, pentru colectarea de date în vederea stabilirii nivelului stocurilor de pește. Cu siguranță, toate acestea vor contura un rol al pescuitului recreativ în politica comună de pescuit. Credem că fondurile din FEPAM trebuie să fie destinate și acestei activități pentru că, într-o perioadă în schimbare, cu provocări climatice, cu provocări care țin de chestiunile de hrană, pescuitul recreativ este o șansă nu numai de recreere, dar și de viață.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já bych chtěl poděkovat opět na úvod paní zpravodajce, protože se pustila do nelehkého tématu. Je to první zpráva o rekreačním rybolovu, jak bylo již řečeno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na úvod bych chtěl říci, že já nejsem příznivcem žádné nové legislativy v tomto oboru a myslím, že o to ani zpravodajka nežádala, že k tomu nehovořila. Pro mne je důležité, pokud neexistuje jednotná definice, tak je možné samozřejmě k ní určitým postupem dospět, ale je důležité, abychom rekreační rybolov skutečně podporovali tam, kde plní především tu samozásobitelskou funkci, tzn. zejména v těch přímořských pobřežních oblastech. Je asi dobré i podporovat určité finanční projekty, které souvisí s tímto rekreačním rybolovem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pochopil jsem, že je důležité, abychom docílili rovněž určitých statistických dat a vědeckých údajů o tomto rybolovu, na druhou stranu mám pocit, že to je někde na pomezí mezi koníčkem a řekněme rekreační činností, která by asi neměla být nadále více regulována, resp. neměla by být předmětem našeho dramatického zájmu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-187-0000" speaker_id="124741" name="Ricardo Serrão Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, antes de mais quero também felicitar a nossa colega Norica Nikolai pelo relatório que produziu. A pesca recreativa é uma atividade importante em toda a União Europeia, não apenas pelo número de pessoas envolvidas ou pelo impacto económico, mas também no contexto da gestão dos recursos.</p>
      <p sl="en">A recolha de dados da pesca criativa tem que ser efetiva para se poder avaliar o real impacto da mesma. Só desta forma se melhoram os aconselhamentos científicos que apoiam os planos multianuais e a gestão dos recursos haliêuticos em geral.</p>
      <p sl="en">A pesca recreativa, como atividade da economia azul, tem de ser devidamente desenvolvida e muito acompanhada, em particular também nas regiões ultraperiféricas como os Açores, de onde provenho. Esta atividade tem um impacto social e económico relevante em muitos portos e áreas costeiras, no entanto há espaço para melhorar o seu enquadramento em locais onde há necessidade de reorientar pescadores para outras atividades.</p>
      <p sl="en">A pesca recreativa ligada ao turismo pode ser uma excelente alternativa e uma complementaridade dando prioridade aos pescadores tradicionais. A pesca turística tem de respeitar a tradição das pescas artesanais.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, a pesca recreativa entendida como a pesca destinada ao consumo próprio ou lazer pode tomar várias formas e utilizar várias artes sendo as mais comuns a pesca à linha, arpão, apanha, existindo também métodos passivos incluindo redes, armadilhas, nassas e palangres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estando cada vez mais disseminada importa conhecer melhor em que condições esta atividade é exercida, obter mais dados de caracterização, incluindo sobre o número de pescadores e as artes mais utilizadas, importa avaliar o impacto da atividade, o impacto ambiental sobre os recursos haliêuticos e sobre o meio marinho em geral, o impacto socioeconómico em particular sobre a pesca profissional de pequena escala, costeira e artesanal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Importa também perceber em que medida não estamos perante situações de pesca profissional dissimulada. A proteção da pesca de pequena escala e dos seus profissionais, a criação de condições que garantam a sua viabilidade e renovação geracional deve constituir uma preocupação central e uma prioridade.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-0000" speaker_id="188906" name="Francis Zammit Dimech" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sur President, qed nitkellmu fuq qasam tas-sajd rikreattiv u interessanti ħafna li anki f’pajjiż żgħir bħal Malta għandek erba’ għaqdiet u federazzjoni ddedikati għal dan l-isport.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jien, fil-ġranet li għaddew, kelli l-okkażjoni anki niltaqa’ ma’ diversi persuni li jipprattikaw is-sajd rikreattiv u rrid naqsam magħkom dak li qed jolqot lilhom. Qed jolqot lilhom pereżempju l-fatt li mhux dejjem ikollhom il-postijiet meħtieġa biex jipprattikaw l-isport tagħhom, anki permezz ta’ kompetizzjonijiet, għaliex il-mollijiet jittieħdu ħafna drabi għal skopijiet purament kummerċjali. Ibatu wkoll mill-problema, pereżempju tal-ghost fishing, fejn jitħallew xbieki fil-baħar li dawk imbagħad inaqqsu l-ħut li huma jistgħu jaqbdu b’mod sostenibbli.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naħseb li dan huwa settur li għandna nippromwovuh, anki għaliex jista’ jorbot ma’ qasam kummerċjali bħal turiżmu sostenibbli. Meta rajthom jipprattikaw l-isport, huma jaħdmu verament b’mod li jirrispetta l-ambjent, b’mod partikolari permezz tal-proċedura tal-catch and release.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, debate over the use of the seas and the right of the common people to fish is hardly new. In the UK alone, two million people fish the seas each year, and this report is a welcome development, not least for the context it provides recognising the economic and social contribution of recreational fishing.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want to make three very brief points. First and most importantly, I welcome that this report recognises that the management of the seas exclusively to serve the interests of commercial fishing is both economically and environmentally outdated. Secondly, involving the recreational angling sector’s stakeholders can only lead to better outcomes. Robust processes for dialogue with stakeholders should be developed and enhanced. And thirdly – and I say this with great regret – whatever process is developed for the collective management of the seas that include UK waters after 2020, it would be a great mistake for that process to replicate the mistakes of the past and exclude the recreational angling sector.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-192-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Tibor Navracsics" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, first I would like to congratulate the rapporteur, Ms Nicolai, and the Committee on Fisheries for their report on this very important issue. Providing a comprehensive overview of the state of play of recreational fisheries in the EU and drawing public attention to this topic is extremely useful and necessary.</p>
      <p sl="en">Scientific advice increasingly suggests that recreational fisheries can have an important impact on the state of some stocks. This is, for instance, the case with cod in the Baltic, sea bass in the Atlantic, and eels. In some of these cases, recreational catches could actually be more important than commercial catches.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is monitoring this situation closely and proposes measures for recreational fisheries on a case—by—case basis when science advises that these are needed. To give you some examples: for eels, the EU regulation requires Member States to make estimates of recreational fishing licenses and their catches. For Western Baltic cod and sea bass in the Bay of Biscay, bag limits currently apply to recreational fisheries. For the northern stock of sea bass, only the catch-and-release practice is allowed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me mention here the pilot project proposed by Parliament to reinforce the control schemes for recreational catches of sea bass in the Atlantic. The study will evaluate existing control measures and tools, identify the strengths and weaknesses of available solutions, assess the costs and benefits of different options, explore good practices and propose recommendations or guidelines to improve control schemes. More generally, the control regulation requires Member States to monitor recreational catches of stocks, subject to recovery plans, excluding fishing from shore. This implies the establishment of sampling plans and biannual reporting to the Commission. This provision is intended to ensure the appropriate monitoring of recreational fisheries of depleted stocks.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our proposal for the revision of the control regulation, adopted only two weeks ago, goes even further. It acknowledges that recreational fishing can have a significant impact on certain stocks and provides for specific tools allowing an effective control of recreational fisheries by the Member States. For example, we are proposing that Member States establish a registration or licensing system to monitor the number of natural and legal persons involved in recreational fisheries and also to collect data on catches from such fisheries through catch reporting or other appropriate data collection mechanisms. Furthermore, for stocks where EU conservation measures apply to recreational fisheries, the Commission proposes that Member States ensure that all persons involved in recreational fisheries record and send catch declarations electronically to the competent authorities on a daily basis or after each fishing trip. To make this happen, we need solid databases, in particular for stock assessment purposes.</p>
      <p sl="en">The ICES Working Group on Recreational Fisheries Surveys highlighted that data from Member States are still missing, in particular in the Mediterranean. To remedy this, we have now made it compulsory for Member States to provide such data and conduct validation pilot projects within two years of the entry into force of the new EU multiannual programme for data collection. This deadline of two years will expire on 31 December 2018. This is a big step forward, as the conservation of some marine biological resources might indeed require measures on recreational fisheries, and these cannot be properly shaped without reliable data.</p>
      <p sl="en">This being said, the one—size—fits—all approach cannot be applied regarding recreational fisheries. This is an issue that we need to look into on a case—by—case basis, stock by stock, also when preparing proposals for multiannual management plans. While the Baltic MAP does not include provisions on recreational fisheries, both the Western Waters MAP and the MAP for demersal fisheries in the western Mediterranean cover recreational fisheries for stocks, where these have an important impact. This shows that the Commission is actively engaging in the discussion around the impact of recreational fisheries.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are open to your ideas and views to further address this issue with a view to ensuring the sustainability of stocks for future generations and the long—term viability of this segment of the sector. Your report provides precious information and guidance in this respect. Once again, thank you for your efforts and input.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-193-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le débat est clos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le vote aura lieu mardi 12 juin 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-195-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour appelle les interventions d’une minute sur des questions politiques importantes (article 163 du règlement intérieur).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-196-0000" speaker_id="39725" name="Iuliu Winkler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Az Európa Tanács 47 országának az önkormányzati képviselői üléseztek a Székelyföldön, az RMDSZ meghívására. Megállapítottuk, hogy szorosabbra kell fűzzük az Európa Tanács és az Európai Unió közötti kapcsolatot, ugyanis azt látjuk, hogy az EU nem vállalja fel a nemzeti kisebbségek jogaira vonatkozó ET-standardokat. Annak ellenére, hogy számtalanszor felvetettük itt, az Európai Parlamentben, a koppenhágai dilemmát nem sikerült feloldani.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az EU-csatlakozás feltétele, hogy a tagjelölt államok biztosítsák az őshonos kisebbségek védelmét, de a csatlakozást követően ez a kötelezettség megszűnik. A mi esetünkben ez azt eredményezte, hogy tizenegy évvel az uniós csatlakozást követően romlott a romániai magyarság helyzete, gyakoribbak a jogtiprások, felerősödött a magyarellenesség. El akarjuk érni, hogy az ET kisebbségvédelmi gyakorlata kerüljön be az EU joganyagába, ezért a két szervezet között sokkal szorosabb együttműködést szorgalmazunk.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-0000" speaker_id="192634" name="Giuseppe Ferrandino" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, in Italia sono stati finanziati 1,6 miliardi per 183 interventi per la depurazione delle acque nelle regioni del Mezzogiorno d'Italia. Il 15 giugno incontrerò il commissario Enrico Rolle per elaborare un piano che possa portare nel minor tempo possibile ad una proposta per superare le procedure d'infrazione comminate all'Italia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Credo che questo Parlamento e la Commissione debbano però discutere meglio anche sui parametri inquinanti tra scarichi urbani e scarichi industriali. Una mancata revisione rischia di penalizzare i comuni del Mezzogiorno, schiacciati da vincoli di bilancio che non permettono nemmeno la gestione dell'ordinario.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non possiamo consentire che le inadempienze delle istituzioni ricadano sulle spalle dei cittadini europei. Un'ipotesi del genere rischierebbe di aumentare ancor di più il divario con le regioni più sviluppate, senza suggerire alcuna soluzione per colmare il ritardo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mi impegnerò nelle prossime settimane con interpellanze alla Commissione europea per dare ai cittadini le risposte che essi chiedono con sempre maggior forza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198-0000" speaker_id="4338" name="Thierry Cornillet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je souhaitais attirer l’attention du Parlement européen sur le cas des enfants fantômes. L’Unicef les estime à 230 millions, dont 95 millions en Afrique subsaharienne, c’est-à-dire dans des pays partenaires de l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qu’est-ce qu’un enfant fantôme? C’est un enfant dont la naissance n’a pas été déclarée à l’état civil, et donc il n’existe pas. Il ne peut pas aller à l’école, il ne peut pas avoir de couverture, il ne peut pas avoir de travail officiel et donc naturellement il est soit exploité, soit mendiant.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors naturellement, il ne s’agit pas de le faire à la place des pays, puisque la prérogative régalienne de l’état civil leur appartient, mais nous pourrions aider un grand nombre d’entre eux à trouver des solutions et à les mettre en œuvre, par exemple un meilleur recours au numérique, des campagnes de sensibilisation de la population ou des bureaux d’état civil ambulants.</p>
      <p sl="en">Avec un certain nombre de collègues qui ont bien voulu me rejoindre, nous avons écrit au commissaire au développement et à l’action humanitaire et au président de la Commission pour leur demander de mobiliser les crédits non utilisés du FED ou de l’ICD (instrument de coopération au développement) afin qu’ils puissent aider ces pays.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-199-0000" speaker_id="185974" name="Jordi Solé" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, ofrecer un puerto seguro a las más de 600 personas que navegan en el Aquarius es una obligación del Derecho internacional y una obligación humanitaria. Querer demostrar mano dura ante estas situaciones dramáticas es irresponsable, además de incoherente, porque 400 de los 629 rescatados lo han sido por parte de la Guardia Costera italiana, a las órdenes del mismo Gobierno que les ha denegado el desembarque en sus costas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Italia tiene razón cuando pide la implicación de todos los Estados miembros, pero no la tiene cuando niega atención a víctimas de naufragio. Celebrar como una victoria alargar la agonía de estas personas es inaceptable. La victoria es salvar vidas. Hoy evidenciamos una vez más el fracaso de la política europea de migración y asilo. Es urgente consensuar nuevas reglas que nos alejen de esta imagen egoísta, prepotente y descoordinada que estamos dando de Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por suerte, hoy tenemos Valencia que, como Barcelona y Cataluña, queremos ser y somos tierras mediterráneas de acogida. Por eso, el Gobierno de Cataluña ya se ha ofrecido a acoger a los 600 refugiados del Aquarius.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, a Comissão Europeia está apostada em entregar ao colosso financeiro norte-americano BlackRock as pensões de milhares de europeus, milhões de europeus. No linguajar da burocracia europeia diz que o objetivo é triplicar o mercado interno dos fundos de pensões até aos 2,1 biliões de euros. Traduzindo, trata-se de um ataque aos sistemas públicos de segurança social universais visando o seu desmantelamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Descobrimos agora que altos quadros da Comissão Europeia e mesmo comissários europeus, como o vice-presidente Dombrovskis, mantiveram comprometedoras reuniões com altos responsáveis da BlackRock. São os mesmos senhores que, nas recomendações por país do Semestre Europeu, não se cansam de alertar para a insustentabilidade dos sistemas públicos de segurança social e de pensões, que defendem e impõem cortes nas pensões, como fizeram em Portugal. Percebemos agora porquê. Até os argumentos utilizados aparecem decalcados do argumentário da BlackRock. Uma empresa que tem sido muito generosa com ex responsáveis políticos europeus aos quais reconhece os bons ofícios. Mais do que explicações exigimos que retirem a proposta que apresentaram. As vossas mãos fora das nossas pensões.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-0000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I wish to draw to the attention of Parliament a fraud by Russian groups targeting EU citizens in Bulgaria and to the inaction of the Bulgarian legal system. EU citizens own flats in the Nestinarka holiday condominium which they use during the holiday season. Last year, Russian nationals exploited gaps in Bulgarian law to set up a property fraud. That law allows formal meetings of owners to set community rules. Some Russian owners convened a non-quorate meeting out of season when most owners were absent. They elected themselves as the new condominium management and imposed a new regime of rules on all owners that enable flats to be seized. After 11 months’ litigation, the Bulgarian courts continue to empower the Russians, even after determining that the claimed meeting was invalid.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is the Commissioners’ responsibility to ensure that justice systems are fit for purpose before and after EU accession. Bulgaria, which holds the presidency, is failing to meet its Treaty obligations. Instead of censure, it will be rewarded with EUR 1.9 billion from the EU budget.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Odwiedziłem w tym weekend Londyn i chciałem zwrócić uwagę na to, co dzieje się w tej chwili w Wielkiej Brytanii w związku ze sprawą Tommy’ego Robinsona. Nie chodzi o to, żeby Parlament wtrącał się w indywidualne postępowanie, bo to jest oczywiście niedopuszczalne, jakkolwiek skandaliczne się ono nie wydaje. Natomiast w tym przypadku władza sądownicza wyszła poza swoje uprawnienia. Próbuje ograniczać prawo do wolności słowa osób postronnych, niebiorących udziału w postępowaniu. Został wydany zakaz informowania o tym procesie, co jest pogwałceniem wolności słowa, swobód obywatelskich, jawności i przejrzystości procesu. I co gorsza, oni tego posłuchali. Brytyjskie media nabrały wody w usta i nie informują o tym procesie. To już tylko czekam, aż Putin wykorzysta okazję, żeby strofować Europę w kwestii stosowania praw człowieka i wolności słowa. Libertarianie w Wielkiej Brytanii czują się zastraszani przez lewicowe bojówki i boją się przyznać w pracy do swoich poglądów. Kiedy rozmawialiśmy o możliwości otwarcia mojego biura poselskiego w Londynie, okazało się, że ludzie boją się wynająć sali w obawie przed bojówkami. To jest Wielka Brytania w roku 2018.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-0000" speaker_id="28141" name="Lívia Járóka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! A múlt héten a Nemzeti Osztag elnevezésű, ukrán nacionalista szervezet tagjai szétvertek egy illegálisan létesített roma tábort Kijev egyik parkjában, baltákkal és kalapácsokkal, és ezt a Facebook oldalukon előre meg is hirdették, majd pedig az atrocitást ki is tették a Facebookra. Ez nem az első ilyen eset volt, sem Ukrajnában, sem Európa többi országában. Vannak olyan tagállamok, például Szlovákia, ahol a rendőrség lép fel túl erőszakosan, és vannak olyan országok ma, például Svédország, ahol a neonácik menetelhetnek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kérem a Bizottságot, hogy Ukrajna kapcsán ne csak a nyelvtörvénynél, és az összes többi tagállamnál is, a kisebbségek biztonsága érdekében, védelme érdekében is lépjenek fel, és ennek az ügynek kapcsán szeretném elmondani, hogy az új európai romastratégiában nagyon fontos, hogy evvel a típusú gyűlölettel vegyük fel a versenyt. Munkahelyekkel, a közös helyek megteremtése, a közös történelem ismerése, ezek az emberek, akik támadnak, és akiket támadnak, a rasszisták és a romák is munkanélküli, elkeseredett emberek, akiknek a közönyét az egymás elleni utálatát csak munkahelyekkel, oktatással lehet ellene felvenni a versenyt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-204-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, 30 June will be Armed Forces Day in the UK. The men and women who serve in our armed forces across the EU are a crucial part of the Union’s defence and security, as well as playing a vital role in peacekeeping around the world. Many British military personnel have been stationed in EU Member States, becoming part of the local community. Some fell in love and married their new-found neighbours. They’ve got children and grandchildren and some have moved back to the UK, taking advantage of European citizenship for their spouses and dependents.</p>
      <p sl="en">But now their right to family life is threatened by Brexit. The UK Government’s careless approach to negotiations has failed to give our service personnel the respect they deserve. People are not bargaining chips. Veterans have served to protect the fundamental values that underpin the European Union. The EU and the UK must now repay that debt and work together to guarantee citizens’ rights to a family life, regardless of the outcome of negotiations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-205-0000" speaker_id="124866" name="Илхан Кючюк" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Взимам думата в тревожен момент за състоянието на демокрацията в моята родина, Република България. Поводът за днешното ми изказване е смяната на имената на 800 местности, носещи турско-арабски имена в община Стара Загора. Нека Ви илюстрирам с един пример за какво говоря. „Ахмед баир“ става „Антонов рид“. Баир може да се смени с рид, но не и Ахмед с Антон. Въпросът е за какво се прави това? За да звучат по-благозвучно? Едва ли.</p>
      <p sl="en">Истинската причина е да се припомни на турците и мюсюлманите в България за последиците от мракобесната политика на комунистическия режим, оставил рани в душите на стотици хиляди български граждани. И ако за този период е отговорен озверелият комунистически режим, то днешните действия носят отпечатъка на овластения краен национализъм, облечен с държавна власт, който стои рамо до рамо с ГЕРБ – политическа партия, членуваща в Европейската народна партия. Ваши колеги членуват в тази политическа партия.</p>
      <p sl="en">Това не може да бъде европейско поведение, още по-малко на страна, председателстваща Съвета на Европейския съюз, и то в европейската година на културното наследство. Само каква ирония. Моята партия „Движение за права и свободи“ ще продължава да бъда стожер на демокрацията и правата на човека от всяка една трибуна.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-206-0000" speaker_id="24942" name="Ana Miranda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Obrigada, Senhora Presidente. Existe na Alemanha a Fundação Hitler? Nein! Existe em Portugal a Fundação Salazar? Não! Existe em Itália a Fundação Mussolini? Non signore! Mas na Espanha, sim, existe a Fundação Franco e essa fundação faz a apologia do fascismo e da ditadura espanhola.</p>
      <p sl="en">Olhem para esta fotografia, é o Pazo de Meirás, património roubado ao povo galego, residência de verão do ditador. Esse Pazo foi tomado por 19 pacifistas que entraram pacificamente para pedir que seja retornado ao povo galego porque agora é da família do ditador, a família Franco. A mesma que, juntamente com a Fundação Franco, acaba de denunciar os 19 ativistas por delito de ódio, entre outros. É o mundo ao contrário.</p>
      <p sl="en">É intolerável que na Europa se realize ainda a apologia do fascismo. O atual presidente Sánchez tem a oportunidade histórica de ilegalizar a Fundação Franco …</p>
      <a text="(A Senhora Presidente retira a palavra à oradora.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-207-0000" speaker_id="124987" name="Liadh Ní Riada" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, tá deacrachtaí an-bhunúsacha againn leis an gcóras oideachais in Éirinn agus ní mór dúinn é a athrú ó bhun go barr. Is léir nach bhfuil an rialtas ag tabhairt tosaíocht dár ndaoine óga maidir le hoideachas. Feicimid páistí gan aon tacaíocht ar fáil dóibh, páistí le riachtanais speisialta, páistí a bhfuil deacrachtaí foghlama acu agus páistí as cúlra bocht, agus cén saghas todhchaí atá i ndán dóibh? Tá ciníochas go forleathan agus easpa múinteoirí cáilithe chun déileáil leis. Gan amhras nuair nach bhfuil an stát ag tabhairt ach pinginí suaracha do mhúinteoirí nua-cháilithe, ní haon ionadh nach bhfuil scoláirí ag iarraidh cáilíochtaí múinteoireachta a bhaint amach. Tá easpa múinteoirí Gaeilge ann atá ag déanamh fíor-dhamáiste dár dteanga dhúchasach mar nach bhfuil na múinteoirí sin ar fáil. Mura dtabharfar aghaidh ar infheistíocht cheart a dhéanamh insan gcóras oideachais beidh costas i bhfad níos mó ar an stát amach anseo agus mar sin táim ag glaoch ar an rialtas anois chun an rud ceart a dhéanamh agus an infheistíocht cheart a dhéanamh ionas go bhfuil todhchaí dhearfach ar fáil dár scoláirí anseo amach.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-208-0000" speaker_id="28497" name="Gerard Batten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, a group of people are being unjustly persecuted in the UK. These are British ex-servicemen who served in Northern Ireland. Men in their 60s and 70s are now in danger of being charged with serious criminal offences because of allegations made against them concerning their service decades ago. These men defended us against the cowardly terrorists and murderers of the IRA and sometimes they had to make split-second life and death decisions. The IRA terrorists received an amnesty under the Good Friday Agreement and were able to walk away from their crimes. One now sits in this House.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want to join those calling for an act of Parliament for an amnesty for these ex-servicemen for their alleged historical offences. I also call on anyone who can, to show their support for these men by attending a protest rally at Parliament Square at 11a.m. this Friday, 15 June.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-209-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, za 3 dny začne svátek všech fotbalistů a fanoušků tohoto sportu, v Moskvě bude zahájen světový šampionát.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fotbal je krásný sport – spojuje, překonává bariéry. Znáte to heslo „Respect – no to racism“, říkají Messi i Ronaldo. Je škoda, že sportovní funkcionáři nepovažují lidská práva za podmínku pro konání vrcholových sportovních akcí. Za to nemůžou ani fotbalisté, ani my fanoušci, ale já osobně bohužel musím tento šampionát bojkotovat, nebudu se na něj dívat. Po olympiádě v Soči následovala anexe Krymu, co máme očekávat po šampionátu v Moskvě?</p>
      <p sl="en">Dámy a pánové, já doufám, že se šampionát přesto vydaří, že zvítězí v rámci fair play ti nejlepší fotbalisté, a věřím také, že i v Rusku jednou zavládne svoboda a demokracie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-210-0000" speaker_id="124691" name="Κώστας Μαυρίδης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, οι ευρωπαϊκές οδηγίες συντάσσονται για να εφαρμόζονται από τα κράτη μέλη και υπερτερούν παντός εσωτερικού δικαίου. Σε αρκετές όμως περιπτώσεις η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή διαπιστώνει αναποτελεσματική εφαρμογή της νομοθεσίας σε σχέση ειδικά με πιστωτικά και τραπεζικά ιδρύματα. Η συνεχιζόμενη αναποτελεσματικότητα στην εφαρμογή των ευρωπαϊκών οδηγιών συνιστά ελλιπή απονομή της δικαιοσύνης. Για παράδειγμα, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση απαιτεί όπως κάθε κράτος μέλος μεριμνά ώστε στις συμβάσεις που συνάπτονται με τους καταναλωτές να μην περιλαμβάνονται καταχρηστικές ρήτρες. Και οι τράπεζες έχουν υποχρέωση, αλλά και το κράτος μέλος οφείλει να μεριμνά για να εξαλείφονται με αποτελεσματικό τρόπο. Δυστυχώς αν δεν υπάρχει δεσμευτικός μηχανισμός, όπως στην περίπτωση της Κύπρου, δεν εφαρμόζεται η ευρωπαϊκή οδηγία για τις καταχρηστικές ρήτρες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-211-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, reaction to the enlargement strategy at the Council meeting in Sofia has made it perfectly clear that there is enlargement fatigue in the EU. My question is the following. Let’s imagine that we have ‘abracadabra power’ and can make all these countries fulfil the criteria immediately: everything, even more than that. Would they be accepted tomorrow as EU members? If the answer to that question is ‘no’, then the problem is on our side, not on theirs. Therefore, I believe we have to start working in parallel: we, the Commissioner and the others, pushing them to fulfil the criteria simultaneously to shape opinion in the European Union. We have to start talking about what we gain from enlargement: about the well-educated regions, the new markets, creating stability, creating lasting peace, etc. – what our citizens will gain. We have to remind everybody else how the opposition to Spain and Portugal was, and how today these countries are regarded seriously and are respected. So if we do not shape this opinion, we will have serious problems very soon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-212-0000" speaker_id="124932" name="Josep-Maria Terricabras" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, el pasado 1 de junio una moción de censura echó del Gobierno de España a Mariano Rajoy. Los casos de corrupción en el PP español se habían acumulado, y había habido sentencia condenatoria. Hoy mismo ha habido otra en la que se dice que el PP ha delinquido. Un juez dictaminó hace meses que el PP era una organización criminal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este ha sido el Gobierno que hasta ahora ha sido aplaudido casi con entusiasmo por las instituciones europeas cuando ha perseguido y encarcelado a dirigentes catalanes.</p>
      <p sl="en">La corrupción, el abandono de los refugiados están sumiendo a la Unión en un descrédito espectacular, mientras en España hay presos políticos y hay exiliados que son políticos electos o artistas o simples ciudadanos que ejercen sus derechos democráticos.</p>
      <p sl="en">El escándalo es mayúsculo. O bien la Unión Europea reacciona, o bien sus lamentos contra las dictaduras y las injusticias en el mundo no serán más que alaridos cínicos de quienes comparten, pero no combaten, los principios antidemocráticos del fascismo y de la extrema derecha antidemocrática. Ahora nos jugamos esto: la libertad, la justicia y la democracia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-213-0000" speaker_id="125047" name="Paloma López Bermejo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, las trabajadoras de Gestipack, subcontrata de la multinacional alemana DHL, denunciaron ante la Inspección de Trabajo que la empresa estaba pagándoles un salario por debajo del establecido en el convenio colectivo. La inspección comprobó la actuación fraudulenta y ordenó a la empresa cumplir con el convenio. Sin embargo, el empresario decidió despedir a toda la plantilla. Mientras, la empresa principal —DHL— se ha desentendido y ha optado por cambiar la contrata sin garantizar la subrogación de las trabajadoras.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este es un claro ejemplo de discriminación laboral por género, causante de las brechas salariales que sufren las mujeres, consentida y ampliada por reformas laborales regresivas que facilitan a empresarios sin escrúpulos explotar a las trabajadoras y posteriormente despedirlas sin apenas coste. La contrata y la empresa principal deben asumir su responsabilidad laboral y social, y corregir inmediatamente esta situación.</p>
      <p sl="en">No debemos mirar hacia otro lado y no lo vamos a hacer si creemos en la igualdad real. Por eso, desde aquí, toda nuestra solidaridad y apoyo con las trabajadoras de Gestipack.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-214-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca, je pochopiteľné, že Súdny dvor Európskej únie v prípade Coman potvrdil, že občania všetkých členských štátov EÚ sú si rovní v právach, ktoré im dávajú európske zmluvy. No fakt, že pojem manželský partner si vyžadoval výklad súdu, je veľmi zlým vysvedčením pre tento parlament ako spolutvorcu práva Únie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Každý dvojznačný termín, ktorý sa kvôli našej snahe o kompromis za každú cenu ocitne v smerniciach a nariadeniach, je zlyhaním parlamentarizmu. Je pozvaním pre sudcov, aby robili prácu poslancov, hoci na to nedostali mandát od voličov a nemusia sa im za svoje rozhodnutia zodpovedať.</p>
      <p sl="en">Radi hovoríme, že hlas každého občana je v Európe dôležitý. To však musí platiť len vtedy, to však bude platiť len vtedy, ak smernice a nariadenia budú používať jasne definované pojmy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-215-0000" speaker_id="189490" name="Răzvan Popa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamna președintă, România este o susținătoare clară a existenței spațiului Schengen. Totuși, nu a primit statutul de membru deși, conform tuturor evaluărilor, îndeplinește criteriile de aderare. În mod repetat, Comisia Europeană și Parlamentul European și-au exprimat susținerea pentru aderarea României la spațiul Schengen. România este una dintre țările care pot întări securitatea la granițele Uniunii Europene, iar acesta este unul dintre motivele clare pentru care ar trebui să fie cât mai rapid parte a zonei Schengen. De asemenea, faptul că România îndeplinește criteriile de aderare în urma unor eforturi costisitoare și de durată îndreptățește cetățenii români și economia românească să beneficieze de avantajele apartenenței la spațiul Schengen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Miercuri, Parlamentul va vota o propunere de rezoluție privind proiectul de decizie al Consiliului European care arată că România și Bulgaria sunt pregătite din toate punctele de vedere pentru aderarea la spațiul Schengen. De aceea, fac apel la colegii deputați să susțină proiectul de rezoluție, acest lucru reprezentând un pas în plus pentru ca România și Bulgaria să devină cât mai rapid membre ale spațiului Schengen, așa cum este corect.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-216-0000" speaker_id="124984" name="Lynn Boylan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this month we mark LGBT Pride, an important reminder of the constant struggles of the LGBT+ community. Pride is a time for solidarity against discrimination and against violence, an assertion of dignity and equality rights of LGBT persons. It is a celebration, but most importantly, Pride is political and Pride is protest. Pride should not be a marketing opportunity for multinationals. We cannot afford to have it trivialised and commercialised, especially not when we still have so much unfinished work to do for the LGBT+ community.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trans people suffer from the highest rates of repetitive violence and hate motivated crimes. Ireland has the second highest prevalence in the EU of hate motivated violence against trans people. Between 2014 and 2016, 62 transgender hate crimes took place on the island of Ireland. So this year, let’s not celebrate Pride by patting ourselves on the back for marriage equality. Let’s make Pride the political struggle it ought to be. Instead of visibility of billion dollar social media networks, let’s have visibility of trans identities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-217-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já bych se chtěl dnes vyjádřit k otázce evropské solidarity, solidarity mezi členskými státy EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">Považuji tuto zásadu za stěžejní, dokonce bych si troufl označit, že tato zásada byla u zrodu EU, a právě na tomto zrodu a na principu fungování EU, na této zásadě bych chtěl ilustrovat přístup české vlády, která naopak zdůrazňuje pouze hledisko evropské jednomyslnosti a evropskou solidaritu zcela přehlíží. My potřebujeme evropskou solidaritu v okamžiku, kdy je nám těžce, ve všech členských státech, může dojít k přírodním katastrofám, určitým tragédiím, nedej bože k terorismu. Právě tam všude má evropská solidarita své místo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chtěl bych také vyzvat českou vládu, aby tedy nebazírovala pouze na otázce evropské jednomyslnosti, ale rovněž dávala více důraz na evropskou solidaritu, která jí tedy skutečně chybí.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-218-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in a few weeks’ time the UK’s National Health Service will celebrate its 70th anniversary, and I take this opportunity here in the European Parliament to say thank you. Thank you to the 62 000 NHS staff from other European nations, and indeed all those from across the world. Doctors, nurses, support staff all help make the NHS what it is through their professionalism and skill and their care and compassion every single day, and with Brexit now causing so much uncertainty, it’s now vital that the rights of those EU nationals working in the NHS are protected for the future. So in the 70th year of the NHS, thank you. Thank you to the brilliant NHS staff from the UK, from across Europe, and from right across the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-219-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the notice issued by the Commission on 27 February this year sets out measures that must be met to ensure continued interoperability of passenger and freight services through the Channel Tunnel after 29 March 2019. The document recently issued by the UK government, in the course of the BREXIT negotiations, gives us some hope that a sensible conclusion might be reached.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, it would be hard to blame people in the UK for having no confidence in the current UK Government to get anything right on the railways. My constituents who use Thames Link and those who use northern rail services in other parts of the country, have seen, since the end of May, hundreds of trains cancelled daily – a total and utter failure to reorganise the timetable.</p>
      <p sl="en">The UK transport Secretary doesn’t seem to accept responsibility and won’t resign. I urge those in the EU who think franchise in UK-style provides any model for how rail should be run, to think again.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-220-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ce point de l’ordre du jour est clos.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Agenda of the next sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
