<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20181115.EN" lang="en" date="2018-11-15" place="Strasbourg" edition="Provisional edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Care services in the EU for improved gender equality (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-006-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la relazione di Sirpa Pietikäinen, a nome della commissione per i diritti della donna e l'uguaglianza di genere, sui servizi di assistenza nell'UE per una migliore parità di genere (2018/2077(INI) (A8-0352/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-007-0000" speaker_id="124889" name="Agnieszka Kozłowska-Rajewicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w zastępstwie sprawozdawczyni. – Panie Przewodniczący! Mam przyjemność rozpocząć dziś debatę nad sprawozdaniem Sirpy Petikainen na temat usług opiekuńczych w Unii Europejskiej w kontekście równości kobiet i mężczyzn. Niestety, jest to bardzo wymowne, że Sirpa nie może tego sprawozdania prezentować dziś osobiście właśnie z powodu obowiązków opiekuńczych. Sirpa, trzymamy kciuki, żeby wszystko było dobrze!</p>
      <p sl="en">Na początek pragnę zaznaczyć, że sprawozdanie jest czasowo i tematycznie związane z legislacyjnym pakietem work-life balance, który zawiera propozycje Komisji Europejskiej dotyczące minimalnego standardu w zakresie urlopów rodzicielskich, a także urlopu ojcowskiego i urlopu opiekuńczego. Sprawozdanie Sirpy Petikainen uzupełnia ten pakiet legislacyjny, pokazując obecną sytuację i wyzwania w zakresie usług opiekuńczych, tak wobec dzieci, jak i wobec wymagających opieki dorosłych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlaczego temat usług opiekuńczych rozważamy dziś w kontekście praw kobiet? Ponieważ tę bardzo trudną, wymagającą pracę wykonują przede wszystkim kobiety. Jeżeli opiekują się członkiem rodziny, bywa, że muszą porzucić swoje normalne zajęcia, bywa, że pracują latami bez jednego dnia urlopu. Ich praca jest nieodpłatna, a jeżeli wykonują ją dla innej rodziny, nawet jeżeli jest płatna, bardzo często jest to praca nierejestrowana. 80% usług opiekuńczych i generalnie usług w sektorze pracownika domowego to praca na czarno bez zabezpieczeń socjalnych, bez przyszłości, bez emerytury. To sprawozdanie dotyczy tego, co w życiu każdego człowieka jest najważniejsze – ludzkiej godności.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mówimy tutaj, w tym sprawozdaniu o kobietach także dlatego, że opieka nad osobami zależnymi jest pierwszą przeszkodą w udziale kobiet w rynku pracy. Przerwy w karierze zawodowej, późniejsze rozpoczynanie kariery, odwlekanie awansu, bo dzieci, wcześniejsze wychodzenie z rynku pracy, bo wymagający opieki rodzice, wybieranie ścieżek edukacyjnych i zawodowych pozwalających na bycie dyspozycyjną wobec rodziny, a nie wobec pracodawcy skutkują niższymi zarobkami, wolniejszymi podwyżkami, okresami nieaktywności zawodowej i w rezultacie niską emeryturą. Przypomnę, że luka emerytalna w Unii Europejskiej wynosi obecnie 38%.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ponieważ obowiązki opiekuńcze są dla kobiet pierwszą przeszkodą w realizacji zawodowej, zapewnienie dostępnych i dobrych jakościowo usług opiekuńczych dla dzieci i dorosłych jest pierwszą powinnością polityków i decydentów w tym zakresie. Demografia jest nieubłagana – potrzeby opiekuńcze rosną, problem jest coraz poważniejszy i będzie narastał, a ofiarami braku skutecznych rozwiązań w tym zakresie są kobiety.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uregulowanie tego rynku, sformalizowanie pracy opiekuńczej, a także znalezienie rozwiązań na bezpieczne pod względem zdrowotnym i finansowym funkcjonowanie opiekunów nieformalnych to główne tezy sprawozdania Sirpy Petikainen, do którego grupy polityczne wprowadziły wiele poprawek i za wszystkie te poprawki w imieniu sprawozdawczyni serdecznie dziękuję. Sprawozdawczyni podnosi w sprawozdaniu wiele istotnych i pilnych potrzeb związanych z kwestią opieki. Zwraca uwagę na fakt, że cele opiekuńcze najefektywniej realizuje się w systemie rodzinnym i środowiskowym, a nie instytucjonalnym. W dalszej części sprawozdania podkreśla wagę takiej domowej, opartej na relacjach z rodziną i przyjaciółmi opieki i apeluje o rozwiązania infrastrukturalne i organizacyjne, które wzmacniają opiekę domową, rodzinną i środowiskową. Kluczowe jest to, aby każdy rodzaj opieki był wspierany niezależnie od statusu zawodowego opiekuna, czyli aby był dostępny zarówno dla osób zatrudnionych w pełnym, jak i niepełnym wymiarze pracy oraz dla bezrobotnych i żeby ciężar polityk opiekuńczych, główny kierunek ich rozwoju opierał się na opiece domowej, kameralnej, a nie na instytucjach.</p>
      <p sl="en">W imieniu grupy PPE popieram to sprawozdanie, jednocześnie zaznaczając, że w kwestii niektórych poprawek składanych przez naszych kolegów z innych grup politycznych, dotyczących rozdzielnego opodatkowania kobiet i mężczyzn, włączenia monitorowania systemów opieki do semestru europejskiego czy przełożenia ciężaru opieki na instytucje nasza grupa polityczna będzie głosowała przeciw, jako że są to propozycje ingerujące w kwestie subsydiarności oraz polityki prorodzinnej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-008-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the Parliament and the rapporteur, Sirpa Pietikäinen, for the work done on this dossier, which highlights some key elements and issues to tackle with regard to care services. The Commission shares the Parliament’s position that such services are crucial for gender equality, in particular to allow women’s equal participation in the labour market and for women’s empowerment and the work-life balance of working parents and carers.</p>
      <p sl="en">This was also part of the work-life balance legislative proposal and the Action Plan to tackle the gender pay gap of November 2017. Ensuring that women and men can combine work with care duties is a key element to close the gender employment gap. Two sides of the same coin are important: having working arrangements that allow workers to combine it with care responsibilities and having access to affordable and high—quality care services for children and other dependents.</p>
      <p sl="en">This will help tackle the gender pay gap, as was highlighted at the Equal Pay Day just a few weeks ago. Having access to care services and working arrangements adapted to one’s care needs are determinant for women to achieve their full employment potential. In addition, the value of women’s work and equal pay for work of equal value are crucial. Indeed, women often carry out care work. It is therefore important to reflect upon the effectiveness of the implementation of the current equal pay provisions, for which I intend to launch an open consultation over the next couple of weeks. The work-life balance proposal is also important in this context. It will offer choices for working parents and is closely linked to affordable childcare facilities. We are making good progress in the trilogues and I hope that we will be able to finalise them before the end of the year.</p>
      <p sl="en">With regard to childcare, the Commission adopted a report on the Barcelona objectives on 8 May this year. While the overall targets for childcare have been reached on average for the EU, less than half of the Member States have met these targets. In order to meet the targets, childcare should not only be available, but also be affordable and of high quality. This is essential for the social inclusion of children from a disadvantaged background, in order for them to have a good educational start in life.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has also adopted a proposal for a Council recommendation on affordable and high-quality early childhood education and care systems, including a quality framework based on principles of availability, affordability, inclusion, a good educational programme, professionalisation and good working conditions for educational staff, good governance and monitoring.</p>
      <p sl="en">Overall, I would like to recall that these issues are monitored in the European Semester process and are reflected in many national reports. Funding through the European Structural and Investment Funds should be prioritised, particularly for those countries lagging behind. I look forward to this debate today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-009-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Pane předsedající, oblast pečovatelských služeb je bezpochyby důležitá a vzhledem k demografickému vývoji bude její význam v budoucnosti ještě posilovat. Toto odvětví je především v pravomoci členských států, jsou to členské státy, které mají zájem na zlepšování podmínek pro všechny pracovníky v těchto službách, ať jsou to ženy nebo muži. Jsou to členské státy, které musí klást důraz na kvalitu a dostupnost všech pečovatelských služeb.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já samozřejmě vnímám vazbu této zprávy na směrnici o slaďování soukromého a pracovního života. V této oblasti podporuji také to, aby pečovatelská doba byla zahrnuta do dovolené, aby pečovatelé měli co nejlepší podmínky pro svoji práci. Ale kompetence členských států je třeba v této věci respektovat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Genderové hledisko se pečovatelské služby týká jen omezeně. Zpráva v tomto ohledu, troufám si říci, není vyvážená a opomíjí řadu faktorů, které by měly být zohledněny, protože pečovatelské služby jsou skutečně komplexní, dotýkají se dalších aspektů, jako je věk, jako jsou ohrožené skupiny a další faktory.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za problematické body považuji mimo jiné to, že se zde vyzývá k oddělenému zdaňování manželů, k co nejširšímu konceptu rodiny, k tomu, aby Komise regulovala a kontrolovala kvalitu služeb, aby vytvořila závazný rámec pro minimální normy pro pracovní podmínky v tomto odvětví a k zaručení finanční podpory pro pečovatele. Tyto a další body podle mého názoru výrazně zasahují do kompetence členských států. Dovolím si říci, že nejen podle mého názoru, ale také podle části skupiny Evropské lidové strany. Přesto děkuji za vypracování této zprávy jako jisté motivace pro naši další práci.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010-0000" speaker_id="28298" name="Iratxe García Pérez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señor presidente, señora comisaria, en la Unión Europea viven en torno a ochenta millones de personas dependientes. El 80 % de los servicios asistenciales prestados en la Unión Europea corresponde a cuidadores informales no remunerados, y de ellos, el 75 % son mujeres. Esto tiene mucho que ver con el problema que existe, en estos momentos, de brecha salarial y de brecha de las pensiones. Es escandaloso que en la Europa del siglo XXI las mujeres estén recibiendo una media de un 45 % menos en las pensiones que los hombres. Y otro dato revelador también que se extrae del informe, es cómo las políticas de austeridad han contribuido al deterioro de los servicios públicos, tan fundamentales para conseguir este principio de conciliación y de corresponsabilidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por lo tanto, damos la bienvenida al informe y mostramos énfasis en que se cumplan aquellas peticiones que se plantean para avanzar en la conciliación de la vida familiar y laboral y en la corresponsabilidad. Por eso también hacemos hoy un llamamiento aquí para que haya un acuerdo por parte del Consejo y se posibiliten las negociaciones con este Parlamento con la Directiva de permisos parentales. Es fundamental. Es indispensable. Las mujeres llevamos toda la vida conciliando. Ahora necesitamos también que sean nuestros compañeros, que sean los hombres los que se incorporen a esta tarea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, además, este informe también hace referencia a la necesidad de que los sistemas de reconocimiento de derechos sociales y pensiones se tengan en cuenta con las cuidadoras y cuidadores. Y por ello, pongo énfasis aquí en iniciativas como la del Gobierno de España, con su proyecto de presupuestos, que incluye volver a incorporar en los sistemas de seguridad social a las mujeres que cuidan a las personas dependientes. Solo con estas iniciativas conseguiremos avanzar en una corresponsabilidad real del cuidado de las personas dependientes y de los niños y de las niñas en la Unión Europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ECR. – Poštovani predsjedavajući, ravnopravnost spolova nešto je čemu apsolutno moramo težiti, ali to mora biti ravnopravnost u prilikama, a ne u krajnjim ishodima. Žene moraju imati jednaku priliku kao i muškarci ostvariti se na raznim područjima u životu, a hoće li to učiniti, to je njihova osobna stvar. Ne mogu se oteti dojmu da feministkinje imaju unaprijed isplaniran život za sve žene, a one koje žele živjeti drugačije za njih su ropkinje ili jednostavno poludjele. Toliko o raznolikosti o kojoj puno pričaju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mjerenje nejednakosti na razini krajnjih ishoda potpuno je pogrešno jer ne uzima u obzir različite biološki definirane afinitete i uloge. Majka je majka, a otac je otac – i imaju različite uloge u životu djeteta prema kojima se onda kroje i neki drugi životni izbori. To je sasvim prirodno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naš je zadatak i ženama i muškarcima osigurati mogućnost izbora, a ne im nametati svoju viziju njihovih međusobnih odnosa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012-0000" speaker_id="125040" name="Beatriz Becerra Basterrechea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor presidente, señora comisaria, la forma en que Europa gestione los servicios asistenciales, la forma en que tratemos a sus profesionales dirá mucho de lo que queremos de la Unión Europea y su futuro.</p>
      <p sl="en">El cuidado de personas dependientes, de mayores y de niños, ha sido tradicionalmente un cometido de las mujeres por el que no han sido remuneradas ni reconocidas. Todavía hoy, el 80 % de los servicios asistenciales prestados en la Unión corresponde a cuidadores no remunerados, de los cuales entre el 75 % y el 80 % son mujeres.</p>
      <p sl="en">La tendencia en Europa es negativa: durante los últimos diez años, el tiempo dedicado por mujeres a cuidados, labores domésticas y actividades sociales ha aumentado en comparación con los hombres. Esto tiene graves consecuencias económicas y sociales, es un obstáculo para la consecución de los objetivos de la Unión en materia de igualdad de género.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es hora de cambiar esto. Es hora de que asumamos el cuidado de los demás como una tarea social clave que marca el nivel de bienestar e incluso el nivel moral de una sociedad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es hora de que los servicios asistenciales estén reconocidos y regulados como lo que son: un pilar europeo de los derechos sociales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tanto las instituciones europeas como los Estados miembros debemos hacer un esfuerzo en esta materia: debemos definirlos correctamente, de manera que comprendan la atención a la infancia y a la educación en primera infancia, la asistencia a las personas de edad avanzada y también la asistencia a las personas con discapacidad. Debemos lograr que sean accesibles y flexibles para atender a las necesidades de familias con diferentes necesidades y situaciones personales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pensemos en las familias monoparentales, en los autónomos, en los trabajadores por turnos en un mundo laboral profunda y radicalmente transformado. Pensemos en una sociedad que debe evolucionar para adecuarse a esos nuevos retos, porque en una Europa que cuida, en una Europa que protege, en una Europa que no deja a nadie atrás, cuidar debe ser una actividad respetada, segura, transparente, profesional y adecuadamente remunerada.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013-0000" speaker_id="124972" name="Ernest Urtasun" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo Verts/ALE. – Señor presidente, en los últimos años la falta de unos servicios de asistencia y de cuidados públicos suficientemente desarrollados y de apoyo a los cuidadores y cuidadoras ha generado que muchas mujeres se hayan visto obligadas a volver a desempeñar tareas de cuidados. La austeridad y los recortes en los servicios públicos han hecho un daño extraordinario a la igualdad entre hombres y mujeres. Y después, evidentemente, esto repercute en la brecha salarial y en la brecha de pensiones, porque muchas mujeres se ven obligadas a abandonar sus puestos de trabajo para dedicarse a las tareas de cuidados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello, es muy importante desarrollar este pilar esencial del Estado del bienestar. Yo celebro que aprobemos hoy este informe en el que se pide claramente que se desarrollen los servicios públicos, que haya inversiones claras en los servicios de atención y de cuidados de los Estados miembros y que haya apoyo a los profesionales, cuidadores y cuidadoras, y formación; y que ese sea un pilar desarrollado que permita, de una vez por todas, tener una sociedad igualitaria.</p>
      <p sl="en">No habrá sociedad igualitaria en la Unión Europea si no tenemos unos servicios públicos que sean capaces de cubrir este pilar esencial del Estado del bienestar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014-0000" speaker_id="125092" name="Κωνσταντίνα Κούνεβα" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, δύο χρόνια μετά την έγκριση της έκθεσής μου για το οικιακό προσωπικό και το προσωπικό φροντίδας, ακόμα περιμένουμε μια νομοθετική πρωτοβουλία στον τομέα της φροντίδας. Γι’ αυτόν τον λόγο τη ζητάμε ξανά μέσα από το κείμενο αυτής της έκθεσης. Δουλέψαμε με τη συνάδελφο Sirpa Pietikäinen για να κάνουμε ένα ακόμα βήμα προς την αναγνώριση και ρύθμιση του τομέα της φροντίδας. Ελπίζω αυτή τη φορά οι συνάδελφοι να μη γυρίσουν την πλάτη τους στα εκατομμύρια εργαζομένων του τομέα, που φροντίζουν τα αγαπημένα μας πρόσωπα και, δυστυχώς, συχνά μένουν στο εργασιακό σκοτάδι όσο εμείς βγαίνουμε στο φως αναζητώντας την προσωπική και επαγγελματική μας εξέλιξη. Τι χρειαζόμαστε λοιπόν, για να βγάλουμε την αόρατη αυτή κατηγορία εργαζομένων στο φως; Πρώτον, ρύθμιση και αναγνώριση του επαγγέλματος σε ευρωπαϊκό επίπεδο. Δεύτερον, γενναίες ευρωπαϊκές επενδύσεις σε δομές φροντίδας σε επίπεδο κοινότητας. Τρίτον, ενίσχυση του πετσοκομμένου κοινωνικού κράτους. Τέταρτον, προγράμματα για εκπαίδευση, υποστήριξη και ενίσχυση δεξιοτήτων του προσωπικού φροντίδας. Συνάδελφοι, ο τομέας της φροντίδας και η διαχείρισή του μπορεί να σας φαίνεται βουνό. Πρέπει, όμως, να το ανεβούμε και όχι απλώς να το κοιτάζουμε. Δεν πρόκειται να γίνει μικρότερο. Είναι καιρός να φροντίσουμε το προσωπικό φροντίδας. Γι’ αυτό και σας καλώ να υπερψηφίσετε την έκθεσή μας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015-0000" speaker_id="124758" name="Mylène Troszczynski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, aider les familles dites «rurales» en réhabilitant les centres de soins locaux ou en créant des centres pour la petite enfance, reconnaître le travail de ceux que vous appelez les «aidants», éviter la discrimination à l’emploi lorsqu’une mère ou un père a fait le choix de servir sa famille sont de bonnes propositions. Mais, comme souvent, vos bonnes intentions s’effacent sous l’idéologie européiste, et c’est à la Commission européenne – via les fonds de solidarité qui ne sont pas les siens – que vous confiez cette tâche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous demandez aux États de mieux répartir les fonds européens, mais vous oubliez simplement que c’est une des souverainetés que vous avez enlevées aux États membres, puisque c’est un pouvoir qui a été donné aux régions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, vous précisez l’objectif réel du rapport, qui n’est absolument pas le bien-être des familles, mais les 370 milliards que représenteraient en une année le manque à gagner pour l’Union européenne et les grandes entreprises lorsque les femmes font le choix de servir leur famille plutôt que de travailler. Vous l’avouez: une mère doit au plus vite retourner travailler à la fin de son congé de maternité. Et pour faciliter ce retour, vous demandez aux hommes de prendre leurs responsabilités.</p>
      <p sl="en">La motivation de ce type de texte démontre une nouvelle fois les ambitions qui sont les vôtres. Je réaffirme donc que les politiques familiales sont et doivent rester une prérogative des États souverains. L’Union européenne n’a pas à entrer dans l’intimité des familles.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, η στρατηγική της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και των βιομηχάνων για ισορροπία μεταξύ επαγγελματικής και προσωπικής ζωής των γυναικών έχει ως στόχο την ακόμη μεγαλύτερη ευελιξία και την εκμετάλλευσή τους. Πίσω από ανέξοδες ευχές στην έκθεση, η φροντίδα της οικογένειας και των ηλικιωμένων, αντί για κοινωνικό δικαίωμα και ευθύνη, μετατρέπεται σε ατομική υπόθεση η οποία το πολύ-πολύ να μοιράζεται ανάμεσα στις γυναίκες και τους άντρες. Προτείνεται, μάλιστα, και η απόσυρση των γυναικών από την εργασία, προκειμένου να φροντίζουν μέλη της οικογένειας έναντι επιδότησης. Τη διάλυση και την εμπορευματοποίηση των υποδομών και των υπηρεσιών στήριξης της οικογένειας και των κρατικών παιδικών σταθμών, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και κυβέρνηση ΣΥΡΙΖΑ-ΑΝΕΛ τις αποκαλούν «στοιχειώδες δίκτυο δημόσιων και ιδιωτικών δομών» με την εργατική λαϊκή οικογένεια να φορτώνεται αβάσταχτα βάρη για τα αυτονόητα. Η δε συμμετοχή της γυναίκας στην κοινωνική εργασία -και μάλιστα με όρους γαλέρας- έρχεται σε σύγκρουση με τη μητρότητα. Άλλωστε -και με σφραγίδα του Δικαστηρίου της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης- νομιμοποιήθηκε, πρόσφατα, η απόλυση εγκύων. Οι γυναίκες των εργατικών λαϊκών στρωμάτων, με τον ταξικό αγώνα τους και την κοινωνική απελευθέρωση από τα δεσμά του εκμεταλλευτικού συστήματος, πρέπει να κάνουν πράξη την ισοτιμία και τη χειραφέτησή τους. Μπορούν!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017-0000" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mano manymu, kalbėdami apie priežiūros paslaugų svarbą Europos Sąjungoje, šiandien ir ateityje, turime iš esmės kalbėti apie du aspektus – kaip priežiūros paslaugos skatina ir prisideda prie moterų ir vyrų lygybės darbe ir namuose, ir, kaip mes galime užtikrinti, kad gerėtų priežiūros paslaugas teikiančių asmenų darbo užmokestis, jų socialinė apsauga, sauga ir sveikata darbe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deja, faktai rodo, kad tinkamų, prieinamų ir saugių priežiūros paslaugų nebuvimas skaudžiai atsiliepia moterų profesinei savirealizacijai, o, kalbant žemiškiau – tiesiog sudaro sąlygas moterų skurdui, kuris akumuliuojasi iki vos ne 40 proc. pensijų skirtumo senatvėje. Kodėl taip yra? Ogi todėl, kad moterų emancipacija namuose vyksta kur kas lėčiau, nei profesinėje srityje. Juk dažniausiai, jei moteris pasirenka karjerą, tai yra suprantama, kaip papildomas jos pasirinkimas šalia neapmokamo vaikų ar sergančių šeimos narių priežiūros, ar namų ūkio ruošos darbo. Moterys vis dar yra baudžiamos, jei pasirenka turėti ir karjerą, ir šeimą. Tačiau dėl to nukenčia ne tik moterys. Dėl to nukenčia visuomenė.</p>
      <p sl="en">Taip, pirmas, svarbiausias žingsnis link lygybės ne tik darbe, bet ir namuose žengtas, dėl ko dar kartą noriu padėkoti Europos Komisijai, ir ačiū, Komisare. Kalbu apie Darbo ir asmeninio gyvenimo suderinimo direktyvos pasiūlymą. O taip pat noriu paraginti Tarybą nedaryti klaidos ir nesumenkinti šito ilgai laukto teisės akto iki tokio, kuris neatneštų apčiuopiamos naudos. Noriu paraginti šalių vyriausybes suprasti, kad šis teisės aktas – tai pati geriausia investicija į mūsų žmonių, į mūsų valstybių ir į mūsų Sąjungos ateitį. Ir pakviesti į tai žvelgti kaip į solidarumo apraišką.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018-0000" speaker_id="128588" name="Linnéa Engström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Fru kommissionär! Vi behöver ”omsorg utan underordning”. Dessa kända ord kommer från Gertrud Åström, som lade grunden till det strategiska jämställdhetsarbetet i mitt hemland Sverige.</p>
      <p sl="en">Omsorgssektorn är kvinnodominerad och underbetald. Några av de viktigaste arbetena i vårt samhälle – att ta hand om barn och unga, sjuka och gamla – är så tunga och dåligt finansierade att nästan ingen orkar arbeta heltid. Ingen maskin eller smart robot kan erbjuda det som en människa kan – en varm hand, tröst, snälla ord i stunder när livet är som mest utmanande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det gör mig livrädd och förbannad att våra sjuksköterskor och läkare knappt hinner äta lunch eller gå på toaletten, att förskolorna inte hittar utbildade förskollärare, att våra gamla förvägras en stunds frisk luft, och att kvinnor måste vara rädda för att föda barn för att barnmorskorna strejkar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Så här kan det inte få fortsätta! I mitt samhälle prioriterar vi kvinnors arbete. Vi ger det högre status och ordentligt betalt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019-0000" speaker_id="127330" name="Tania González Peñas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, el 75 % de las personas dedicadas a los trabajos de cuidados en la Unión Europea son mujeres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los trabajos de cuidados, realizados históricamente por las mujeres de manera invisible en el ámbito privado, son hoy una fuente de precariedad en el mercado laboral y, sin embargo, son esenciales para el sostenimiento de la vida. Los cuidados no pueden seguir realizándose de manera informal a costa de las condiciones de vida y la salud de las mujeres. Apelo, por tanto, al sentido común para eliminar la referencia a los cuidados informales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Debemos profesionalizar el sector y garantizar los derechos laborales por tres motivos: el primero, porque es un derecho, por justicia social; en segundo lugar, porque es una necesidad de nuestras sociedades; y, en tercer lugar, porque no solamente es un problema que solucionar, sino que también es una oportunidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Según la Conferencia Internacional de Sindicatos, en los países de la OCDE, invirtiendo entre un 2 % y un 6 %, en muchos de ellos se podría incrementar hasta un 8 % el empleo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Invertir en cuidados de calidad con servicios públicos de calidad puede ser una gran oportunidad para generar empleos de calidad y mejorar la vida de nuestras sociedades.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! W uzasadnieniu tego sprawozdania stwierdza się z ubolewaniem, że istnieje negatywna tendencja, zgodnie z którą kobiety spędzają więcej czasu na opiece w gospodarstwie domowym i wykonują bezpłatną pracę. Takie rzeczy może pisać tylko osoba, która kompletnie nie rozumie, o czym pisze, i kompletnie nie rozumie ekonomii. Jeśli mamy dwie osoby: jedna pani pracuje na poczcie, a druga pracuje w domu, zajmując się swoimi dziećmi bezpłatnie, to taka sytuacja według sprawozdawców jest gorsza, niż kiedy one zamienią się miejscami: matka pójdzie pracować na pocztę, a urzędniczka z poczty przyjdzie zajmować się jej dziećmi. Obie będą wtedy miały płatną pracę. Według was ta sytuacja jest lepsza, jak rozumiem. Dlaczego według was jest lepsza? Dlatego, że wówczas państwo „położy łapę” na pieniądzach z ich wynagrodzeń. O to wam chodzi. Boli was, że gdy praca jest wykonywana bezpłatnie w domu, to nie macie z tego pieniędzy z podatków. A wy chcecie zbierać tam, gdzie nie posialiście. Chcecie dobierać się do cudzych pieniędzy i chcecie, żeby jak najwięcej pieniędzy wpływało do waszych budżetów. Nie chodzi o żadne dobro ludzi, tylko o wasze pełne kieszenie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-0000" speaker_id="28131" name="Anna Hedh" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Detta är en mycket viktig feministisk fråga, eftersom den påverkar kvinnors dagliga liv och samhället i stort. Dock tycker jag att betänkandet är alldeles för långtgående. Hur medlemsstaterna ska organisera sin omsorg ska vara upp till medlemsstaterna och inga andra. Jämställdhetsperspektivet är emellertid oerhört viktigt och kan inte betonas nog mycket.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kvinnor och män i EU deltar på arbetsmarknaden i olika utsträckning. Kvinnor tar huvudansvaret för omsorgen om barnen och det obetalda hemarbetet. En del lämnar arbetsmarknaden för en tid. En del kommer aldrig tillbaka. Situationen är förödande ekonomiskt sett. För kvinnan blir inkomsten mindre – för att inte tala om pensionen. Dessutom förlorar samhället massor av pengar på att kvinnor inte arbetar i samma utsträckning som män.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kvinnor diskrimineras också i omsorgen. Kvinnor får sämre tillgång till vård, har längre väntetider, och deras oro tas inte på lika stort allvar som mäns. Allt detta måste vi tala om! Allt detta måste vi ha med oss i vårt politiska arbete! Alla vi här i huset har precis lika stort ansvar, oavsett om vi är kvinnor eller män!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023-0000" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, and thanks to our rapporteur. I’m very conscious, colleagues, that there are carers who have not slept overnight because they’re looking after a sick child, a person with a disability or elderly parents, and the statistics that 80% of care is unpaid and informal and that 75% of it is done by women are worth repeating. This isn’t just an ideological debate or about money; this is about the type of society we want for the future. We are going to face an enormous challenge in encouraging people to get into the paid care sector because it is low-paid, and indeed we have smaller families, so we will have fewer people who are available to care. And maybe for selfish reasons those of us of a certain age in this House might ponder those difficulties. So I think this debate should be about a vision for the future, where people who care are cared for by others and have respite and recognition.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamna comisar, stimați colegi, 32 de milioane de copii cu vârstă preșcolară: analiza arată că situația îngrijirii copiilor – și nu numai a copiilor, ci și a persoanelor în vârstă – în Uniunea Europeană nu arată bine. Este un eșec, sigur, și al statelor membre, dar și al Uniunii Europene, pentru că avem foarte multe directive, foarte multe reglementări care, de fapt, nu-și ating scopul.</p>
      <p sl="en">Avem nevoie de infrastructură. Trebuie să alocăm fonduri în zona rurală, unde sunt cei mai mulți copii și unde nu avem posibilitatea de a le asigura o îngrijire eficientă și corectă. Trebuie să asigurăm o remunerație bună și corectă și echitabilă a femeilor, pentru că, în majoritate, femeile fac aceste îngrijiri și, da, trebuie să ne gândim cum putem instituțional să îmbunătățim situația, pentru că, iată, avem situații – în Finlanda, de exemplu – când copiii sunt luați și separați de mamă și ținuți în instituție cu forța.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deci avem foarte multe lucruri de făcut și, pentru un lucru echitabil, trebuie să îmbunătățim și remunerația femeilor și legislația privind drepturile copilului și îngrijirea persoanelor în vârstă.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhora Comissária, a participação desigual de homens e mulheres na prestação de cuidados a crianças, idosos ou pessoas com doenças crónicas, na realização de tarefas domésticas e na participação em atividades sociais na União Europeia continua a ser um fator alarmante na nossa sociedade.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dos cuidados prestados na União Europeia, 80% são prestados por cuidadores informais não remunerados, dos quais 75% são mulheres, pelo que urge avançar a nível europeu com instrumentos legais capazes de promover a igualdade de género na prestação de cuidados e na regulamentação homogénea da profissão.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gostaria de realçar que alguns Estados-Membros já criaram programas destinados a apoio e a proteção a doentes com Alzheimer, às suas famílias e a profissionais de saúde. Por isso, pergunto: para quando a criação de um programa semelhante para os prestadores de cuidados formais e informais?</p>
      <p sl="en">Caros colegas, tendo em conta que a grande maioria dos prestadores de cuidados são mulheres, a futura diretiva sobre o equilíbrio de vida entre a vida profissional e a vida privada deve, efetivamente, proteger a mulher e garantir que a mesma não seja despedida por motivos intrínsecos à condição feminina.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, συζητούμε ένα σοβαρό θέμα, το οποίο έχει άμεση σχέση με τη φροντίδα τόσο των ηλικιωμένων όσο και των παιδιών. Ένα θέμα που απασχολεί τη σύγχρονη κοινωνία. Βεβαίως, επί της ουσίας, είναι ένα κοινωνικό δικαίωμα των πολιτών και η αντίστοιχη υποχρέωση του κράτους είναι να διασφαλίσει αυτήν τη φροντίδα και για τους ηλικιωμένους και για τα παιδιά. Τα στοιχεία δείχνουν ότι το 80% της φροντίδας παρέχεται από μη αμειβόμενους άτυπους φροντιστές, το 75% των οποίων είναι γυναίκες. Ταυτόχρονα, το 27,5% αυτού του ποσοστού των γυναικών εργάζεται με μερική απασχόληση προκειμένου να μπορεί να φροντίζει τα παιδιά. Πρέπει, λοιπόν, να υπάρξει ορθός συνδυασμός εργασίας και υπηρεσιών φροντίδας. Φυσικά, η λιτότητα έχει ως αποτέλεσμα να μειωθούν οι δημόσιες δαπάνες και να χτυπηθεί αυτό το κοινωνικό δικαίωμα. Στην Ελλάδα, πάνω από 35 000 παιδιά έμειναν εκτός παιδικών σταθμών φέτος. Αντιλαμβάνεται κανείς ότι πρέπει να ληφθούν συγκεκριμένα μέτρα και να δοθούν φορολογικά κίνητρα και να ενισχυθεί, βεβαίως, και η αγρότισσα, προκειμένου να μπορεί και αυτή να έχει άπλετο χρόνο, δεδομένου η φροντίδα των παιδιών την απασχολεί πάρα πολύ.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027-0000" speaker_id="124895" name="Krzysztof Hetman" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Warunki opieki zarówno nad dziećmi, jak i osobami zależnymi w poszczególnych krajach Unii Europejskiej znacznie się od siebie różnią. Dotyczy to zarówno samego dostępu do infrastruktury, jak i jakości oferty świadczonych usług. Dlatego też uważam, że choć na poziomie unijnym potrzebujemy wspólnej strategii i zintegrowanego podejścia, nie należy stosować podejścia „jedno rozwiązanie dla wszystkich”, tylko brać pod uwagę indywidualne potrzeby lokalne i regionalne.</p>
      <p sl="en">W celu poprawy standardów usług opieki warto korzystać z narzędzi, które oferuje nam polityka spójności. Uważam, że fundusze strukturalne powinny być ukierunkowane na inwestycje w infrastrukturę na tych obszarach, gdzie wciąż takich ośrodków brakuje lub wymagają one modernizacji. Europejski Fundusz Spójności natomiast może zarówno być wsparciem dla kadr, jak i pomagać młodym rodzicom i opiekunom w powrocie na rynek pracy po przerwie spowodowanej opieką.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ważne jest także promowanie elastycznego podejścia wśród pracodawców, aby osoby sprawujące opiekę mogły łączyć swoje obowiązki z karierą zawodową.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, Commissioner, it’s very important that this report underlines the role of women at the care services within the context of the work-life balance proposal and emphasises the importance of the availability of diverse, quality, accessible and affordable care infrastructure and support for childcare and care for other dependents – either at home or in home-like situations. This is very important to have it in a report of the European Parliament. I would like to underline the fact that the draft report discusses as well the targets for development of different services, and finally includes recommendations related to the funding of care infrastructure and services. The compromises found for the focus on the informal care sector an improvement of conditions in the formal care sector. In addition, my Group, the S&amp;D, underlined the need for investment by the public sector in care services as well as in awareness of the difficult situation of women working in this sector, having in mind the different familiar composition which leads to needing care. The S&amp;D Group also demands to set social progress indicators to be monitored in the context of the European semesters, in addition to be able to reach the Barcelona targets.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in today’s societies, care work is disproportionately carried out by women and girls. They do most of this work for free, and it’s taken for granted. Women’s care work, both formal and informal, is sadly still a source of shocking inequality. Austerity policies and the resulting increase in poverty have seriously exacerbated the problem as vital services have been cut to the bone. Yet, changing demographics mean that more of us are in need of care, so we’re seeing families and dependants forced to fall back on traditional gender roles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Domestic workers, who are mostly migrant women, are open to terrible abuse by employers. Meanwhile, in the UK, Brexit threatens the future supply of care workers, leaving the elderly and disabled vulnerable. I’m happy to see that the report stresses that EU funding should support the transition from institutionalisation to a community and family—based model of care services, both for disabled people and other vulnerable groups such as children, and also that the report highlights the need for a work—life balance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, many children in Central and Eastern European countries are at risk of not being effectively supported in their early ages in order to reach their full potential. If we want the future generation of the European Union to form a healthier and more successful society we need to make early childhood development a priority.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is growing evidence that preventive education can generate lifelong changes in cognitive development and social behaviour when children reach adolescence and adulthood. Early childhood intervention programmes can alleviate the issues of social exclusion, unemployment, poverty, and would also reduce the proportion of mental disease in Member States. In Romania, 40% of disabled children don’t attend any form of education, for instance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Helping vulnerable children to develop at an early age, according to their needs, is part of a sustainable solution to social integration in the EU. I call on the EU to share best practices and I urge the Commission to present a European carers programme that includes early childhood intervention services.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031-0000" speaker_id="124736" name="Merja Kyllönen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, kollegat, ikääntyvä Eurooppa tarvitsee kipeästi toimivia pelisääntöjä. Lapsia syntyy entistä vähemmän, huoltosuhde alkaa olla varsin huono. Monessakin Euroopan jäsenmaassa ikääntyviä ihmisiä on enemmän ja enemmän ja hoivapalveluihin tarvittaisiin lisää työvoimaa niin omaishoidossa omaisia kuin myös julkisissa palveluissa. Se vaatii meiltä toimenpiteitä ja tekemistä niin, että kaikkein haavoittuvimmassa asemassa olevat eurooppalaiset tulevat hoidetuiksi ja huolenpidetyiksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">En usko, että tasa-arvo, oikeudenmukaisuus ja yhdenvertaisuus ovat keneltäkään tässä maailmassa pois. Ne ovat arvoja, joiden eteen meidän kaikkien pitää tehdä töitä.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-032-0000" speaker_id="96813" name="Barbara Matera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ringrazio Sirpa per il suo eccellente lavoro su questa importante relazione collegata al congedo. Nell'Unione europea l'impari partecipazione degli uomini e delle donne alle attività di assistenza e alle incombenze domestiche rimane una sfida continua. Il fatto che le donne dedichino una quantità di tempo sproporzionata allo svolgimento di attività lavorative non retribuite rispetto agli uomini ha gravi conseguenze economiche e sociali e rappresenta un ostacolo per il raggiungimento degli obiettivi dell'Unione europea in materia di parità di genere.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gli ultimi dati disponibili ci parlano di un divario di genere medio relativo alle pensioni nell'Unione europea pari al 40 % a seguito delle disuguaglianze accumulate nel corso della vita dalle donne rispetto agli uomini nel mercato del lavoro. Uno dei principali motivi per cui le donne sono inattive sul mercato del lavoro è costituito dalle possibilità limitate di combinare in modo efficiente, flessibile ed efficace sotto il profilo dei costi un'occupazione retribuita e le responsabilità familiari.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, thank you for your interventions which are very valuable to the Commission. Let me react on several comments here regarding the competence of the European Union to legislate and to come with measures in this area.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission analysed very thoroughly the legal competences of the EU in this field of a combination of work and family duties, and as you mentioned here the family matters fall under the competence of the Member States, while gender equality is the competence of the EU, and also we have a very strong economical case because we see in all the Member States, without any exception, that the situation is not sustainable, that we cannot continue like that, that we have to enable women who want to work to work and to share also the family duties.</p>
      <p sl="en">I speak about the unsustainability of the current situation and economically inadvisable solution because we have at this moment more than 60% of the graduates at universities who are women, and then we do not use the potential of women at all or only in a limited way. Many of you mentioned here the worrying demographic line. This is something we have to do a lot about and while speaking about the social services we have a tendency to speak about the problem of women. No, this is the problem of the whole society. If we do not solve this problem, we will have in the near future a very strong issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission’s position on how to solve the problem was to respect the limited competences we have, but to use them in full, and this is reflected in our work-life balance package which, as you know, is the combination of legislative and non-legislative measures. As for the legislation, you know very well what we are proposing. As for non-legislative measures, we are recommending that the Member States take steps to have a fairer social and tax system which does not bring disadvantages to women who are usually considered to be the first parents, and also we are addressing the Member States through country-specific recommendations, where we are proposing to increase the salaries in the jobs in the social services sphere and in the jobs which are predominantly occupied by women, it means the education, social services and health sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Among the non-legislative proposals, there is also a very strong recommendation to use more public funding for better social services which will be more achievable or accessible and more affordable for all the people who need such services, and I heard from this side of the Parliament that this is the money of the Member States, so they should have a sovereign the competence to decide. Well, we recommend something regarding the EU money, the EU structural funds, where for many years the position of the Commission was that the social services fall under the national competence and it is the traditional, the classical cost, so it should be covered by the Member States. This Commission came with a change of paradigm, we said no, this is not the cost, this is investment and this is investment which has a very quick and high return of investment which pays off and which can be covered by EU money, and this is a change, and some Member States reacted positively on that and some are still maybe hesitating.</p>
      <p sl="en">We want to do everything to through the work-life balance package. The trialogs are on a good track and I do hope that it will be one of our legacies that we came with the legislation which can bring a real difference for the lives of people.</p>
      <p sl="en">Last comment on work-life balance legislation. No, we are not dictating how the people should live. We are not dictating how the people in the family, the men/women, should divide their duties. We are just doing what I am sure is our obligation, opening wider variety of choices for working parents and for carers to combine better their duties in the family and at the workplace.</p>
      <p sl="en">So, ladies and gentlemen, thank you once again for this debate. Thank you once again for the important report which is coherent with what the Commission wants and plans and tries to promote. We indeed need to have a comprehensive approach and to make sure that this issue needs to remain high on the European agenda with a view to reach gender equality.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-035-0000" speaker_id="124889" name="Agnieszka Kozłowska-Rajewicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">sprawozdawczyni. – Panie Przewodniczący! Szanowni Państwo! Pani Komisarz! Serdecznie dziękuję za wszystkie uwagi i komentarze, które padły podczas tej debaty, do bardzo ważnego sprawozdania Sirpy Pietikäinen. Dziękuję pani komisarz Jourovej za deklarację wspierania polityki opiekuńczej z poziomu Unii Europejskiej oraz za pakiet work-life balance, który jest teraz omawiany w ramach rozmów trójstronnych, i trzymam kciuki, żeby rozmowy te zakończyły się powodzeniem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Temat opieki nad osobami zależnymi – zarówno nad dziećmi, dorosłymi, jak i niepełnosprawnymi – wymaga pilnych działań w krajach członkowskich. Z Parlamentu Europejskiego apelujemy do wszystkich osób, które podejmują w tej sprawie decyzje, o podjęcie pilnych działań. Problem opieki to problem kobiet, ponieważ opiekunami są przede wszystkim kobiety. Większość z nich, jak tutaj dzisiaj mówiliśmy, pracuje nieodpłatnie albo nielegalnie bez zabezpieczeń społecznych, bez emerytury w przyszłości, bez urlopu, nadwyrężając swoje zdrowie i siły. Jest to niesprawiedliwe i należy to zmienić także dlatego, że obowiązki opiekuńcze są pierwszą przeszkodą dla kobiet w realizacji zawodowej, a przerwy i ograniczenia w pracy skutkują czterdziestoprocentową luką emerytalną w najbogatszej gospodarce świata. Potrzebujemy dobrej jakości usług opiekuńczych, a najbardziej tych, które realizowane są w systemie rodzinnym i środowiskowym. Potrzebujemy wynagrodzenia za pracę opiekuna i uwzględniania tej pracy przy naliczaniu emerytury. Potrzebujemy wsparcia dla opiekunów nieformalnych bez względu na ich status zawodowy, aby nie musieli rezygnować z pracy w celu pełnienia obowiązku opieki wobec najbliższych. Potrzebujemy pilnych rozwiązań w tym zakresie na poziomie państw członkowskich, a także europejskiej strategii i planu, aby krajowe polityki mogły być skuteczniej realizowane. Zapewnienie dostępnych i dobrych jakościowo usług opiekuńczych dla dzieci i dorosłych jest pierwszą powinnością polityków i osób podejmujących decyzje w tym zakresie, czyli także nas. Dlaczego? Ponieważ demografia jest nieubłagana. Potrzeby opiekuńcze rosną. Problem jest coraz poważniejszy i będzie narastał, a ofiarami braku skutecznych rozwiązań w tym zakresie są kobiety.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-036-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione si svolgerà giovedì 15 novembre 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037-0000" speaker_id="28314" name="Anneli Jäätteenmäki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – Arvoisa puhemies, on erittäin tärkeää, että koko unionissa on saatavilla laadukkaita lasten, vanhusten ja vammaisten hoitoon liittyviä palveluita. Edelleen vastuu läheisten hoitamisesta on useammin naisten kuin miesten vastuulla. Luotettavat ja saatavilla olevat palvelut mahdollistavat siksi myös naisten osallistumisen työelämään. Hoitopalvelut koskettavat lähimmäisiämme, joten on selvää, että niiden on oltava laadukkaita ja sellaisia, että tavallisella ihmisellä on niihin varaa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yhä edelleenkin joudumme puhumaan työn ja perhe-elämän yhteensovittamisesta. Vaikka asenteet ovat muuttuneet, vielä on tehtävä työtä sen eteen, että vastuu kodin ja perheen hoitamisesta jakautuu tasapuolisesti. Toivon, että näissä asioissa päästäisiin jo eteenpäin, missä laadukkailla hoitopalveluilla on keskeinen rooli.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037-5000" speaker_id="125021" name="Agnes Jongerius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftelijk. – Voorzitter, Hoewel ik hoopte dat het ondertussen niet meer nodig zou zijn, kaart ik het toch nog een keer aan: we moeten de loonkloof sluiten. Gemiddeld verdienen vrouwen 16% minder dan mannen. Hoewel er eerder vooruitgang werd geboekt, wijst recent onderzoek uit dat het gat al twee jaar niet krimpt. Ondertussen lopen vrouwen een verhoogd risico op armoede, zeker eenoudergezinnen en gepensioneerden. Onacceptabel en onverklaarbaar als je het mij vraagt. Voorzitter, Gendergelijkheid op de werkvloer is nog niet gerealiseerd. Verlof bij de geboorte van een kind mag geen beperking zijn voor een carrière, maar een recht voor iedereen. Onbetaald werk als huishouden of zorg zou mensen niet mogen dwingen om parttime te gaan werken. Laten we iedereen de mogelijkheid geven om zelf een balans te maken tussen werk en privé, zonder dat gender daar invloed op heeft. Voorzitter, Gelijkheid komt er niet vanzelf, het is tijd voor actie en er valt veel te doen. Het uitbreiden van het vaderschapsverlof is daar een voorbeeld van. Ook is het aanbieden van goede en betaalbare zorgdiensten belangrijk. Denk hierbij aan kinderopvang, ouderenzorg en faciliteiten voor gehandicapten of chronisch zieken. De oplossingen liggen klaar: laten we het gat voor eens en altijd dichten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038-0000" speaker_id="124749" name="Marijana Petir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Kada govorimo o stvaranju ravnoteže između obiteljskog i poslovnog života, iznimno je važno da žene, jer uglavnom su one te koje „nose teret” skrbi na svojim leđima, ali podjednako i muškarci, imaju na raspolaganju kvalitetne i pristupačne usluge javne i privatne skrbi kojima mogu povjeriti svoju djecu ili bolesne ili starije članove obitelji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Važno je stoga ulagati u stvaranje adekvatne infrastrukture, važno je ulagati u obrazovanje u području skrbi. S druge strane, potrebno je prepoznati vrijednost rada njegovatelja i kao takvog ga vrednovati te njegovateljima osigurati sva prava koja iz njihovog radnog odnosa proizlaze. Potrebno je također adresirati rješavanje pitanja statusa neformalnih njegovatelja - osoba koje se same odlučuju preuzeti brigu za članove svoje obitelji, a kojih je na području Europske unije 80 %.</p>
      <p sl="en">Moramo imati razumijevanja za situacije u kojima pomaganje članu obitelji i njega člana obitelji postane posao na puno radno vrijeme. Taj posao nije lak, upravo suprotno, on zahtijeva potpunu predanost i posvećenost drugoj osobi. To uistinu jest posao na puno radno vrijeme koji kao takav mora biti prepoznat, reguliran i vrednovan.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039-0000" speaker_id="125050" name="Ángela Vallina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – En la UE tres cuartas partes de los cuidadores son mujeres. Este dato demuestra una situación muy desigual, que es consecuencia de unas estructuras patriarcales injustas y que condena a millones de mujeres a un acceso al trabajo mucho más limitado que los hombres, por no hablar de los estereotipos asociados que refuerzan la idea de que ante todo debemos estar en casa y ocuparnos de forma exclusiva de las tareas de cuidados. Frente a ello, la UE tiene tratados y toda una serie de directivas que pueden desarrollar y mejorar en materia de conciliación familiar y laboral y de reconocimiento de derechos a las cuidadoras. Por ello, pedimos que la Comisión apoye un programa y un paquete de medidas concretas, que incluyan la prolongación de los permisos de maternidad, para favorecer la igualdad y la conciliación real. Además, queremos que los Estados se involucren dotando de servicios públicos de calidad e infraestructuras clave, como los centros de día o guarderías, con especial énfasis en las zonas rurales o más castigadas por la despoblación. Finalmente, no olvidemos aumentar la dotación de recursos a la política de cohesión para fortalecer la provisión de unos servicios asistenciales públicos y de calidad.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Lyme disease (Borreliosis) (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-041-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la discussione sull'interrogazione con richiesta di risposta orale alla Commissione sulla malattia di Lyme (borreliosi) presentata da Alojz Peterle, Daciana Octavia Sârbu, Jadwiga Wiśniewska, Frédérique Ries, Merja Kyllönen, Michèle Rivasi, Mireille D'Ornano, Sylvie Goddyn, a nome della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare (O-000088/2018 - B8-0417/2018) (2018/2774(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-042-0000" speaker_id="124736" name="Merja Kyllönen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">laatija. – Arvoisa puhemies, komissaari, hyvät naiset ja herrat, rakkaat kollegat, haluaisin kiittää mahdollisuudesta esittää tämän suullisen kysymyksen komissiolle liittyen borrelioosiin eli Lymen tautiin ympäristön, kansanterveyden ja elintarvikkeiden turvallisuuden valiokunnan puolesta. Borrelioosin esiintyvyydestä ei ole olemassa faktatietoa. Esiintyvyysluvut perustuvat arvailuun ja vaihtelevat hyvin suuresti lähteestä riippuen. Monissa maissa borrelioosia ei edelleenkään tilastoida mitenkään ja asialla on suuri merkitys borrelioosin vakavasti otettavuuteen sekä esimerkiksi tutkimusmäärärahojen suuntaamiseen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Borrelioosin hoitokäytännöistä on olemassa runsaasti eriäviä näkemyksiä. Borrelioosia hoidetaan ensisijaisesti antibiooteilla. Yleensä ollaan yhtä mieltä siitä, että parhaat hoitotulokset saadaan silloin, kun hoito päästään aloittamaan varhaisessa vaiheessa. Sen sijaan lääkkeen annostuksesta, hoitoajan pituudesta ja kroonisen borrelioosin hoidosta esiintyy toisistaan poikkeavia näkemyksiä.</p>
      <p sl="en">Borrelioosiin sairastuneiden oirekuvat ovat hyvin yksilöllisiä ja osalla tautiin liittyy vaikeita lisäinfektioita. Vasta-ainetesteissä voi olla useitakin ongelmia, kuten se, että vasta—aineiden tuotanto ei ole vielä ehtinyt käynnistyä, koska infektioista on liian lyhyt aika, tai siksi, että vasta-aineet ovat sitoutuneet immunokomplekseihin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Borrelioosin ja siihen liittyvien lisäinfektioiden tutkimus on tällä hetkellä valitettavan riittämätöntä. Eri hoitomuotojen tehoa pitäisi todella nopeasti alkaa tutkimaan laajemmin. Tärkeä tutkimusaihe on myös borrelioosin kroonistuminen. Potilaat, joiden oireilu jatkuu pitkien antibioottikuurien jälkeenkin, jäävät valitettavan usein vaille kuntoutusta ja hoitoa. Ja heidän kuntonsa ja työkykynsä on usein menetetty pitkäksi aikaa, jopa pysyvästi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pientä edistystä on tapahtunutkin jo, sillä Lymen neuroborrelioosi on lisätty epidemiologisen seurannan piiriin kuuluviin tartuntatauteihin, mutta yhä enemmän tarvitaan panostusta borrelioosin torjuntaan sekä borrelioosia koskevan tietoisuuden parantamiseen. Jäsenvaltioiden hoitokäytäntöjä pitää kyetä yhtenäistämään ja parantamaan ja ennen kaikkea potilaiden, asiakkaiden, hoitoon pääsyä tulee tehostaa ja parantaa. Lisäksi diagnostiikkaa tulee tarkentaa ja olisi meillä toiveissa rokotekin jonain päivänä Lymen borrelioosia vastaan. Edellä esitettyihin ongelmiin, haasteisiin, haluaisimme ystävällisesti pyytää komissiolta vastauksia, ratkaisuja, tulevaisuudensuunnitelmia ja ajatuksia, mitä teillä tämän asian suhteen on.</p>
      <p sl="en">Valitettavasti punkkien määrä kasvaa erittäin voimakkaasti Euroopassa ja niiden maantieteellinen esiintyvyys laajenee koko ajan. Tämän arvellaan johtuvan ilmastonmuutoksen mukanaan tuomasta ilmaston leudontumisesta. Pakkastalvet ovat Pohjois-Euroopassakin kohta harvinaisuus ja tämä suosii erityisesti punkkeja ja niiden isäntäeläimiä. Tässä suhteessa tulevaisuus ei näytä siis lainkaan paremmalta, ennemminkin päinvastoin. Borrelioosiin sairastuneiden lukumäärän odotetaan yhä vaan kasvavan. Sen takia toivomme nopeita aktiivitoimia asian korjaamiseksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lopuksi haluaisin kiittää kollegoitani ympäristövaliokunnassa ja koko parlamentissa erittäin hyvästä yhteistyöstä ja vahvasta tuesta. Haluan kiittää niin kansainvälistä Lymen borrelioosiyhdistystä kuin kansallisiakin yhdistyksiä borrelioosiin sairastuneiden henkilöiden aseman parantamiseksi tehdystä työstä ja erityisesti haluan kiittää irlantilaista kollegaamme Liadh Ní Riadaa, joka on pitänyt tätä asiaa urhoollisesti jo vuosien ajan esillä. Onneksi nyt olemme saaneet koko ympäristövaliokunnan tiimin mukaan tähän työhön. Kiitos siitä. Yhteistyöllä eteenpäin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-043-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Lyme disease, or Borreliosis, is a real health concern for European citizens, who are increasingly exposed to ticks and the associated risks of Lyme disease. In fact, Lyme disease is the most prevalent tick-transmitted infection in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Recent studies estimate that the incidence of Lyme disease at 22 cases per 100 000 persons per year, with a steadily increasing occurrence in several Member States. In the absence of a consistent surveillance system in the past, it remains difficult to accurately assess the overall trend of Lyme disease. It is, however, clear that the northward spread of ticks and adaptation of altitude are associated with climate change and land-use change.</p>
      <p sl="en">Currently, there is no vaccine against Lyme disease so the recommendation is to take general prevention methods, such as tick awareness, appropriate clothing in tick-infested areas and the removal of attached ticks. These are particularly important for citizens living in areas where Lyme disease is endemic and high-risk groups, such as agricultural and forestry workers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me now address each of the questions you raised. Question one: the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) and Member State experts worked on a proposal to include Lyme disease on the EU list of notifiable diseases. However, the diagnosis of Lyme disease is challenging, as the symptoms are varied and often non—specific. In addition, different diagnostic criteria and tests are used in different countries. Thus, the disease may go undetected, with the subsequent risk of developing serious chronic manifestations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Neuroborreliosis is the most serious complication of the Borrelia bacterial infection, seen in about 10% of patients with Lyme disease. The definition of neuroborreliosis is more standardised than other Lyme disease manifestations, with the possibility to confirm cases based on a common EU case definition.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is why, based on a scientific assessment, it was therefore decided to include Lyme neuroborreliosis in the list of EU notifiable diseases under the decision on serious cross—border threats to health. The Commission remains fully committed to tackle the disease, working with Member States to strengthen prevention, surveillance and control of Lyme disease. As a key element, the decision on serious cross—border threats to health, which I have just mentioned, provides for epidemiological surveillance of communicable diseases through the use of comparable and compatible data.</p>
      <p sl="en">Question two: with the recent inclusion of Lyme neuroborreliosis in the list of EU notifiable diseases, all EU and EEA Member States are required to report such cases using the standard EU case definition. The epidemiological information on neuroborreliosis will be collected by the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control, starting in 2019 for cases diagnosed in 2018. In time, this will allow a better evaluation of the disease prevalence and trend of Lyme disease in Europe. Cooperation on surveillance, prevention and control between Member States is ongoing, coordinated by the centre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Question three: the centre is actively contributing to enhance awareness about Lyme disease among professionals and the general population. Several publications and tools are available, including information about the disease and the vector infographics disease fact-sheets for professionals and health practitioners and a communication toolkit on tick-borne diseases and preventive measures against tick bites.</p>
      <p sl="en">To strengthen preparedness and exchange of best practices, the Commission organised a workshop on the challenges of managing outbreaks of vector-borne diseases in September 2017. The centre has also conducted community preparedness case studies, including on Lyme disease, focusing on synergies on community and hospitals.</p>
      <p sl="en">Question four: as regards diagnostic practices, reporting of Lyme neuroborreliosis cases from 2018 onwards will be done according to a common case definition and diagnostic criteria. This will help to allow for a more accurate picture of the prevalence of Lyme disease in the EU. In addition, the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control has conducted a systematic literature review on the diagnostic accuracy of serological tests for Lyme disease. It will start collecting data on the laboratory methods to evaluate the diagnosis for Lyme neuroborreliosis in 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">Question five: as you know, the Commission is not in a position to harmonise treatment practices as this falls within the competence of the Member States. This being said, the Commission is committed to help develop new and better diagnostics for Lyme disease. This effort has seen significant financial support in recent years.</p>
      <p sl="en">Question six: let me highlight that there is indeed currently very significant funding behind efforts to improve the prevention, diagnosis and treatment of Lyme disease in the EU. The Commission has recently supported research on improved diagnostics that will permit early and accurate diagnosis of Lyme disease through the provision of EUR 7.8 million. It is also worth noting that, in 2016, the European Investment Bank granted EUR 25 million for the development of a Lyme vaccine. Additionally, the Commission has provided EUR 3 million to fund the development of an anti-tick vaccine aiming to protect against all tick-borne diseases in Europe. The remaining two years of Horizon 2020, and in particular its forthcoming calls for research and innovation project proposals, will offer further opportunities to support research on Lyme disease.</p>
      <p sl="en">We now need to implement a robust Lyme disease surveillance to have a clearer picture on the disease burden and trends across the EU. We will further focus on awareness raising, improving community preparedness and prevention and supporting research efforts to develop new diagnostic methods and vaccines.</p>
      <p sl="en">I hope, and indeed trust, you share the intention to drive matters forward, to strengthen prevention and reduce the prevalence and the suffering associated with Lyme disease.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044-0000" speaker_id="23693" name="Alojz Peterle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">v imenu skupine PPE. – Gospod predsednik. Spoštovana gospa komisarka, kolegice in kolegi, vesel sem, da danes razpravljamo in glasujemo o limski boreliozi, ki postaja vse večji zdravstveni izziv.</p>
      <p sl="en">Komisarki Jourovi sem hvaležen za izčrpen odgovor Komisije. Prihajam iz Slovenije, ki spada v evropski in svetovni vrh glede obolevanja s to boleznijo in z njo imam tudi osebne izkušnje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Borelioza je bakterijska bolezen, ki jo je težko pravočasno odkriti, diagnosticirati in zdraviti. Tako so mnogi bolniki deležni napačnih diagnoz in terapij. Število obolelih narašča, klimatske spremembe pa pospešujejo širjenje bolezni. Nimamo še registriranega cepiva, ki bi preprečevalo bolezen. Imamo zelo različne prakse po državah članicah, bolniki pa zaradi tega tudi višje stroške.</p>
      <p sl="en">Potreben je skupen pristop na ravni Evropske zveze. Potrebujemo enotne podatkovne zbirke, več skupnih raziskav in enotne smernice za zdravljenje. Zato pozivamo Komisijo, da pripravi evropski načrt boja proti boreliozi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045-0000" speaker_id="97014" name="Karin Kadenbach" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Sehr geehrter Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin! Ein herzliches Danke schön für Ihre sehr intensive Beantwortung unserer Fragen.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Niederösterreich hatte wir einen Landeshauptmannstellvertreter, der von einer Zecke gestochen wurde; das Ganze wurde nicht rechtzeitig erkannt, sodass es am Ende dazu geführt hat, dass er eine Herztransplantation gebraucht hat, um überhaupt zu überleben. Um dieses dramatische Beispiel nicht allzu oft in Europa zu wiederholen, glaube ich, brauchen wir ganz konkrete Pläne, um die Borreliose rechtzeitig zu erkennen, Daten zu haben, damit wir auch wissen, wie wir sie behandeln, und ganz wesentlich – wie Sie auch angesprochen haben – ist die Erforschung einer Impfung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Was wir auch brauchen, ist Aufklärung der Bevölkerung. Nicht nur jener, die intensiv mit dem Forst und der Landwirtschaft zu tun haben, denn hier gibt es ja schon Leitlinien, hier ist auch schon ein gewisses Bewusstsein entstanden. Aber in der Bevölkerung, die das Recht darauf hat, ihre Freizeit in der Natur zu verbringen, entsteht zum Beispiel oft der falsche Eindruck, dass durch eine Impfung gegen FSME, eine virale Erkrankung, die ebenfalls von der Zecke übertragen wird, hier ein genereller Schutz bei Zeckenbissen besteht. Das heißt, ich glaube, hier ist es auch ganz in der Verantwortung der Mitgliedstaaten, die Leute einzuladen, ihre Freizeit in der Natur zu verbringen, aber sie auf die Gefahren, die dort lauern, aufmerksam zu machen. Eine FSME-Impfung schützt nicht gegen Borreliose.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Pani komisarz! Neuroborelioza jest najbardziej rozpowszechnioną chorobą odzwierzęcą w Europie. Cierpi na nią obecnie około – szacuje się – miliona obywateli. Ugryzienie przez zakażonego kleszcza, a także objawy boreliozy mogą być nierozpoznawalne, a to prowadzi do bardzo poważnych komplikacji.</p>
      <p sl="en">W związku z tym, że nie ma szczepionki na boreliozę, konieczne jest podjęcie intensywnych działań. Konieczne jest szkolenie lekarzy pierwszego kontaktu, wprowadzenie badań profilaktycznych, jak i szybkiej ścieżki leczenia dla osób pracujących zawodowo w sektorze rolno-leśnym. Konieczna jest wymiana dobrych praktyk, a także prowadzenie intensywnych i efektywnych kampanii informacyjnych w regionach najbardziej dotkniętych rozprzestrzenianiem się neuroboreliozy. Apeluję do Komisji, by opracowała europejski plan zwalczania boreliozy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047-0000" speaker_id="4253" name="Frédérique Ries" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ALDE. – Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, le courage des personnes atteintes de la maladie de Lyme force l’admiration, car c’est un véritable mur auquel elles se heurtent souvent dans leur parcours de souffrance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Relevons d’abord l’incompréhension de très nombreux médecins non spécialistes qui n’ont tout simplement pas les outils pour détecter à temps cette maladie qui touche pourtant déjà un million d’Européens, un chiffre qui augmente sans cesse, notamment à cause du changement climatique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les malades sont aussi confrontés à un autre obstacle: le conservatisme des académies de médecine. Dans bien des cas, celles-ci continuent de prétendre aujourd’hui que le test Elisa serait fiable à 100 %, alors que toutes les publications scientifiques démontrent l’inverse. Nous dénonçons, dans notre texte, cette prise en otage des patients, qui ont le droit de bénéficier de tests totalement fiables.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est donc essentiel de s’approprier les meilleures pratiques existantes, assorties d’une bonne prise en charge des patients souffrant de la maladie de Lyme chronique, comme c’est le cas en Allemagne et au Grand-Duché de Luxembourg. C’est clairement ce que nous demandent toutes les associations européennes, qui sont des centaines sur le terrain. Chez moi, en Wallonie, je pense particulièrement à Sonia Boulanger, qui coordonne l’ASBL Time for Lyme.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’espoir est là – on en a déjà parlé dans ce débat –, des portes s’ouvrent. L’Union européenne vient d’ajouter la borréliose de Lyme à la liste des maladies transmissibles, ce qui est essentiel pour mettre les chercheurs en réseau. L’OMS a récemment changé les codes de la maladie de Lyme dans la classification internationale des maladies, reconnaissant la démence qui y est liée et la transmission de la mère à l’enfant qu’elle porte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour conclure en un mot, nous l’avons dit: il est essentiel de financer la recherche sur la maladie Lyme, car son diagnostic est complexe et ses formes cliniques sont variées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans les dix secondes qui me restent, je vous rappellerai ceci: un geste, une habitude, une carte, une pince à tiques pour les parents et pour les enfants pourraient déjà, pour commencer, éviter bien des complications.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048-0000" speaker_id="96743" name="Michèle Rivasi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, merci des réponses que vous nous avez apportées au niveau de la Commission. Je me réjouis de cette résolution qui prend enfin en compte la souffrance de ces malades. On a parlé «d’errance thérapeutique». Je ne sais pas si vous le savez mais, comme l’a souligné ma collègue Frédérique Ries, cette maladie est souvent très mal comprise, parce qu’elle présente une forme chronique et qu’elle n’est pas du tout abordée dans les programmes et les formations des médecins.</p>
      <p sl="en">Une forme de déni entoure cette maladie qui ne rentre pas dans les codes. C’est ce qui explique, par exemple, qu’en France, les malades se rendent en Allemagne. Comme vous le proposez, une meilleure harmonisation est donc effectivement nécessaire, car il faut absolument disposer de moyens de diagnostic efficaces. Ce n’est pas parce que les tests sont négatifs que la maladie n’est pas présente.</p>
      <p sl="en">De même, il faut créer des groupes de travail, comme vous l’avez proposé, pour mettre en place un échange de bonnes pratiques, à la fois sur le diagnostic, le dépistage et le traitement. Certains pays refusent de traiter les patients avec une forte dose d’antibiotiques. Et puis, il y a la formation des médecins, qui souvent connaissent mal les problèmes de santé liés à l’environnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, il faudrait développer la recherche, augmenter le financement et améliorer la reconnaissance de cette maladie en tant que maladie professionnelle. L’enjeu est donc important. Mais l’Europe peut apporter une valeur ajoutée pour dresser l’état des lieux, mieux comprendre cette maladie et, bien sûr, mieux la soigner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-049-0000" speaker_id="124750" name="Mireille D’Ornano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe EFDD. – Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, le degré de fiabilité des tests sérologiques et des traitements non conventionnels de la maladie de Lyme est préoccupant et aurait dû, à mon sens, être abordé dans cette question orale. Je relève également l’absence de références au phénomène de l’errance médicale dans laquelle se retrouvent certains patients, ainsi qu’aux mouvements transfrontières des patients cherchant à se faire soigner de cette maladie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous aurions également pu demander si la Commission comptait encourager des campagnes de sensibilisation aux risques afférents à la maladie de Lyme à la suite de morsures de tiques, et notamment au fait que l’infection se manifeste avec un décalage dans le temps et présente des symptômes très variés.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, pourquoi ne pas demander à la Commission de rendre des comptes sur les conclusions scientifiques faisant suite à l’investissement de plusieurs millions dans la recherche sur la maladie et dans l’élaboration d’un vaccin? C’est le rôle des élus que de savoir où va l’argent public.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, l’explosion du nombre de cas de maladie de Lyme témoigne d’une double fracture.</p>
      <p sl="en">Relevons d’abord la fracture territoriale et sociale, puisque la zoonose la plus répandue d’Europe touche avant tout les habitants des zones rurales, ce qui explique sans doute le désintérêt des pouvoirs publics et la difficile reconnaissance de cette affection comme maladie professionnelle. Dans ma région, en France, beaucoup de très jeunes hommes qui travaillent sur les pommiers, par exemple, souffrent de cette maladie dramatique. Certains cas sont vraiment très difficiles et s’aggravent jusqu’à la démence. Cela fait vraiment beaucoup de peine.</p>
      <p sl="en">La fracture sépare ensuite l’homme et la nature, puisque la traque des prédateurs, pourtant essentielle à l’écosystème, charriera dans son sillage la prolifération de certains parasites. Une étude récente démontrait le rôle du renard, parfois considéré comme nuisible, dans l’éradication des tiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">Reste qu’à l’heure où entre 650 000 et 850 000 Européens sont affectés chaque année de cette pathologie, on ne saurait tolérer le véritable parcours du combattant infligé à tant de patients confrontés aux insuffisances de la médecine moderne. Au-delà d’un vaste effort commun à l’échelle européenne, ces malades méritent avant tout notre écoute et surtout notre respect.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051-0000" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, elles sont plus petites qu’une tête d’épingle, mais elles font de gros ravages. Les tiques sont le premier vecteur de maladies animales dans le monde, le deuxième pour les maladies humaines, après le moustique.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est un vrai sujet de santé publique. On l’a déjà dit: de plus en plus de personnes sont atteintes de cette maladie parce que, malheureusement, elle est largement sous-diagnostiquée et parfois asymptomatique. Elle ne fait l’objet d’aucun consensus quant à son diagnostic ou à son traitement. Ce manque de reconnaissance a affecté durablement les patients atteints de cette maladie, qui se retrouvent en situation d’errance diagnostique et thérapeutique.</p>
      <p sl="en">On doit d’abord penser à eux, parce qu’au-delà des simples symptômes grippaux qui peuvent se développer dans la première phase de la maladie, une infection par la bactérie Borrelia peut, si elle est maltraitée, devenir chronique et invalidante. C’est donc une pathologie qu’il faut prendre au sérieux.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’ai bien entendu vos propositions, Madame la Commissaire. Il est urgent d’intensifier les efforts de recherche et un vaccin doit être mis au point le plus rapidement possible. Mais la prévention est également essentielle. Il nous faut mieux informer les citoyens sur la façon de se prémunir contre les piqûres de tiques et sur la nécessité de se faire dépister après une morsure. La borréliose de Lyme étant présente partout en Europe, nous sommes confrontés à un véritable défi transfrontière qui requiert une action européenne coordonnée.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052-0000" speaker_id="193292" name="Tilly Metz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, chacun et chacune d’entre nous peut attraper la maladie de Lyme, la borréliose. Une seule promenade en forêt suffit.</p>
      <p sl="en">La maladie de Lyme peut avoir des conséquences graves sur la santé: des paralysies, des infections articulaires ou des problèmes cardiaques. Tout le monde sait que les tiques transmettent la maladie de Lyme à l’être humain. Mais les tiques, comment attrapent-t-elles la maladie de Lyme? C’est par les petits rongeurs, comme la souris, que les tiques attrapent la borréliose, ou maladie de Lyme. C’est là que le héros de mon histoire entre en scène: le renard. En effet, plus il y a de renards, moins les souris et les petits rongeurs sortent de leur trou et circulent, et moins la maladie se propage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous lance une appel, Mesdames et Messieurs, laissons faire notre écosystème naturel, laissons vivre le renard et surtout laissons le faire son travail, parce qu’il contribue en grande partie à la prévention de la maladie de Lyme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053-0000" speaker_id="21331" name="Sylvie Goddyn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, je crois que nous pouvons être satisfaits du travail accompli pour aboutir à cette résolution sur la maladie de Lyme qui était, vous le savez, très attendue par de nombreuses associations de malades. Chaque année, ce sont près d’un million d’Européens qui seraient touchés par cette maladie, dont le diagnostic demeure, pour beaucoup, incertain et la prise en compte au niveau médical peu satisfaisante.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous savons que la prolifération des tiques et la multiplication des morsures sont directement responsables de l’ampleur de cette maladie. Les tiques cantonnées autrefois aux forêts et aux montagnes prolifèrent maintenant jusque dans les zones péri-urbaines et menacent des foyers de population bien plus importants. C’est la raison pour laquelle il est urgent d’agir à notre niveau, car cette maladie rurale a longtemps souffert de l’inaction, du manque de moyens et du désintérêt des pouvoirs publics.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je me réjouis donc qu’aujourd’hui nous réagissions collectivement à la mesure du défi que représente la lutte contre cette maladie. Bien plus encore, j’entends la voix des malades et des familles qui verront dans notre démarche l’espoir d’être enfin entendus et correctement pris en charge par le monde médical. C’est pourquoi nous devons soutenir cette résolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054-0000" speaker_id="125030" name="Annie Schreijer-Pierik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, de toename van de ziekte van Lyme baart grote zorgen en het is een groot probleem. Er is geen Europese consensus over de behandeling, en diagnose en screening van de ziekte van Lyme is niet aan de orde en de nationale praktijken lopen behoorlijk uiteen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Onnodig veel patiënten hebben geen toegang tot de behandeling die passend voor hen zijn of krijgen niet meteen de juiste diagnose gesteld. Ik spreek ook uit eigen ervaring uit onze eigen familie: mijn neef had afgelopen zomer gewoon de gevolgen van de ziekte van Lyme en de bacteriële infectie daarvan. Hij ging naar de huisarts toe. De familie ging naar de huisarts en de huisarts zegt gewoon tegen deze jongen: “Je hebt gewoon de griep, ga maar weer naar huis.” Op het laatst – hij was bijna overleden – is het nog goed gekomen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar die gevolgen zijn ook in Oostenrijk aan de orde en we moeten hier met elkaar meteen mee aan de slag gaan. Want ook huisartsen weten niet hoe het zit. Ik ben dan ook blij met het uitvoeringsbesluit van de Europese Commissie om Lyme borreliose in de lijst van overdraagbare ziekten op te nemen. Laten we dan nu ook samen deze verschrikkelijke ziekte erkennen als beroepsziekte en het onderzoek en de bewustmaking bevorderen teneinde de ziekte te voorkomen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar niet alleen dat, de hele familie, onze hele omgeving vroeg zich af: wat gaan we daaraan doen? Het zijn niet alleen mensen die in de natuur werken. Het zijn kinderen die fietsen, ook uit steden. Het zijn ook de burgers! Het vereist gewoon een nationale aanpak en dank voor uw aanzet daarbij.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055-0000" speaker_id="96847" name="Claudiu Ciprian Tănăsescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, boala Lyme sau boala cu o mie de fețe, care afectează întregul organism, este cea mai comună și mai larg răspândită afecțiune transmisă de căpușe în Europa. Îngrijorarea noastră cu privire la prevalența bolii Lyme în Europa este cuprinsă în prezenta rezoluție. Salutăm includerea bolii Lyme pe lista europeană a bolilor transmisibile, ceea ce va permite pacienților să beneficieze de avantajele unui sistem de sănătate robust și structurat de identificare rapidă și fiabilă a cazurilor de borelioză Lyme în Uniunea Europeană, precum și de asistența reciprocă în domeniul analizei și al interpretării datelor colectate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Însă trebuie să consemnăm și faptul că această boală cu o mie de fețe solicită finanțări suplimentare față de cele alocate de Uniunea Europeană până acum, în vederea creșterii eforturilor de cercetare pentru detectarea precoce, diagnosticarea și tratamentul boreliozei.</p>
      <p sl="en">De asemenea, avem nevoie de mai multe campanii de informare și de sensibilizare a persoanelor cu risc crescut de îmbolnăvire, precum și de campanii de diseminare a celor mai bune practici de diagnosticare și de depistare a bolii Lyme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056-0000" speaker_id="96897" name="John Stuart Agnew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Lyme disease is one of 10 diseases that afflict humans as a result of contact with ticks. Sometimes there can be two simultaneous infections. There has been a 400% increase in Lyme disease in the UK in the last four years. Good livestock farming practices can make an immense beneficial difference here by reducing tick numbers, yet the Green lobby, with its naive ideas of re-wilding, want to remove the livestock entirely. Between them, sheep as teeth grazers and cattle as tongue grazers can prevent grasses from becoming damp and rank and thus deny the ticks a habitat. Meanwhile, the farmers also control the bracken, another favourite tick habitat. Any ticks that do appear will attach themselves to these animals and will be dealt with by the routine application of recommended insecticides.</p>
      <p sl="en">Twenty years ago, this involved the use of potentially dangerous organophosphorus compounds. Now, thanks to the research efforts of large companies, safer products which are simple to apply will readily destroy ticks. In the absence of these livestock, the ticks will multiply and settle on ground-nesting birds in fatally large numbers, yet the Green lobby will tell you that it’s farmers who threaten bird numbers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unlike grass, ticks do not thrive in heather, which is an alternative feed for sheep. However, the Green lobby frown on attempts to re-establish heather because of its association with politically incorrect grouse shooting. So we have a choice: a thriving tick-free upland economy based on livestock heather and grouse on the one hand, or the Green lobby’s paradise of abandoned land, welfare payments, tick-infested wildlife and human disease.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057-0000" speaker_id="28115" name="Mairead McGuinness" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Thank you, President. I hope that members of the medical profession are listening to this debate, because it has been quite interesting that, across the House from all Member States, what we are hearing from patients is that they are not being listened to when they visit their general practitioner. That is perhaps because there isn’t sufficient awareness of the myriad symptoms of Lyme disease, but we certainly need greater awareness among the first port of call, which is the medical practitioners in the local clinics.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want to compliment Tick Talk Ireland. They have been tirelessly campaigning to raise awareness about this disease. They want patient—centric best practices, and we support them in that. I have read some terrible stories of people who are suffering chronic conditions because of Lyme disease misdiagnosis and lack of treatment. This is a really important debate; it is about the health of our citizens, and I want to thank the Commission for the answers you have given to our questions today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, από τη συζήτηση αποδείχθηκε ότι η νόσος του Lyme ή βορρελίωση είναι μία επικίνδυνη βακτηριακή νόσος, που προκαλείται από το τσίμπημα από τσιμπούρι το οποίο έχει μολυνθεί από το εν λόγω βακτήριο. Επηρεάζει τον άνθρωπο και τα ζώα, και το γεγονός ότι έχουμε 850 000 κρούσματα ετησίως δείχνει πόσο σοβαρό είναι αυτό το θέμα. Πρόκειται για μια επαγγελματική νόσο που επηρεάζει τους γεωργούς αλλά και τους δασοκαλλιεργητές, και νομίζω ότι χρειάζεται πλέον να προχωρήσουμε με συγκεκριμένα βήματα, διότι οι μέθοδοι θεραπείας πρέπει να ενισχυθούν. Πρέπει να υπάρξει ανταλλαγή βέλτιστων πρακτικών μεταξύ των κρατών μελών. Απαιτείται, επιπλέον, κατάρτιση των γιατρών, καθώς και χρήση κλινικών εξετάσεων. Ταυτόχρονα, νομίζω ότι πρέπει να δοθούν χρήματα για την περαιτέρω έρευνα στον τομέα αυτόν, ούτως ώστε να αντιμετωπιστεί η νόσος, που είναι ιδιαίτερα επικίνδυνη –σύμφωνα και με την Παγκόσμια Οργάνωση Υγείας- καθώς μεταδίδεται από τη μητέρα στο έμβρυο. Νομίζω ότι χρειάζονται πολύ συγκεκριμένα μέτρα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-060-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, last Sunday week in my own town, Killarney, there was a group from the Men’s shed – a hundred of them – and they got the European Citizens Prize this year. They came to help control the rhododendron, which is a beautiful plant but is invasive in our National Park. Also in our National Park, we have a very famous herd of deer, and as part of the preparation for their work, they were given an outline on Lyme disease and what steps they should take to ensure they wouldn’t go back home with it, and I think one of the key points mentioned there was that within 48 hours one is safe enough if a tick attaches itself to your body and it’s removed. I think that’s the key point here. We must create awareness and encourage people to check their bodies, especially if they are in parks where there are deer, etc., and remove the tick promptly. That will ensure that nothing will happen. So I welcome what the Commissioner has said in creating awareness and research, etc., because there’s up to a million people affected in Europe and we need to help them.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-062-0000" speaker_id="128588" name="Linnéa Engström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Fru kommissionär! Fästingar är en smygande epidemi. Varje år drabbas runt 800 000 européer av borrelia, och det skapar stort mänskligt lidande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det finns en förklaring till varför fästingburna sjukdomar som TBE och borrelia ökar. Fästingar älskar fuktigt och varmt väder, och det är det som klimatförändringarna ger oss.</p>
      <p sl="en">Klimatförändringarna går fortare och är mer omfattande i vår norra del av världen. Fästingar är effektiva smittbärare, och deras utbredning påverkas av klimatförändringarna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Problemet med ett varmare klimat och fästingars utbredning går hand i hand med andra hälsoproblem. Med ett extremt väder sprids bakterier, inte bara i vatten, utan även i mat. Nya sjukdomar och virusinfektioner får spridning i Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Därför behöver vi en gemensam EU-strategi för att kunna hantera denna tysta epidemi av borrelia. Detta är ett symptom på den stora utmaning vi står inför: att stoppa klimatförändringarna och leva upp till Parisavtalet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-063-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Zajmuję się przede wszystkim problematyką bezpieczeństwa, w tym oczywiście bezpieczeństwa zdrowotnego, możliwością użycia rozmaitych elementów broni biologicznej przez terrorystów czy państwa totalitarne. Od razu powiem, żeby nie było wątpliwości: borelioza nie jest interesująca z punktu widzenia możliwości wykorzystania jej w atakach biologicznych. Niestety po raz kolejny obserwuję, że także w tej problematyce charakteryzuje nas niekonsekwencja, brak determinacji, brak spójności oraz izolowanie poszczególnych tematów, które – podkreślam – mają wspólny mianownik. Zwrócę uwagę na zaniedbania w edukacji, luki informacyjne, braki w diagnostyce, co potwierdziła pani komisarz. Chcę wyraźnie podkreślić, że obywatele Unii Europejskiej potrzebują paszportów i wiz, choroby niestety nie. Dziś mamy problem przechodzenia odry z Ukrainy w kierunku zachodnim, na przykład do Polski. Zwracam na to uwagę, bo tolerowanie takich zjawisk może niestety powodować poważne zagrożenia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-064-0000" speaker_id="23699" name="Kateřina Konečná" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já bych chtěla především moc poděkovat mé kolegyni Merje Kyllönenové, která toto téma přinesla tady na plénum, a jak se ukazuje, je to téma, které jde napříč Evropou, které jde napříč politickými skupinami. Je to téma, které chceme všichni řešit. Řešit ho můžeme samozřejmě tak, že si budeme v Evropě říkat, že víme, že existuje, ale měli bychom ho řešit především tak, že budeme propojovat naše kapacity v oblasti zdravotnictví, a především to, že v Evropské unii dodnes neexistuje jednotný názor na to, jak léčit, diagnostikovat ani provádět screening lymské boreliózy, změníme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Problémem prostě je, že diagnostika nemoci se neděje v čase, který bychom potřebovali. Pacienti jsou velmi často odkázáni na nějakou další banální léčbu, která nezabírá, a následně se opravdu ta expertní léčba odehrává až ve chvíli, kdy už vlastně není moc pomoci a je tam řada dalších problémů.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proto bych chtěla poprosit a děkuji moc paní komisařce za to, že řekla, že se budeme obecně zabývat tím, abychom tuto nemoc lépe zkoumali, lépe hledali příčiny, ale lépe hledali také léčbu. Prosím ji o to, věnujme tomu i finanční prostředky, bez nich to prostě nepůjde, a pokud je nenajdeme, nemáme šanci to změnit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-065-0000" speaker_id="28116" name="Marian Harkin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, and apologies, I’m just arriving, we were at a vote in the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs but I thank you for this one minute. Commissioner, my office has been listening to your responses and, I have to say, I’m not fully satisfied with your response on the need for a proper, harmonised approach to diagnosis. The truth is that many people who have Lyme disease are undiagnosed and this is a double whammy for people who suffer from this most debilitating disease.</p>
      <p sl="en">I know in Ireland many patients have to go abroad so that they can be properly tested. It’s very expensive for them, many of them have suffered for many years and they cannot get a diagnosis in Ireland. Specialists and doctors will tell them: clinically, the results say you’re fine. They go abroad and they get a diagnosis of Lyme disease. I believe that the EU can act in a much stronger way by strongly encouraging a harmonised, accurate test for Lyme disease so that all EU citizens can have access to timely and accurate diagnosis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-066-0000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, drago mi je da je ovo pitanje došlo na dnevni red jer, zaista, lajmska bolest predstavlja veliku opasnost za zdravlje. Kao što znamo simptomi se ponekad jako kasno uočavaju i problem je s dijagnostikom. Moramo učiniti sve, kao što je gospođa Jourová rekla, da radimo na istraživanju te bolesti, ne samo bolesti nego i cjepiva. Čuli smo da nema cjepiva i to je osnovni problem. Čuli smo da postoje različite prakse u različitim zemljama, znači, moramo ujednačiti prakse liječenja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Smatram da je neophodno naći cjepivo. Spomenuli ste Horizon istraživanje, mislim da je to put do cilja, ali naravno nije naodmet ovdje spomenuti i klimatske promjene koje su činile, odnosno pogodovale da ima sve više i više prijenosnika, odnosno krpelja i da su na velikim poljoprivrednim površinama i šumama zaista problemi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Znači, moramo učiniti sve kako bismo svoje građane, odnosno pacijente zaštitili, ali i kako bismo liječnicima opće prakse omogućili da lakše dođu do dijagnostike i da, ako uspijemo, pronađemo cjepivo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-068-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, I have listened with great interest to the views during this discussion, and I am grateful for all your valuable insights and interest to address the burden of Lyme disease in Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allow me to repeat that the emphasis now should be on implementation and concrete action to support Member States in their efforts. With the recent inclusion of Lyme neuroborreliosis in the list of EU notifiable diseases, we will strengthen surveillance across the EU using a common EU case definition and diagnostic criteria.</p>
      <p sl="en">This will lead to a more accurate assessment of the disease burden and trends of Lyme disease in Europe. We will continue to raise awareness at EU, national and community levels, among both the public and health professionals. Here, the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control has a key role to play.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, the development of new and better diagnostics and vaccines will be further supported through the framework programme for research and innovation, Horizon 2020 and through other available instruments.</p>
      <p sl="en">I once again thank you for your interest in this issue and look forward to working closely together towards achieving strengthened surveillance, earlier diagnosis and, ultimately, prevention of this disease.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-069-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Έχω λάβει, σύμφωνα με το άρθρο 128 παράγραφος 5 του Κανονισμού, μία πρόταση ψηφίσματος.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί την Πέμπτη 15 Οκτωβρίου 2018.</p>
      <p sl="en">Γραπτές δηλώσεις (άρθρο 162 του Κανονισμού)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070-0000" speaker_id="135540" name="Czesław Hoc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Można powiedzieć: „Najwyższy czas!”. Powstała rezolucja Parlamentu Europejskiego w sprawie neuroboreliozy z Lyme (boreliozy). Wreszcie Europa wydała walkę najczęstszej chorobie odkleszczowej. Na boreliozę w Europie cierpi obecnie ok. 1 mln obywateli. Obliczono, że w sytuacji ustanowienia niezawodnej wczesnej diagnozy boreliozy i tym samym wyraźnego zmniejszenia przypadków zaawansowanego stadium tej choroby, zaoszczędzimy ok. 330 mln euro na kosztach opieki zdrowotnej w ciągu pierwszych 5 lat! Co ważniejsze, oszczędzimy cierpienia wielu ludziom! Musimy też pamiętać, że borelioza jest chorobą zawodową leśników i rolników. To także koszty odszkodowawcze! Zatem w trybie pilnym należy wprowadzić europejski plan zwalczania tej cichej epidemii, stworzyć europejską sieć ds. boreliozy, a więc wprowadzić odrębny kod ICD (Międzynarodowa Statystyczna Klasyfikacja Chorób i Problemów Zdrowotnych) dla wczesnego i późnego stadium choroby, wprowadzić badania profilaktyczne, szybką i niezawodną identyfikację przypadków boreliozy w Unii, ustalić szybką ścieżkę terapii wg EBM (medycyny opartej na faktach) i wprowadzić stały europejski monitoring.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070-5000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Lajmska borelioza je bakterijska bolest koju uzrokuje bakterija Borrelia burgdoferi koja se na ljude prenosi ujedom krpelji koji su također kontaminirani bakterijom. Lajmska bolest zarazna je bolest ljudi i nekih vrta domaćih i divljih životinja koja se prenosi krpeljima. U Europi ima oko 650 000 – 850 000 procijenjenih slučajeva, a geografski je veća učestalost u srednjoj Europi. Zaraza pojavljuje u proljetnom i ljetnom razdoblju (od travnja do listopada) stoga je borelioza prepoznata kao profesionalna bolest poljoprivrednika, šumarskih radnika i istraživača na terenu u zemljama u kojima je prisutna. EU izražava zabrinutost u pogledu zabrinjavajućih razmjera širenja lajmske bolesti kod europskog stanovništva, s obzirom na to da su korištene metode izračuna pokazale da oko 1 milijun građana pati od te bolesti. Unija je do sada dodijelila velika sredstva za istraživanje u pogledu ranog otkrivanja i budućeg liječenja lajmske borelioze (do 16 milijuna eura kroz projekte kao što su ANTIDotE, ID-LYME i LYMEDIADEX). Iznimno je važno i dalje raditi na temeljnim saznanjima o mehanizmu koji lajmsku bolest pretvara u kroničnu bolest stoga ovo Izvješće poziva na obvezno izvješćivanje u svim državama članicama pogođenima lajmskom bolešću.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Debates on cases of breaches of human rights, democracy and the rule of law  (debate)"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="4.1. Vietnam, notably the situation of political prisoners">
    <intervention id="4-073-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Το επόμενο σημείο στην ημερήσια διάταξη είναι η συζήτηση επί έξι προτάσεων ψηφίσματος σχετικά με το Βιετνάμ, ιδίως την κατάσταση των πολιτικών κρατουμένων (2018/2925(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-074-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Panie Przewodniczący! Państwa komunistyczne często ewoluują, wielu z nas wie to najlepiej, bo widziało to w ciągu swojego życia, ale komunizm to komunizm i niestety w naszych relacjach z państwami, które mają tego typu rządy, musimy zawsze zwracać uwagę na konieczność odejścia od tej ideologii. W Wietnamie trwają systematyczne prześladowania chrześcijan, czasami bardzo drastyczne. Pastor Nguyen Trung Ton został skazany na 12 lat więzienia, jest chory, rodzina nie ma z nim możliwości kontaktu, a w sytuacji braku leczenia jego życie jest naprawdę poważnie zagrożone. Burzy się kościoły, zakazuje się druku Biblii w języku mniejszości narodowych, na przykład Muongów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ale w tym miejscu warto również zwrócić uwagę na to, co dzieje się gdzie indziej w Azji Wschodniej. W Chinach również nasilają się prześladowania Kościoła. Biskup Peter Shao Zhumin został niedawno aresztowany, podobnie jak czterech jego księży. Prosiłbym pana komisarza o zajęcie stanowiska w tej sprawie, dlatego że milczenie będzie …</p>
      <a text="(Przewodniczący odebrał mówcy głos)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-075-0000" speaker_id="96728" name="Barbara Lochbihler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasserin. – Herr Präsident! In Vietnam beobachten wir eine Zunahme an willkürlichen Verhaftungen und politisch motivierten Verurteilungen von Menschenrechts- und Umweltaktivisten, von Rechtsanwälten und Bloggern. Wer seine Meinung frei äußern will, wer Kritik an Missständen übt oder das Recht auf Versammlungsfreiheit nutzt, muss mit Verfolgung und Verhaftung rechnen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich war AFET-Berichterstatterin für das Partnerschaftsabkommen mit Vietnam, dessen Vorgaben für Menschenrechtsschutz auch für das Freihandelsabkommen gelten. Es ist unerlässlich, dass die EU klare Benchmarks für Menschenrechtsschutz formuliert, die Vietnam erfüllen muss, bevor dem Freihandelsabkommen zugestimmt wird. Dazu gehören vor allem die umgehende Freilassung politischer Gefangener, die Überarbeitung des Strafgesetzbuches und die Ratifizierung der IAO-Abkommen 87, 98 und 105. Die EU muss deutliche Worte zu den Menschenrechtsverletzungen in Vietnam finden und die Zivilgesellschaft vor Ort auch durch Prozessbeobachtung und Gefängnisbesuche unterstützen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-076-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autore. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, quando noi parliamo del Vietnam ci vengono in mente le immagini dalla guerra sanguinosa con gli americani, le bombe e appunto le armi, però in realtà la guerra al nemico si è trasformata in una guerra al dissenso. Nel paese del Sud-Est asiatico, se si esprime un'opinione contraria, specie in materia di diritti umani o diritti ambientali, si finisce in cella, e lì iniziano maltrattamenti, bastonate, elettroshock, iniezioni di sostanze. E noi cosa facciamo per rispondere a tutto questo? Noi premiamo il Vietnam con un bel accordo commerciale. Allora la risposta di questo Parlamento deve stare lì, nel negare appunto questo accordo commerciale, nel rispondere nei fatti alle violazioni dei diritti umani che avvengono in questo paese.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-077-0000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">auteure. – Monsieur le Président, la situation en matière de droits humains au Vietnam est préoccupante. Alors que l’Union européenne négocie un accord commercial avec le Vietnam depuis 2012, la situation se détériore de jour en jour. La répression contre la liberté d’expression et la condamnation de toute critique politique à l’égard du gouvernement s’intensifient. Blogueurs, militants pro-démocratie, militants en faveur des droits sociaux et environnementaux sont poursuivis, violentés, torturés, arrêtés arbitrairement, condamnés à de lourdes peines pouvant aller jusqu’à la peine de mort. Faut-il rappeler que ce pays a exécuté, en moyenne, 147 personnes par an entre 2013 et 2016?</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans ce contexte, nous demandons aux autorités du Vietnam de libérer les prisonniers politiques et les activistes, d’adopter les lois nécessaires pour garantir la liberté d’expression, de ratifier et de respecter les conventions de l’OIT, notamment en matière de liberté d’association.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous demandons aussi à la Commission de prendre en considération cette situation désastreuse en matière de droits humains dans le cadre des discussions sur l’accord commercial.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078-0000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, a staggering 160 human rights activists are in prison in Vietnam, reflecting the systematic repression in the country: from free expression to freedom of belief, all the way to the abysmal prison conditions and the application of the death penalty.</p>
      <p sl="en">We call on the Vietnamese authorities to respect human rights and to release those only detained for exercising their human rights. We urge access for UN special rapporteurs on human rights defenders, the Working Group on Arbitrary Detention and the UN Special Rapporteur for freedom of expression. We remind the Vietnamese authorities that human rights are a clear conditionality when it comes to trade relations.</p>
      <p sl="en">And I wanted to specifically zoom in on freedom of expression, online and offline, given the fact that Vietnam ranks 175th out of 180 countries on the Reporters Without Borders’ list of press freedom in the world. They really have to start respecting the rights of freedom of expression, online and offline, and the least we can do in Europe is to stop the export of surveillance systems that are used to track and trace human rights defenders.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-079-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Autorka. – Pane předsedající, Vietnam je dynamicky se rozvíjející země, která má před sebou slibnou budoucnost. Stejně jako v Číně ale i zde dochází pod vládou komunistické strany k masivnímu porušování lidských práv a svobod. Vidíme tu také podobný paradox jako v jiných takzvaně komunistických systémech – neexistence odborů, masivní porušování práv pracujících nebo závislost médií na politických aktérech.</p>
      <p sl="en">Index Reportéři bez hranic uvádí, že v roce 2018 se závislost médií na komunistické straně dokonce ještě zvýšila. Svobodný tisk prakticky neexistuje a jakýkoliv nezávislý projev v médiích je ve většině případů trestán odnětím svobody.</p>
      <p sl="en">Také chci zmínit, že trest smrti je ve Vietnamu stále aktuální záležitostí a o to více je alarmující skutečnost, že Vietnam drží počet odsouzených k trestu smrti v tajnosti před mezinárodním společenstvím. Toto jsou závažná fakta, ke kterým nemůžeme mlčet. Přimět k něčemu Čínu je složité, ale v případě Vietnamu máme v rukou jistý nástroj. Na spadnutí je totiž podpis dohody o volném obchodu mezi Evropskou unií a Vietnamem. Evropský parlament v tomto usnesení dává najevo, že mu situace politických vězňů, blogerů, aktivistů, křesťanských duchovních a masy obyvatel sledované režimem pomocí moderních technologií není lhostejná. Evropský parlament bude trvat na zlepšení ze strany Vietnamu, jinak neudělí obchodní dohodě souhlas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vietnam je pro mě země paradoxně velmi blízká, protože v České republice žije sto tisíc Vietnamců, což je největší komunita v Evropě. Proto bych si přála, aby Evropská unie měla s Vietnamem dobré ekonomické vztahy. Bez podmínek to ale nepůjde. Jsem také ráda, že k tomu je velký konsensus napříč politickými stranami v Evropském parlamentu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-080-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">I condemn the types of practices mentioned in this resolution and call on the Vietnamese authorities to release anyone it has imprisoned for exercising their fundamental right. I would also call for the criminal code to be reassessed and any laws which restrict these basic undertakings.</p>
      <p sl="en">In my opinion, Vietnam should ratify all human rights treaties of the United Nations, and cannot be seen to take human rights seriously until having done so. At the same time, having visited Vietnam a couple of years ago on a mission on behalf of INTA, I know Vietnam to be a wonderful, beautiful country with exceptionally nice and decent people.</p>
      <p sl="en">But I must stand up to this injustice and insist that it stop occurring. The relationship between the EU and Vietnam is a great one but full respect of the fundamental rights to freedom of expression, association, and peaceful assembly must be respected on both sides and the EU should work with Vietnam to ensure this can happen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-081-0000" speaker_id="4533" name="Neena Gill" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Commissioner, with the EU-Vietnam trade and investment agreements on the table, we need to be more serious about the ‘essential elements’ clauses. Domestic repression has worsened in Vietnam. Human rights activists and bloggers not only face surveillance, intimidation and arbitrary arrest, but long stints in pre-trial detention, solitary confinements and excessive sentences.</p>
      <p sl="en">So Commissioner, I’d like you to clarify a couple of points, please. In terms of, firstly, what concrete human rights improvements has Vietnam made following the FTA negotiations?</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, how will the Commission ensure that Vietnam amends its repressive legal framework, in particular the penal code, the law on cyber security, bringing it into full compliance with international human rights standards?</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, besides pressing Vietnam to release political prisoners, has the EU pushed for establishment of an Independent Police Complaints Commission to investigate grievances and provide oversight over these authorities?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-082-0000" speaker_id="117477" name="Mark Demesmaeker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, er is al veel gezegd in dit debat en af en toe moeten we toch eens in de spiegel kijken. Natuurlijk is een vrijhandelsakkoord van groot belang voor de dynamiek en de ontwikkeling van een land als Vietnam, voor de welvaart van zijn mensen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar herhalen we ook niet altijd dat vrije handel en een vrije samenleving hand in hand moeten gaan? Snakken mensen ook en vooral niet naar vrijheid? Antwoordt u eens eerlijk: heeft de overheid van Vietnam in uw ogen al voldoende getoond dat het concrete stappen zet om een einde te maken aan de massale mensenrechtenschendingen en de repressie?</p>
      <p sl="en">De feiten: journalisten, mensenrechtenverdedigers, bloggers, geestelijken, politieke activisten, zij belanden voor het minste kritische geluid in de cel. Ik noem nadrukkelijk Hoang Duc Binh, Nguyen Nam Phong, Nguyen Trung Truc en Le Dinh Luong. Zij moeten vrijgelaten worden, net als honderden anderen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik verzoek de Commissie daarom met klem om Vietnam tijdens de mensenrechtendialoog blijvend te wijzen op zijn verplichtingen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-083-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Monsieur le Président, les régimes communistes européens se sont effondrés en 1989, deux ans avant que l’URSS ne disparaisse à son tour. On trouve malgré tout encore quelques régimes communistes dans le monde, comme par exemple au Vietnam, qui fait figure de dinosaure.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Constitution vietnamien proclame, je cite, que «le Parti communiste, avant-garde de la classe ouvrière, est la force qui dirige l’État et la société». L’Assemblée nationale et la justice sont donc à ses ordres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le Vietnam cherche depuis vingt ans à s’insérer dans la société internationale, c’est ainsi qu’il a adhéré à l’ASEAN en 1995, à l’APEC en 1998, à l’OMC en 2007 et qu’il a signé un accord de partenariat avec l’Union européenne en 2012.</p>
      <p sl="en">Malgré tout, le Vietnam n’en demeure pas moins une dictature qui emprisonne ses opposants politiques, comme par exemple M. Dinh Luong, condamné à vingt ans de prison le 16 août dernier. Le Premier ministre français vient pourtant de faire l’éloge du président Hô Chi Minh, fondateur de cette dictature communiste, en échange de la signature de contrats commerciaux.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Union européenne aurait pu sauver l’honneur européen, mais elle ne le fera pas, car elle s’apprête à signer un accord de libre-échange avec le Vietnam. Bientôt les consommateurs européens pourront donc acheter à vil prix les produits fabriqués par les prisonniers politiques vietnamiens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-084-0000" speaker_id="188624" name="Wajid Khan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Vietnam is actually reducing its citizens' freedom in every area. There are over 100 human rights defenders languishing in jail, often in awful conditions, and the new cyber security law will give authorities more tools to silence dissent. It might surprise Members that despite all this, the EU is accelerating the EU-Vietnam Free Trade Agreement process, pushing for a swift implementation. This Parliament must make it clear that we will not ratify this unless there is solid progress on human rights. The EU risks losing its credibility, if on the one hand it withdraws trade preferences with Cambodia over human rights abuses, and on the other hand, it signs a trade agreement with one of the most repressive states in Southeast Asia. Therefore, I urge Vietnam to release political prisoners, bring its legislation in line with international human rights standards, halt all executions and ratify the ILO conventions, and I call on the EU to strengthen their efforts to ensure concrete human rights improvements in Vietnam. The EU trade policy was designed as a tool to promote human rights in third countries and, Mr President, we must use it as such.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-085-0000" speaker_id="124755" name="Jean-Luc Schaffhauser" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, le conflit naissant en mer de Chine orientale doit amener nos États à agir avec la plus grande précaution.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous sommes enserrés entre les États-Unis, qui soufflent sur les braises, les États de la région, qui se réarment, et la Chine, qui investit massivement dans sa marine de guerre. La situation devient extrêmement critique et nous faisons face à un risque de conflit majeur. J’ai toujours combattu le communisme et je n’ai aucune tendresse pour le régime de Hanoï. Je trouve particulièrement intolérables les persécutions dont souffrent les catholiques vietnamiens. Ce ne sont pas des proclamations grandiloquentes, mais des actions diplomatiques discrètes et résolues de nos États qui pourront les faire cesser. Mais en Asie, on négocie toujours en respectant la souveraineté nationale de ses interlocuteurs. Il suffirait de refuser l’accord commercial, produit de votre idéologie et qui livre d’ailleurs nos économies au dumping féroce d’un pays sans règles, pour obtenir des concessions et obtenir une plus grande démocratie. Alors pourquoi n’allez-vous pas dans cette direction?</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc, une fois de plus, agissez avec prudence et fermeté!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-087-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Nie podpisałem się pod tą rezolucją, ale oczywiście zagłosuje za nią. Nie podpisałem się, bo uważam, że autorzy tego typu rezolucji powinni być świetnie zorientowani we wszystkich szczegółach i wiedzieć o każdym punkcie coś więcej, niż tylko wynika to z uzasadnienia. Zagłosuje oczywiście za tą rezolucją przede wszystkim ze względu na trzy punkty: J, K i M, czyli te, które obejmują prawa organizacji pozarządowych, prawa dziennikarzy, działalność wolnych mediów. Sami Reporterzy bez Granic piszą, iż państwo to zasługuje rzeczywiście na szczególną uwagę ze względu na najgorsze warunki pracy dziennikarzy i wolnych mediów. Przypomnę: jest to chyba 175. lub 176. państwo na 180 ocenianych, jeżeli chodzi o prawa dziennikarzy do wykonywania zawodu. Z tego powodu, podkreślam, poprę ten apel i treść rezolucji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-088-0000" speaker_id="124953" name="Jude Kirton-Darling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it’s becoming increasingly difficult to ignore the human rights situation in Vietnam. Well, that’s for everyone except for our trade negotiators. Human rights defenders report a deteriorating situation on the ground, whether they be online bloggers, religious minorities or trade union leaders in shoe factories or in the fishing industries. In a country where basic freedoms such as the freedom of speech or religious rights are routinely denied to the population and where political opposition is systematically repressed and over 150 reported prisoners of conscience and human rights activists are currently detained in often terrible conditions, if the EU was serious about securing progress in terms of human and labour rights in Vietnam it would insist on the release of these prisoners and the pre-ratification of human rights and ILO core conventions as a precondition to our ratification of the trade and investment agreements. At the very least, the EU should articulate a series of tangible human rights benchmarks that Vietnam must meet before those agreements come before this House for approval. That’s at the very least – we need more, and we need better.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-089-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το Βιετνάμ είναι το νέο Eldorado. Οι πολυεθνικές στήνουν πάρτι. Έχουν κάνει επενδύσεις, αξιοποιούν τους μισθούς πείνας του Βιετνάμ και, βεβαίως, κερδίζουν υπερβολικά ποσά. Γι’ αυτό υπάρχει και ανοχή στην ασυδοσία όσον αφορά την προστασία των εργασιακών δικαιωμάτων στο Βιετνάμ και -πολύ περισσότερο- ανοχή, πλέον, στην καταπίεση, στην παραβίαση των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων, στις καταδίκες ακτιβιστών και στην κακομεταχείριση των κρατουμένων, οι οποίοι δεν έχουν καν πρόσβαση σε δικηγόρο. Είναι γεγονός ότι ο ποινικός κώδικας του Βιετνάμ δεν είναι καν συμβατός με τα διεθνή πρότυπα και, φυσικά, η καταπίεση έχει επεκταθεί και στους χριστιανικούς πληθυσμούς. Απαιτείται, λοιπόν, μορατόριουμ στη θανατική ποινή και, φυσικά, λήψη σκληρών μέτρων κατά του Βιετνάμ. Δεν μπορεί να υπάρχει αυτή η προνομιακή μεταχείριση, με εργαλεία συνεργασίας της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και με ελεύθερες συναλλαγές, και να συνεχίζεται αυτή η κατάσταση στο Βιετνάμ.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-090-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Fabio Massimo Castaldo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, esprimere le proprie idee ha un prezzo in Vietnam: rinunciare alla propria libertà e a volte anche alla propria vita. Lo dimostra bene il caso di Hoang Duc Binh, noto blogger vietnamita di 34 anni. La sua denuncia del disastro ambientale causato dalla compagnia taiwanese Formosa gli è costata assai cara: la condanna a ben 14 anni di carcere.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'accusa: resistenza a pubblico ufficiale e, udite udite, abuso delle libertà democratiche contro gli interessi dello Stato. Paradossale perché l'abuso presuppone il godimento pieno di questa libertà. Libertà di cui però i vietnamiti non beneficiano affatto, specialmente dopo la revisione del codice penale, che addirittura richiede agli avvocati di denunciare i propri stessi assistiti, se colpevoli di determinati reati.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi chiedo, allora, colleghi, cosa è cambiato dopo gli accordi firmati con un governo che continua a reprimere con la forza anche il minimo dissenso. Un governo che si fa beffe delle convenzioni internazionali dallo stesso firmate e che è divenuto ormai un paradiso per le multinazionali. Le nostre richieste sono chiare: rilascio immediato e incondizionato di tutti gli attivisti, giornalisti, prigionieri di coscienza e semplici cittadini. Pretendiamo il pieno rispetto dei diritti umani, se questi accordi non sono carta straccia. Su questo no, proprio non possiamo negoziare.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário, é recorrente nesta casa falarmos do Vietname e, infelizmente, nunca pelos melhores motivos, devo acrescentar. Desta vez, a regra não é excecionada e, uma vez mais, eis-nos aqui a debater a falta de liberdade e democracia e a constante violação dos direitos humanos no Vietname.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desta vez, Sr. Comissário, o que nos traz aqui é a denúncia efetuada pelo Projeto 88 de que atualmente estão atirados, em condições sub-humanas, para as tristemente célebres prisões vietnamitas, cento e sessenta ativistas e que as autoridades vietnamitas continuam a prender, a perseguir e a intimidar os defensores dos direitos humanos, os jornalistas, os bloguistas, os advogados defensores dos direitos humanos e os ativistas da sociedade civil numa escala sem precedentes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sr. Comissário, a União não pode continuar a pactuar com os Estados que sistematicamente violem os seus compromissos internacionais na defesa dos direitos humanos e que persigam quem expressa opinião diferente da oficial. Por isso, Sr. Comissário, é da mais elementar justiça e decência moral que a União inste as autoridades vietnamitas a libertarem, sem exceção, todos os presos políticos, sob pena de ficar comprometido o acordo de cooperação e parceria com o Vietname.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não podemos, Sr. Comissário, não podemos tolerar mais estes abusos da dignidade humana.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já bych chtěl zdůraznit, že Vietnam skutečně udělal zásadní pokrok v uplynulém období, nicméně je důležité si uvědomit, že to skutečně není svobodný stát, že nemá v žádném případě demokratický charakter. Pokud mluvíme o jedné straně, kde neexistuje opozice, neexistují odbory, pokud mluvíme o nesvobodě médií, neexistenci pluralitních názorů, naopak dokonce pro jiný názor jsou zde političtí vězni, tak to je jednoznačné, že se nejedná o demokratický charakter státu, o tom ostatně nikdo ani nepochybuje. Máme zde nejen politické vězně, ale i náboženské vězně.</p>
      <p sl="en">Co můžeme udělat více? Máme zde nástroj té obchodní dohody, myslím si, že bychom měli více tlačit na vietnamskou vládu. Samozřejmě i naše diplomatické úsilí, naše delegace, které vyráží do Vietnamu, musí o těchto našich základních výhradách hovořit. My můžeme mluvit, a proto bychom na těchto delegacích skutečně mluvit měli i o těchto palčivých otázkách a já samozřejmě tuto rezoluci podporuji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Christos Stylianides" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the European Union is closely following the human rights situation in Vietnam. Vietnam has made significant economic and social progress over the past twenty years, which resulted in a substantial advancement in socio-economic rights. However, I personally underline that we share your concerns, Parliament’s concerns, regarding political prisoners in the country. The frequent use of vaguely drafted national security provisions in Vietnam’s Penal Code results in numerous arrests, sentencing and detention of Vietnamese citizens who peacefully express their opinion both online and offline.</p>
      <p sl="en">As the European Union, we systematically discuss our concerns over limitations to freedom of expression and freedom of religion with authorities, including at the highest levels, calling on the Government to end persecution and harassment, and to release all peaceful advocates of human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">The continued harassment and detention of an increasing number of human rights defenders is systematically raised during our annual Human Rights Dialogue. This is also where we discuss a number of individual cases. Moreover in Hanoi, the EU regularly asks for the possibility to attend trials, to visit human rights defenders in prison or under house arrest, and insist on prisoners having access to legal counsel, medical care and, of course, family visits.</p>
      <p sl="en">We extend specific support to the Government in order to strengthen respect for human rights and the rule of law. We share best practices with selected ministries, provide input to the National Assembly on the legal framework including on the Penal Code, Labour Law and on Cybersecurity, and promote joint actions with like-minded partners and countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vietnam and the EU are committed to work towards a closer partnership by implementing the Partnership and Cooperation Agreement and the Free Trade Agreement. No doubt, a key tool is the institutional and legally binding linkage between the Free Trade Agreement and the partnership and cooperation agreement ensuring that respect for human rights is an essential element of the trade relations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union wants a prosperous Vietnam, a country that respects the rule of law and human rights and honours its international commitments. While firmly stating that the negative trend of restricting the right to freedom of expression needs to be reversed, the EU stands ready to engage with Vietnam to improve the human rights conditions in the country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί μετά τη λήξη των συζητήσεων.</p>
      <p sl="en">Γραπτές δηλώσεις (άρθρο 162 του Κανονισμού)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095-2500" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">In Vietnam, human rights defenders and political activists face extreme hardships as they continue to be imprisoned, detained, and harassed by Vietnamese authorities. Currently an estimated 160 activists are serving prison sentences, according to the Vietnamese Political Prisoner Database. The freedom of press, expression and peaceful assembly, or the right to privacy are strongly restricted as aut6horities abuse the repressive provisions embedded in the Criminal Code of Vietnam. These actions directly contradict the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, to which Vietnam acceded in 1982. Political intimidation, threats of prolonged prison sentences and the restrictions to freedoms are some factors resulting in Vietnam’s rank of 175 out of 180 on the 2018 Reporters Without Borders Press Freedom Index. The Vietnamese government needs to repeal all repressive laws, releasing human rights defenders and prisoners of conscious while providing them with appropriate medical and legal support in addition to trial monitoring. The comprehensive discussions between the EU and Vietnam in Human Rights Dialogue continue to be necessary as key instruments used to encourage Vietnam in the implementation of human rights reforms. The European Union must continue to press for concrete human rights improvements in Vietnam.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095-5000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Despite its economic progress, Vietnam’s human rights situation remains dire. Basic rights, including freedom of speech, opinion, press, association, and religion, are restricted, while the criminal justice system lacks independence. In its relations with Vietnam, the EU should pressure its important trading partner’s authorities to ease restrictions on civil and political rights and to act in defence of human rights activists calling for democracy and greater freedoms. In particular, it should firmly call on the Vietnamese authorities to immediately and unconditionally release all human rights defenders and prisoners of conscience detained or sentenced, including Hoang Duc Binh, Nguyen Nam Phong, Nguyen Trung Truc and Le Dinh Luong.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="4.2. The human rights situation in Cuba">
    <intervention id="4-097-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Το επόμενο σημείο στην ημερήσια διάταξη είναι η συζήτηση επί έξι προτάσεων ψηφίσματος σχετικά με την κατάσταση των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων στην Κούβα (2018/2926(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-098-0000" speaker_id="96272" name="Pavel Svoboda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Autor. – Pane předsedající, Evropský parlament již v letech 2002, 2005 a 2010 udělil Sacharovovu cenu kubánským obhájcům lidských práv. Podle dnešní rezoluce je Kuba stále totalitním státem jediné komunistické strany, který se neobtěžuje s dodržováním základních lidských práv. Obhájci těchto práv nebo jen ti, kteří se chtějí svobodně vyjádřit či shromažďovat, jsou zastrašováni nebo nezákonně vězněni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jen teď v říjnu bylo takto uvězněno více než dvě stě Kubánců jen proto, že uplatnili svá práva podle Všeobecné deklarace lidských práv. Státní orgány neumožňují existenci lidskoprávních organizací a zabraňují vycestování jejich představitelů. Svoboda vyznání na Kubě existuje v minimální míře, církevní představitelé jsou pod dohledem státních orgánů. Kuba uplatňuje cenzuru a neumožňuje existenci jiných médií než státních.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tento stav volá částečně k odpovědnosti i nás, Evropskou unii a její členské státy. To my jsme u nové dohody s Kubou netrvali na jasné podmíněnosti jejího uplatňování dodržováním základních práv. Nicméně ani tento nedostatek nesnižuje naši povinnost ve všech vnějších vztazích Evropské unie trvat na dodržování těchto práv, jak nám to ukládá čl. 21 odst. 1 Smlouvy o Evropské unii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je proto třeba se jasně postavit za základní práva Kubánců a využívat k tomu i všechny ekonomické příležitosti, které nová smlouva s Kubou otevřela. Nesmíme se nechat chlácholit konáním voleb, ve kterých nesmějí kandidovat nezávislí kandidáti. Je třeba maximálně posílit kontakt s občanskou společností a neúnavně poukazovat na všechny represivní metody, které kubánský stát uplatňuje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-099-0000" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles Tannock" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, when the Obama administration broke the diplomatic stalemate with Cuba in 2014 and reopened the US embassy in Havana, there was much optimism in the West for a reset. But we now continue to watch with alarm as the new President, Miguel Diaz—Canel, sets out his vision for the country under its new constitution.</p>
      <p sl="en">So far, sadly, there’s very little evidence from observers of any true progress in human rights in that country. Political rights and civil liberties continue to be repressed, with the regime choosing to use short—term incarceration as a strategy for intimidating dissidents. Although it’s thought that, overall, the number of political prisoners is decreasing, sadly, one of the first laws signed by the new President imposes punitive measures on artists and musicians who operate without prior authorisation. The Ladies in White, who won the Sakharov Prize in 2005, continue to be harassed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thus, this is a mixed picture, so the EU must continue in its stick—and—carrot efforts to encourage the Cuban Government to transition towards a free and democratic state.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-100-0000" speaker_id="4334" name="Elena Valenciano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autora. – Señor presidente, quiero recordarles que Cuba era el único país de América con el que la Unión Europea no tenía relaciones, porque durante más de veinte años la derecha europea, capitaneada por José María Aznar, impidió que se cooperase con la isla a través de la Posición Común. Ahora, bajo la excusa de una urgencia, el PP y alguna de sus compañías traen de nuevo los mismos argumentos que utilizaron para dificultar la aprobación del Acuerdo de Diálogo Político entre la Unión Europea y Cuba. No es razonable.</p>
      <p sl="en">No es razonable porque, en estos dos años de Acuerdo —solo dos años—, el mecanismo que prevé el Acuerdo se ha puesto en marcha; porque el esfuerzo de la alta representante y del señor Lambrinidis ha sido mantener cuatro —cuatro— reuniones de diálogo sobre derechos humanos; que puede que les parezca mal, pero es la primera vez que podemos dialogar con la isla sobre derechos humanos.</p>
      <p sl="en">También pueden ustedes presentar alguno de sus casos particulares en la Delegación de la Unión Europea en Cuba —dirigida, por cierto, por uno de los mejores diplomáticos europeos, el señor Alberto Navarro—.</p>
      <p sl="en">No es razonable lo que ustedes hacen, ni tiene —me parece a mí— mucho que ver con los problemas que tiene la isla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si quieren hablar de lo urgente, también les sugiero que solicitemos urgentemente el cierre de Guantánamo, que ha dicho el señor Trump que va a seguir abierto durante veinticinco años: sí parece que eso sea un tema de derechos humanos, ¿verdad? Y también para devolverle esa parte de la soberanía a Cuba.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, por último, creo que esta urgencia no es ajena a un hecho que se va a producir en este mismo mes, que es el viaje del presidente del Gobierno de España a la isla. Hace treinta años que un presidente del Gobierno de España no viaja a la isla. En este caso, el presidente Sánchez lo va a hacer justamente porque ahora tenemos un marco estable de relaciones con Cuba.</p>
      <p sl="en">¡Por supuesto que sigue habiendo muchísimos problemas! Pero para eso está el marco del diálogo de derechos humanos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ese es el trabajo que se ha hecho desde la Unión Europea a través de la gestión de la señora Mogherini, del señor Lambrinidis y del esfuerzo que todos tenemos que hacer para, por fin, tener un diálogo estructurado con aquella parte del mundo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-101-0000" speaker_id="125997" name="Javier Couso Permuy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Señor presidente, con esta urgencia asistimos a un torpe intento de reeditar la Posición Común que impulsó Aznar, utilizando los derechos humanos, otra vez, como un instrumento de injerencia y de cambio de Gobierno justo en el momento en que está empezando a caminar el Acuerdo de Diálogo Político y Cooperación firmado entre la Unión Europea y Cuba.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay actores en este Parlamento que abrazan la agenda Trump y buscan hacer descarrilar la normalización de relaciones entre la Unión Europea y Cuba. Pero, por mucho que lo intenten, ustedes están fuera de la realidad. Hablan un lenguaje caduco alimentado por una supuesta oposición asalariada desde el exterior de la isla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Miren, hoy el pueblo cubano, con extraordinaria participación, está debatiendo su nueva Constitución, que será ratificada en referéndum. Su contenido no lo decidirá el Parlamento Europeo ni la Unión Europea. Y menos, los mercenarios pagados por Miami u otra capital de Europa. Lo decidirán los cubanos y las cubanas en pleno ejercicio de su soberanía e independencia.</p>
      <a text="(El orador se niega a que Tomáš Zdechovský le formule una pregunta con arreglo al procedimiento de la «tarjeta azul».)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-102-0000" speaker_id="124972" name="Ernest Urtasun" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Señor presidente, hace dos años este Parlamento decidió poner fin a una situación completamente irracional, a saber, que Cuba fuera el único país de América Latina con el que la Unión Europea no tenía ninguna relación, fruto de una Posición Común caduca y que no tenía ningún sentido. No entiendo exactamente qué estamos haciendo con este texto, puesto que creo que este Parlamento mostró una voluntad de avanzar y de normalizar las relaciones con la isla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me da la sensación de que tenemos ganas de crear problemas al Servicio Europeo de Acción Exterior en la implementación de este Acuerdo, cuando cuestionamos que la señora Mogherini no rinda cuentas del resultado de la implementación de este Acuerdo aquí —cuando vino hace muy poco— o cuando implícitamente se dice que las instituciones europeas en Cuba, en su trabajo, no respetan los principios básicos de la UE, poniendo en cuestión el trabajo de uno de los mejores diplomáticos que tiene la Unión Europea, como es el señor Alberto Navarro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Con lo cual, me parece francamente que esta es una Resolución totalmente inoportuna y que lo que deberíamos desear es que este Acuerdo funcione en todas sus partes, incluido el diálogo sobre derechos humanos. Y, por eso, creo que este texto no tiene lugar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-103-0000" speaker_id="124706" name="Pavel Telička" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, colleagues, this is not about Spanish politics, and this is not against the Political Dialogue Agreement, it is in support of the implementation. I know Alberto Navarro maybe longer than many of you Spaniards in this Hemicycle. He is an excellent diplomat, but the fact is that we are implementing the dialogue for already two years with basically no results, and this is something that we need to acknowledge. Read the draft constitution. There is nothing about free elections there. Read the draft resolution; in it there are provisions about basically any measures, any force can that can be taken. This is in fact in support of the Cuban dissidents who are continuously harassed. This is in support of those, even the Laureats of the Sakharov Prize, who are not invited to EU events. This is in support of the opposition that is to be recognised not just by the Cuban regime but also by us. We should not be calling dictators friends, but we should be inviting these people to a dialogue. We should recognise them. It is not just a message to the Cubans emphasising the need to implement, but also a message to ourselves. So yes, please, who votes against this resolution basically votes against the basic rights of these people.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-104-0000" speaker_id="28400" name="Francisco José Millán Mon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, el Acuerdo entre la Unión Europea y Cuba se aplica ya desde hace un año. Por eso, parece totalmente lógico hacer un balance ahora. Recuerdo, además, que este Acuerdo supuso un giro muy importante en la política exterior de la Unión Europea hacia la isla. Lamentablemente, en materia de derechos y libertades fundamentales el balance de este año no es positivo. Siguen los acosos y la intimidación a los defensores de los derechos humanos, siguen detenidos en las cárceles cubanas personas de la calidad de Eduardo Cardet.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Resolución que hoy votaremos detalla más casos de detenciones arbitrarias y de violaciones de derechos humanos. Las propuestas de visitas oficiales de este Parlamento siguen siendo rechazadas por las autoridades cubanas. Desgraciadamente, tampoco hay perspectivas de cambio político en Cuba. El proyecto actual de reforma constitucional consagra el sistema de partido único y pretende hacerlo, además, irreversible. Las esperanzas de reforma que estaban en la base del apoyo por este Parlamento al Acuerdo con Cuba se han visto defraudadas por ahora.</p>
      <p sl="en">El diálogo anual sobre derechos humanos tiene que producir resultados tangibles. No es un fin en sí mismo, como aquí se pretende decir. Son muchos los vínculos que nos unen a los europeos con el pueblo cubano. Queremos para este lo mismo que para nosotros: respeto de las libertades, pluralismo y Estado de Derecho.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-105-0000" speaker_id="4507" name="Bas Belder" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, graag wil ik de Europese Commissie en ook de EU-delegatie in Havana twee grote zorgen van de kerken in Cuba voorleggen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ten eerste: vanwege de explosieve groei van het aantal christenen hebben de kerken dringend behoefte aan nieuwe godshuizen. De Cubaanse overheid staat deze nieuwbouw echter niet toe, ook niet bij geregistreerde kerken. Commissie, uw ambassade in Havana, ik vertrouw erop dat u dit essentiële kernpunt van geloofsvrijheid – eredienst in legale godshuizen – verdedigt tegenover de Cubaanse autoriteiten. Of streven die soms naar een wildgroei aan huiskerken? Ik kan me dat nauwelijks voorstellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tweede punt: christelijke organisaties in Europa staan al jaren klaar om elementaire sociale zorg te bieden aan alle noodlijdende Cubaanse burgers, maar dan wel zonder de huidige schadelijke overheidscontrole. Zo creëerde de Cubaanse overheid zelf een illegaal hulpcircuit. Commissie, EU-delegatie in Havana, agendeer en overtuig Cubaanse gezagsdragers dat bilaterale hulp van buitenaf, vanuit Europa, voor 100 % rechtstreeks bij de behoeftige burgers behoort aan te komen. Dat is sociaal, dat is voor Cuba!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-106-0000" speaker_id="135491" name="María Teresa Giménez Barbat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señor presidente, compañeros, hemos celebrado cuatro acuerdos de diálogo Unión Europea-Cuba, y ¿para qué sirven? Tras cuatro años desde el primero, la situación sigue siendo penosa, a pesar de lo que digan la izquierda sanchista y sus socios.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se detiene y encarcela arbitrariamente a defensores de derechos humanos y disidentes políticos. No nos engañemos: en Cuba no hay libertad de expresión y de reunión. Se persigue y se censura a cualquiera que se atreva a pensar diferente del régimen.</p>
      <p sl="en">No hay un pluralismo político como en las democracias normales y el nuevo proyecto de Constitución no parece arreglarlo. Al revés, refuerza el poder del Partido Comunista e incluye disposiciones surrealistas, como la prohibición a las generaciones futuras de decidir su propia forma de gobierno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Como dice mi compañero el vicepresidente Telička, esto no es una discusión entre españoles; se trata de los derechos del pueblo cubano y de los valores de todos los europeos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-107-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, repudiamos o sistemático desrespeito e ingerência em países soberanos promovidos desde o Parlamento. Denunciamos a espúria instrumentalização dos direitos humanos nessa estratégia, matéria em que a União Europeia não tem autoridade para pregar.</p>
      <p sl="en">É lamentável o ataque que daqui se pretende desferir ao processo de normalização e desenvolvimento de relações da União Europeia e dos seus Estados-Membros com Cuba, com a celebração do acordo de diálogo político e cooperação. Reafirmamos o exemplo inquestionável de Cuba na expressão do internacionalismo, da cooperação, da resposta solidária a graves situações humanitárias em países terceiros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Saudamos os avanços da revolução cubana, um país sem fome, sem analfabetismo, com saúde e educação gratuita para todos, avanços alcançados não obstante o criminoso bloqueio económico e financeiro que há quase sessenta anos os Estados Unidos impõem a Cuba, um bloqueio cujo fim se exige, como reiterado na última Assembleia-Geral das Nações Unidas por todos os países, à exceção dos Estados Unidos e de Israel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cabe ao povo de Cuba definir soberanamente a sua própria via de desenvolvimento e o modelo de sociedade que querem construir.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-109-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ολοκληρώθηκε ο κατάλογος των εγγεγραμμένων ομιλητών. Προχωρούμε στη διαδικασία catch-the-eye. Έχουμε ένα πρόβλημα χρονικής πίεσης, διότι είναι Πέμπτη σήμερα και οι ψηφοφορίες πρέπει να αρχίσουν στις 12.00. Έχω δεχθεί έξι αιτήματα, όλα από την ίδια πολιτική ομάδα. Οι τέσσερις από τους έξι συναδέλφους έχουν ήδη μιλήσει σήμερα το πρωί στη διαδικασία catch-the-eye, οπότε -λόγω και της έλλειψης χρόνου- θα κάνω δεκτά μόνον τα δύο αιτήματα των συναδέλφων που δεν έχουν κάνει χρήση της διαδικασίας catch-the-eye.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-110-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já se domnívám, že Evropská unie nemůže polevit v podpoře lidských práv, ať se to děje kdekoliv. Mě zaujala slova pana kolegy Urtasuna, který se ptal, proč chceme vstupovat do něčeho, co funguje. Lidskoprávní dialog funguje, ale jestliže funguje lidskoprávní dialog, to ještě neznamená, že fungují lidská práva na Kubě, jestliže je tam sto třicet politických vězňů a další, kteří jsou pronásledováni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já se domnívám, že Evropská unie musí vést tento dialog, ale musí vnímat také, jaké jsou výsledky. Pokud výsledky nejsou, tak je na místě, aby Evropský parlament se ozval, aby bylo zřejmé, že nepolevíme. Politická pluralita a svobodná opozice je náš cíl, který v této otázce sledujeme. Já doufám, že socialisté také.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-111-0000" speaker_id="124713" name="Tomáš Zdechovský" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, k demokracii patří dialog a myslím si, že dialog se vede skrze to, že si vzájemně vyměňujeme svoje pozice. Myslím si, že to, že tento parlament má zavedeny modré karty, ukazuje na to, že je otevřený dialogu. Dialog právě může prohlubovat demokracii. Proto jsem trochu zaskočen tím, že kolega z komunistické strany odmítl se mnou tento dialog vést. Já možná vím, pane kolego, proč jste odmítl. Protože jste na Kubě asi nikdy nebyl. Nikdy jste se tam nesetkal s lidmi, kteří jsou v opozici, a nikdy jste neviděl zatýkání opozičních lídrů. Já jsem ho viděl, já jsem viděl mlácení lidí, kteří se shromáždili kvůli tomu, aby vyjádřili svoje přesvědčení, že lidská práva, demokracie, svoboda je něco, co se nedá vyměnit za paštiku, tak jako vy to vyměňujete v řadě zemí. Jedna věc je o demokracii a o svobodě mluvit, druhá věc je demokracii a svobodu žít. Na závěr mi dovolte vám vyjádřit jednu věc – slepec není ten, kdo nevidí, ale ten, kdo nechce vidět.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-112-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Η απόφασή μου για το catch-the eye είναι οριστική και σας παρακαλώ να μην χάσουμε άλλο χρόνο επ’ αυτού του θέματος. Κύριε Faria, έχετε τον λόγο επί της διαδικασίας. Παρακαλώ επικαλεστείτε το άρθρο του Κανονισμού βάσει του οποίου ζητάτε τον λόγο επί της διαδικασίας.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-113-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, o catch the eye é um mecanismo que está à disposição dos deputados quando não têm a oportunidade de expressar a sua voz de outra forma. Eu fiz um catch the eye nesta casa hoje. E, portanto, agradeço que o Sr. Presidente me deixe exercer o meu direito a falar, a expressar as minhas opiniões aqui, por favor, e que não faça, como muitos têm feito aqui nesta casa, que é cortar a palavra aos deputados eleitos livremente. Faz favor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-114-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Faria, δεν θέλω να παραβιάζετε τον Κανονισμό. Δεν έχετε τον λόγο. Έχουμε εκλεγεί όλοι ελεύθερα αλλά, με βάση τον Κανονισμό, ο προεδρεύων έχει το δικαίωμα να επιλέγει πώς θα χρησιμοποιεί τη διαδικασία του catch-the-eye. Σας θυμίζω ότι υπάρχουν φορές που δεν παίρνει κανείς τον λόγο με βάση το catch-the-eye. Εξήγησα προηγουμένως ότι για τα τέσσερα από τα έξι αιτήματα, που και τα έξι έχουν υποβληθεί από την ίδια πολιτική ομάδα, χρησιμοποιήθηκε σήμερα το πρωί το δικαίωμα του catch-the-eye. Σας παρακαλώ, λοιπόν, να σεβαστείτε και τον χρόνο και το ότι έχουμε ακόμη μία συζήτηση και πρέπει να αρχίσει η ψηφοφορία στις 12.00.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-115-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we have to accept your decision. I understand that, but normally there are at least five taken. You have a request for six. It was four extra minutes. We lost several minutes all along, but we have to accept your decision. It was unnecessary though.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-116-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ευχαριστώ πολύ που σέβεστε την απόφασή μου. Ξέρετε πολύ καλά -γιατί δεν είναι πρώτη φορά που προεδρεύω- ότι όποτε έχουμε χρόνο δέχομαι όλα τα αιτήματα, ακόμη και αν είναι παραπάνω από πέντε. Αυτή τη φορά σας παρακαλώ να σεβαστείτε την απόφασή μου, διότι όλοι και όλες ξέρετε πολύ καλά ότι όλα τα επιχειρήματα έχουν ακουστεί από όλες τις πλευρές με πλήρη άνεση. Δεν υπάρχει ούτε ένα επιχείρημα που δεν έχει ακουστεί.</p>
      <a text="(Λήξη της διαδικασίας catch-the-eye)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-117-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Christos Stylianides" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, almost two years ago, the European Union, our Member States and Cuba, signed a new agreement – the so—called Political Dialogue and Cooperation Agreement – which opened a new chapter in our relations with Cuba. Around a year ago this agreement entered into provisional application, after having received Parliament’s overwhelming support in its assent vote.</p>
      <p sl="en">While there is broad—ranging agreement on political dialogue and cooperation, it was very clear from the beginning that human rights should be a central part of it, and even before its formal application we started holding human rights discussions, both in Brussels and Havana.</p>
      <p sl="en">Last May, at the Joint Council meeting, Federica Mogherini and the Cuban Foreign Minister decided to start formal political dialogues on a number of areas. The very first formal political dialogue we had with Cuba was precisely the Human Rights one held last month in Havana. This was an important point for us to underline the continued relevance of human rights in our bilateral relations. For the first time, it involved the participation of our EU Member States as observers, and the organisation of a civil society seminar in its margins.</p>
      <p sl="en">We all know that there are still important differences between the EU and Cuba on many issues, notably on the way human rights and democracy are applied. This is why during last month’s Human Rights Dialogue we raised important matters, such as the need for ratification and implementation of the relevant international instruments on human rights, proper legal guarantees in criminal proceedings, freedom of association and expression, and the protection of human rights defenders.</p>
      <p sl="en">The civil society seminar that was organised in the margins of the Dialogue tackled the situation of LGBTI groups and gender equality. While only registered Cuban civil society organisations were able to attend the seminar on this occasion, we recalled the importance to enlarge these discussions to the whole range of civil society, whether registered or not.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to give some numbers about our projects. Most of these projects, indeed for around EUR 10 million, are implemented by European and Cuban civil society organisations, including religious organisations. Vulnerable Cuban people’s rights have been specifically addressed by a number of these projects – women, elderly people, people with disabilities and LGBTI – lesbian, gay, bisexual and so on. We will continue raising this, and all other subjects that are close to our hearts, with our Cuban counterparts in different meetings. Human rights need to be promoted on a day—to—day basis.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to reiterate our conviction that the best way to address the differences we have with Cuba in these matters is through a process of dialogue based on clear and consistent messages. It is certainly difficult and trying, but it is the best manner to sustain results in the long term and to contribute to Cuba’s and its population’s path to reform and modernisation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-118-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί μετά τη λήξη των συζητήσεων.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="4.3. The human rights situation in Bangladesh">
    <intervention id="4-120-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Το επόμενο σημείο στην ημερήσια διάταξη είναι η συζήτηση επί επτά προτάσεων ψηφίσματος σχετικά με την κατάσταση των ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων στο Μπανγκλαντές (2018/2927(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-121-0000" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles Tannock" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Bangladesh has, for many years, struggled with the problem of terrorist threats. Given the similar problems we see in our own countries, we are only too aware that preventing threats from turning into attacks is a difficult and costly business, so we do so with the benefit of more resources in the European Union, better intelligence and fewer potential threats. Despite the progress Bangladesh has made in recent years, it remains one of the poorest countries in the world, with a population of over 150 million people. As such, we must therefore remain cautious when criticising its efforts to tackle clear and present threats.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nevertheless, this cannot be routinely offered as a blanket universal explanation, and in cases such as the jailing of the photographer Shahidul Alam we cannot deny that the provisions of the Information and Communication Technology Act (ICT Act) are, at times, being used inappropriately by the government.</p>
      <p sl="en">I welcome therefore today’s resolution and, as a close friend of Bangladesh, call for the authorities there to avoid bringing its counterterrorism measures into disrepute. Finally, as we approach the elections next month, I call on all parties to participate peacefully and hope that we will not see a repeat of the violence that we saw five years ago.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-122-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autore. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, signor Commissario, il Bangladesh aveva intrapreso un percorso virtuoso, migliorativo, soltanto che l'avvicinarsi delle elezioni probabilmente ha fatto precipitare di nuovo la situazione, quindi con una lotta a qualsiasi forma di dissenso, una riduzione delle libertà fondamentali, una lotta alla libertà di informazione e quindi un atteggiamento da parte del governo da parte nostra inaccettabile.</p>
      <p sl="en">La cosa che poi stupisce, di cui secondo me dobbiamo parlare, è che il Bangladesh è anche diventato membro dello Human Rights Council. Vista la presenza al suo interno di Arabia Saudita e Filippine, dovremmo chiederci se questo Consiglio dei diritti umani non è il Consiglio dei violatori dei diritti umani, forse una riflessione andrebbe fatta. Ricordiamoci che il Bangladesh beneficia del regime preferenziale nel programma "Everything but arms" in cui è previsto il rispetto dei diritti fondamentali, quindi facciamo in modo di utilizzare la nostra pressione per farli rispettare.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-123-0000" speaker_id="124997" name="Soraya Post" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we in the EU must remind Bangladesh of its international human rights obligations. There is a visible increase in attacks on, and arrests of, journalists, students, human rights defenders and members of the political opposition. This crackdown on civil society must stop. Bangladesh must safeguard media freedom and freedom of expression and release all activists, journalists and students. The rates of early marriage are still alarmingly high in Bangladesh. It has one of the highest rates of child marriage in the world. Bangladesh has to ensure that the minimum age of marriage for women is 18, without exceptions. I also urge the Government of Bangladesh not to return thousands of Rohingyas living in the refugee camps in Cox’s Bazar to Myanmar against their will and in spite of objections by the UN.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-124-0000" speaker_id="4531" name="Jean Lambert" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I speak as the Chair of Parliament’s Delegation for relations with the countries of South Asia, which covers Bangladesh. As we know, it’s a relatively young country still facing many difficulties and is looking forward to its full graduation from ‘least-developed country’ status. Part of that graduation is due to the ready—made garment sector, and government and manufacturers know that change is needed. So we’re concerned that the government has decided not to take full advantage of all that the accord offers in terms of assisting that change and building on progress to safe and inclusive working environments.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also recognise, as my colleague has said, the government’s zero—tolerance policy towards terrorism. But that approach has to be built on human rights, and we’re concerned about continuing unexplained disappearances, extrajudicial killings and the direction of legislation at the moment. Lastly, I too would echo the call for an open and inclusive, peaceful election – in which all parties participate – to give the people of Bangladesh a full and meaningful choice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-125-0000" speaker_id="131507" name="Miguel Urbán Crespo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Señor presidente, desapariciones, ejecuciones, torturas, detenciones arbitrarias, represión sindical y de prensa. Esto pasa hoy en Bangladés, uno de los principales socios comerciales de la Unión Europea. Un país que ha acordado con Myanmar/Birmania el inicio del retorno forzado de las y los rohinyás y que ha mandado al ejército a los campos de refugiados para intimidar aún más a esa población. Un país que no quiere renovar el Acuerdo sobre Prevención de Incendios y Seguridad que firmó tras el incendio y el crimen del Rana Plaza. ¡Qué rápido olvidamos las tragedias!</p>
      <p sl="en">Rechazamos el acuerdo de repatriación forzada y exigimos que Bangladés acepte la extensión del Acuerdo sobre Prevención de Incendios y Seguridad. Una vez más, llamamos a que la Comisión inicie una investigación sobre el incumplimiento de los convenios internacionales y que proponga una legislación vinculante sobre obligaciones de diligencia debida para las cadenas de suministro del sector de la confección. No podemos seguir mirando hacia otro lado. Tenemos que tener exigencias claras.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-126-0000" speaker_id="96945" name="Marietje Schaake" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Shahidul Alam is well-known photographer and a human rights defender, and under the controversial Digital Securities Act and ICT Act for online speech, he is now accused of ‘speech that hurts the image of the nation in Bangladesh’, while we consider it to fall under his right to freedom of expression. We call for his release and for the dropping of all charges against him.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sadly, Alam is not the only one repressed in Bangladesh. There is a pattern of harassment, arrests and enforced disappearances, and we call on the High Representative to assess whether Bangladesh still complies with the trade arrangements we have under the ‘anything but arms’ agreement, because conditionality and accountability are very important when it comes to human rights and we must do what we can to improve the situation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-127-0000" speaker_id="124713" name="Tomáš Zdechovský" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Autor. – Pane předsedající, pane komisaři, Evropská unie dlouhodobě patří mezi jedny z největších a nejstabilnějších partnerů a podporovatelů mladého státu, jako je Bangladéš.</p>
      <p sl="en">Myslím si, že právě ta otevřenost dialogu by měla být daleko větší, a to především v oblasti lidských práv. Evropská unie nesmí zavírat oči před tím, co se děje v Bangladéši. Už proto, že v rámci skupiny pro dobré vládnutí a lidská práva máme mandát dohlížet na to, co se v zemi děje. I přesto dochází v této zemi ke zneužití státní moci. Vláda nechává zmizet novináře a aktivisty, kteří proti ní vystupují. Myslím si, že je to absolutně nepřípustné a je nutné se proti tomu opakovaně ozvat. Novináři, aktivisté, právníci, obhájci lidských práv, ti všichni jsou v současné době oběťmi režimu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rezoluce se týká dvou konkrétních případů novináře a právníka, kteří bojovali za lidská práva. Oba tito lidé zmizeli ze světa a nikdo neví, kde se tito aktivisté v současné době nachází. Existuje důvodné podezření, že vláda zatčené mučí či dochází k mimosoudní likvidaci těchto osob. Musíme bezodkladně vyzvat vládu k vyjádření k těmto případům a vést aktivní dialog o dodržování mezinárodních závazků. Zejména práva na spravedlivý proces, práva na obhajobu, práva na přístup k soudu, který musí být dodržován. Aktivisté a bojovníci za lidská práva jsou velmi důležitou součástí jakékoliv demokracie a je nezbytné, aby měli v tomto systému své místo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-128-0000" speaker_id="124895" name="Krzysztof Hetman" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy PPE. – Panie Przewodniczący! Nie ulega wątpliwości, że wymuszone zaginięcia, czyli zwykłe porwania dokonywane przez aparat władzy są jedną ze strategii siania terroru oraz wymuszania uległości w społeczeństwach. Dzięki wywoływaniu poczucia niepewności i zastraszaniu władze mogą w łatwiejszy sposób kontrolować społeczeństwa oraz wymuszać uległość. Niestety, pomimo deklaracji Bangladeszu o wzmocnieniu współpracy z Unią Europejską w zakresie ochrony praw człowieka praktyka ta jest w dalszym ciągu stosowana w tym kraju, co potwierdza chociażby zaginięcie Szahidula Alama.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stosowania wymuszonych zaginięć nie usprawiedliwiają żadne wyjątkowe okoliczności, ale w sprawie Alama jeszcze bardziej bulwersujący jest powód, dla którego do niego doszło. Warto przypomnieć, że ten obrońca praw człowieka skrytykował rząd i stanął w obronie osób domagających się zwiększenia bezpieczeństwa na drogach. Nie ma naszej zgody na takie działania i nie powinno być zgody Unii Europejskiej na zastraszanie i torturowanie politycznych oponentów.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-129-0000" speaker_id="125021" name="Agnes Jongerius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the collapse of the Rana Plaza factory was a wake—up call for the whole world to improve the working conditions in the ready—made garments industry. Unfortunately, at the end of the month, due to a highly questionable verdict, the Bangladesh Accord will be thrown out of the country. This means that the safety of thousands of workers in the garment industry in Bangladesh is at stake.</p>
      <p sl="en">As we all know, the Government of Bangladesh is not yet capable of taking over the inspections of the garment factories, and, as we all know, the labour law reform in the country is still pending. As we also all know, freedom of association is not guaranteed in Bangladesh. Therefore, let us be clear to the Bangladeshi authorities that they need to get serious about workers’ rights and safety. If you want to use the EU trade preferences, you have to fulfil the commitments we agreed upon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130-0000" speaker_id="28481" name="Sajjad Karim" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I speak as Chair of the South Asia Trade Monitoring Committee. We have constantly been appealing to the Government of Bangladesh to make progress on its commitments under the Everything but Arms scheme, to democracy, human rights and the rule of law. Whilst we can see that there has been an improvement, more needs to be done. The accord is at a critical juncture, and commitments from the Government of Bangladesh towards the Sustainability Compact are highly insufficient, as demonstrated by the technical status report recently published.</p>
      <p sl="en">The roadmap is here, requirements are on the table, and now we need to see tangible results and steps in the right direction. It must be clear that we are at a crucial stage, and we are moving ever so slowly from issuing further notifications for action to actual action. It has been initiated in terms of investigative reviews for withdrawal of Generalised Scheme of Preferences (GSP) mechanism for Myanmar and Cambodia. Bangladesh could be next on the list.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-131-0000" speaker_id="124766" name="Petras Auštrevičius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Mr President, freedom of expression in Bangladesh is under attack. This is no surprise, as this year Bangladesh is ranked 146 out of 180 on the World Press Freedom Index. We see visible signs that the authorities have increased their crackdown on civil society and government critics, with such means as detentions, enforced disappearances and the use of violence. In addition, on 5 August, writer, former journalist and activist Shahidul Alam was imprisoned after speaking out against state violence on the student protest in Dhaka. This must stop. I call the government to repeal its Digital Security Act used to crack down on dissidents and human rights defenders and immediately release Shahidul Alam. I call on the Commission to assess if the tariff preferences that Dhaka enjoys for the time being under the Everything but Arms agreement should not be put under question. The EU cannot be just a watcher in this regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-132-0000" speaker_id="96858" name="Marie-Christine Vergiat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe GUE/NGL. – Monsieur le Président, nous allons envoyer un message d’alerte au Bangladesh, à la veille des élections de décembre. Les voyants sont au rouge. Les violences, les arrestations, les détentions arbitraires et exécutions extrajudiciaires se multiplient. La guerre contre le terrorisme et la guerre contre la drogue ont bon dos. Le photographe Shahidul Alam, le blogueur Limon Fakir ou, pire, Shahzahan Bachchu, assassiné en juin dernier, n’en sont malheureusement que quelques exemples.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur le plan social, ce n’est guère mieux. Après l’horreur du Rana Plaza, peu de choses ont changé malgré les engagements. Les ouvrières du textile restent parmi les plus mal payées du monde, les conditions de sécurité restent catastrophiques et un nouveau drame est possible à tout moment. La Fast Fashion continue de faire la loi et les multinationales européennes en sont toujours les grandes bénéficiaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, en deux mots, j’associe notre voix à celle de ceux qui demandent aux Bangladais de ne pas mettre en œuvre l’accord sur les Rohingyas. Ce serait les envoyer à la mort, ce n’est donc pas possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Fabio Massimo Castaldo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il 30 dicembre si terranno in Bangladesh le elezioni generali. Quando queste scadenze si avvicinano, emerge la vera natura di chi al potere potrebbe perdere il suo ruolo in caso di sconfitta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Bangladesh è un paese che, pur con tutta una serie di problemi, incassava lo scorso maggio i complimenti dell'ONU che, nell'Universal Periodic Review, valutava i progressi di Dacca come notevoli. La situazione è cambiata molto e molto velocemente. Assistiamo a una violenta repressione della libertà di espressione dei media e delle opposizioni, nonché ad arresti, sparizioni forzate, uso della tortura. È un caso emblematico quello del fotogiornalista Shahidul Alam.</p>
      <p sl="en">Colleghi, l'UE ha con il Bangladesh l'"Everything but arms", un'esenzione tariffaria che concediamo su tutti i beni, armi escluse, a paesi in via di sviluppo. Ebbene, questo meccanismo delle clausole di sospensione legate al rispetto dei diritti umani, ma se non abbiamo il coraggio di menzionare quelle clausole, di attivarle quando è il caso, sembreremo sempre un gigante dai piedi d'argilla, un grande mercato del business as usual e nulla di più. È questa l'immagine che vogliamo dare dell'Europa nel mondo?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134-0000" speaker_id="111014" name="Josef Weidenholzer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the situation in Bangladesh is very worrying. The country is facing growing repression against civil society, political activists and human rights defenders. There are reports of extrajudicial executions, mass arbitrary arrests and enforced disappearances. Press freedom is under attack and bloggers are increasingly intimidated. General elections are due by the end of this year, but freedom of expression, which is a prerequisite for fair elections, does not exist. The Opposition is fundamentally constrained and its leader, Khaleda Zia, has been barred from contesting these elections and sentenced on politically motivated charges.</p>
      <p sl="en">The forthcoming elections set the country at a crossroads. This is a last chance: either return to democracy and the rule of law, or slip into lawlessness and chaos. Europe will be faced with the consequences if this happens. I appeal to the authorities to establish conditions where people can freely speak out and can prepare for fair elections.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-135-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ολοκληρώθηκε ο κατάλογος των εγεγραμμένων ομιλητών. Προχωρούμε στη διαδικασία του catch-the-eye. Έχω δεχθεί επτά αιτήματα. Κανονικά, υπό την προϋπόθεση ότι οι ψηφοφορίες αρχίζουν στις 12.00, θα έπρεπε να δεχθώ μόνον τα δύο από αυτά, όσων δεν έχουν μιλήσει με τη διαδικασία του catch-the-eye. Με ενημερώνουν όμως οι συνεργάτες μου από τις υπηρεσίες ότι ακόμη δεν έχει ολοκληρωθεί η Διάσκεψη των Προέδρων. Κατόπιν αυτού, προχωρώ με τη διαδικασία για έναν από κάθε πολιτική ομάδα, έτσι ώστε να μην αδικηθεί κανένας συνάδελφος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-137-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Przy tej okazji chciałem zwrócić uwagę na jeden, bardzo ważny element: na inflację podobnych rezolucji. Proszę zauważyć, że w sprawie Bangladeszu mieliśmy rezolucje z listopada 2015 r., z kwietnia 2017 r., z czerwca 2017 r., oświadczenie z września 2018 r. i sprawozdanie także z tego roku. Z powodów oczywistych zagłosuję za tą rezolucją, natomiast zwracam uwagę na to, że liczba tych rezolucji nie przekłada się na faktyczną zdolność Parlamentu Europejskiego czy naszych instytucji do wywierania określonego nacisku na władze Bangladeszu, aby rzeczywistość w tym kraju zmieniała się zgodnie z wartościami, które są nam najbliższe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-138-0000" speaker_id="96812" name="Juan Fernando López Aguilar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, la primera vez que oí hablar de Bangladés, yo era un niño. El legendario concierto para Bangladés de George Harrison nos dio noticias a quienes no sabíamos nada de un país donde había derramamiento de sangre, guerras, catástrofes naturales e inundaciones. Y más de cuarenta años después, la situación no es mucho mejor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oímos hablar de Bangladés en relación con desapariciones forzadas, torturas, abusos policiales, discriminación contra el colectivo LGTBI, explotación de mano de obra infantil y matrimonios infantiles; y por la tragedia del Rana Plaza en 2013, que motivó un acuerdo transversal de seguridad en los edificios, que debe ser cumplido en todos sus términos. Por haberlo defendido está detenido Shahidul Alam.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y es imprescindible que la Unión Europea, que es el primer socio comercial de Bangladés, emplee toda la fuerza diplomática no solamente para conseguir la liberación, sino el restablecimiento del acuerdo en todos sus términos, y que la Unión Europea garantice que su diplomacia y su cooperación al desarrollo son influyentes para la protección de los derechos fundamentales de los más vulnerables, en un país que continúa dando malas noticias por sus catástrofes y sus desastres.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-139-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το Μπανγκλαντές είναι ο παράδεισος των πολυεθνικών: υπερεκμετάλλευση των εργαζομένων, υπερκέρδη, μισθοί πείνας, καμία ρύθμιση και καμία προστασία των εργαζομένων. Είχαμε την περίπτωση του Rana Plaza, με 1127 νεκρούς και 2500 τραυματίες –όλοι εργαζόμενοι–, διότι δεν τηρούνται οι προδιαγραφές υγείας και προστασίας της ασφάλειας των εργαζομένων. Και, φυσικά, περνούμε πλέον σε ένα αυταρχικό καθεστώς. Δεν υπάρχει ελευθερία έκφρασης, διώκονται οι ακτιβιστές, δεν έχουν δίκαιη δίκη, και έχει αρχίσει πλέον να επιβάλλεται και η θανατική ποινή, η οποία πρέπει να καταργηθεί. Ταυτόχρονα, έχει ξεκινήσει πλέον επίθεση και στους ίδιους τους Rohingya. Απαιτείται να υπάρξουν εργασιακά δικαιώματα, το δικαίωμα του συνεταιρίζεσθαι και, φυσικά, να σταματήσει η προνομιακή εμπορική μεταχείριση της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης προς το Μπανγκλαντές, για να μπορέσουμε έτσι να επιβάλουμε συμμόρφωση των αρχών.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-140-0000" speaker_id="23699" name="Kateřina Konečná" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, považuji za důležité, že se zde každý štrasburský týden ve čtvrtek sejdeme a pohoříme zde o stavu lidských práv v jiných zemích. Jsem přesvědčena, že je nutné se ptát bangladéšské vlády na to, proč nezlepšuje podmínky zaměstnanců ve vlastní zemi, je nutné vědět, proč vláda dlouhodobě zastrašuje a zatýká odborové předáky a neudělala zásadní reformy, které by umožnily bangladéšským zaměstnancům bojovat za svá práva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zároveň je však nutné podívat se k nám domů, do našich obchodů s oblečením. Pokud tak učiníme, musíme se ptát na to, proč tolik evropských firem stále neřeší, že jejich dodavatelé z Bangladéše ignorují nejzákladnější sociální, environmentální a lidská práva. Odpověď je jasná: Proč si nenamastit kapsu na levné práci? Staré pravidlo kapitalismu totiž říká: „Levně nakoupit a draze prodat.“ a v této rovnici není pro lidská práva a lidskou důstojnost místo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-141-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the arrest, detention and alleged torture of the award—winning photographer Shahidul Alam shines a light on the poor human rights situation in Bangladesh. Alam is the founder of many important cultural, media and training initiatives in South Asia. He’s also a visiting professor at Sunderland University in the UK. His arrest, 100 days ago, for criticising the government’s response to the Bangladesh road-safety protests, points to the worrying global trend of many governments to silence artists and journalists.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I call for the immediate and unconditional release of Shahidul Alam and for all charges against him to be dropped. I also call for the Bangladeshi authorities to provide him with the urgent medical assistance he needs. These attacks on freedom of expression and assembly in Bangladesh, as well as women’s, girls and LGBTIQ+ rights give wider cause for concern. The High Representative should take all necessary diplomatic steps to put pressure on the Bangladeshi government to improve its human rights record, starting with the release of Shahidul Alam.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142-0000" speaker_id="188624" name="Wajid Khan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Bangladesh is approaching general elections under the worst circumstances. The government has embarked on a campaign of intrusive surveillance upon its own citizens. It is monitoring social media and curtailing freedom of expression in the name of national security. The Digital Security Act has gagged the media and all those who criticise the government and the harassment and intimidation of journalists and activists grows on a daily basis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Peaceful political dissent should not be silenced or criminalised. We urge the government to revise the Digital Security Act, halt the crackdown on freedom of expression and conduct investigations into the cases of enforced disappearances. We want Bangladesh to progress towards a functioning democracy, not drift into an authoritarian police state.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-144-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Christos Stylianides" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the European Union has a substantial and long-lasting relationship with Bangladesh. Our political dialogue has intensified over the past months in the context of the refugee crisis.</p>
      <p sl="en">We appreciate the Government’s and people of Bangladesh’s efforts to host the Rohingya refugees. The return of the refugees to their place of origin remains the objective, but it must be voluntary, safe, sustainable and dignified. It should not go against those fundamental requirements. It is important that the return of refugees is conducted in line with international law and with the involvement of UNHCR. It is critical that the conditions in Rakhine State are conducive for a safe and sustainable return.</p>
      <p sl="en">Human rights are a key priority of our dialogue with Bangladesh. The EU regularly expresses its concerns on the situation of human rights, and we see it as a positive development that the Government of Bangladesh is engaging with the EU on this issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">In joint press statements adopted at the Sub-group on Good Governance and Human Rights in April, and at the Diplomatic Consultations held in Dhaka in July, the authorities undertook to address the shortages and enforce policies respectful of human rights, fundamental freedoms and democracy. However, the situation is of serious concern and more needs to be done: human rights and fundamental freedoms are being increasingly challenged as parliamentary elections are coming close.</p>
      <p sl="en">While continuing its dialogue with the Government of Bangladesh, together with EU Member States and other like-minded partners on the ground, the EU has addressed this in a number of recent public statements. This was particularly necessary in the context of the reaction to the recent Digital Security Act and violence against students and press during the summer. We are notably very concerned over the situation of Mr Shahidul Alam.</p>
      <p sl="en">The preparation of the parliamentary elections is discussed regularly with the Bangladeshi authorities. The EU expects that the upcoming elections will be held in a transparent, inclusive and impartial way. The rule of law, freedom of expression and freedom of peaceful assembly should be upheld and protected. The Government needs to ensure a safe and enabling environment for civil society, journalists and human rights defenders. As regards labour rights, the Government needs to fully implement the International Labour Organization’s recommendations, notably on freedom of association.</p>
      <p sl="en">Human rights are a crucial part of the EU’s development cooperation with Bangladesh, with more than EUR 40 million committed for democratic governance. The EU focuses on ensuring democratic ownership through engagement with civil society, promoting democratic empowerment and local governance, notably by addressing access to justice.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-145-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Πρόεδρος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Η συζήτηση έληξε.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ψηφοφορία θα διεξαχθεί μετά τη λήξη των συζητήσεων.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="5. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-148-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Abstimmung.</p>
      <a text="(Abstimmungsergebnisse und sonstige Einzelheiten der Abstimmung: siehe Protokoll.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="5.1. Vietnam, notably the situation of political prisoners (B8-0529/2018, B8-0530/2018, B8-0531/2018, B8-0540/2018, RC-B8-0526/2018, B8-0526/2018, B8-0527/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="5.2. The human rights situation in Cuba (RC-B8-0528/2018, B8-0528/2018, B8-0532/2018, B8-0534/2018, B8-0537/2018, B8-0541/2018, B8-0543/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="5.3. The human rights situation in Bangladesh (RC-B8-0533/2018, B8-0533/2018, B8-0535/2018, B8-0536/2018, B8-0538/2018, B8-0539/2018, B8-0542/2018, B8-0544/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="5.4. Transparent and predictable working conditions in the European Union (A8-0355/2018 - Enrique Calvet Chambon)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-154-0000" speaker_id="129407" name="Enrique Calvet Chambon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señor presidente, señorías, ¿por qué un texto que fue aprobado en la comisión especializada por 30 votos a favor y solo 7 en contra, con un mandato de 32 votos a favor y 15 en contra —menos de la mitad—se convierte en objeto de todas las batallas para revocar el mandato contra toda lógica y tradición parlamentaria? Hay una explicación: evidentemente, no es la de mejorar el texto, cosa que se hará y en gran medida en las negociaciones tripartitas, abundantes y ya planificadas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lo que sucede es que hay unas poderosas fuerzas, poderosos lobbies, totalmente legítimos, por supuesto, que prefieren, con mucho, que no haya ninguna directiva sobre este tema en esta legislatura. Saben que una manera de conseguir una «no directiva» es dilatar los procesos, puesto que, con una pequeña dilación, se convierte en prácticamente imposible acabar nuestro trabajo en este mandato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto es lo que está en juego, tener o no tener directiva. Detrás están en juego distintas visiones de Europa, evidentemente. La que cree en una Europa de los ciudadanos no puede permitir que antes de una campaña electoral nos presentemos con las manos vacías frente a los ciudadanos que nos exigen protección y atención. No concebimos salir a la calle a decir que Europa no ha podido tomar en cuenta al ciudadano frente a los cambios acelerados del mercado y las tecnologías.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si hoy no votamos a favor del mandato, no podremos iniciar negociaciones tripartitas el 21 de noviembre. Y si no empezamos el 21 de noviembre, habrá que ir pensando en dejarlo para otra legislatura, y les dejo imaginar lo que acontecerá. Por eso, a los que creen que seguramente podemos mejorar el texto en las negociaciones tripartitas, pero que es fundamental conseguir ahora una directiva aceptable por el bien de los ciudadanos, para los que creen en una Europa de los ciudadanos, les ruego que voten más y confirmen mi mandato, para hacer posible una buena directiva, pero, sobre todo, para que la directiva exista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señores, con todo el respeto, voten en su alma y conciencia, pero sin dejar de pensar en la ciudadanía europea.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="5.5. Rail passengers' rights and obligations (A8-0340/2018 - Bogusław Liberadzki)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="5.6. Persistent organic pollutants (A8-0336/2018 - Julie Girling)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-158-0000" speaker_id="96956" name="Julie Girling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Mr President, in the interests of speed, under Rules 59(a) and 69(f), I request plenary to refer the matter back to committee for interinstitutional negotiations.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="5.7. Care services in the EU for improved gender equality (A8-0352/2018 - Sirpa Pietikäinen)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="5.8. Lyme disease (Borreliosis) (B8-0514/2018)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-162-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you very much. I should have raised this at the beginning, but I did not want to delay Members. Yesterday, on the final vote on humanitarian visas, there was controversy: it fell 26 votes short of the overall majority required, and at that stage 81 Members had left or did not vote. I think the controversy could be avoided in future if, when there are votes that require a majority of the constituent members, it should be put higher up the list. You can see every day that there are far more voting in the middle or thereabouts. At the end, for one reason or another, Members will have to leave to catch planes or have other meetings. So this controversy could be avoided with a bit of common sense by the Conference of Presidents if they put votes that required a majority of our constituent members higher up the list when you would have all those who were eligible to vote here. It was reasonable to suggest that, when it was only 26 votes short and 349 voted in favour, if it was higher up the list then it would have got the required majority. I just want to make that point as a suggestion for the Conference of Presidents.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-163-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Kelly! Ich will mal darauf hinweisen, dass hier alle Berichte gleich wichtig sind. Möglicherweise hat der eine etwas höhere politische Bedeutung, aber grundsätzlich sind alle Berichte gleich wichtig, weil sie die Arbeit der Kollegen hier im Hause auch widerspiegeln.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es gibt eine klare Geschäftsordnungsregelung, in welcher Reihenfolge über Dossiers abgestimmt wird, und da geht z. B. Gesetzgebung vor anderen Dossiers. Von dieser Geschäftsordnung kann nur in Ausnahmefällen abgewichen werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich persönlich bedaure es sehr, dass nunmehr bereits am Mittwoch Kollegen früher gehen. Andererseits können wir auch keine Gewissenserforschung betreiben. Es gibt auch Kollegen, die sich bewusst an Abstimmungen nicht beteiligen – die sich nicht bloß enthalten wollen, sondern die sich nicht an Enthaltungen beteiligen wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das Problem mit dieser gestrigen Abstimmung ist gesehen. Ich kann Sie unterrichten, dass die Konferenz der Präsidenten beschlossen hat, den LIBE-Ausschuss zu ermächtigen, erneut in dieses Verfahren einzusteigen. Die Abstimmung von gestern können wir nicht wiederholen. Da gibt es auch klare Regeln. Aber der Ausschuss kann das Verfahren noch mal neu aufrollen und dann gucken, wie zügig der Ausschuss mit einem Dossier wieder hier im Plenum landet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-164-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Ja chciałem powiedzieć, że takie głosy jak pana Kelly’ego uważam za kompletnie niepoważne. Brak szacunku posłów do wykonywanej pracy naprawdę nie może być usprawiedliwieniem do powtarzania głosowań. Wynagrodzenia posłów są wystarczająco wysokie, żeby mogli zaczekać tutaj pół godziny, aż głosowania się skończą. Więc takie gadanie o tym, żeby przesunąć głosowania, które dla pana Kelly’ego są ważniejsze, na taką godzinę, żeby panu Kelly’emu chciało się tutaj zostać, jest naprawdę nie do uwierzenia. Ludzie tego słuchają na galerii dla publiczności. Przestańmy wygadywać takie rzeczy, bo to wstyd.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-165-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vielen Dank, Herr Sośnierz! Ich glaube, das braucht man nicht weiter zu kommentieren. Ich will nur sagen – das ist vielleicht nicht üblich: Die Kritik an Herrn Kelly richtet sich an den Falschen. Er ist in der Regel von Anfang bis Ende bei allen parlamentarischen Arbeiten anwesend.</p>
      <p sl="en">Damit ist die Abstimmungsstunde geschlossen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="6. Explanations of vote"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="6.1. Rail passengers' rights and obligations (A8-0340/2018 - Bogusław Liberadzki)">
    <intervention id="4-179-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">This report says that the railway sector has to provide excellent and modern services to customers at an affordable price, and I agree. It has been a torrid time on the railways for my constituents this year as train companies have profited from consumer misery. This summer, GTR, who run Thameslink and Great Northern, cancelled 8 000 services in the first three weeks of the new timetable being introduced, yet these problems were foreseeable. Each train needs a driver who has been trained on the model of the train and the route on which they are operating, but this does not happen quickly enough, and when the problems came to light, the rollout wasn’t paused. I blame the fragmented nature of the industry. The Government has set up a review of our railways and I hope that it can learn from our European friends as Brits spend five times more of our income than our European counterparts on rail travel. I call on the Government to include in its review the putting back of our railways into public ownership after 25 years of failed privatisation. That will mean that we run our profits in the interests of passengers, not for private profit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-180-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I am very pleased at the progress we have made on this report today. I spoke in the debate on this yesterday, but I want to raise a slightly different issue which is covered in this report, and that is ensuring our railways are accessible for disabled people, and particularly wheelchair users. Because time after time on our railways in the UK but indeed in other parts of Europe as well, I see a system that isn’t working.</p>
      <p sl="en">You see people who use wheelchairs having to wait for assistance with ramps and assistance at stations they booked and that assistance not turning up. That is a system which isn’t working. People have to sit on trains waiting for that assistance. We have to make sure our railways are accessible to all, and today’s vote in this House taking this report forward is an important step in doing that.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-181-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, podporila som správu, pretože verím, že po prijatí navrhovaných opatrení sa cestovanie železničnou dopravou stane pre spotrebiteľov príťažlivejšie a preferovanejšie. Som potešená, že správa EP a Rady o právach a povinnostiach cestujúcich v železničnej preprave okrem iného stanovuje aj právny rámec s cieľom prispôsobiť železničnú infraštruktúru osobám so zníženou pohyblivosťou, a tak im umožniť úplnú nezávislosť na železničných staniciach a vlakoch. Súhlasím so spravodajcom, že zlepšenie a modernizácia železničného odvetvia by mali byť aj naďalej trvalým cieľom pre toto odvetvie vrátane ochrany spotrebiteľa. Za skutočne dôležité považujem prilákať do železničnej dopravy nových cestujúcich a odbremeniť cestnú dopravu. V mojej krajine na Slovensku vláda zaviedla bezplatné cestovanie železnicou pre študentov a dôchodcov a týmto opatrením sa výrazne zvýšil počet cestujúcich v železničnej doprave. Toto opatrenie by mohlo byť vzorom aj pre iné členské štáty, čím by sme efektívnejšie využívali sieť železníc, výrazne by sme znížili aj CO2 a prispeli k lepšej kvalite života.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-182-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, meškania vlakov sa v poslednom čase stali bežným javom nielen na Slovensku, ale vo viacerých štátoch Európskej únie. Posilnenie práv cestujúcich je preto u nás možno ešte aktuálnejšie než inde. Podporujem vyššiu informovanosť o právach cestujúcich, zlepšenie pomoci ľuďom s obmedzenou pohyblivosťou a najmä zvýšenie odškodnenia pre tých cestujúcich, ktorých vlak mešká. Kvalita železničnej dopravy sa meria spokojnosťou cestujúcich. Vždy môže prísť k zlyhaniam, ale dôvera ľudí k železničnej doprave závisí aj od toho, ako sa dopravca vyrovná so vzniknutými nedostatkami. Som rada, že novou legislatívou mu v tom môžeme pomôcť, a preto som návrh podporila.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-183-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">I welcome this report also, after some compromises. Rail travel is such an important part of our shared European identity, and it is imperative that this is done properly, seeing that hundreds and thousands of Europeans travel by rail every day. Citizens deserve to know their rights when they travel, and deserve to have all information available to them before, during and after travel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cancellations and delays have become almost expected across many rail providers. This should not happen, but if it must occur for some unavoidable reason then passengers should be compensated properly, and I am delighted to see it being discussed and voted upon today.</p>
      <p sl="en">Although a small country, Ireland’s citizens make use of our rail system and Iarnród Éireann provide an excellent service, but these regulation updates are still extremely welcome and can only serve to benefit customers and providers in the long run. So I am very pleased to support it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-184-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, you won’t find a single Member of this Chamber who opposes any of the aims set out in this report: making it easier for people to take bicycles on trains, having greater information or rights to compensation if you have been mistreated, greater access for disabled people. Not a single Member in any of these groups will think that those are bad ideas, and do you know what? Neither will the operators of the rail networks. It is a bad business model not to try and accommodate your customers.</p>
      <p sl="en">The problem is that we’ve moved from thinking that these are desiderata into thinking that they require legislation. It is a kind of legislative virtue-signalling. Our primary purpose is not to remedy and identify a problem, but to let the world know what very nice people we are. The result is that there will be additional bureaucracy, additional paperwork, additional distraction of resources by the people who know more about it than we do in this Chamber, which means in the end that they are not able to concentrate on delivering the best possible customer service. I wish we would have the modesty to accept that we are not always the experts.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="6.2. Care services in the EU for improved gender equality (A8-0352/2018 - Sirpa Pietikäinen)">
    <intervention id="4-215-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, pečovatelské služby jsou přirozeně doménou žen, a proto také zpráva, kterou jsme přijali na úrovni Evropského parlamentu, byla nazírána zejména z pohledu žen, které pracují v pečovatelských službách. Bohužel během hlasování se nepodařilo prosadit důležité pozměňovací návrhy a vypustit některá ustanovení, která jsou v této zprávě opravdu zavádějící a narušují subsidiaritu pravomocí členských zemí. Například považuji za naprosto nevhodné, aby na evropské úrovni byla prováděna regulace a kontrola kvality pečovatelských služeb, aby byl na evropské úrovni stanoven právní rámec pečovatelské profese. Je mi tedy líto, že jsem nemohla tuto zprávu podpořit a zdržela jsem se.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-216-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the employment rate for women is 12% lower than for men. One in four people in the EU lives at risk of poverty and over half of them are women. The main reason is the difficulties that arise when families have children or when they have to care for elderly or disabled persons. Those difficulties are due to the shocking lack of public care infrastructure and the persistent gender-based division of labour. It’s high time that the Member States address this situation. It is actually 2018, even though not everybody has realised it.</p>
      <p sl="en">I urge Member States to develop paternity leave, to step up efforts to provide good care for children, the elderly and disabled people, and to ensure equal opportunities for women and men regarding participation in the labour market. That’s why I voted for this report.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-217-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Po raz kolejny zostało udowodnione na tej sali, że karta do głosowania w rękach socjalisty jest bardziej niebezpieczna niż brzytwa w rękach dziecka. Ludzie, którzy z jednej strony mówią, że potrzebujemy więcej lepszej opieki, więcej usług opiekuńczych, jednocześnie mówią, że należy je sformalizować i opodatkować. A przecież jak coś opodatkujemy, to będziemy mieli tego mniej, a nie więcej. Jeśli do tej pory płaciliśmy opiekunce sto złotych, to teraz będziemy musieli zapłacić drugie sto na dodatkowe opłaty i podatki dla państwa. Więc albo opiekunka dostanie mniej, albo my będzie musieli zarobić więcej, żeby to wszystko spłacić. Z jakiegoś powodu ci sami ludzie, którzy wierzą, że mandaty na drodze za szybką jazdę zniechęcą ludzi do szybkiej jazdy, nie rozumieją tego, że mandaty w postaci podatków za pracę zniechęcą ludzi do pracy. Przecież to tylko nazwą się różni, a działa dokładnie tak samo. Jeśli chcemy mieć mniej pracy, mniej usług, to dawajmy ludziom mandaty i nazywajmy je podatkami i w ten sposób osiągniemy niespotykany dotąd dobrobyt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-218-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, aj keď sa každoročne venujeme postaveniu žien a dievčat v rodovej rovnosti, výsledky, ktoré v EÚ dosahujeme, sú nedostatočné. V tejto širokospektrálnej činnosti služieb starostlivosti chcem upriamiť pozornosť na nedostatočnosť verejných služieb, ktoré vysokými nákladmi majú negatívny vplyv na deti z rodín s nízkymi príjmami a znevýhodňujú nielen deti od raného veku, ale aj rodičov, hlavne matku, v jej začlenení do aktívneho pracovného života. Preto musíme vyvinúť maximálne úsilie, aby hlavne v národných programoch dominovali opatrenia na primeranú odmenu v týchto službách. Členské štáty musia prehodnotiť túto oblasť, v ktorej sú zaradené predovšetkým ženy, ako voľbu ich kariéry. Na druhej strane vítam úsilie, ktoré by zaviazalo Komisiu vytvoriť právny rámec pre minimálne normy pre pracovníkov v odvetví starostlivosti o odkázaných. Aby sa primerane investovalo do dobrých životných podmienok osôb, ktoré tieto služby poskytujú, do dobrého vzdelávania týchto ľudí, aby sa neustále vytvárali dobré životné podmienky pre opatrované osoby. Všetka táto činnosť leží na pleciach žien a to je tá podstata: dostať odmeňovanie za prácu na takú úroveň, aby sa čím skôr zotreli 16 % rozdiely v odmeňovaní a 40 % rozdiel v dôchodkoch medzi mužmi a ženami.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-219-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, text spravodajkyne Pietikäinen potvrdzuje mnohé veci, na ktoré som dlhodobo upozorňovala. Niektoré z navrhnutých opatrení by si vyžadovali dlhšiu diskusiu, mnohé by však mohli byť cenným zdrojom inšpirácie pre členské štáty. Sem patrí napríklad návrh, aby sa obdobie výkonu neplatenej starostlivosti započítalo tým, ktorí ju vykonávajú, do odpracovaných rokov pri nároku na dôchodok. Úlohou Únie v sociálnej oblasti, pokiaľ ide o starostlivosť, by mala byť podpora členských štátov v tom, aby ich politiky rešpektovali a chránili ľudskú dôstojnosť. Žiaľ, tento dokument opakovane zachádza ďalej a žiada, aby tieto politiky Únia sama prijímala, aj keď na to nemá kompetencie. Aj preto som sa nakoniec pri záverečnom hlasovaní zdržala.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-220-0000" speaker_id="124927" name="Branislav Škripek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, aj ja som sa pri tejto správe zdržal, hoci má viaceré dobré ohľady. Správa dobre poukazuje na to, že je potrebné zaoberať sa rozvojom dostupnosti a kvalitou služieb starostlivosti o občanov. Ale milujúcu starostlivosť rodinných príslušníkov nikdy nenahradia chladné kamenné domovy sociálnych služieb, aj keď sa tam bude naozaj dobre pracovať. Mali by sme preto podporovať rodiny pri tejto starostlivosti a dať im možnosť prijať vonkajšiu pomoc, ktorú mnohokrát aj naozaj potrebujú. Táto profesionálna pomoc musí byť finančne aj prakticky dostupná. Umiestňovanie do ústavov by malo nasledovať až po tom, keď sa domáca starostlivosť nezvládne. Musím však zdôrazniť, že pri ošetrovaní o ľudí majú ženy nezastupiteľnú úlohu. V istých prípadoch vie muž zastať rovnako túto službu. Ja sám som pôsobil ako ošetrovateľ a jeden z mojich troch synov je postihnutý. Ale treba povedať, že je nutné zachovať človeku odkázanému na tieto služby dôstojnosť a zobrať do úvahy pri tom rôzne faktory. Napríklad, nie je možné aby sme v mene rodovej rovnosti žiadali od mužov, napríklad synov, aby prebaľovali svoje choré a starnúce ženy matky, lebo sa budú naozaj zle cítiť.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-221-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Thank you, Mr President, Friedrich Hayek observed that there is all the difference in the world between treating people equally and attempting to make them equal. The first, he said, is the precondition for a free society; the second leads to servitude.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is the case that government assistance can free up people’s time. If the state decided to offer me someone to wash the dishes and do the housework for me without my having to do it, I would have more time to work. That’s true for all of us, it doesn’t become more or less true when you have children at home.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is an argument, and various regimes down the years – some savoury and some not – have made the argument that the state should be philoprogenitive; that we should be encouraging people to have babies through the tax system. Fine, if that’s the argument you want to make, let’s make it honestly and openly, but let’s not pretend that it is an issue of gender equality.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="6.3. Lyme disease (Borreliosis) (B8-0514/2018)">
    <intervention id="4-238-0000" speaker_id="124984" name="Lynn Boylan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I welcome today’s vote on Lyme disease and the calls made for greater ambition to improve diagnostics treatment and prevention of this disease. It will help give a voice to all those who suffer from Lyme and associated tick-borne diseases.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infected ticks and Lyme disease are spreading geographically, driven by climate change and land-use change. Symptoms can go unnoticed and often doctors are not trained in looking for those symptoms, thereby delaying medical intervention. Current diagnostic tests are also not reliable enough. The antibody-based only test is 30% to 50% accurate and the PCR test is only 62% accurate. This means that the actual number of Lyme cases is much higher than what is believed.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is crucial to focus our attention on the sharing of best practice, patient—centred research and patient—centric guidelines. Patients must be involved in any new developments. I welcome the inclusion of Lyme disease on the EU list of communicable diseases and epidemiological surveillance to facilitate the monitoring of the EU distribution of the disease.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-239-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Public Health England estimate that there were 3 000 cases of Lyme disease last year. There is a quadrupling in the number of cases in recent years in the UK, and that is reflected in other Member States as well.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is an extremely debilitating, serious disease. We need to see more research, more investment in treatments, a broadening and a deepening of the medical knowledge of this disease, and that is why I support that work taking place at European Union level.</p>
      <p sl="en">It makes sense to do that, and I hope that going forward, whatever happens in Westminster today or indeed, in the coming weeks and months, that the UK can remain an active, full partner of that work and indeed, wider medical research work at a European level. That is in the interests of patients in the UK and across the European Union as well.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="7. Corrections to votes and voting intentions : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="8. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="9. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="10. Action taken as a result of a request for waiver of immunity: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="11. Role of the German Youth Welfare Office (Jugendamt) in cross-border family disputes (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-260-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Erklärung der Kommission zu der Rolle des deutschen Jugendamts bei grenzüberschreitenden Familienstreitigkeiten (2018/2856(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-261-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank the European Parliament and the Committee on Petitions and to acknowledge the high importance and sensitivity of the issues raised in the numerous petitions that were received over the last few years on the issue of the Jugendamt.</p>
      <p sl="en">The issues raised by some petitions and the discussions held in the framework of the Committee on Petitions work have fed into the Commission proposal to revise the process to a regulation. More precisely, the proposal aims at strengthening the rights of the child by ensuring that their views are heard in the legal proceedings concerning them. The mutual recognition of Member States’ practices in this respect will avoid refusals at the stage of recognition or enforcement, thus allowing a true circulation of judgments in the Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">We hope that the Council will reach a political agreement on this file in December. Furthermore, the cross-border nature of the family cases requires a close cooperation between Member States’ authorities. The proposal ensures a more effective cooperation between central authorities which in Germany is the Federal Office of Justice. They are the direct interface with parents and should play a key role in supporting the judges in applying the regulation. In addition, we proposed to integrate cooperation with child welfare authorities in the overall cooperation system. On the other hand, I have to recall that the functioning of the National Child Protection Agencies is governed by national law in cases of concern about the proper functioning of such a system redress had to be sought at a national level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Over the past years, the Commission has used several tools to promote exchanges between Member States to facilitate mutual understanding, with a view to ensuring the protection of the rights of children. It has done so through the annual forum on the rights of the child, the calls for proposals under the rights, equality and citizenship programme, as well as the focus put on the promotion of integrated child protection systems.</p>
      <p sl="en">Under the Justice programme, one of the funding priorities for 2018 is improving the situation of children involved in civil cases, for example through better procedures, case handling and cooperation in the area of family law in such areas as parental responsibility, international child abduction, the protection of children and maintenance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Once again, let me highlight the importance that the Commission attaches to these issues and I look forward to your views.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-262-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, within the German Youth Welfare Office, the Jugendamt, it has come to the attention of the European Parliament that there appears to be alleged discrimination against non-German parents in family disputes on parental responsibility and child custody.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the main issues that has been highlighted to the Committee on Petitions (PETI) is the alleged impossibility for a non-German spouse to have contact with their child even during supervised visits, notably because of the strictly applied language rules whereby only the German language can be used. If this is the case, it is of course extremely distressing for parents and children. The Jugendamt plays a central, important role in the German family law system as it is one of the prior parties in all family disputes involving children, and so these accusations should be taken seriously.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is important to mention, though, that fact-finding missions have not found any systemic failures. But, in my opinion, if there are many concerns like this coming from parents, then reassurances should be given and cases should be looked at. Discrimination of any kind is not acceptable and, while I would need further evidence and rulings to determine if this is a case of discrimination, the petitions brought forward at least highlight that there is a perception of such by some in this case, and that perhaps measures could be taken to eliminate any possibility of this. I think these cases should be looked into, but let us reserve judgment until we have more information. Of course, at the end of the day, the child’s best interests must be paramount in all decisions related to childcare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I just want to say that it’s important to point out that PETI also received similar complaints from at least three other Member States. So perhaps a more Union—wide, global approach would be desirable to address these issues rather than perhaps honing in on one particular country.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-263-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the single market and the absence of borders has given us many chances to seek economic advantages in another country. Many children have, however, become victims of our striving for a better life. We are faced with a new phenomenon today: Euro orphans, that is to say children temporarily abandoned by parents working abroad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Did you know that the number of Euro orphans in the EU is estimated at between 500 000 and one million? This is a huge number, but the reunification of such families has not been taken for granted, and in some cases becomes a nightmare for parents. During the last ten years, Parliament has received an enormous amount of petitions related to involvement of the Jugendamt in cross-border family disputes.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the majority of cases, non-German parents denounce systematic discriminations and arbitrary measures, including the prohibition of the use of the parents’ mother tongue in contact with children. The national administrative system of non-German parents do not have a say in this process and in addition, the German competent authorities have failed to implement the recent recommendation of our Committee on Petitions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Clearly, the question of parental responsibility and child custody falls under the competence of the Jugendamt and, without it, there is no alternative way to solve these questions. Therefore, we must find new, effective solutions to all issues experienced by non-German parents. The European Commission needs to have a regular oversight of Jugendamt activities. Bilateral consular services must get involved and multilateral platforms must be created to guarantee that the cross-border character of a dispute does not endanger the well-being of children.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-264-0000" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Niemiecki Urząd ds. Młodzieży, tzw. Jugendamt, który w swoim założeniu miał dbać o dobro dzieci i młodzieży, w rzeczywistości często działa przeciwko dzieciom, naruszając artykuły karty praw dziecka, odbierając dzieci rodzicom – szczególnie obcokrajowcom z krajów Europy Środkowo-Wschodniej – bardzo często z błahego albo wyimaginowanego powodu. Na prawie 140 tysięcy wszczętych postępowań kontrolnych tylko w 22 tysiącach spraw stwierdzono w pełni uzasadnione działania.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wielu moich rodaków mieszka z rodzinami w Niemczech i wielokrotnie słyszymy w Polsce skargi zrozpaczonych rodziców, którym Jugendamt odebrał dzieci, zakazując spotkań z rodzicami, utrudniając porozumiewanie się w języku polskim lub ojczystym, (petycje składane są także przez rodziców należących do innych narodów europejskich), a nawet zakazując go.</p>
      <p sl="en">Spory z Jugendamtami trwają latami, urząd krytykowany jest za opieszałość, zbytnie ingerowanie w życie rodzin, naruszanie prywatności, a wszystko to nie sprzyja rozwojowi dziecka, a nawet prowadzi do zaburzeń psychicznych, osobowości i tożsamości.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-265-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ALDE. – Poštovani predsjedavajući, poštovana povjerenice Jourová, želim se u ime ALDE grupe priključiti brizi koju svi iskazujemo ovdje u ovom Parlamentu za rad Jugendamta. Naime, evidentno je da mnoge predstavke koje se bilježe očito ukazuju na nepravilnosti u radu, odnosno na diskriminaciju, a to je sigurno ono što zadnje želimo u Europskoj uniji. Diskriminirati naše građane i to još po pitanju djece. To je zaista ono najgore što nam se može dogoditi.</p>
      <p sl="en">S pravom si možemo postaviti pitanje kakvu mi Uniju zaista želimo. Želimo li Uniju u kojoj će biti glavno trgovati slobodno ili želimo Uniju u kojoj će se građani zaista osjećati sigurno i Uniju u kojoj ćemo mi raditi za te iste građane koji se onda trebaju osjećati sigurno i dobro?</p>
      <p sl="en">Naravno da trebamo poći od najboljeg interesa djeteta. To je ono od čega treba krenuti u svim razmišljanjima i zato očekujem od vas, od Komisije, da učini sve kako bi Vijeće uskladilo zakonodavnu infrastrukturu Europske unije i da zaista djeca i roditelji ne budu diskriminirani.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-266-0000" speaker_id="124779" name="Eleonora Evi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, sono state centinaia le petizioni ricevute dalla commissione per le petizioni negli ultimi dieci anni e il numero continua a crescere. Petizioni che denunciano gravi discriminazioni nei confronti dei genitori non tedeschi, discriminazioni che sono perpetrate dallo Jugendamt nell'ambito delle controversie familiari transnazionali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tutto questo è in contrasto con le norme e i principi del diritto dell'Unione europea e va a grave pregiudizio della tutela del benessere dei minori coinvolti. La commissione per le petizioni, nel corso di questi dieci lunghi anni, ha emesso delle raccomandazioni rivolte alle autorità tedesche, rivolte alla Commissione europea, rivolte al Consiglio, ha fatto due missioni conoscitive, ha addirittura istituito un gruppo di lavoro che ha lavorato per un anno intero, che io ho avuto l'onore di presiedere, ma tutte le raccomandazioni fatte sono rimaste ad oggi lettera morta. Questo sia per il rifiuto di collaborare costruttivamente da parte delle autorità tedesche, che più volte sono state sollecitate in tal senso, sia anche per l'inaccettabile approccio formalistico e superficiale da parte della Commissione europea, che purtroppo ha perseverato nel negare le indagini accurate sulle criticità denunciate nel sistema tedesco in merito al diritto di famiglia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Faccio riferimento, in particolare, alle statistiche. Noi abbiamo chiesto più volte che vengano raccolti dei dati statistici sia per quanto riguarda gli esiti giudiziari nelle controversie familiari sulla custodia dei minori in presenza di un genitore non tedesco, sia sul numero dei casi, sempre in presenza di un genitore non tedesco, in cui un giudice si è discostato dalla raccomandazione emessa dallo Jugendamt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo chiesto anche che si facesse luce sulle discriminazioni legate all'uso della lingua, più volte negata durante gli incontri tra i genitori e i figli. Io mi auspico che questa risoluzione possa finalmente far luce su questo tema, possa scaturire delle azioni concrete da parte non soltanto della Commissione europea, ma anche da parte degli Stati membri. Io mi auguro che quanto meno questo tema possa essere approfondito e comunicato e che le pratiche che vengono adottate in concreto dal sistema del diritto di famiglia tedesco possano essere comprese e comunicate e appunto affrontate in maniera serena, perché questo è il modo con cui dovremo affrontare questo problema se vogliamo che questa Unione europea, questa nostra casa comune, possa chiamarsi tale a tutela soprattutto delle generazioni future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-267-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Cieszę się, że w końcu zajmujemy się tutaj, w naszym parlamencie, prawdziwymi problemami dotyczącymi praworządności. Szkoda, że takie ważne dyskusje są przesuwane na tak późną porę, kiedy już tylko wiatr hula po korytarzach parlamentu po ostatnich głosowaniach. No ale dobre i to.</p>
      <p sl="en">Widzimy, w jaki sposób w Niemczech zagrożone są prawa człowieka i prawa dzieci. Niemcy próbują pouczać Polskę chociażby w sprawie sądów, a u siebie mają dużo poważniejsze problemy. Nie jest to jednak wyłącznie sprawa Niemiec. W wielu krajach istnieją podobne praktyki. Problem polega na tym, że budujemy państwo totalne. Państwo totalne charakteryzuje się tym, że nie uznaje żadnej władzy poza własną. Dlatego państwo totalne walczy z władzą rodziców. Państwo totalne uważa, że wie lepiej od rodziców, co jest dobre dla dzieci. Posługuje się dobrem dziecka w imię ingerencji w życie rodziny. Nie może być przypadków, żeby w imię dobra dziecka urzędnicy mogli ingerować we władzę rodzicielską. Jedynie popełnienie czynu karalnego, poważnego przestępstwa, może upoważnić do odbierania dzieci, a nie dobro dziecka, gdyż dobro dziecka każdy może rozumieć inaczej i ma święte prawo rozumieć inaczej niż urzędnik. Smutne jest, że na naszym kontynencie my, dumni dziedzice indoeuropejskiego dziedzictwa, pozwalamy sobie, aby urzędnicy pomiatali nami tak, że bez jednego wystrzału oddajemy swoje dzieci.</p>
      <a text="(Mówca zgodził się odpowiedzieć na pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki (art. 162 ust. 8 Regulaminu))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-268-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">zilās kartītes jautājums. – Dārgais kolēģi, liels paldies, ka jūs pieņēmāt manu zilās kartītes jautājumu. Es zinu, ka jūs bieži ļoti asi kritizējat Eiropas Savienību — ka mums šis nav labi un tas nav labi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bet īstenībā arī no jūsu runas es tā arī nesadzirdēju atbildi, ko jūs piedāvājat, kas ir jādara, lai, no vienas puses, saglabātu bērnu dzimto valodu un, no otras puses, negrautu Eiropas Savienību.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-269-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odpowiedź na pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. – Powiedziałem, co powinniśmy zrobić: dziecko należy do rodziców i tylko rodzice powinni decydować, co jest dobre dla dziecka, a nie urzędnicy. Nie jest to więc oczywiście kwestia wyłącznie Jugendamtów i wyłącznie Niemiec, choć tam tę politykę doprowadzono do pewnej skrajności, która razi poza granicami tego kraju. Rozwiązaniem jest to, żeby urzędnicy nie mieli prawa powoływać się na dobro dziecka przeciwko rodzicom. Jedynie popełnienie przestępstwa wobec dziecka może upoważniać do interwencji, a nie jakieś wyimaginowane, rozumiane swoiście dobro dziecka.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-270-0000" speaker_id="124898" name="Julia Pitera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Od 2006 r., czyli przez 12 lat, do Komisji Petycji wpłynęło łącznie 258 petycji zawierających skargi w sprawie Jugendamtów. W tej liczbie 196 petycji, czyli 76 %, dotyczyło dzieci obywateli niemieckich. Pozostałe 62 petycje pochodziły od obywateli innych państw. Komisja Petycji w toku prac dysponowała zazwyczaj tylko relacją autora petycji, a przecież żadna instytucja nie może ograniczyć przynależnych obywatelowi praw bez wyroku sądu, również w sprawach opieki nad dziećmi. Tak więc wyroki w każdej sprawie musiały zapadać. Tymczasem do większości petycji nie dołączano wyroku, pomimo, a może właśnie dlatego, że wyrok sądu jest jedynym pełnym źródłem wiedzy o problemie. Opiera się na zeznaniach obojga rodziców, dzieci i świadków. Komisja więc z konieczności opierała swoje opinie głównie na relacji autora petycji, jedynej ze stron sporu. Z tego powodu skierowałam do Trybunału Praw Człowieka w Strasburgu zapytanie, który z 62 autorów petycji o narodowości innej niż niemiecka złożył skargę do Trybunału. Uzyskałam odpowiedź, że tylko siedemnaście osób skargę taką złożyło i że wszystkie te skargi zostały uznane za niedopuszczalne. Również w 2011 r., w trakcie misji do Niemiec, członkowie Komisji Petycji nie stwierdzili nieprawidłowości. Tymczasem temat ten regularnie powraca, stając się, podobnie jak histeria antyszczepionkowa, narzędziem w walce politycznej, zwłaszcza w okresach przedwyborczych. Zasiewa niepokój i podważa nie tylko zaufanie do władzy, ale i wzajemne zaufanie w ramach Wspólnoty Europejskiej. I ten aspekt powinien zwrócić naszą szczególną uwagę.</p>
      <a text="(Mówczyni zgodziła się odpowiedzieć na pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki (art. 162 ust. 8 Regulaminu))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-271-0000" speaker_id="124884" name="Kosma Złotowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. – Wielce Szanowna Pani Poseł! Czy uważa Pani w związku z tym, że Jugendamty w Niemczech działają poprawnie, bez zarzutu i że wszystkie zarzuty, o których jest tu mowa, o których jest mowa w środkach masowego przekazu, są wyimaginowane? Czy w związku z tym postulowałaby może Pani, żeby rozszerzyć jurysdykcję Jugendamtów albo utworzyć podobne urzędy w innych krajach Unii Europejskiej?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-272-0000" speaker_id="124898" name="Julia Pitera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odpowiedź na pytanie zadane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki. –(początek wystąpienia poza mikrofonem) … ani nie atakuje. W pracy każdy polityk powinien opierać się na faktach i dokumentach, a nie na doniesieniach prasowych, często opierających się na emocjach jednej osoby, która czuje się skrzywdzona. Jak Pan wie, również w Polsce wydziały opieki społecznej o podobnej strukturze jak Jugendamty też czasem nie dopilnowują swoich obowiązków. W związku z tym jednak byłabym skłonna namówić Pana, żeby czytał Pan dokumenty, bo one są najważniejsze, a nie emocje jednego człowieka.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-273-0000" speaker_id="124947" name="Edouard Martin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, imaginez que je vous parle sans interprétation. Vous ne comprendriez rien à mes propos. Imaginez que vous soyez jugé dans un pays qui n’est pas le vôtre et que vous ne connaissiez rien à ses règles parce que personne ne vous les a expliquées. Imaginez que, sur convocation, vous vous présentiez à un tribunal avec votre enfant, confiante ou confiant d’être dans votre bon droit, et que vous repartiez sans lui. Imaginez que vous soyez obligé de payer une pension alimentaire pour votre enfant, qu’on ne vous laisse pas voir depuis des années. Imaginez qu’après toutes ces années d’absence, votre enfant ne parle plus votre langue, ne connaisse plus votre culture et, pire, ne sache même plus qui vous êtes, vous, son parent. Imaginez.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eh bien! c’est la situation à laquelle sont confrontés des milliers de parents face au Jugendamt, c’est pour ainsi dire David contre Goliath. Non, cette résolution n’est pas un texte contre l’Allemagne. Ce texte, c’est un appel au droit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si le Jugendamt veut vraiment défendre l’intérêt supérieur de l’enfant, comme il le prétend, il doit le laisser profiter pleinement de sa mère et de son père. C’est la base même de son équilibre et de son émancipation. C’est cette richesse culturelle multiple qui en fera un adulte solide, ouvert et une personne aimante, car c’est bien de cela qu’il s’agit, de l’amour. Comment peut-on être aussi obtus pour empêcher un parent de dire à son enfant qu’il l’aime, qu’il lui manque, qu’il a envie de le serrer dans ses bras. Comment?</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette résolution, j’ose le dire, est un appel à l’amour, n’en déplaise à certaines ou certains, parce que j’entends trop souvent dire que la politique ne doit pas être basée sur l’affect – cela explique d’ailleurs peut-être pourquoi la situation du monde est aussi chaotique. Alors, chers collègues, je vous demande d’ouvrir votre cœur et de permettre à ces enfants de ressentir l’amour de leurs deux parents. L’amour, encore l’amour, toujours l’amour.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Europe ne peut pas rester spectatrice et nous ne pouvons pas être les spectateurs de cela. Nous devons agir et nous pouvons, à cet effet, nous baser sur les déclarations, pas plus tard qu’hier, de Mme Merkel. Chiche, Madame la Chancelière, soyons plus solidaires! Donc, permettez une harmonie familiale au seul et unique profit de l’enfant. C’est cela qui compte et rien d’autre.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-274-0000" speaker_id="124884" name="Kosma Złotowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Działania niemieckich urzędów do spraw dzieci i młodzieży wielokrotnie budziły oburzenie opinii publicznej w Polsce, ale problem jest dużo szerszy i dotyczy przecież obywateli wszystkich państw Unii Europejskiej, którzy zetknęli się z tą instytucją. Bezprawne, ale legalne niestety w świetle niemieckiego prawa odbieranie dzieci czy zakazywanie używania języka ojczystego w kontaktach z rodzicami to częste praktyki Jugendamtów. W Polsce mamy jak najgorsze historyczne skojarzenia z tego typu działaniami.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pani kanclerz Merkel mówiła dwa dni temu w tej Izbie, że narodowe egoizmy stoją w sprzeczności z wartościami europejskimi. Nie przeszkadza jej jednak to, że niemieccy urzędnicy faworyzują niemieckojęzycznych rodziców i dyskryminują obywateli innych państw w rodzinach mieszanych. Parlament i Komisja bardzo chętnie zajmują się zwalczaniem wszelkich form dyskryminacji, więc mam nadzieję, że nie zabraknie im determinacji, aby stanąć po stronie m.in. polskich rodziców, którzy padli ofiarą Jugendamtów.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-275-0000" speaker_id="112753" name="Jozo Radoš" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, gospođo povjerenice, kolegice i kolege, najprije bih htio zahvaliti Odboru za predstavke i gospođi zastupnici Wikström na pokretanju ove inicijative na plenarnoj sjednici Europskog parlamenta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prema brojnim predstavkama koje su stigle proteklih desetak godina, makar nemamo pravosudni pravorijek o negativnosti rada njemačkog ureda za skrb o djeci, očito je da se radi o kršenju niza međunarodnih konvencija, programa Europske unije za prava djeteta, uključujući i odgovarajuće zakonodavne dokumente Europske unije. Radi se o postocima koji su prilično komplicirani, koji uključuju prekograničnu suradnju, administrativnu suradnju, suradnju socijalnih tijela, tijela za socijalnu skrb u pojedinim državama članicama koje najčešće nemaju dovoljno razvijene odjele za međunarodnu suradnju. Stoga je za očekivati da se ovakvi problemi, poteškoće događaju i u drugim državama članicama i stoga pozdravljam sve zahtjeve koji su naznačeni u rezoluciji sa ciljem poboljšanja prekogranične pravosudne i upravne suradnje u najboljem interesu djece koja žive u razdvojenim obiteljima.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-276-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the resolution is based on petitions by non—German parents in binational couples, which alerted Parliament to cases of alleged discriminatory, judicial and administrative procedures related to family disputes on parental responsibility and child custody. The Committee on Petitions has received petitions raising similar allegations related to the functioning of social systems in Sweden, Denmark and the UK.</p>
      <p sl="en">Being a parent myself, I cannot even picture the pain that a family goes through when faced with such a dramatic situation. However, as a Member of the European Parliament, I would like to underline the fact that, while family law is the sole competence of Member States, social welfare institutions, courts of law or any other competent public body must put the best interest of the child at the centre of the decision or action that they take. We cannot give those families false hope that we have tools to help bring children back home.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, the European institutions and Member States should promote cross-border cooperation on family matters, providing training for judges and professionals, information on legal aid, and bilingual lawyers, and involving embassies and consular representatives from the start of all childcare proceedings involving their nationals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-277-0000" speaker_id="124900" name="Beata Gosiewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Szanowni Państwo! W imieniu tysięcy pokrzywdzonych polskich rodziców, którym od lat bezprawnie, często pod osłoną nocy lub w wyniku pomówień, odbiera się dzieci i zakazuje się kontaktu z nimi, bo chcą rozmawiać z nimi w ojczystym języku, pytam: kiedy zostaną zlikwidowane pozostające bez centralnego nadzoru urzędy Jugendamt, których niechlubna historia sięga II wojny światowej, i w to miejsce utworzony zostanie nadzorowany centralny urząd wspierający rodziców w wychowywaniu dzieci, a państwa, których obywateli sprawy dotyczą, będą na bieżąco informowane i będą aktywnie uczestniczyć w kontroli przestrzegania praw dzieci? Pan Wojciech Pomorski tak wspomina swój dramat: od porwania córeczek w 2003 r. widziałem je pierwszy raz po dwóch latach pod dozorem przez pięć i pół godziny – już były zgermanizowane – potem po roku, w 2006 r., przez pięć godzin, ostatni raz w 2010 r. przez pięć i pół godziny, też jak zwykle pod nadzorem. Łącznie: 16 godzin w ciągu 15 lat. Zakaz używania języka polskiego uzasadniono tak: nie leży w interesie dzieci, by podczas spotkań nadzorowanych rozmawiano w języku polskim. Gdy to niekonsekwentne postępowanie …</p>
      <a text="(Przewodniczący odebrał mówczyni głos.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-278-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Mamikins, wenn ich jemandem das Wort entziehen musste, weil er die Redezeit überschritten hat, gebe ich grundsätzlich keine Gelegenheit für eine Frage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Spontane Wortmeldungen</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-279-0000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich bin froh, dass dieses Thema hier diskutiert wird. Ich komme aus dem Landkreis Neumarkt in der Oberpfalz in Bayern, war dort auch zwölf Jahre stellvertretender Landrat und bin seit 28 Jahren Abgeordneter. An mein Büro ist nicht ein einziger Fall von Beschwerden bezüglich des Jugendamtes herangetragen worden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deutschland ist ein föderaler Staat, wir haben 16 Bundesländer. Vielleicht gibt es einzelne Bundesländer, wo es gewisse Schwierigkeiten gibt. Aber hier die Jugendämter unter Generalverdacht zu stellen, halte ich für falsch. Es wird in vielen Jugendämtern eine hervorragende Arbeit geleistet. Wenn hier schon Fälle in meinem Kreis da gewesen wären, dann wären die Beschwerden auch sicher bei mir angekommen, und das ist in diesen 28 Jahren nicht einmal der Fall gewesen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mir ist auch bekannt, dass hier bei Verdolmetschungsnotwendigkeit die Dolmetscher auch zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Vielleicht sind sie nicht immer gleich zeitlich erreichbar, aber grundsätzlich stehen die Dolmetscher zur Verfügung, wenn es notwendig ist.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-281-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Honourable Members, thank you very much for this debate. I am aware of a number of complaints which the Committee on Petitions has received and I have tried to find the legal way to get into the problem and to come up with some measures. But I have to fully respect the division of competences stipulated in the primary law.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I said before, family-law matters are highly sensitive, and the EU has very limited legal competence to act in this field, so everybody should act in accordance with the applicable legislation. For the Member States, this is clearly the Charter of Fundamental Rights and the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, which are legally binding on them. They have to ensure that in all actions related to children, the child’s best interests are the primary consideration, and the national courts are best placed to assess the application of the principle of the best interests of the child in individual cases.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding the EU’s competence, I want to clarify once again the EU family law is limited to common rules on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of existing judgments in another Member State. The high sensitivity of family-law matters is also reflected in the requirement for unanimity in the Council for family-law matters. This is also the case for the Brussels 2A Regulation, and I hope we will be able to adopt the revision of this regulation in December.</p>
      <p sl="en">The revision of the Brussels 2A Regulation should make proceedings in cross-border cases easier and quicker. We are indeed considering the best interest of the child. We had to work extremely hard to get all the Member States on board for this process – the revision of the Brussels 2A Regulation – and I do hope that they will all vote for this in December.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me thank you again for the support expressed in the Parliament opinion on the Brussels 2A Regulation. I hope, as I said, that the negotiations on this instrument in the Council will be finalised soon, and the regulation will enable the more efficient handling of cross-border cases.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-282-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet während der nächsten Tagung statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-282-5000" speaker_id="28353" name="Anna Elżbieta Fotyga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Niemiecki urząd do spraw dzieci i młodzieży (Jugendamt) to instytucja założona w 1922 roku w Republice Weimarskiej, której działalność w okresie III Rzeszy zapisała się czarnymi zgłoskami w historii Europy, w tym przede wszystkim Polski. Z uwagi m.in. na wspominane uwarunkowania historyczne, realizacja zadań urzędu także dziś jest kwestią wrażliwą i jest przedmiotem szczególnej troski. Tym bardziej, iż bieżąca praktyka urzędu wiąże się z drastyczną ingerencją w życie rodzin objętych opieką. Pracownik urzędu jest uprawniony do umieszczenia dziecka w pieczy zastępczej na podstawie nieprecyzyjnych przepisów, dających szerokie pole do nadużyć,co wielokrotnie skutkuje odebraniem dzieci rodzicom bez wystarczającego uzasadnienia, bez ścieżki odwoławczej od arbitralnej decyzji. Szczególnie skandaliczny jest zaś fakt, że pracownicy urzędów w jawny sposób dyskryminują osoby innego pochodzenia niż niemieckie. Podczas nadzorowanych spotkań dzieci nie mogą komunikować się z rodzicami w języku innym niż niemiecki. Takie działanie urzędu stoi w sprzeczności z konwencją ONZ o prawach dziecka, w szczególności z art.8, który gwarantuje poszanowanie prawa dziecka "do zachowania jego tożsamości, w tym obywatelstwa, nazwiska, stosunków rodzinnych, zgodnych z prawem, z wyłączeniem bezprawnych ingerencji". Ponadto, działalność Jugendamtów oraz ramy prawne regulujące ich funkcjonowanie, naruszają zapisy szeregu artykułów EKPC. Dlatego oczekuję, iż omawiana w Komisji Petycji sprawa Jugendamtów, będąca także przedmiotem obrad plenarnych, przyczyni się do reformy bulwersującego stanu rzeczy.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem26" title="12. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem27" title="13. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem28" title="14. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="15. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem30" title="16. Dates of forthcoming sittings: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem31" title="17. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem32" title="18. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="4-291-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die Sitzungsperiode des Europäischen Parlaments für unterbrochen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
