<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20180301.EN" lang="en" date="2018-03-01" place="Brussels" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Banking Union - Annual Report 2017 (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-006-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pierwszym punktem porządku dnia jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Sandera Loonesa w imieniu Komisji Gospodarczej i Monetarnej w sprawie unii bankowej – sprawozdanie roczne za rok 2017 (2017/2072(INI)) (A8-0019/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-007-0000" speaker_id="128717" name="Sander Loones" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Dank u wel, mijnheer de Voorzitter. Het is vroeg in de ochtend. Ik ben een goede slaper, op dat vlak heb ik geluk. Ik slaap redelijk gemakkelijk, maar er zijn mensen die minder goed slapen, die zich zorgen maken 's nachts omdat ze zich onzeker voelen, onder andere over hun toekomst, en die zich afvragen of hun spaargeld veilig is. Het is onze taak om die zorgen serieus te nemen, om die aan te pakken, en om die, waar nodig, ook te remediëren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mensen zijn immers nog niet vergeten welke diepe wonden de eurocrisis heeft geslagen, hoe hun spaargeld in gevaar is gekomen. We hebben toen allemaal gezegd: dit mag nooit meer gebeuren. Dat is de vraag die we vandaag behandelen in dit verslag. Hebben wij woord gehouden? Zal dit nooit meer gebeuren? Hebben wij regels uitgewerkt die ons bankensysteem robuuster hebben gemaakt, steviger hebben gemaakt wanneer banken failliet gaan?</p>
      <p sl="en">Laten we beginnen met het eerlijke antwoord: ja, dat hebben wij gedaan. Het systeem ís steviger en robuuster geworden, omdat we bij en na die financiële crisis ook de eerlijke en juiste analyse hebben gemaakt die luidde dat er te weinig regels waren, waardoor bankiers te grote risico's konden opbouwen. Dat hebben we aangepakt. We hebben meer regels op tafel gelegd en ingevoerd.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ten tweede hebben we ook de logica omgedraaid. Vroeger was het zo dat grote aandeelhouders, grote obligatiehouders van banken, met de winsten gingen lopen wanneer het goed ging, maar de verliezen doorschoven naar de belastingbetaler wanneer het fout ging. Die logica hebben wij omgekeerd.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wat dit verslag bijzonder maakt, is dat wij niet alleen de regels gezien hebben, maar dat we ook de toepassing van de regels gezien hebben, voor de eerste keer in de Europese Unie en een aantal verschillende landen, met wisselend succes. We hebben dit weekend nog gezien wat er in Letland is gebeurd, maar vorig jaar hebben we vooral de cases gezien in Spanje en Italië, waar de geest van de regels in het ene geval al wat meer is gerespecteerd dan in het andere geval. Ik denk dat we bijvoorbeeld in Italië een wat creatievere interpretatie gezien hebben van de bankenregels. Ik denk dat net dát, collega's, de Europese ziekte is. We hebben eigenlijk betere regels, maar we passen ze niet altijd toe. We zorgen ervoor dat er extra maatregelen worden genomen, maar als er achterpoortjes zijn, dan zijn die toch niet helemaal gesloten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik denk dat we daarmee zouden moeten starten, met eens eindelijk te doen wat we hebben afgesproken. Dat we de regels die op tafel liggen ook effectief zouden toepassen. Maar neen, dan zie je dat hier in het Europese debat zowat het idee circuleert dat je problemen per definitie het makkelijkst oplost door ze te gaan solidariseren, door ze te gaan spreiden. Ik ben papa van drie jonge kindjes. Wanneer onze dochter Suzanne iets fout doet, dan spreek ik haar daarop aan, en dan moet zij daarvoor boeten. Wanneer ik mijn kindjes niet op z'n Vlaams zou opvoeden maar op z'n Europees, dan zou ik niet alleen haar moeten aanspreken, maar ook haar broertjes, Tuur en Cas, terwijl die eigenlijk niets verkeerd hebben gedaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dat is zo'n beetje de logica die je ook ziet in het bankensysteem, dat we solidair moeten zijn, dat lidstaten die niets fout hebben gedaan per definitie toch gevraagd worden om solidair te zijn met lidstaten die wel in de fout gaan. Ik denk dat dat niet juist is. Ik denk dat we eerst moeten vragen dat die lidstaten verantwoordelijkheid opnemen om de rekeningen op orde te zetten vooraleer we zaken gaan solidariseren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dat is ook de reden waarom ik in alle eerlijkheid soms wat nerveus word wanneer ik dossiers zie die op de Europese tafel liggen, bijvoorbeeld het Europese deposito- en garantiefonds. Vandaag zijn er nationale fondsen die bevoegd zijn om een regeling te treffen wanneer het spaargeld van mensen tot 100 000 euro in gevaar zou kunnen komen. Europa, de Europese Commissie in het bijzonder, zegt nu dat die nationale potjes te klein zijn, dat we ze zouden moeten vervangen door één grote Europese pot, waardoor banken en spaarders hier in Noord-Europa garant zouden komen te staan voor spaarders in Zuid-Europa. Ik denk dat we hiermee toch moeten oppassen. Ik vind het een goed systeem als wij risico's solidariseren, maar wel op voorwaarde dat de lidstaten eerst zelf hun risico's inperken. Op dat vlak is er toch best nog wel wat werk te doen, in Zuid-Europa in het bijzonder.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-008-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank Mr Loones for his annual report on the Banking Union. It has provided us with an excellent account of how much has so far been achieved since the last financial crisis and of what remains to be done in the future.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you know, the completion of the Banking Union is one of the Commission’s highest priorities and we very much welcome the attention and engagement Parliament shows in its annual report for 2017. Major steps have been taken towards Banking Union and results have been achieved since the same debate took place last year, but we agree that we are not done yet.</p>
      <p sl="en">First, regarding the banking sector, good progress has been made in the negotiations on the November 2016 banking package, which will strengthen the prudential framework and increase banks’ ability to absorb losses in times of crisis – without the help of taxpayers’ money. EU banks are significantly stronger than they were before the crisis, thanks to their own efforts to adjust their business models and also thanks to the regulatory reforms we introduced and to better supervision. However, non-performing-loan ratios remain high in some Member States. To address this, the Commission – as announced in the First Progress Report on the Reduction of Non-Performing Loans in Europe, in January 2018 – will adopt a comprehensive package tackling non-performing loans this spring.</p>
      <p sl="en">The package will focus on requiring banks to put aside sufficient means to cover losses if new loans become non-performing; tackling delays in debt recovery; opening up secondary markets; and, lastly, clarifying with a blueprint how EU countries can set up national asset-management companies if they so decide.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bank exposure to sovereigns is another area where the Commission shares Parliament’s view: this problem has multiple implications, including the financial stability and international dimension.</p>
      <p sl="en">Regarding financial technology (fintech), the Commission fully agrees with the need to ensure a level playing field for all market participants, based on the ‘same activity, same rule’ principle. In line with Parliament’s call, the Commission will adopt on 7 March a communication on fintech, in the form of an Action Plan, which will also include a number of initiatives to strengthen the cyber resilience of the EU financial sector.</p>
      <p sl="en">Coming to my second point, on the institutional setting of Banking Union, this is an area where more needs to be done. Recent experience will help to improve further the practical application of the rules, as well as coordination among the Commission, the Single Resolution Board, the Single Supervisory Mechanism and the European Banking Authority.</p>
      <p sl="en">Overall, the two pillars of Banking Union (supervision and resolution) are working well and, as numbers demonstrate, have helped further to reduce risks in the banking sector. But for Banking Union to deliver its full potential it must be complete. For this reason, the Commission welcomes the report’s call to complete the Banking Union with common deposit insurance arrangements, and we are committed to working with Parliament and the Council to advance rapidly on the European Deposit Insurance Scheme. Quick progress is also needed to build up a readily available common backstop for a single resolution fund, in order to increase its credibility.</p>
      <p sl="en">These are just some of the areas highlighted in your report, and we are looking forward to pursuing work in these areas with you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-009-0000" speaker_id="96779" name="Danuta Maria Hübner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, dear colleagues, I think it is very good that the Banking Union Report has been successfully established as one of the routine exercises of the European Parliament. This time around, on many issues related to the functioning of the Banking Union, we have had the opportunity to express ourselves for the first time. I am thinking here of the actions undertaken by the European Institutions to fight non-performing loans or the recent bank resolution cases.</p>
      <p sl="en">But this year we also have a chance to move forward on legislation. We have received from the Commission a proposal for a fiscal backstop for the Single Resolution Fund. We have also the Commission communication on the Banking Union that, among others, intends to relaunch the discussion on the European Deposit Insurance Scheme (EDIS), the missing pillar of the Banking Union, and to test a new approach to the design of the system. And of course, the Banking Package is still under discussion. But this is also the moment for those Member States that do not share a common currency yet to consider joining the Banking Union as soon as possible. It is a shock-absorption mechanism and also comes with governance arrangements that help deal with home host issues. The benefits of belonging to such a system would be particularly pronounced in Central Europe, where Member States are host countries, hosting a huge number of branches and subsidiaries of institutions that actually come from the Banking Union area. Also, at a time of questions on the future of the Union and the risks of increased fragmentation, a broad membership of the Banking Union would be a way of containing supervisory divergence and fragmentation and of involving all Member States in a common project that fosters resilience and financial stability.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-010-0000" speaker_id="124776" name="Mady Delvaux" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, je voudrais féliciter Sander Loones et le remercier et saluer les rapporteurs fictifs pour leur bonne coopération. Il est incontestable que des progrès ont été accomplis: le système bancaire européen est plus robuste qu’il ne l’était, mais il serait illusoire de penser qu’il est à l’abri d’une prochaine crise tant que l’union bancaire n’est pas complète.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le troisième pilier, pourtant indispensable, n’est pas en place. La première application du régime de résolution soulève bien des interrogations. Il sera nécessaire de faire toute la transparence et de tirer les conclusions pour l’améliorer. Et je ne parle pas de la sous-capitalisation de certaines banques, des créances douteuses, de la dette souveraine, du partage de risques insuffisant et de la nécessité d’une meilleure coordination entre autorités, sans oublier les défis que constituent les cyberattaques, qui exigent une attention accrue et des investissements importants dans la sécurité.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-011-0000" speaker_id="124820" name="Bernd Lucke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ECR-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, meine Damen und Herren! Auch mein Dank gilt dem Berichterstatter für einen wirklich vorzüglichen Bericht zur Bankenunion, der, glaube ich, in diesem Hause zum Teil falsch gelesen wird – jedenfalls was EDIS betrifft. Er hat eine ganz andere Sprache als frühere Berichte zur Bankenunion. Es wird eben nicht EDIS gefordert, Herr Kommissar, wie Sie es gerade falsch gesagt haben, sondern es wird ganz klar gemacht, dass die Bankenunion in ihren bestehenden beiden Säulen wichtige Aufgaben erfüllt, dass wir aber gleichzeitig im Bereich der Einlagensicherung durchaus Mechanismen haben, die bereits sehr vernünftig gestaltet sind, in dem Sinne nämlich, dass wir die Einlagensicherungsrichtlinie haben, die es ermöglicht, dass nationale Einlagensicherungssysteme in Krisen Kredite an bedrängte andere Einlagensicherungssysteme geben, aber sie nicht dazu verpflichtet. Mit diesem Design ist die Bankenunion komplett.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist völlig falsch, ständig zu behaupten, dass wir sie noch komplettieren müssten. Es ist geradezu gefährlich, wenn wir nationale Einlagensicherungssysteme dazu verpflichten würden, in Krisensituationen einen Ressourcenabfluss hinzunehmen, weil gerade das in den helfenden Einlagensicherungssystemen zu einem bank run führen könnte, zu einem Vertrauensverlust führen könnte, der die Sparer dazu bewegt, ihre Einlagen abzuziehen. Das Einlagensicherungssystem EDIS, könnte also zusätzliche Risiken erzeugen, und deshalb ist es ein falscher Schritt, in diese Richtung weiter voranzuschreiten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-012-0000" speaker_id="4338" name="Thierry Cornillet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ALDE. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le rapporteur, Monsieur le Vice-Président, l’union bancaire est une jeune mais une très bonne invention. Il est utile d’en rappeler les objectifs fondamentaux: garantir la solidité des banques et leur capacité à résister à des crises futures, éviter le recours à l’argent du contribuable lorsque ces banques sont en difficulté, harmoniser les règles et, dernier objectif mais non des moindres, renforcer la stabilité financière de la zone euro et, par voie de conséquence, celle de l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">La mise en place du mécanisme de surveillance unique et du mécanisme de résolution unique est récente, elle est donc perfectible. Il y a notamment des marges de progression en matière de transparence, de prévisibilité ou de lisibilité des décisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le troisième pilier de cette union bancaire, c’est le système européen d’assurance des dépôts. Le travail sur celui-ci est nécessaire, même s’il faut prendre le temps d’y réfléchir. Il est utile d’arriver à un système qui incite les banques à la vertu – le rapporteur l’a rappelé tout à l’heure – et garantisse la stabilité du système au bénéfice de tous.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je rappelle aussi que l’union bancaire est ouverte même à ceux qui n’ont pas encore l’euro comme monnaie. Certains membres qui ne font pas encore partie de la zone euro hésitent, je n’hésite pas à leur dire: venez, vous êtes les bienvenus pour participer activement au renforcement de la stabilité financière et donc, par voie de conséquence, de la stabilité de l’Union européenne toute entière.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-013-0000" speaker_id="124972" name="Ernest Urtasun" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the ‘too big to fail’ problem of the European banks remains unchanged. Our banking system has not changed as much as the crisis showed it was needed. On the contrary, we are in a period of regulatory rollback at international and EU level, lowering standards in financial regulation. In this context, the Greens strongly support decisive steps towards risk reduction that should go hand-in-hand with risk-sharing, and we see with concern that this is actually not happening. 2017 was the year when we saw obstacles to resolvability of the Venetian banks and the first resolution under the EU framework, the popular case which shows that further transparency is clearly needed.</p>
      <p sl="en">We would like to thank Mr Loones for the good work, because the Annual Report on the Banking Union addresses some of our concerns: concerns with resolvability and with mis-selling; good wording on EDIS, which we believe are very important; concerns that our Group has traditionally had with shadow banking, for instance. We believe that this is a good report and we would like to thank the shadow rapporteurs for their cooperation and we will vote in favour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-014-0000" speaker_id="124778" name="Marco Valli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ci tenevo anch'io a ringraziare il relatore Loones perché ha fatto un discreto lavoro. Per noi, purtroppo, rimangono dei punti molto difficili da accettare, in generale sull'unione bancaria, a partire dal primo pilastro sulla vigilanza: ci sono evidenti lacune di vigilanza da parte del sistema di supervisione bancaria e la Commissione dovrebbe porvi rimedio. Parlo degli asset di secondo e terzo livello, i derivati, che sono un mercato pari a quasi 12 volte gli NPL – si parla di 6 800 miliardi, arriviamo a 453 miliardi di nozionali.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Commissione secondo me dovrebbe fare un esame di coscienza e capire se il problema sono solo gli NPL, e quindi il credito, e non invece aggredire anche quello che è un problema sistemico, ovvero quello legato al mercato degli asset level 2 and level 3, perché lì sono gli interessi delle grandi banche d'affari e c'è il vero rischio sistemico.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda il secondo pilastro, la risoluzione, abbiamo visto che il bail in porta i risparmiatori e la fiducia nel sistema finanziario a essere poco credibili. Quindi bisognerebbe creare anche un sistema di garanzia di tutti i depositi, in modo tale che i risparmiatori siano e si sentano veramente tutelati, cosa che l'unione bancaria oggi non sta riuscendo a fare, e quindi c'è bisogno di questo. In più, bisogna smetterla di andare a parare sulle conseguenze delle crisi bancarie, ma andare a parare sulle cause. L'unico modo è applicare una vera e reale separazione bancaria riaprendo il progetto di BSR, ovvero banking structural reform, che si è appunto dimenticato e andrebbe invece ripreso.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-015-0000" speaker_id="125024" name="Barbara Kappel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ENF-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, Herr Vizepräsident der Kommission! Aufsicht und Abwicklung sind heute die zwei tragenden Säulen der Bankenunion. Der Berichterstatter hat das im Bericht sehr gut herausgearbeitet. Die dritte Säule – die Einlagensicherung – wird kontrovers diskutiert; wir haben das heute im Rahmen dieser Diskussion hier schon miterleben dürfen. Aber es gibt große Mitgliedstaaten, die durchaus der Meinung sind, dass ein systemischer Abbau hoher Risiken in den Bankbilanzen der EU-Institute zu erfolgen habe, bevor es zu einer gemeinsamen Einlagensicherung kommt – also Risikoreduzierung vor Risikoteilung. Ich würde mich dieser Forderung anschließen wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Während eine Einigung bei der Einlagensicherung doch in weiter Ferne ist, sollte die Bankenaufsicht funktionieren. Wenn ich jetzt den Fall der drittgrößten lettischen Bank, der ABLV, anführe, die nach bestandenem Stresstest nach massiven Geldwäschevorwürfen vor dem Zusammenbruch steht und ein Fall für die Bankenabwicklung ist, so stärkt das das Vertrauen in die Aufsicht nicht. Auch dass dieser Fall nicht durch die Bankenaufsicht der EZB aufgedeckt wurde, sondern durch die amerikanischen Finanzbehörden, stärkt das Vertrauen nicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Bankenunion hat den Finanzsektor zweifellos sicherer gemacht. Das wird auch durch den letzten Fortschrittsbericht der Kommission über den NPL-Abbau deutlich. Der Kommissar hat es angeführt. Die Quoten sind noch unterschiedlich, aber vielleicht sollte man einen Vorschlag des Berichterstatters annehmen und den Stresstests der Bankenaufsicht konsistentere Maßnahmen folgen lassen, damit so ein Fall wie Lettland zukünftig nicht mehr passiert.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-016-0000" speaker_id="125100" name="Miguel Viegas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, durante o ano de 2017, mais uma vez, os contribuintes foram forçados a pagar o resgate da banca italiana, com uma entrada massiva de 17 mil milhões de dinheiros públicos. Este dinheiro retirado diretamente do bolso dos trabalhadores serviu para salvar dois bancos falidos e proteger os seus obrigacionistas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em Portugal, o dinheiro dos contribuintes continua a pagar as resoluções do BPN, do Banif e do Banco Espírito Santo. Assistimos, igualmente, a uma vaga de fusões e à criação de gigantescos grupos financeiros, todos eles controlados por grupos estrangeiros, ou seja, tudo ao contrário do que foi anunciado pela União Bancária, que foi criada para acabar com os bancos demasiado grandes para falir e acabar com o regabofe de fundos públicos para pagar as favas da especulação e da irresponsabilidade financeira.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para o PCP, a União Bancária foi desenhada para reforçar o papel da finança e retirar aos Estados nacionais qualquer capacidade de intervir no sistema financeiro. Sabemos, hoje, que a supervisão é uma farsa e que a resolução não é credível. A nossa proposta é muito clara: só um controlo público da banca poderá colocar o sistema financeiro ao serviço da economia e do desenvolvimento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-017-0000" speaker_id="38398" name="Esther de Lange" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dank u wel, mijnheer de Voorzitter. Ik zou allereerst in onze gedeelde taal Sander Loones als rapporteur willen bedanken voor zijn verslag.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will turn to English as I have put away my prepared short intervention, and I would like to take up some words that we heard from the Commissioner, which are of course well appreciated. He mentioned that the two pillars of the Banking Union are working well – and they are, but not fully. I do think that the situation that has come to light, for example in Latvia – brought to our attention by the US rather than European supervision – shows that there are also still some blind spots in the first and second pillars. I am not mentioning this to be difficult; I am mentioning this because I know it makes the work on the third pillar more difficult. You have heard from colleagues how controversial the European Deposit Insurance Scheme (EDIS) proposal is. There is a will to progress, I think, among many in this House, and I welcome in that regard the Commission Communication that we saw at the end of last year, and also the words of the Commission on the initiatives that we can expect on non-performing loans (NPLs) and exposure to sovereigns. I think these are key, especially if at some point we want to move EDIS beyond liquidity support only. But I believe that progress, especially in these two fields, needs to be measurable, proven and concrete, not only on the flow, but also on the stocks, of NPLs. So there is quite a lot of work ahead of us. The spirit is positive and I thank the Commission for that, but it will, I am afraid, take time.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-019-0000" speaker_id="2278" name="Paul Rübig" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Meine Frage geht in die Richtung der Risikoreduzierung. Wir wissen ja, dass es bei großen Ausfällen bis jetzt üblich ist, dass der Staat einpringt. Bei kleinen Betrieben wird eigentlich relativ schnell und sofort exekutiert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Glauben Sie, dass die Risikoreduzierung vor allem auch die kleinen und mittleren Betriebe unterstützen sollte, damit sie in der Liquidität bessere Möglichkeiten haben, dementsprechend ihre Geschäftsmodelle durchzuführen?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-020-0000" speaker_id="38398" name="Esther de Lange" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – It is always a pleasure to get a blue card from your own Group. Without going into the detail of the EDIS proposal and the implications for certain Member States and smaller banks, what is clear is that the resolution cases that we have seen taking place in Europe have not all followed the ideal model that we foresaw when we put the legislation into place. That just proves my point that there are still some blind spots in the way that the legislation was meant to be. But I can reassure, in some regards, the colleague from Austria that we are, of course – also in working on the EDIS proposal – aware that the legislation that we make should suit big banks, but also the smaller ones and the particular cases that we have seen in the case of Einlagensicherung in Germany and in Austria.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-021-0000" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, l’union bancaire est le parapluie du concept de réduction des risques, de partage des risques. J’ai parfois l’impression que, dans la balance, on déséquilibre les choses et qu’on oublie d’évaluer l’ensemble des efforts qui ont déjà été faits en matière de réduction des risques, y compris dans la façon dont l’Union européenne va intégrer les nouveaux concepts internationaux pour lui permettre de respecter ses engagements, s’agissant de l’absorption des pertes – le fameux TLAC – ou encore d’abaisser la valeur domestique des prêts non performants (NPL), sur lesquels nous attendons de nouvelles propositions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais ce rapport annuel, aujourd’hui, est un point de rendez-vous qui nous permet peut-être d’identifier trois domaines dans lesquels davantage doit être fait.</p>
      <p sl="en">D’abord, on l’a dit ici, les piliers manquants. Au fond, j’en identifie deux, bien sûr, et dix sur lesquels aucune proposition valable ne pourra être faite si on n’avance pas en parallèle sur la question de la liquidité et sur la question de l’absorption des pertes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais il y a aussi ce fameux «dispositif de soutien budgétaire» sur lequel des progrès pourraient être faits avec la transformation du Mécanisme européen de stabilité, mais nous vous invitons à être vigilants pour que cela se fasse selon la méthode communautaire, bien évidemment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et puis, il y a la question du lien entre les souverains bancaires et les États. Nous pensons que l’union bancaire doit nous permettre de faire jouer ces fameuses dérogations qui permettent de se servir des bénéfices acquis du fait de l’existence de l’union bancaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, un troisième chantier s’ouvre à nous à la suite du cas letton et de la chute de la banque ABLV, qui nous indiquent à quel point on ne pourra pas avoir une union bancaire sûre et stable si on ne regarde pas la dimension fiscale et notamment l’impact de la lutte contre le blanchiment d’argent sur la stabilité et le caractère systémique des banques.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-022-0000" speaker_id="96730" name="Sven Giegold" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir haben nach Jahren der Finanzmarktreform eine absurde Situation. Einige Großbanken sind nach wie vor mit Verschuldungsquoten von lediglich 4 % an ihrer Bilanzsumme im Markt unterwegs,während auf der anderen Seite – ich habe mir das in meinem Wahlkreis mehrfach angeschaut – kleinere Institute, die mit einer Verschuldungsquote von 8 – 10 % bestens dastehen, überschüttet werden mit Meldeanforderungen der Zentralbank, national wie europäisch, der Aufseher, national wie europäisch, der Europäischen Bankenaufsichtsbehörde und auch noch der nationalen Statistikbehörden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diese Meldeanforderungen sind im Verhältnis zum Ziel der Finanzmarktstabilität völlig disproportional. Deshalb ist es richtig, dass wir hier fordern, dass es ein einheitliches europäisches Meldewesen gibt, das dafür sorgt, dass auch kleinere Finanzmarktakteure nach den Finanzmarktreformen überleben können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bitte Sie, Herr Kommissar, helfen Sie uns in der aktuellen Gesetzgebung, ein solches umfangreiches europäisches einheitliches Meldewesen auf den Weg zu bringen, damit der bürokratische Aufwand sinkt und wir gleichzeitig die Ziele der Finanzmarktstabilität erreichen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-023-0000" speaker_id="190518" name="Jörg Meuthen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, verehrte Kollegen! Wir reden heute über die Bankenunion. Die deutsche Bundesregierung hat im Jahr 2012 eine Bankenaufsicht durch die EZB gefordert; das hielt man damals für einen cleveren Schachzug. Heute muss man sagen, dass die Bundesregierung auf ganzer Linie gescheitert ist. Die Bankenunion wird zunehmend zur Transferunion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Bericht fordert eine Letztsicherung der Bankenabwicklung durch den Fiskus. Er behauptet frech, dass dies einen Rückgriff auf Staatsgelder vermeide. Meine Damen und Herren, Sie müssen mir erklären, wie man etwas fiskalisch absichern kann, ohne den Fiskus zu belasten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Bericht fordert auch, den ESM in einen europäischen Währungsfonds zu verwandeln, der diese fiskalische Absicherung übernimmt. Meine Damen und Herren, ich lade Sie ein, meinem Änderungsantrag zuzustimmen und dies abzulehnen. Es ist Zeit, Farbe zu bekennen – gegen Bankenrettung auf Steuerzahlerkosten, gegen eine europäische Einlagenversicherung und gegen den Ausbau der Bankenunion zur Transferunion.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-024-0000" speaker_id="39721" name="Theodor Dumitru Stolojan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, uniunea bancară este domeniul în care am progresat destul de mult și Comisia Europeană merită felicitări pentru persistență în acest domeniu. Sunt sigur că vom găsi o soluție rațională și pentru garantarea depozitelor bancare ale oamenilor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ceea ce este însă îngrijorător este modul în care se aplică reglementările bancare de către unele bănci europene. Este deranjant să aflăm din Statele Unite ale Americii despre cazuri de spălare a banilor prin bănci europene și să nu aflăm acest lucru din sistemul bancar al Uniunii Europene, pe care l-am creat. Să nu uităm că un miliard de dolari a dispărut din Republica Moldova prin bănci europene, fără ca noi, aici, în Uniunea Europeană, să acordăm atenție și să clarificăm și asemenea cazuri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-025-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Othmar Karas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Herr Vizepräsident, meine Damen und Herren! Herzlichen Dank für diesen Bericht, der uns zeigt, dass wir in der Bankenunion viele Schritte nach vorne gemacht haben, aber gleichzeitig auch noch nicht fertig sind. Wir haben die erste Säule der gemeinsamen Aufsicht geschaffen, müssen aber Größe und Komplexität der Institute künftig angemessener berücksichtigen. Wir haben den Bestand an faulen Krediten seit Mitte 2014 um ein Drittel reduziert, aber wir müssen weitere Maßnahmen ergreifen, da der Bestand mit 950 Milliarden Euro noch immer über dem Vorkrisenniveau liegt. Wir haben die zweite Säule der gemeinsamen Abwicklung geschaffen, aber wir müssen bestehende Inkonsistenzen zwischen staatlichen Beihilferegeln und EU-Recht beseitigen. Wir haben die Abwicklungsregeln das erste Mal angewendet, aber wir müssen die Beschlussfassung darüber, ob eine Bank ausfällt oder wahrscheinlich ausfallen wird, verbessern. Und wir haben den Einlagenschutz in Europa gestärkt. Aber wir haben die Arbeiten an der dritten Säule, einer gemeinsamen Absicherung, noch nicht abgeschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich erwarte mir vom Rat, dass Sie EDIS jetzt in Gang setzen, dass Sie den Zeitplan für Risikoreduzierung und Risikoteilung klar festlegen. Es geht nicht mehr um das Ob, es geht nur mehr um das Wie. Bauen wir das Haus der Bankenunion in dieser Legislaturperiode fertig!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-027-0000" speaker_id="1922" name="Thomas Mann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Durch die Europäische Bankenunion wurden der institutionelle und der regulatorische Rahmen seit der Wirtschaftskrise wesentlich gestärkt. Die Eigenkapitalquoten und die Liquiditätsquoten der Banken im Euro-Raum haben sich eindeutig verbessert. Aber in einigen Mitgliedstaaten ist der Anteil an Problemkrediten viel zu hoch. Die Risiken innerhalb bestimmter nationaler Bankensysteme werden nur unzureichend angegangen. Dabei tragen die Mitgliedstaaten und die Banken selbst die primäre Verantwortung für den Abbau von faulen Krediten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei allen aufsichtsrechtlichen Anforderungen dürfen die Kosten der Banken nicht über die Maßen wachsen, mit erheblichen Auswirkungen auf die Finanzierungsmodelle für kleine und mittelständische Unternehmen. Der Grundsatz der Proportionalität muss erhalten bleiben. Allerdings sind Erleichterungen für Banken mit einfachen Geschäftsmodellen notwendig. Die Vielfalt unserer europäischen Banken ist nach wie vor eine stabile Basis für die Konkurrenzfähigkeit unserer Finanzsysteme im globalen Maßstab.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-028-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, raportul este binevenit. Vreau să-l felicit pe raportor și vreau să mă refer la un lucru pe care l-a spus raportorul. Sigur, criza financiară se resimte și acum. Să ne punem întrebarea dacă băncile își asumă riscuri prea mari sau riscuri prea mici. Dar vorbea raportorul și de câștiguri mari în sistemul bancar și de bonusuri și de tot felul de premii. Băncile nu își asumă riscuri pentru IMM-uri. IMM-urile încă nu pot să ia credite și sunt decapitalizate. Din păcate, băncile își asumă riscuri dând asemenea venituri angajaților, peste medie, în sistemul bancar fiind câștigurile cele mai mari.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu cred că trebuie, domnule comisar, (sigur, s-au făcut progrese), să se întâmple ceea ce ați spus. Nu este suficient să avem aici reglementări, este foarte important să se și aplice. Cum garantăm depozitele? Există un mare decalaj în unele bănci între cât costă un credit și cât se dă dobândă la un depozit. Și nu sunt garantate, într-adevăr, pentru cetățeni. Noi trebuie să protejăm, și eu, în calitate de membră a comisiei IMCO, mă gândesc cum protejăm consumatorii, IMM-urile, cum protejăm cetățenii. Deci aici trebuie să progresăm, pentru că altfel batem pasul pe loc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-029-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Serdeczna prośba o przestrzeganie reżimu czasowego. Musimy rozpatrzyć cztery projekty i o godz. 11.30 przystąpić do głosowań.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-030-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, λόγω της οικονομικής κρίσης, τρισεκατομμύρια EUR Δημοσίου χρήματος διατέθηκαν για τη διάσωση των τραπεζών, επιβαρύνοντας το δημόσιο χρέος των κρατών κι όλα αυτά τη στιγμή που τα κεφάλαια που διατέθηκαν για την αντιμετώπιση της ανεργίας ήταν ελάχιστα. Στην Ελλάδα έγιναν τρεις ανακεφαλαιοποιήσεις τραπεζών που αύξησαν το δημόσιο χρέος και κοινωνικοποίησαν τις ζημιές των τραπεζών, μια και διέσωσαν τους μετόχους των τραπεζών, πολλοί από τους οποίους ήταν ξένοι μέτοχοι. Μάλιστα, με το τρίτο μνημόνιο πωλήθηκαν ξανά οι τράπεζες σε ιδιώτες, αντί πινακίου φακής, με αποτέλεσμα το δημόσιο να ζημιωθεί τουλάχιστον 30 δισεκατομμύρια EUR και, σαν να μην έφτανε αυτό, οι τράπεζες που διασώθηκαν επιτίθενται πλέον κατά των ίδιων των καταθετών, κατά των ίδιων των πολιτών, οι οποίοι τις διέσωσαν, οι οποίοι δυστυχώς έχουν κόκκινα δάνεια και ενεργοποιούν πλέον ηλεκτρονικούς πλειστηριασμούς στην Ελλάδα, με αποτέλεσμα τα κοράκια να αρπάζουν τα σπίτια των Ελλήνων. Είναι απαράδεκτο. Δεν πρέπει να συνεχιστεί αυτή η κατάσταση. Ο ελληνικός λαός δεν θα επιτρέψει να αρπάξουν τα κοράκια τα σπίτια των Ελλήνων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-031-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Δημήτριος Παπαδημούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, χωρίς το ευρωπαϊκό σύστημα εγγύησης καταθέσεων, χωρίς τον τρίτο πυλώνα, δεν υπάρχει τραπεζική ενοποίηση. Δεν είναι θωρακισμένα η ευρωπαϊκή οικονομία και το ευρωπαϊκό σύστημα απέναντι σε μία μελλοντική κρίση. Στο θέμα αυτό, η ολοκλήρωση του τρίτου πυλώνα, που είναι θετικός για τους πολίτες, την ευρωπαϊκή προοπτική, τις μικρομεσαίες επιχειρήσεις, καθυστερεί επικίνδυνα γιατί υπάρχουν ορισμένα κράτη μέλη μέσα στο Συμβούλιο, η Ολλανδία, η Γερμανία, μια μικρή μειοψηφία, αλλά πολύ ισχυρή, που ουσιαστικά βάζει βέτο. Γιατί και μέσα στο Ευρωκοινοβούλιο, υπάρχουν ενστάσεις και αντιρρήσεις από την δεξιά και την άκρα δεξιά πλευρά του πολιτικού φάσματος. Αλλά πρέπει να προχωρήσουμε διότι αυτό είναι το συμφέρον των πολιτών. Έχουν γίνει σημαντικά βήματα στη μείωση του ρίσκου. Πρέπει να γίνουν βήματα και στην αμοιβαιοποίηση του ρίσκου. Η ευρωπαϊκή ενοποίηση δεν μπορεί να είναι «αλά καρτ», πρέπει να προχωρήσει και στο ευρωπαϊκό σύστημα εγγύησης καταθέσεων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-032-0000" speaker_id="125090" name="Σωτήριος Ζαριανόπουλος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε πρόεδρε, οι τελευταίες αποφάσεις του Εurogroup με την υπογραφή της κυβέρνησης ΣΥΡΙΖΑ είναι σαφείς: 11 000 πλειστηριασμοί μόνο για φέτος στην Ελλάδα. Τραπεζική Ένωση δηλαδή σημαίνει περαιτέρω κεφαλαιακή ενίσχυση των τραπεζών, το οποίο στην Ελλάδα σημαίνει τρία μνημόνια, απολύσεις και δραματικές μειώσεις μισθών και συντάξεων δίχως τέλος, ακόμη και μετά την τυπική λήξη του μνημονίου, τώρα πια και με απώλεια της λαϊκής στέγης και της πρώτης κατοικίας, με σκοπό την ανάκτηση τραπεζικών κεφαλαίων, με χιλιάδες ηλεκτρονικούς πλειστηριασμούς και με πωλήσεις δανείων στα κοράκια των Funds με ένα και μοναδικό σκοπό: να χρηματοδοτηθούν οι βιώσιμες (βλέπε μεγάλες) επιχειρήσεις. Μια ακόμα τεράστια κλοπή λαϊκής περιουσίας για το κεφάλαιο. Είναι τόσο πιεστική αυτή η ανάγκη του συστήματος που η λαϊκή αντίσταση στους πλειστηριασμούς τιμωρείται σαν ιδιώνυμο έγκλημα, χτυπιέται με δακρυγόνα και με ΜΑΤ, όπως χθες στην Αθήνα. Η Ελληνική Κυβέρνηση και η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση ας το πάρουν χαμπάρι: ο λαός δεν πρόκειται να κάνει πίσω. Χωρίς όρους προστασία της λαϊκής κατοικίας, όχι στους εκβιασμούς των τραπεζών και του κράτους!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-033-0000" speaker_id="118658" name="Brian Hayes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, congratulations to Mr Loones on his report. I have just three observations to make. Firstly, the last pillar of banking union needs to be done. I agree with Mr Karas that it is how it is done, and I fully back the approach of Esther de Lange when she spoke to the House about the necessity of having risk-sharing and risk reduction at the same time. This has to be done in a phased way. We have made progress, and it remains to be done in terms of the last issue.</p>
      <p sl="en">My second remark is in relation to NPLs. It is really important that we resolve this issue, because without resolving this issue, we will stop lending to the real economy, to households, to SMEs, and the longer we put it off, the longer it takes for real growth and investment to occur in our economies. In my own country, we have a significant problem with NPLs in some of our banks, which have to be resolved. We also need a system which works within a code that the ECB have set, which is fair and equitable while at the same time recognising the necessity to resolve this issue. We do need more progress on insolvency laws across Europe, more judicial guidance, and we also need a code that is in place for all Member States of the eurozone.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-034-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, if you do not maintain order at home, then you should not be surprised if your house is managed by strangers. This fully applies to the European Banking Union. Two weeks ago, the US Financial Crimes Enforcement Network imposed sanctions on ABLV Bank, the third-largest bank in my country, Latvia, by prohibiting it from opening and maintaining a correspondent account in the United States. ABLV was under European Central Bank supervision. Neither the Latvian regulator nor the European Central Bank tried to check the accuracy of the charges. Moreover, after the bank had such difficulties, they helped to push back into the EDIS. The bank was forced to announce self-liquidation. Hundreds of Latvians lost their jobs. Dear colleagues, the authorities of another country can destroy large EU banks by a mere statement of suspicion. Such a situation is unacceptable. The European Union must protect its interests and the interests of European businesses. We need the European Union and European banking as a real thing.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-035-0000" speaker_id="124691" name="Κώστας Μαυρίδης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, θα ήθελα καταρχάς να δώσω τα συγχαρητήριά μου στην εισηγήτρια για την έκθεση. Θα επικεντρωθώ μόνο σε δύο σημεία. Στην έκθεση αυτή καταγράφεται το ζήτημα των μη εξυπηρετούμενων δανείων, το οποίο είναι κυρίως πρόβλημα των τραπεζών αλλά, όπως σημειώνεται στην έκθεση, είναι επίσης ζήτημα πολιτικών των κρατών μελών, αλλά και πολιτικών σε ευρωπαϊκό επίπεδο, ούτως ώστε να αποφύγουμε μια νέα υπερδιόγκωση αυτού του προβλήματος. Τώρα περνώ στο επόμενο ζήτημα που συζητάμε εδώ και καιρό, για την τραπεζική Ένωση. Συνάδελφοι, συμφωνήσαμε πριν πολλά χρόνια την τραπεζική Ένωση με τρεις πυλώνες. Εφαρμόσαμε τους δύο. Η χρονική σειρά εφαρμογής των πυλώνων είχε σκοπό να απαντηθούν εκείνες οι εύλογες ανησυχίες των κρατών μελών που έλεγαν ότι δεν πρέπει να έχουμε υπερβολική μεταφορά κινδύνων. Τώρα προβάλλονται τεχνικοί λόγοι για να μη εφαρμόσουμε την τραπεζική εγγύηση. Προς την Επιτροπή: κύριε Dombrovskis ποιοι είναι οι πραγματικοί λόγοι - και όχι οι τεχνικοί - που εμποδίζουν την εφαρμογή του τρίτου πυλώνα;</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-037-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, let me once again thank Mr Loones for his excellent report and for today’s debate. The debate shows once again that we agree on the importance of the Banking Union in order to ensure a robust and stable financial system where banks are able to play their role of lending to the economy and helping to stimulate further economic growth.</p>
      <p sl="en">To achieve this common goal, we should move from our current positions and make every effort to find solutions that could accommodate all interested stakeholders. As we have emphasised a number of times, we need to move with risk-sharing and risk-reduction hand—in—hand.</p>
      <p sl="en">Several colleagues raised issues relating to the ABLV Bank, and I think it has exposed certain weakness in a banking union. In recent years we have substantially strengthened the EU’s anti-money laundering (AML) framework, whereas the enforcement of this framework remains largely national. So there we must really see what we can do more at European level as regards AML enforcement.</p>
      <p sl="en">As has been said several times, also by the Commission, we need to take advantage of this favourable economic moment to complete the Banking Union. This is the only way to ensure that the overall economic and monetary union is completed as well and is strong enough to cope with a future crisis. We count on your efforts and support to help move this regulatory agenda forwards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-038-0000" speaker_id="128717" name="Sander Loones" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Dank u wel, mijnheer de Voorzitter. Dank u wel aan de collega's, vooral aan de schaduwrapporteurs, voor de fijne samenwerking en voor het interessante debat. Ik denk dat het interessant is dat zowat iedereen die we hier gehoord hebben, zegt: ja, er is veel werk gedaan, goed werk, maar er ligt ook nog werk op de plank. We hebben dus nog wat zaken te doen. In dat opzicht is dit ook een behoorlijk kritisch verslag geworden, met een aantal aanzetten tot de discussies van de toekomst. Als u mij persoonlijk zou vragen waarop nu de focus moet liggen, dan zie ik zelf vier punten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eén: ik denk dat wij onze staatssteunregels meer moeten aanscherpen. Dat hebben we geleerd uit de bankenreddingen in Italië. Twee: we moeten meer werken op het vlak van supervisie. Recent nog hebben we gezien – en er is ook herhaaldelijk naar verwezen in dit debat – wat er in Letland is gebeurd. Drie: we hebben nood aan meer transparantie. Ook op dat vlak ligt er nog bijzonder veel werk op de plank. En ten slotte vier, en dat is toch het belangrijkste: de regels moeten nog scherper worden en mogen niet worden afgezwakt.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dat verband kijk ik toch met meer dan enige belangstelling naar wat bijvoorbeeld in Italië gebeurt. Daar staan er dit weekend verkiezingen op de agenda en zowat elke prominente Italiaanse politicus pleit voor een afzwakking van de bankenregels. Dat is niet de weg die wij moeten opgaan. De richting die wij moeten inslaan, is om eerst te kiezen voor verantwoordelijkheid en dan voor solidariteit. Ik hoor de commissaris ook spreken over risk sharing en risk reduction, risicodeling en risicobeperking. Dat is juist, maar het is tegelijk ook fout. Het zou andersom moeten zijn. In dit Parlement zouden wij eerst moeten praten over risk reduction en dan pas over risk sharing. Eerst praten over verantwoordelijkheid en dan over solidariteit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-039-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się w środę 1 marca 2018 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-039-0002" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – O ano de 2017 viu repetir-se uma história conhecida: mais uma vez, os contribuintes foram forçados a pagar resgates de bancos privados. O resgate da banca italiana envolveu 17 mil milhões de euros de recursos públicos. Este dinheiro, retirado diretamente do bolso dos trabalhadores, serviu para salvar dois bancos falidos e proteger os seus obrigacionistas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em Portugal, o dinheiro dos contribuintes continua a pagar as resoluções do BPN, do Banif ou do BES. Mas a tão propagandeada União Bancária, servida aos povos adocicada com a falsa promessa do fim dos resgates feitos com dinheiro dos contribuintes, significa, na verdade, bem mais do que a continuação desses mesmos resgates. Assistimos igualmente a uma vaga de fusões e ao impulso para a concentração monopolista do sector financeiro à escala europeia, com a criação de gigantescos grupos financeiros, todos eles controlados por grandes grupos, no caso de Portugal todos estrangeiros. Ou seja, tudo ao contrário do que foi anunciado com a União Bancária, supostamente criada para acabar com os bancos «demasiados grandes para falir» e acabar com o regabofe de fundos públicos para pagar as consequências da especulação e da irresponsabilidade financeira.</p>
      <p sl="en">Só um controlo público da banca poderá colocar o sistema financeiro ao serviço da economia e do desenvolvimento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-039-0001" speaker_id="28192" name="Vladimír Maňka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne – Hlavnou úlohou bankovej únie, tvorenej jednotným mechanizmom dohľadu a jednotným mechanizmom riešenia krízových situácií, je zabezpečenie spoľahlivého a bezpečného bankového sektora v Európskej únii. Finančná stabilita v Únii ovplyvňuje celý ekonomický a hospodársky život a má dosah na každý subjekt. Podporujem posilnenie dohľadu nad bankovým sektorom tak, aby v prípade ohrozenia dokázala Únia včas reagovať a flexibilne prijať potrebné opatrenia. Rovnako pokladám za zásadné, aby bolo čo najskôr prijaté nariadenie o európskom fonde na ochranu vkladov, ktorý posilní finančnú stabilitu a zvýši dôveru obyvateľov vo finančný a bankový sektor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-039-5000" speaker_id="98341" name="Eva Maydell" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">With all European economies performing considerably better, 2018 has been the first time since 2012 that we can focus on upgrading our economic structure – to equip the Banking Union and the euro area with all the necessary tools in case of a new crisis. It is now time for the economies of the countries of the community to be supported with adequate tools to increase their resilience to future shocks. We want banks to act responsibly and our responsibility as policymaker is to help them by completing the Banking Union. We must not get complacent and rely on good economic times lasting forever. Reaching an agreement on a common financial backstop for the SRF, adopting the financial instruments for reforms and meeting the conditions to set up a European deposit insurance scheme must be top priorities for the EU and finalised before the end of the legislative term of EC and EP. It must be clear that the Banking Union is not an end in itself for the regulators. It is a condition to ensure that taxpayers money is not first in line to pay for banking shocks.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-040-0000" speaker_id="132366" name="Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – Pankkiunionin vuosikertomuksessa käsitellään Euroopan talous- ja rahaliiton EMU:n loppuunsaattamista. Käytännössä kyse on talous- ja rahaliiton syventämisestä kohti suurempaa yhteisvastuuta pankkien veloista ja vastuista, mitä en voi kannattaa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yhteisvastuun laajentamiseen kuuluu myös koko euroalueen kattava talletussuojajärjestelmä. Pankkien ongelmien taso vaihtelee suuresti eri maiden välillä, eivätkä vuosikertomuksessa esitetyt keskimääräiset luvut kerro paljoakaan kokonaistilanteesta. Monissa maissa, kuten Italiassa, pankkisektorilla muhii valtavia riskejä.</p>
      <p sl="en">Periaatteessa pankkiunionissa on siirrytty pankkien pelastamiseen omistajien rahoilla. Käytännössä vuonna 2017 esiin tulleet tapaukset kuitenkin osoittavat, ettei pankkien pelastamisesta veronmaksajien rahoilla ole päästy eroon. Ongelmaluotot tulee selvittää perusteellisesti ja pankkien taseet siivota, ennen kuin voidaan edes keskustella siirtymisestä yhteiseen talletussuojajärjestelmään. Ilman näitä toimenpiteitä puheet veronmaksajien rahojen suojelemisesta ovat tyhjiä lupauksia.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Mandatory automatic exchange of information in the field of taxation (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-042-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dnia jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Emmanuela Maurela w imieniu Komisji Gospodarczej i Monetarnej w sprawie wniosku dotyczącego dyrektywy Rady zmieniającej dyrektywę 2011/16/UE w zakresie obowiązkowej automatycznej wymiany informacji w dziedzinie opodatkowania w odniesieniu do raportowanych uzgodnień transgranicznych (COM(2017)0335 – C8-0195/2017 – 2017/0138(CNS)) (A8-0016/2018).</p>
      <p sl="en">W tym momencie napotykamy na pewien proceduralny problem – nie ma pana komisarza Moscovici. Sprawdzałem, to nie my przyspieszyliśmy nasz harmonogram czasowy debaty, to raczej pan komisarz się lekko spóźnia. Czy będzie zgoda, żebyśmy rozpoczęli naszą debatę od wystąpienia pana posła sprawozdawcy z nadzieją, że komisarz przyjdzie?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-043-0000" speaker_id="24505" name="Emmanuel Maurel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, depuis les dernières élections européennes, nous sommes quelques-uns dans cet hémicycle à nous être consacrés à la lutte contre l’évasion fiscale. Il faut reconnaître que ce n’est pas facile, puisque, en quatre ans, nous avons vu quand même beaucoup de scandales, beaucoup de révélations et nous avons parfois le sentiment que notre travail, nos propositions, tout ce que nous essayons de faire avec la Commission ne nous permettent pas d’avancer très rapidement. Et c’est la vérité, malheureusement. Mais c’est aussi la raison pour laquelle, dès que nous avons des petites victoires, nous devons y puiser un peu de courage, un peu d’énergie et, avec ce texte, c’est une petite victoire – victoire certes modeste, mais une victoire quand même et il faut l’acter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Une victoire d’abord sur la délinquance en col blanc, les fraudeurs, les planificateurs professionnels de la fuite des profits et ceux évidemment qui les aident, c’est-à-dire les intermédiaires. Il existe – vous le savez ici, chers collègues – une véritable industrie de l’optimisation fiscale, avec des sociétés discrètes, et nous demandons à ce qu’elles rendent des comptes sur les montages qu’elles conçoivent, qu’elles conseillent, qu’elles commercialisent. Avec cette réforme dite d’ACCIS, tous les montages qui ne rempliront ne serait-ce qu’un seul critère possible d’optimisation fiscale agressive devront être rapportés au fisc, sous peine de sanctions.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est aussi une victoire sur la concurrence navrante – la concurrence fiscale – que se livrent parfois hélas les États membres. Toutes les informations collectées seront obligatoirement et automatiquement échangées entre les États membres de l’Union européenne. Tout progrès dans ce domaine est bon à prendre, car nous le savons, les États se livrent à une affligeante course au moins-disant fiscal et ne s’échangent des informations utiles que s’ils y sont contraints et forcés. Eh bien contraints, ici, ils seront, et c’est tant mieux.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est enfin une petite victoire pour le Parlement européen, plus spécifiquement, car à travers le vote unanime de la commission des affaires économiques, qui a amélioré d’ailleurs de façon substantielle le texte, nous prouvons que notre institution est une de celle qui est le plus en pointe sur la question de l’évasion fiscale. Vous allez me dire que c’est normal, puisque que nous sommes peut-être l’institution qui prend le plus en compte le souverain, le peuple, l’opinion publique. Or, sur ce sujet, la société européenne est fatiguée des inégalités devant l’impôt et elle est aussi légitimement révulsée par tous ces scandales auxquels je faisais allusion. Les gens regardent de près ce qui se passe à Bruxelles sur cette question et c’est la raison pour laquelle nous sommes et nous devons toujours être au diapason des attentes populaires en la matière.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, c’est une victoire techniquement solide, puisque la directive ACCIS, telle qu’elle est soumise au vote aujourd’hui, est considérablement enrichie, et je remercie pour cela, évidemment, tous les rapporteurs fictifs et tous les élus qui ont participé à ce travail.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons d’abord l’obligation de notifier au fisc les montages fiscaux douteux, obligation qui concernera non seulement les conseillers fiscaux, mais aussi les auditeurs. Pour moi, c’est très important, parce que cela inclut les grandes firmes systématiquement impliquées dans les scandales fiscaux et que l’on désigne sous le nom de «Big Four».</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous avez aussi la fuite des profits qui continue parfois à travers des montages anciens qui sont toujours fonctionnels, et nous avons obtenu, nous demandons, que tous les montages, même créés il y a plusieurs années, soient notifiés dès lors qu’ils sont encore en vigueur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, et c’est très important, nous avons élargi les indices d’optimisation fiscale agressive pour que le radar – en quelque sorte, si j’ose m’exprimer ainsi – soit le plus complet possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc nous avançons, nous faisons des propositions, nous travaillons avec la Commission. Il reste beaucoup à faire, mais c’est une petite victoire, c’est un pas dans la bonne direction, qu’il faut saluer. Je remercie, encore une fois, les élus qui se sont penchés sur ce dossier, et en particulier les rapporteurs fictifs, et je vous invite à voter massivement – pour ne pas dire unanimement – ce texte qui va dans la bonne direction.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-044-0000" speaker_id="129164" name="Tom Vandenkendelaere" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de PPE-Fractie. – Dank u wel, mijnheer de Voorzitter. Goedemorgen, collega's. Lekken als de Panama en de Paradise papers houden de publieke verontwaardiging brandend. En dat is nodig, want met publieke druk kunnen we politieke actie teweegbrengen. Ik denk dat deze richtlijn daar een echt goed voorbeeld van is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vooral de Paradise papers hebben getoond hoe groot het belang van de tussenpersonen bij belastingontwijking is. Het zijn die specialisten die de meest optimale fiscale achterpoorten als het ware verkopen aan hun klanten. Elk individu en elk bedrijf heeft in principe het recht om deze fiscale achterpoorten te gebruiken, maar de kern van het probleem ligt hem echter in het feit dat niet elk individu, niet elke onderneming daar de middelen toe heeft. Een kmo in West-Vlaanderen kan de diensten van zo'n gespecialiseerde consultant simpelweg niet betalen. Dit gaat verder dan concurrentie, dit is gewoon oneerlijk.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dit verslag is daarom erg evenwichtig en dat vind ik belangrijk. Een goed voorbeeld daarvan is de meldingsplicht die we vragen voor nieuwe en oude constructies met een mogelijk geurtje. Maar tegelijk mag het ook geen klopjacht worden. De uitzondering om oude constructies die niet meer actief gebruikt worden buiten deze meldingsplicht te laten, vind ik daarom verdedigbaar.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dit Parlement, collega's, hebben we een tijd geleden al de duidelijke keuze gemaakt voor meer fiscale rechtvaardigheid en meer transparantie. Dit verslag past daar perfect in.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-045-0000" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Monsieur le Président, même s’il est étrange de mener un débat en plénière sans le Conseil et sans la Commission, permettez-moi de présenter toutes mes félicitations au rapporteur, car il a apporté à cette proposition de législation des éléments d’avancée absolument significatifs, et tous les scandales à répétition que nous avons connus nous montrent à quel point l’évasion fiscale passe trop souvent par la mise en place de montages transfrontaliers complexes. Ceux-ci n’existent que parce que des intermédiaires, ceux auxquels nous nous intéressons aujourd’hui, qu’ils soient avocats, comptables, banquiers, conseillers fiscaux ou gestionnaires de patrimoine, les imaginent et les vendent à des multinationales, celles qui ont les moyens de s’offrir une telle panoplie de services. Est-il normal que des lanceurs d’alerte doivent faire face à la justice parce qu’ils révèlent des fraudes, tandis que ceux qui les conçoivent seraient protégés?</p>
      <p sl="en">En obligeant à déclarer, sous peine de sanctions, aux autorités nationales compétentes les régimes fiscaux transfrontaliers mis en place pour leurs clients, ce texte permet de dissuader la mise en œuvre de tels mécanismes douteux qui reflètent une volonté de contourner la loi ou de réduire abusivement le montant des impôts dus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les autorités nationales devront également échanger entre elles les informations recueillies, facilitant ainsi, au sein d’un cadre législatif européen commun, la coopération entre États membres. Il revient maintenant à ceux-ci de prendre leurs responsabilités et il nous semble que cela mérite d’être salué comme un pas important dans la mise en œuvre d’une réelle équité fiscale au sein de l’Union européenne. Nous attendons bien évidemment les États membres au tournant.</p>
      <a text="(L’oratrice accepte de répondre à une question «carton bleu» (article 162, paragraphe 8 du règlement).)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-046-0000" speaker_id="2278" name="Paul Rübig" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Meine Frage geht in die Richtung: Wir haben jetzt von den Banken und auch von den Konsumenten gehört, dass jetzt sehr viel neue Bürokratie eingezogen ist. Es gibt massive Beschwerden, dass die Bürokratie in diesem Bereich gerade für kleine und mittlere Betriebe, die grenzüberschreitende Geschäfte tätigen, extrem zugenommen hat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gibt es hier auch Vorschläge, die Bürokratie hintanzuhalten und automatisierte Systeme einzusetzen?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-047-0000" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">réponse "carton bleu". – Je crois que M. Rübig a utilisé un «carton bleu» pour faire un plaidoyer en faveur des PME, qui est sans rapport avec l’objet de cette proposition, si ce n’est qu’en facilitant la dénonciation et en supprimant le rôle des intermédiaires qui favorise les grandes multinationales, a contrario, évidemment, cela rétablira des conditions de concurrence plus saines et plus favorables aux PME.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-048-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Witam serdecznie pana komisarza Moscovici. Chciałem pana poinformować, że jesteśmy na następującym etapie: było wystąpienie pana posła sprawozdawcy, były dwa wystąpienia grup politycznych (PPE i S&amp;D). W tym momencie chciałem poprosić pana o wystąpienie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-049-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Pierre Moscovici" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Monsieur le Président, pardon de ce retard, totalement indépendant de ma volonté, mais j’ai dû prendre un train ce matin et la neige l’avait un peu retardé, ce qui m’a privé du plaisir d’entendre les intervenants précédents. Je veux en particulier saluer le rapporteur, M. Maurel, pour son rapport que je trouve de très grande qualité. Je reviendrai dans quelques instants sur les propositions qu’il contient.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je me réjouis de pouvoir présenter devant vous l’une des propositions phares de notre Commission en matière de transparence fiscale alors que vous vous apprêtez à voter cet après-midi sur une proposition relative aux intermédiaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les scandales récents – les «Panama Papers», les «Paradise Papers» – ont montré que les banques, les comptables, les conseillers fiscaux, les avocats – certains avocats – avaient joué un rôle clé pour favoriser certaines multinationales et pour organiser des montages qui permettent à de riches individus d’échapper à l’impôt. Face à ce phénomène, nous avons besoin de davantage de transparence, avec une idée simple qui est de renforcer la capacité des États membres à prévenir, à détecter cette planification fiscale agressive qui prive les gouvernements et les citoyens de ressources légitimes. C’est la raison pour laquelle, en juin dernier, la Commission a adopté une proposition pour faire davantage la lumière sur les pratiques de ces intermédiaires. Il s’agit, en un mot, d’obliger les conseillers à informer les autorités fiscales de certains dispositifs transfrontaliers – pas tous – qu’ils vendent à leurs clients et qui peuvent les aider à éluder l’impôt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je veux commencer par résumer, en quelques questions, la proposition que j’ai eu l’honneur de présenter en juin dernier.</p>
      <p sl="en">Première question: pourquoi ces exigences en matière de déclaration pour les intermédiaires contribueraient-elles à réduire l’évasion fiscale? La proposition donne aux États membres davantage d’informations sur les mécanismes de planification fiscale qui pourraient faciliter la fraude et l’évasion fiscale. Les autorités fiscales nationales, si la proposition est adoptée – ce que je souhaite –, seront alors en mesure de réagir plus rapidement au risque de pratiques fiscales abusives. Elle permettra aussi d’avoir un effet dissuasif pour ceux qui favorisent les mécanismes de planification fiscale agressive, puisque les autorités fiscales seront en bien meilleure position pour contester une telle planification avec des systèmes d’alerte précoce.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qui sont les intermédiaires dont nous parlons? Il s’agit notamment de banquiers, d’avocats, de consultants financiers, de conseillers fiscaux, de comptables, etc. y compris – on l’a vu à travers un certain nombre de cas spectaculaires – d’agents sportifs. Évidemment, je veux le dire parce que je ne veux pas laisser penser que cette proposition est stigmatisante de professions qui sont utiles au bien commun et qui concourent au fonctionnement de la justice, tout le monde dans ce secteur n’est pas associé à la planification fiscale agressive et tout montage fiscal n’est pas un montage de planification fiscale agressive.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quels types de dispositifs les intermédiaires doivent-ils communiquer à l’administration? Ils devront rendre compte de tout arrangement transfrontalier qui contient un ou plusieurs des marqueurs désignés dans la proposition par les hallmarks en anglais. Ces marqueurs sont des éléments ou des caractéristiques de la transaction qui pourraient permettre l’évasion fiscale. Par exemple, l’utilisation de modalités particulières qui impliquent des régimes fiscaux favorables dans des pays qui ne respectent pas les normes de bonne gouvernance internationale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qui est tenu de signaler ces dispositifs aux autorités fiscales? Les intermédiaires auront l’obligation principale de rapporter ces régimes, mais cette obligation peut être transférée au contribuable dans certaines circonstances. Par exemple, lorsque l’intermédiaire est protégé par la confidentialité ou par le secret professionnel, lorsque l’intermédiaire est établi dans un pays tiers ou lorsqu’il n’existe pas d’intermédiaire parce que le régime a été conçu en quelque sorte «in house». Les États membres échangeront automatiquement les informations qu’ils reçoivent à l’aide d’un répertoire central géré par la Commission, entièrement accessible à tous les États membres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le rapport que vous débattez contient des points de vue et des idées que je partage. Par exemple, la Commission reconnaît que l’absence de réaction de la part des autorités fiscales sur les dispositifs déclarés ne doit pas signifier qu’ils ne peuvent pas être contestés à l’avenir. Nous convenons également que les administrations fiscales et les cellules de renseignement financier concernant le blanchiment des capitaux et le financement du terrorisme doivent mieux se coordonner. Le rapporteur a raison de le souligner.</p>
      <p sl="en">Toutefois, sur votre proposition de donner à la Commission un accès total au répertoire central – même si je peux bien sûr la comprendre et l’apprécier –, je crois qu’il convient d’admettre que nous savons que les États membres ne l’accepteront pas. Nous ne sommes pas une autorité fiscale, nous n’avons pas les mêmes normes de secret fiscal, donc si j’ai de la sympathie pour la proposition en tant que telle, je pense qu’elle suppose un certain nombre de réformes institutionnelles en amont dont nous ne disposons pas à l’heure actuelle. Je n’estime pas non plus que nous devrions harmoniser davantage le rôle des comptables ou prévoir la publication des sanctions imposées aux administrations, aux intermédiaires et aux contribuables qui ne respecteraient pas leurs obligations. Bien entendu, cela ne change rien au fait que si un intermédiaire ne communique pas les informations qui lui sont demandées, des sanctions nationales s’appliqueront alors. La proposition exige des États membres qu’ils veillent à ce que ces sanctions soient suffisamment sévères pour décourager les cas de non-conformité et nous veillerons à ce que ce soit bien le cas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour conclure, permettez-moi de souligner combien de progrès ont été accomplis en trois ans pour accroître la transparence et la coopération entre les États membres sur les questions fiscales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur ce dossier des intermédiaires, je me réjouis de constater que le sujet a été mis à l’ordre du jour du prochain Ecofin le 13 mars, c’est la preuve que le dossier avance. Je vous invite naturellement à ne pas relâcher la pression – je vous fais confiance pour cela – pour que ce travail se poursuive maintenant au niveau des États membres en partenariat avec la présidence bulgare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur nos autres propositions, les États membres ont convenu de procéder à l’échange automatique d’informations sur les comptes financiers, les décisions fiscales anticipées transfrontières, les déclarations pays par pays des multinationales – je continue de penser que celles-ci doivent être rendues publiques. Ils se sont aussi mis d’accord sur de nouvelles règles qui donneront aux autorités fiscales l’accès aux informations de lutte contre le blanchiment des capitaux, qui est une idée proposée dans le sillage des «Panama Papers».</p>
      <p sl="en">Et bien entendu, je n’oublie pas notre proposition d’avril 2016 de rendre publiques les déclarations pays par pays pour les multinationales pour permettre aux citoyens et à la société civile d’exercer plus de contrôle sur les pratiques fiscales. Je sais que certains États membres continuent de résister, je le regrette, mais cela va dans le sens de l’histoire, et je suis sûr que nous allons prochainement aboutir à un accord, c’est notre responsabilité partagée. Je sais que le Conseil, la Commission et le Parlement sont sur la même ligne et voient la nécessité d’être ambitieux et de faire avancer les choses.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je tiens à remercier une nouvelle fois le Parlement européen pour sa contribution importante à nos travaux et je me réjouis dans la perspective, d’abord, de la suite de ce débat et, ensuite, du vote de votre Assemblée, que j’attends avec beaucoup de confiance.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-050-0000" speaker_id="132366" name="Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ECR-ryhmän puolesta. – Arvoisa puhemies, kiitos kaikille, jotka osallistuvat vilpittömästi veronkierron vastaiseen tärkeään työhön. Lukuisat veroskandaalit, kuten LuxLeaks ja Panaman paperit, nostattivat kohun, jonka pohjalta on tehty paljon työtä veronkierron ehkäisemiseksi. Viimeisin Paratiisin paperit -tietovuoto osoitti, kuinka työ on vielä pahasti kesken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esitys rajatylittäviä verojärjestelyjä koskevasta pakollisesta automaattisesta tietojenvaihdosta, lyhyesti DAC6, laajentaa hallinnollista yhteistyötä verotuksen alalla. Rajatylittäviä verotusjärjestelyjä suunnittelevia tai edistäviä tahoja, kuten pankkeja ja veroneuvojia, velvoitetaan ilmoittamaan epäilyttävistä verojärjestelyistä ennen niiden käyttöönottoa veroviranomaisille. Esitys edellyttää tietojen toimittamista Euroopan komissiolle ja jäsenvaltioiden veroviranomaisten käyttöön.</p>
      <p sl="en">DAC6 on välttämätön uudistus, mutta voidaan kysyä, onko se riittävä. Tietojenvaihdon toimivuutta on siis huolella seurattava. Mikäli tämä uudistus ei riitä, on asiaan palattava nopeassa aikataulussa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-051-0000" speaker_id="183022" name="Lieve Wierinck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ALDE-Fractie. – Beste Voorzitter, beste collega's, velen van ons praten over eerlijke belastingen, maar weinigen bieden een echte oplossing. Belastingontwijking is een probleem dat vele facetten kent, maar aan de bron hiervan ligt meestal een gebrek aan informatie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vandaag stemmen we de DAC 6. Het is het laatste voorstel in een hele reeks om belastingontwijking tegen te gaan en zou de laatste mazen in het net moeten dichten. Wat dit voorstel zo anders maakt, is dat het preventief werkt. In plaats van belastingontwijking tegen te gaan, geven we de lidstaten de kans om hierop te anticiperen en hun inkomsten veilig te stellen voor agressieve belastingconstructies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarnaast zorgt het ervoor dat de informatie die zij vergaren automatisch met elkaar gedeeld zal worden. Deze aanpak over de grenzen heen zal ervoor zorgen dat misbruiken van de verschillende systemen tussen landen weer een stuk moeilijker worden, want het zou naïef zijn te denken dat dit probleem helemaal op nationaal niveau kan opgelost worden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik geloof dat dit voorstel het beoogde doel zal bereiken.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-052-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Δημήτριος Παπαδημούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κύριε Πρόεδρε, θα ήθελα να συγχαρώ τον κ. Maurel για την έκθεσή του. Η ομάδα μου θα την υπερψηφίσει. Είναι ένα θετικό βήμα και θέλω να πω ότι είναι μία από τις εκθέσεις που προσπαθεί να ενισχύσει μία θετική, αν και καθυστερημένη, πρόταση της Επιτροπής. Για την καταπολέμηση της φοροδιαφυγής και της φοροαποφυγής, ποτέ δεν είναι αρκετά αυτά που γίνονται. Πάντα χρειάζεται να γινόμαστε αποτελεσματικότεροι γιατί χάνονται τεράστια ποσά, και από τους κρατικούς προϋπολογισμούς και από την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, σε βάρος των έντιμων φορολογουμένων, σε βάρος του κοινωνικού κράτους, σε βάρος των κατακτήσεων και σε βάρος της ηθικής και της δεοντολογίας του τίμιου ανταγωνισμού ανάμεσα στις επιχειρήσεις. Όσοι αντιτίθενται σε αυτή την πρόταση, ουσιαστικά διευκολύνουν αυτούς που φοροδιαφεύγουν και εξαπατούν. Επομένως, θα πρέπει να έχουμε αυστηρότερο πλαίσιο, κυρώσεις, διαφάνεια, συνεργασία και να ενισχύουμε διαρκώς το οπλοστάσιο για την καταπολέμηση της φορολογικής απάτης που κερδίζει διαρκώς έδαφος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-053-0000" speaker_id="124942" name="Molly Scott Cato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Panama Papers demonstrated the key role played by intermediaries such as banks, accountants and lawyers in helping their clients create offshore structures for tax evasion, tax avoidance and money laundering, so we welcome this revision to the directive on administrative cooperation, whose aim is to ensure that aggressive tax planning schemes are reported to tax authorities so that they can investigate where necessary. It creates an obligation for intermediaries to disclose potentially aggressive tax planning arrangements, and this information will then automatically be exchanged with other Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parliament has strengthened the Commission’s proposal by requiring an obligation for auditors to report suspect schemes when statutory audits of their clients’ businesses are being carried out and by proposing that the Commission itself should have access to the data exchanged. So we are glad to support this proposal as part of our ongoing work to counter the tax avoidance industry.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-054-0000" speaker_id="124967" name="David Coburn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, these proposals requiring mandatory exchange of tax information undermine tax sovereignty of the nation states, individual privacy and attorney-client privilege, and also the directors’ duty to arrange the tax affairs of companies in order to pay as little tax as possible. We in Britain believe that the taxpayer has the right to do everything possible within the law – I say within the law – to minimise their tax exposure. You should not have to pay any more tax than is required: not one penny piece. Taxpayers should be allowed to enjoy the fruits of their hard labour, and not have it wasted by the state.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union wants to maximise taxation throughout Europe to pay for the fat-cat salaries and the gilded pensions of EU bureaucrats, under increasing bureaucratic tax bunching. This attitude to the rights of the individual is one of the reasons the UK is leaving the EU, and I encourage the Czechs, the Hungarians and the Poles to do likewise.</p>
      <a text="(The speaker agreed to take a blue-card question under Rule 162(8))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-055-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card question. – It is always a pleasure to address a question to my friend, especially when he is talking about Brexit. Do you know, Mr Coburn, that in the City of London, which is so famous for its banks and the financial companies settled there, lots of European Union directives on taxation have not yet been applied? It seems that the city is already a kind of fiscal paradise. After Brexit it is probably going to become the biggest fiscal paradise in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-056-0000" speaker_id="124967" name="David Coburn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card answer. – Yes, I think the City of London will become a fiscal paradise and I think Europeans throughout Europe will be wanting to put their money into Great Britain and into the enterprise that is the City of London, so that they are better off.</p>
      <p sl="en">And, of course, we are the bankers of Europe. Many countries, including Italy, would be in tremendous trouble if they could not borrow money from us. Their banks are in danger of collapse, as is the entire euro system, hence why we are leaving.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-057-0000" speaker_id="124792" name="Laurenţiu Rebega" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului ENF. – Domnule președinte, iată că, în urma scandalurilor tot mai dese legate de lupta împotriva evaziunii fiscale, aflăm că este tot mai greu pentru statele membre de a-și proteja bazele fiscale naționale împotriva eroziunii. În paralel, structurile de planificare fiscală devin din ce în ce mai sofisticate și profită de mobilitatea sporită a capitalului, dar și de lipsa unei mai mari transparențe în spațiul european.</p>
      <p sl="en">Consider că lupta împotriva planificării fiscale agresive și împotriva structurilor ce practică acest gen de activități nu se poate duce atâta timp cât ele nu încalcă de fapt nicio prevedere legislativă.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sunt de părere că instituțiile europene sunt datoare să implementeze o legislație sănătoasă și eficientă în spațiul Uniunii, care să permită protejarea mai întâi a intereselor financiare a statelor membre și, în al doilea rând, ale Uniunii în ansamblul ei. Până când aceste condiții preliminare nu vor fi îndeplinite printr-o legislație strictă și transparentă, orice schimb de informații între statele membre nu va putea produce niște rezultate concrete.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-058-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, αυτή είναι άλλη μια φορά που η Ένωση αποτυγχάνει να ανταποκριθεί στις προσδοκίες των πολιτών. Ακόμη χειρότερα, όχι απλά η έκθεση αυτή δεν θα αντιμετωπίσει τη φοροδιαφυγή των μεγάλων εταιρειών αλλά δημιουργεί και εύλογες ανησυχίες σχετικά με την ασφάλεια των προσωπικών δεδομένων και το πώς μπορούν αυτά να χρησιμοποιηθούν στο μέλλον. Αρχικά, το ίδιο το φορολογικό καθεστώς πολλών κρατών μελών επιτρέπει τη νόμιμη φοροαποφυγή σε όσους βέβαια έχουν τα μέσα, ώστε να εντοπίσουν και να εκμεταλλευθούν τα διάφορα κενά του νόμου. Σημαντικότερο όλων όμως είναι το γεγονός πως η ίδια η ιδέα της ενιαίας αγοράς προτρέπει στη φοροαποφυγή, μιας και δεν έχουν όλες οι χώρες το ίδιο φορολογικό καθεστώς. Βεβαίως, είναι παράλογο να περιμένουμε από μία εταιρεία να παραμείνει σε μία χώρα και να πληρώνει πολλαπλάσιο φόρο, ενώ μπορεί, εκμεταλλευόμενη την ενιαία αγορά, να μεταφέρει την έδρα της και να γλιτώσει τεράστια ποσά, εκτός βεβαίως από τις μικρές και μεσαίες επιχειρήσεις οι οποίες, από τη φύση τους, αδυνατούν να κάνουν κάτι τέτοιο. Επειδή όμως η ενιαία φορολόγηση θα ήταν απαράδεκτη εκχώρηση εθνικής κυριαρχίας για εμάς, υποστηρίζουμε την επιστροφή των συνόρων όσον αφορά την κίνηση αγαθών ή την παροχή υπηρεσιών εντός της Ένωσης.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-059-0000" speaker_id="124929" name="Ivan Štefanec" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pán predsedajúci, dámy a páni, efektivita výberu daní je ukazovateľom elementárnej spravodlivosti. Ak štát nedokáže vybrať dane podľa platných pravidiel, znamená to, že niečo podstatné nie je v poriadku, a ak sa objavujú škandály typu Panama papers či Paradise papers, situácia je o to vážnejšia. Boj proti daňovým únikom a podvodom musí byť samozrejmou prioritou na našom spoločnom európskom trhu pri jeho pokračujúcej integrácii. Ja som presvedčený, že daňová subsidiarita má svoj význam a kompetencie o rozhodovaní o výške daní na národnej úrovni by mali byť zachované. Zároveň je ale jednoznačne potrebné urobiť viac pre spoluprácu jednotlivých krajín. Povinná automatická výmena informácií pri cezhraničných záležitostiach je tak určite správny krok, ktorý potrebujeme pre zlepšenie transparentnosti a prístupu k informáciám, a teda pre zlepšenie výberu daní. Táto povinná výmena informácií pomôže predovšetkým samotným členským štátom, ktoré v mnohých prípadoch prichádzajú o daňové príjmy. Deje sa tak najmä v cezhraničných prípadoch, kedy národné opatrenia ani nemôžu byť úplne efektívne. Stále sme svedkami aj prípadov nastrčených firiem v iných krajinách so snahou zakryť identitu skutočných vlastníkov. Verím, že povinná výmena informácií je správnou cestou pre zabezpečenie všetkých informácií pre daňové úrady. Verím, že kroky Európskeho parlamentu pomôžu pre zlepšenie výberu daní, spravodlivejšie podnikanie a tvorbu pracovných miest.</p>
      <p sl="en">(Rečník súhlasil, že odpovie na otázku položenú zdvihnutím modrej karty (článok 162 ods. 8 rokovacieho poriadku)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-060-0000" speaker_id="124967" name="David Coburn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">blue-card question. – I wonder if you agree with me that all this is in preparation for a pan-European income tax in the future? Do you think the people of your country will be as pleased as the people of all the other European nations to be hit with yet another whopping great tax to pay for the ‘Folies Bergère’ that is the European Parliament?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-061-0000" speaker_id="124929" name="Ivan Štefanec" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odpoveď na otázku položenú zdvihnutím modrej karty – Nie, pán kolega, nevidím to tak ako Vy a určite som nie presvedčený, že by toto mal byť základ pre nejaké spoločné zdaňovanie či nové dane. Som zástancom zotrvania daňovej suverenity, som zástancom toho, že o daniach sa má rozhodovať v národných krajinách, ale zároveň potrebujeme urobiť opatrenia pre zlepšenie výberu daní. A cez povinnú výmenu informácií vidím dobrý a efektívny spôsob pre zlepšenie výberu daní.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-062-0000" speaker_id="97078" name="Ramón Jáuregui Atondo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, yo creo que esta Directiva es una directiva importante en la lucha contra la evasión fiscal. Me felicito de la iniciativa de la Comisión y felicito a mi colega, el señor Maurel, precisamente por el trabajo que ha hecho este Parlamento, que creo que ha hecho aportaciones interesantes a la iniciativa, especialmente en lo que se refiere a la necesidad de contar con un registro público en la Comisión sobre estas materias y a la necesidad, también, de establecer sanciones para el incumplimiento de las obligaciones que establece esta Directiva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero destacar, sin embargo, que lo que el Parlamento hace es una opinión y que en la lucha contra la evasión fiscal estamos sufriendo lo que yo llamaría una actitud retardataria y casi de boicot de muchos países de la Unión en el Consejo. El Consejo está generalmente vetando, a través de la necesidad de unanimidad, muchas iniciativas en esta justa lucha por la justicia fiscal y está estableciendo exigencias y está amparando espacios fiscales opacos o paraísos fiscales europeos. Y esto no puede ser: eso es insolidario, insostenible e incompatible con un mercado único en la Unión Europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-063-0000" speaker_id="119436" name="Ivana Maletić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, naša obveza je poduzeti sve mjere i zaštititi poštene poduzetnike i porezne obveznike, zaštititi građane od onih koji obavljaju aktivnosti i zarađuju u našim državama, ali pronalaze načine izbjegavanja plaćanja poreza i time ne samo da oštećuju proračune država već i na nepošten način konkuriraju na tržištu i uništavaju kvalitetne poduzetničke pothvate. Moramo spriječiti nove porezne skandale Panama i Paradise Papers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Upravo zato su važne izmjene ove direktive. Ključna je razmjena informacija o uočenim nepoštenim poreznim praksama, ali potrebno je i više od toga. Potrebne su informacije koje će omogućiti preventivno djelovanje i uspostavu mehanizama koji će odvratiti tzv. savjetnike od osmišljavanja i plasiranja aranžmana za smanjenje poreznog opterećenja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bolja razmjena informacija, edukacija poreznih uprava, razmjena znanja i iskustava, uključivanje financijskih institucija i revizora u otkrivanju informacija poreznim upravama o potencijalnim situacijama izbjegavanja plaćanja poreza ključni su za stvaranje sustava pravednijeg oporezivanja i tržišta koje će biti poticajno za stvaranje novih poslova, a to je ono što želimo u Europskoj uniji – rast i razvoj na kvalitetnim temeljima. Utaje poreza sigurno tome ne doprinose.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-064-0000" speaker_id="28394" name="Dariusz Rosati" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Szanowni Państwo! W tej Izbie wielokrotnie krytykowaliśmy niekorzystne praktyki związane z unikaniem opodatkowania, z konstruowaniem agresywnych schematów podatkowych, z tak zwaną optymalizacją podatkową. To wszystko są praktyki, które, nawet jeśli są zgodne z prawem, panie Coburn, są sprzeczne z duchem prawa i z całą pewnością wprowadzają bardzo szkodliwą dyskryminację, w szczególności krzywdzą małe i średnie przedsiębiorstwa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlatego z zadowoleniem witam wniosek ustawodawczy Komisji i dlatego również chcę powiedzieć, że będę popierał sprawozdanie pana Morela, ponieważ te dokumenty zmierzają w kierunku ukrócenia tych praktyk. Będą miały z całą pewnością z jednej strony efekt mrożący i zapobiegną, w wielu przypadkach, proponowaniu przez pośredników finansowych, banki, doradców podatkowych rozmaitych podejrzanych schematów podatkowych. A z drugiej strony stanowią bardzo ważną informację dla władz podatkowych, które będą mogły dzięki temu uszczelniać system podatkowy i eliminować te niekorzystne praktyki.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-066-0000" speaker_id="28306" name="Ana Gomes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, os esquemas de evasão fiscal e lavagem de dinheiro destacados pelos Panama Papers e Paradise Papers, entre outros escândalos, mostram como existe uma transfronteiriça teia de intermediários, incluindo consultores, banqueiros, advogados, contabilistas e outros prestadores de serviços que se especializaram em arquitetar esquemas de evasão fiscal e branqueamento para as grandes multinacionais, para clientes ricos e para máfias, para evitarem impostos e outras obrigações legais com opacidade e impunidade.</p>
      <p sl="en">É por isso que esta proposta da Comissão que segue o apelo do Parlamento em vários relatórios é tão importante. Visa assegurar a obrigação de denunciar os esquemas transfronteiriços, concebidos por intermediários fiscais ou contribuintes, às autoridades fiscais de cada Estado-Membro, incluindo as informações recolhidas na troca automática de informações entre as autoridades fiscais na União Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">O excelente relatório de Emmanuel Maurel, que será hoje aprovado, visa reforçar a Comissão por parte do Parlamento. Esperemos que os Governos no Conselho não reduzam o âmbito das obrigações de reportar informação e de partilhar informações recolhidas, de forma a adotarmos legislação robusta, sem subterfúgios contra a transparência e a prestação de contas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-068-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία πρόεδρε, είναι δεδομένο ότι πρέπει να χτυπηθεί η φοροδιαφυγή και η φοροαποφυγή. Αυτό το γνωρίζουμε και αυτό μπορεί να γίνει, πρώτα απ` όλα, όταν επιβληθεί η υποχρέωση να φορολογούνται οι πολυεθνικές εκεί που πραγματικά βγάζουν τα κέρδη. Το δεύτερο είναι ότι οι πολιτικές του επιθετικού φορολογικού σχεδιασμού ουσιαστικά στηρίζονται στις ρυθμίσεις που έχουν τα ίδια τα κράτη μέλη και επομένως, αλλάζοντας τη νομοθεσία, μπορεί κανείς να αντιμετωπίσει αυτή την κατάσταση, διότι μόνο έτσι θα σταματήσει ο αθέμιτος ανταγωνισμός. Επομένως, είναι θετική η έκθεση και φυσικά πρέπει να γίνει ανταλλαγή πληροφοριών αλλά αυτό που πρέπει να κάνουμε είναι να κλείσουμε, νομοθετικά, τα διάφορα «παραθυράκια» που επιτρέπουν τη φοροδιαφυγή και την φοροαποφυγή των διάφορων πολυεθνικών. Άρα εκεί πρέπει να σταθούμε κυρίως, αυτό είναι το βασικό στοιχείο: να κλείσουν όλα τα τρικ και όλα τα φορολογικά «παράθυρα».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-069-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, direct taxation is not harmonised across the European Union, which means that the freedom of EU citizens and their businesses can enable some taxpayers to avoid or evade tax in their country of residence.</p>
      <p sl="en">The automatic exchange of information on tax rulings should allow the Member States to combat tax evasion, detect companies’ abusive tax practices and consequently take any necessary action against them. I support the Commission proposal to improve and strengthen administrative cooperation between the Member States’ tax administrations, and I consider it important for the Member States to strengthen the financial and human resources of the tax administration. Nevertheless, it is important to have strong and corresponding sanctions, which should be financial as well as granting access to the central depository. This could also strengthen the EU’s competitive policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-070-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, razmjena informacija o prekograničnim aranžmanima u kontekstu boljeg, transparentnijeg i pravednijeg oporezivanja i borbe protiv izbjegavanja plaćanja i utaje poreza iznimno je važna. Želimo li mobilnost kapitala i ljudi te funkcionalno jedinstveno tržište, moramo imati jasna pravila prema kojima se subjekti na njemu ponašaju.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pritom moramo uvijek voditi računa o tome da dodatna regulacija košta i da će veliki gospodarski subjekti puno lakše podnijeti taj trošak od srednjih i malih tvrtki koje čine kralježnicu europske ekonomije.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stoga ovim putem još jednom apeliram na promjenu poreznih politika koje moraju biti stimulativne, dok kazne za izbjegavanje i utaju trebaju postati oštrije. Na taj način ove štetne prakse i kaznena djela postaju neisplativi pa će sve manje subjekata uopće pokušati skriti svoj novac od države.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-071-0000" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, le strutture di pianificazione fiscale hanno subito un'evoluzione diventando particolarmente sofisticate e traendo spesso vantaggio dall'accresciuta mobilità di capitale e persone nel mercato interno. Esse consistono generalmente in meccanismi che si sviluppano tra varie giurisdizioni e trasferiscono gli utili imponibili verso regimi tributari favorevoli o hanno come effetto quello di ridurre le imposte esigibili nei confronti dei contribuenti. In queste condizioni risulta sempre più difficile per gli Stati membri proteggere le basi imponibili nazionali dall'erosione, il che impedisce loro di applicare politiche fiscali favorevoli alla crescita.</p>
      <p sl="en">La modifica della direttiva sulla cooperazione amministrativa nel settore fiscale volta al rafforzamento della trasparenza rappresenta senza dubbio un importante tassello nella strategia di lotta all'evasione e all'elusione fiscale della Commissione. Resta ancora senza risposta, però, il principale problema della mancanza di un equo sistema fiscale europeo, ovvero di un'unione fiscale, cosa che vanifica completamente ogni tentativo di coesione economica e sociale in Europa e amplia a dismisura le possibilità di evadere ed eludere il fisco.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-073-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Pierre Moscovici" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Madame la Présidente, je voudrais d’abord remercier les députés pour cet échange de vues très intéressant et qui, surtout, augure d’une bonne conclusion pour ce texte, et ce sera un signal important si ce texte est voté, comme je peux le ressentir à la conclusion de ce débat, de manière largement transpartisane.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous partageons tous – ou presque tous – la conviction que le temps est venu d’une plus grande transparence sur les pratiques des intermédiaires. Ceux-ci ont en vérité trop longtemps travaillé dans l’ombre. J’ai utilisé récemment l’image audacieuse – j’en conviens – de vampires pour qualifier certains auteurs de fraude fiscale. Pourtant, même si elle est audacieuse, la formule n’était pas inexacte: certains prospèrent tant qu’il y a du secret et ne prospèrent que dans le secret. La transparence est donc la seule arme efficace, la principale arme pour contrer l’évasion et la fraude fiscales. C’est l’objectif que poursuit de nouveau notre proposition sur les intermédiaires. Les autorités fiscales – j’en suis persuadé – ont besoin de cette source supplémentaire d’information, car dans le cas contraire, elles ne pourraient pas repérer un dispositif particulier au cours de l’audit d’une entreprise faute d’avoir une vue d’ensemble.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je pense que cette nouvelle proposition va considérablement aider les autorités fiscales à améliorer leur efficacité dans la lutte contre les mécanismes d’évasion fiscale. Je crois qu’elle représente une nouvelle étape pour soutenir l’équité dans le domaine de la fiscalité. Une fois adoptée, cette directive permettra de garantir des conditions de concurrence équitables. Elle fournira une plus grande sécurité aux intermédiaires qui respectent l’esprit et la lettre de notre législation et elle rendra la vie très difficile à ceux qui ne le font pas.</p>
      <p sl="en">À l’heure actuelle, reconnaissons qu’il peut s’avérer compliqué pour certaines entreprises qui ne pratiquent pas de planification fiscale de rivaliser avec les multinationales qui utilisent les régimes fiscaux agressifs pour éviter de payer leur juste part d’impôts. C’est une situation qui est d’autant plus injuste qu’elle signifie également que les contribuables honnêtes doivent payer plus que leur juste part pour compenser le manque à gagner et assurer le financement des services publics et des biens communs dont nos concitoyens ont besoin. Je me suis engagé à mener ce combat jusqu’au bout de mon mandat et je le ferai, parce que depuis le premier jour, mon objectif et celui de cette Commission est d’aboutir à ce que tous les contribuables, citoyens et entreprises, soient sur un pied d’égalité, que nul ne soit indument privilégié.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je veux à nouveau féliciter le rapporteur pour son excellent travail qui – me semble-t-il – constitue une base pour une approbation très large de votre Assemblée, laquelle sera un signal politique de volonté très fort et que j’attends avec beaucoup d’impatience.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous remercie de votre attention et de cette nouvelle preuve de soutien à ce que la Commission entreprend depuis novembre 2014 – à son rythme sans doute, et ce rythme est aussi celui de la décision publique – mais avec une totale détermination, que nous partageons, et je crois que c’est pour le bien de tous.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-074-0000" speaker_id="24505" name="Emmanuel Maurel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, Monsieur le Commissaire, merci pour ces propos qui témoignent quand même d’une quasi-unanimité dans cet hémicycle, qui consistent à dire que les inégalités fiscales menacent notre pacte démocratique, qu’il n’y a pas d’égalité des citoyens sans égalité devant l’impôt et qu’il n’y a pas d’État stable et d’Europe stable et respectée qui laissent fuir chaque année des dizaines de milliards d’euros de recettes publiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">Donc, j’ai entendu les commentaires des uns et des autres et, pour reprendre un collègue, il ne s’agit évidemment pas de stigmatiser des professions, mais bien de tenter de dissuader certains de ces professionnels de s’adonner à ce que j’ai appelé une «industrie de l’évasion fiscale», en tout cas de l’optimisation fiscale, que nous avons tous dénoncée ce matin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le commissaire Moscovici nous invitait à prendre conscience des progrès qui avaient été réalisés depuis trois ans. Il est vrai que la Commission et le Parlement essaient de travailler, à leur rythme, pour trouver des réponses. Il est vrai aussi, quand même – soyons honnêtes, chers collègues – que le Conseil ne nous aide pas beaucoup et qu’il ne va pas falloir relâcher la pression face à des États membres qui, sur ce dossier, sont rarement en avance et ont rarement envie d’anticiper un certain nombre de débats.</p>
      <p sl="en">Merci chers collègues, je souhaite que ce texte soit voté avec la plus large majorité possible pour que nous envoyions – pour reprendre les mots du commissaire – un signal politique, celui de la volonté de restaurer l’égalité des citoyens et des entreprises devant l’impôt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-075-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place shortly.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-0000" speaker_id="39721" name="Theodor Dumitru Stolojan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Schimbul automat obligatoriu de informații în domeniul fiscal pentru aranjamentele trans-naționale reprezintă principalul instrument aflat la dispoziția statelor membre în vederea prevenirii și identificării evaziunii fiscale, precum și a situațiilor în care veniturile impozabile nu sunt declarate. De aceea, inițiativa Comisiei Europene, în acest sens, este salutară. Consider că este nevoie, și în acest caz, să avem o listă a jurisdicțiilor fiscale care nu doresc să coopereze în domeniul respectiv și , eventual, să introducem sancțiunile necesare. Evaziunea fiscală și evitarea obligațiilor fiscale, prin fel de fel de practici, trebuie oprite în interesul general al cetățenilor.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-077-0000" speaker_id="124703" name="Tibor Szanyi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Üdvözlöm az adózás területére vonatkozó kötelező automatikus információcseréről szóló jelentést és egyúttal gratulálok az EP-nek, de kiváltképpen az S&amp;D frakciónak, amely hosszú ideje küzd az európai adóigazságosság helyreállításáért – és amely számos komoly eredményt ért már el e téren. Az agresszív adótervezés ellen nem lehet egyedül, kizárólag tagállami kompetenciában küzdeni. Közösségi, európai fellépésre van szükség, hogy végre bezárjuk a kiskapukat, csak így vehetjük le az igazságtalan adóterheket a becsületes adófizetők állampolgárok és kkv-k válláról.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az adóhatóságok közötti automatikus információcsere, a transzparencia növelése, az adókikerülési konstrukciókban segítséget nyújtó köztes szereplők elleni szigorúbb fellépés ebben fog segíteni. Ugyanakkor emlékeztetnék arra, hogy a jogszabály abból indul ki, hogy európai jogállamokban működő, független adóhatóságokkal dolgozik együtt. És itt van a jogszabály korlátja, hisz Magyarország esetében sajnos ez nem létezik – se jogállamról, sem a magyar kormánytól független hatóságokról nem beszélhetünk. Így szomorúan hívom fel a figyelmet arra, hogy jelen feltételek mellett ettől a tagállamtól az EU biztosan nem számíthat jóhiszemű együttműködésre az agresszív adótervezés elkerülése terén sem.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Cutting the sources of income for Jihadists - targeting the financing of terrorism (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-079-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Javier Nart, on behalf of the Committee on Foreign Affairs, on a European Parliament recommendation to the Council, the Commission and the Vice-President of the Commission / High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy on cutting the sources of income for jihadists – targeting the financing of terrorism (2017/2203(INI)) (A8—0035/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-080-0000" speaker_id="125005" name="Javier Nart" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, la derrota del Estado Islámico en Siria y en Irak no significa su fin: en sus manos queda una ingente cantidad de dinero que ha sido almacenado a lo largo de su califato con la venta de petróleo, la captura o inversiones de negocios legítimos, impuestos revolucionarios, robos, asaltos bancarios, raptos, tráfico de antigüedades, venta de armas. Son aproximadamente unos 400 millones de dólares los que se estima que están siendo blanqueados en Siria y en Irak, teniendo en cuenta que el volumen aproximado de su movimiento económico, en la época del califato, era de unos 80 millones de dólares mensuales.</p>
      <p sl="en">El objetivo de esta Recomendación es colapsar, evitar que se puedan utilizar estos fondos, que se puedan blanquear, que se pueda comercializar su botín, porque es necesario que los servicios de inteligencia funcionen de forma coordinada para atajar la financiación del terrorismo. Por ello, se propone a la Comisión, a los Estados miembros y al Servicio Europeo de Acción Exterior una visión completa, integral que ahonde en la cooperación necesaria entre los servicios de inteligencia europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">La creación de una plataforma horizontal de los servicios de inteligencia europeos donde puedan compartir datos e investigaciones es una necesidad estratégica. No se trata de crear una nueva institución sino, con realismo, de establecer una plataforma de cooperación donde exista una base de datos conjunta y donde puedan compartirse estos datos. Y esta plataforma que proponemos ha de construirse sobre la base de lo que ya existe en Europol, con el punto de mira en un intercambio proactivo de información sobre financiación de los grupos terroristas.</p>
      <p sl="en">También se anima a los Estados miembros a que dediquen más esfuerzos a dotarse de personal cualificado, ingenieros informáticos que puedan detectar e investigar debidamente los movimientos económicamente sospechosos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pedimos también la pronta implementación de la quinta Directiva antiblanqueo de capitales para mejorar la competencia de las unidades de inteligencia nacionales y que puedan acceder a datos bancarios, incluyendo dentro del ámbito de la Directiva, para su investigación, las monedas virtuales y las tarjetas de prepago, tarjetas que, hasta ahora, se recargaban de una forma anónima, y eso debe acabarse.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las nuevas tecnologías tienen un rol y una responsabilidad fundamental. Las monedas virtuales, las plataformas de crowdfundig son utilizadas por los terroristas. Las nuevas tecnologías son, por su propia naturaleza, transfronterizas, como debe ser la respuesta al terrorismo, que también es transfronterizo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Disponemos de acuerdos internacionales en materia de intercambio y trazabilidad de información financiera ligada al terrorismo pero, muy curiosamente, no hacemos lo mismo dentro de la Unión Europea. Es el caso de la zona única de pagos en euros, y proponemos, por tanto, a la Comisión que adelante medidas que puedan complementar el sistema internacional con una respuesta conjunta europea, todo ello aplicando con rigor los estándares de protección de datos y el respeto a los derechos fundamentales que nos definen como respetuosos de derechos en la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">También proponemos que, en la Unión Europea, concretamente las modalidades de transferencia tradicional de dinero, desde la hawala al fei ch'ien chino y otras modalidades tradicionales, se encuentren reguladas mediante un registro de las transacciones de obligado cumplimiento, como ocurre con cualquiera de nuestros conciudadanos, que, cuando transfieren dinero, lo hacen de una manera controlada: igualdad ante la ley y no discriminación. La hawala está siendo utilizada por el Estado Islámico, por las organizaciones terroristas para exportar su dinero desde Siria y desde Irak, y ese dinero llega a Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">De la misma manera, en Europa debemos poner nuestra atención en centros de culto, culturales y asociaciones caritativas —aparentes asociaciones caritativas— cuando haya razones para sospechar que tienen vínculos con el terrorismo, para evitar un uso negligente o imprudente de los fondos que reciben, todo ello con muy especial atención a la lucha contra esta nueva forma de racismo y de xenofobia que es la islamofobia.</p>
      <p sl="en">El terrorismo definido como yihadismo es una blasfemia contra el Corán y las principales víctimas de esta actividad terrorista son precisamente los musulmanes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por último, en nuestra dimensión externa, en las misiones que enviamos y financiamos desde nuestra política común de seguridad y defensa, dentro de la asistencia que proporcionamos a la construcción de resiliencia en los Estados víctimas del crimen terrorista, debemos añadir la dimensión de la lucha contra la financiación del terrorismo y, especialmente, contra la integración en la economía propia de los fondos capturados por los terroristas, esto es, el blanqueo del dinero a través de actividades económicas lícitas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para concluir, quiero dar las gracias a los compañeros con los que he negociado el texto, y también al comisario King, con quien he tenido la ocasión de intercambiar puntos de vista sobre la propuesta de Recomendación. He pretendido que la Recomendación sea realista y posible y efectiva. Y agradezco que mis esfuerzos para conjugar el necesario y difícil equilibrio entre libertad y seguridad hayan obtenido el consenso de todos los grupos políticos. Gracias a todos ellos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-081-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Julian King" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, terrorists need to raise and move funds to maintain their networks, cover their logistical needs and commit their attacks. We need to close down the space in which they can do this. Countering terrorist financing is not only about limiting their capacity to act, but also about, as we have just heard, using financial intelligence to detect and stop terrorists before they act.</p>
      <p sl="en">Recent attacks perpetrated in Europe have been financed with relatively small sums of money, and that poses some new challenges to those who are working on the front line to prevent terrorist attacks. We need to give law enforcement and our public authorities the tools they need to do their job and to help keep us safe. So I very much welcome the timely recommendations in this report.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tackling terrorist financing is a high priority for all of us. From the Commission side, it is a key part of our work to build an effective security union. Our approach was set out in the Action Plan for strengthening the fight against terrorist financing of February 2016, and we are now taking that work forward on two fronts: detecting and preventing terrorist funding, and disrupting the sources of revenue. That covers a range of different measures: preventing the misuse of the financial system for money laundering and terrorist financing; increasing cooperation and the exchange of information between competent authorities, in particular financial intelligence units; tracing the financial movements of terrorists; improving the effectiveness of asset-freezing systems; reinforcing the judicial response to terrorist financing and money laundering; supporting third countries in countering terrorist financing and money laundering in their implementation of the Financial Action Task Force standards; supporting customs authorities with tools to identify sources of revenue of terrorist organisations; and supporting third countries as they engage with international partners, not only through the FATF, as I mentioned, but also other bodies such as the Anti-ISIS Coalition working group on countering financing of terrorism, and indeed the work that is done in the framework of the G-7. So I am glad to see that many of the report’s recommendations are in line with the work that we are undertaking.</p>
      <p sl="en">We welcome the emphasis in the report on information-sharing, in particular among financial intelligence units, as well as other national agencies. We welcome your support for the establishment of central bank account registries. I am glad to say, as announced in the Commission work programme for this year, we will soon present initiatives to improve cross-border access to financial data for law enforcement authorities. This will include measures to facilitate access to national centralised bank account registries and retrieval systems within Member States. We will also propose measures to improve the cooperation between law enforcement authorities and the various financial intelligence units. In line with the report’s recommendations, we have reinforced Europol’s role in this fight against terrorist financing. We take note of the call for increasing monitoring of prepaid cards. The Fifth Anti-Money Laundering Directive is a step forward, I think, in reinforcing the transparency around this means of payment.</p>
      <p sl="en">With its list of non-cooperative jurisdictions, the EU is also acting to increase the exchange of information on tax matters with third countries, as you have been discussing. This will help national administrations to detect the presence of illicit money and money-laundering.</p>
      <p sl="en">We appreciate your support for the EU-US Terrorist Finance Tracking Programme and we take note of your call for a European system to complement that.</p>
      <p sl="en">On asset-freezing, we appreciate the report’s support for existing measures. The EU’s asset-freezing efforts have been reinforced with the autonomous EU regime against al-Qaeda and Daesh. We appreciate the emphasis on hawala. In the supranational risk assessment of money laundering and terrorism financing risks, the Commission recommended that hawala service providers should apply the requirements related to money-transfer systems under the payment services directive and the Anti-Money Laundering Directive, and we are committed to keeping this particular sector under close review. In relation to high-value goods, I would like to underline that the proposal to amend the Cash Control Regulation expands the definition of cash to gold and other high-value commodities.</p>
      <p sl="en">We appreciate your support for our proposed regulation on the import of cultural goods. This issue remains of high importance in addressing the problem of cultural goods being illegally taken from third countries, from their proper historical and archeological context, and being brought to the EU. This can in turn foster organised crime, terrorist financing, money laundering and tax evasion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Member States should also soon adopt the Commission’s proposals to strengthen the VAT system and reinforce the collective fight against VAT fraud, which again can feed criminal and terrorist organisations.</p>
      <p sl="en">So in a nutshell, I am glad that the work the Commission is doing in this area is in line with many of the measures you call for and support in today’s report. Some other new measures you suggest merit further analysis. We will take a careful look at them and we will come back to you on them.</p>
      <p sl="en">Countering financing of terrorism is a core component of the EU strategy in the fight against terrorism and hence in our work to build an effective security union. As the terrorists and their supporters constantly modify and change the ways they collect, move and get access to funds, we need to be ready to adopt and adapt our response. The EU needs to adapt its instruments and measures to deprive terrorists of the space and the means they use as they seek to do us harm. I count on your continued support as we take this work forward.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-082-0000" speaker_id="124990" name="Lars Adaktusson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would first like to congratulate my colleague, Javier Nart, for a well drafted report. Despite the defeat of ISIS, we are not in a position to declare victory over terrorism. Instead, we should learn from both the rise and fall of Islamic State. One lesson is that the combination of military means and cutting off the financial lifeblood of ISIS has paved the way for its departure.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another lesson is that, after the dismantling of an organisation like ISIS, there will be a vacuum. Certain actors will do their utmost to fill that space with new Jihadist organisations, and for that they will need money. Cutting the funding sources of terrorist networks should therefore be considered a key priority. It constitutes an effective tool, hampering the effectiveness of these networks. To achieve this, implementation is crucial: the Member States, for instance, should deliver when it comes to the exchange of intelligence. With common efforts, the EU is able to cope with the bloodstream of Jihadism: the capital flow that today finances international terrorism.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-083-0000" speaker_id="124944" name="Clare Moody" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would also like to thank the rapporteur and my fellow shadow rapporteurs for the constructive way in which we have worked together. I believe this has led to a good report with realistic recommendations. The changes we suggested in this report can be embraced by law-enforcement bodies across Europe, for example by creating a platform where data can be shared. The small amounts of money that are needed for terrorists to carry out their criminal acts in our cities mean that we need to be better at monitoring even small transactions, including traditional forms of exchange, such as hawala. We also need to recognise that Daesh move money into legitimate businesses but in countries with weak institutions, which is why we need to support institution-building in fragile states.</p>
      <p sl="en">This report also stresses that, while we must deal with terrorist financing, it is ultimately through tackling the root causes of poverty, social exclusion and human rights abuses that we will defeat the destructive ideology that breeds terrorism. I have mentioned just a few of the examples of the practical solutions that are outlined in this report. Our citizens rightly expect us to keep them safe, and that is why I believe this report is important. It is a demonstration of the practical ways that the EU works for the people across Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-084-0000" speaker_id="4521" name="Charles Tannock" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it goes without saying that tackling and tracking terrorists’ financial resources is one of the key tools in our fight against global terrorism. I too welcome many of the recommendations in the Nart report and strongly support the overall endorsement of greater cooperation amongst the EU Member States in this area.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s clear that terrorism and its financing know no borders and this can only be tackled at the multilateral level. In the UK there is some evidence that ISIS may well have sold some of its antiquities smuggled out. As the UK leaves the EU, external and internal security will be one of the key areas where it is vital, no matter what else transpires for Britain, to stay plugged in.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I welcome the Prime Minister, Ms May’s positive comments in this regard during her Munich security conference speech and I hope that accommodation can be found to avoid a security cliff edge if no deal were to transpire during phase two of the negotiations. Finding ways to ensure data protection regulation alignment between the UK and the EU post-Brexit will also be one of the keys to unlocking coordination in the long term between the EU 27 and a post-Brexit Britain.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-085-0000" speaker_id="130100" name="Hilde Vautmans" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, first of all I would really like to thank my colleague Javier Nart for his excellent work and the very relevant initiative. Gracias Javier.</p>
      <p sl="de">Collega's, de burgers vragen ons natuurlijk om op te treden tegen terroristen en dus moeten we er ook voor zorgen dat we de financiering van de terroristen droogleggen. Daarom denk ik dat de aanbevelingen die we vandaag vanuit het Parlement naar de Commissie en de commissaris sturen om die financiële stromen echt droog te leggen heel belangrijk zijn.</p>
      <p sl="de">Ze zijn heel concreet, mijnheer de commissaris. U heeft ze opgesomd: meer controle op de grote en, zoals de anderen zeggen, de kleine transacties. Meer controles op die prepaidkaarten. Kijken welke giften er naar het buitenland gaan. Wat gebeurt er met de geldstromen naar de moskeeën?</p>
      <p sl="de">We moeten niet onnozel zijn. Terroristen hebben financiering nodig als ze terroristische aanslagen willen plegen. Vandaar dat ik ook heel blij ben met het inlichtingenplatform rond financiën dat we vandaag vragen om op te richten.</p>
      <p sl="de">Maar, collega's, ik wil vandaag nog een stap verder gaan. Sedert 2014 zijn er in Europa 17 aanslagen gebeurd en als je gewoon kijkt naar de daders, dan zaten van de meeste aanslagen één of meerdere daders in één of meerdere databanken. Daarom wil ik van dit moment vandaag gebruikmaken om nog eens een statement te maken. We moeten verder gaan. We moeten gaan naar een echte Europese inlichtingendienst.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-087-0000" speaker_id="125091" name="Σοφία Σακοράφα" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, καταρχήν θέλω να ευχαριστήσω τον κύριο Nart, γιατί κατάφερε να παρουσιάσει μια συμπεριληπτική και ισορροπημένη έκθεση. Κύριοι συνάδελφοι, δεκαεννιά χρόνια από το πρώτο σχετικό ψήφισμα των Ηνωμένων Εθνών, σήμερα δρουν περισσότερες τρομοκρατικές οργανώσεις με περισσότερα χρήματα από ποτέ. Η πραγματικότητα αυτή δεν πρόκειται να αλλάξει όσο εμμένουμε, μονοσήμαντα, στην αποτροπή της χρηματοδότησης των τρομοκρατών μέσω του διεθνούς χρηματοπιστωτικού συστήματος. Εξάλλου, το σύστημα αυτό είναι που αναπτύσσει και υιοθετεί ορισμένα από τα μέσα που χρησιμοποιούν οι τρομοκράτες για τη χρηματοδότησή τους. Επιπλέον, οι περισσότερες επιθέσεις στην Ευρώπη απαιτούν σήμερα πολύ λίγους πόρους και οι τρομοκράτες χρησιμοποιούν μεθόδους μεταφοράς και συγκέντρωσης κεφαλαίων που αποφεύγουν το διεθνές χρηματοπιστωτικό σύστημα. Είναι υποκριτικό να προσποιούμαστε ότι προσπαθούμε να καταπολεμήσουμε την τρομοκρατία όταν συνεργαζόμαστε με χώρες που εσκεμμένα επιτρέπουν την εκκόλαψή της.</p>
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Επίτροπε, πείτε μας ποια είναι τα κράτη και τα καθεστώτα με τα οποία συνεργάζεται η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση, παρόλο που αυτά έχουν εμπλακεί έμμεσα ή άμεσα στη χρηματοδότηση τρομοκρατικών οργανώσεων; Πείτε μας ποιος τους εξοπλίζει; Πείτε μας τι κάνετε για να βοηθήσετε τις περιοχές στις οποίες αναπτύσσονται τρομοκρατικές οργανώσεις ώστε να αντιμετωπίσουν τις παράνομες οικονομικές δομές που τις τροφοδοτούν; Πότε εργαστήκατε πραγματικά για την προώθηση της ανάπτυξης στις περιοχές αυτές; Πότε εργαστήκατε για τη βελτίωση της διακυβέρνησης και την καταπολέμηση της διαφθοράς στις περιοχές αυτές; Σε αυτά θα πρέπει να επικεντρωθεί η πολιτική σας στη μάχη κατά της τρομοκρατίας, αν πραγματικά πιστεύετε ότι μπορείτε και θέλετε να την νικήσετε.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-088-0000" speaker_id="125214" name="Bronis Ropė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verts/ALE frakcijos vardu. – Iš tikrųjų sveikinu ir džiaugiuosi pranešėjo parengtu darbu, kuris, manau, ypatingai svarbus šios dienos kontekste. Taip pat noriu atkreipti dėmesį į dvi kertines spragas, kurias turime pašalinti. Tai, visų pirma, bankinės veiklos skaidrumas. Nors bankinė sistema yra laikoma per daug svarbi, kad būtų galima imtis radikalių reformų, visgi skaidrumas ir, visų pirma, efektyvios priemonės, skirtos mokesčių rojams sunaikinti, apsunkintų terorizmo finansavimą ir padėtų visos Europos ekonomikos konkurencingumui. Antra – ideologinė. Didžioji dalis teroristinių grupuočių veikia religiniu pagrindu. Gal visgi pats laikas pagalvoti apie tai, kad Europa turėtų imtis realių veiksmų, kad skatintų demokratinių religinių judėjimų atsiradimą kaip savotišką krikščionių demokratų partijos analogą. Tai taptų gyvybinga alternatyva religiniam ekstremizmui ir sudarytų galimybes šiuo metu marginalizuotų konfesijų atstovams save išreikšti demokratiniame politiniame gyvenime.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-089-0000" speaker_id="124971" name="James Carver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Commissioner, despite the myriad rules and regulations introduced into the banking system, I strongly believe that the only way to stop the flow of funds to jihadists is to physically deny them their safe havens. We know sympathisers raise funds across the globe and extort money through kidnapping and other crimes to support these wicked people. However, the greatest funding comes from control of a territory, especially territory such as we’ve seen in Iraq, with natural resources such as oil and gas. It is imperative that we prevent jihadists from controlling such areas and incumbent on nation states – not the European Union – to protect their citizens by empowering their military forces to take whatever necessary action.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-090-0000" speaker_id="124751" name="Dominique Martin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Madame la Présidente, Madrid, Londres, Paris, voilà plus de dix ans que nous attendons ce rapport. Devons-nous rappeler que les attentats terroristes en Europe, c’est 2 400 morts depuis 2001? 2 400 morts depuis 2001! Que les revenus annuels de Daech s’élèveraient à 3 milliards de dollars? 3 milliards de dollars!</p>
      <p sl="en">Évidemment que nous devons nous assurer de ne pas participer à ce financement, notamment par l’achat du pétrole. Mais que nous proposez-vous? Que nous proposez-vous? De confier notre sécurité aux institutions européennes et aux établissements bancaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sur 100 dollars blanchis dans le monde, les banques n’en interceptent que 80 centimes – le prix d’une baguette – démontrant ainsi leur impuissance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quant aux institutions européennes, elles soutiennent – et je cite Mme Mogherini, haute représentante de l’Union européenne pour la politique de sécurité – que «l’islam politique a sa place en Europe». L’islam politique a sa place en Europe. Souhaitez-vous vraiment leur confier notre sécurité?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-091-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, ο ISIS μπορεί να έχει ηττηθεί στρατιωτικά σε όλα τα μέτωπα, πλην όμως, για να καταπολεμηθεί αποτελεσματικά η τρομοκρατική δραστηριότητα των τζιχαντιστών πρέπει να διακοπεί ή να περιοριστεί τουλάχιστον η δυνατότητα χρηματοδότησης τους. Η προσπάθεια αυτή είναι δύσκολη, διότι οι τρομοκράτες μεταβάλλουν συνεχώς τις μεθόδους χρηματοδότησης. Αυτή τη στιγμή, γνωρίζουμε ότι η χρηματοδότηση των τρομοκρατών γίνεται κυρίως μέσω τραπεζών δυτικών αλλά και αραβικών χωρών, οι οποίες τις υποστηρίζουν απροκάλυπτα, καθώς επίσης και από δωρεές υποστηρικτών με μικρά ποσά, τα οποία προέρχονται από κέρδη μικρών επιχειρήσεων και έτσι παρακάμπτεται το χρηματοπιστωτικό σύστημα. Για το λόγο αυτό, πρέπει να υπάρξει συνεργασία όλων των αρχών και των υπηρεσιών ασφαλείας όλων των χωρών, ούτως ώστε να υπάρξει ανταλλαγή πληροφοριών. Πρέπει επίσης να ελέγχονται στις τράπεζες οι λογαριασμοί των υπόπτων καταθετών. Αυτό όμως δεν επιτρέπει την παραβίαση των δικαιωμάτων των καταθετών. Δεν πρέπει επίσης να χρησιμοποιηθεί για τη δίωξη πολιτικών αντιπάλων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-092-0000" speaker_id="28306" name="Ana Gomes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, este relatório de Javier Nart é muito importante. O Daexe não acabou, mesmo se territorialmente derrotado. Acabaram outras cabeças da rede terrorista, da Al Qaeda ao Boko Haram. O combate ao terrorismo tem de estar no centro da agenda da segurança da União Europeia, em particular com atenção à região MENA, sem o deixar instrumentalizar por ambições políticas, geopolíticas e sectárias de Estados regionais.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prioritário neste contexto é o seguimento e bloqueio do financiamento às redes terroristas via sistemas como as wallets e criptomoedas, mas também investindo em negócios legais, em particular no Iraque, na Turquia, mas também na própria União Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">O próprio Comissário Moscovici, num relatório sobre a «fraude carrocel» no IVA, há um ano, mostrou que 50 mil milhões de euros por ano são desviados e reciclados por organizações terroristas, incluindo grupos terroristas como a Al Qaeda.</p>
      <p sl="en">Os nossos Estados-Membros continuam a recusar as reformas que foram propostas no sistema de IVA para obviar a isto. A quarta diretiva contra o branqueamento de capitais ainda não está a ser implementada por vários Estados-Membros e os Estados-Membros recusaram, no âmbito da quinta diretiva, a criação de uma unidade de investigação financeira europeia, que é absolutamente indispensável para combater o financiamento do terrorismo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-093-0000" speaker_id="124875" name="Anders Primdahl Vistisen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Det er glædeligt, at Europa-Parlamentet med den betænkning, som vi behandler i dag, og med nedsættelsen af et udvalg, der ser på antiterrorisme, begynder at tage truslen fra og kampen mod terror alvorligt. I alt for mange år har Europa-Parlamentet været stopklods for effektiv antiterrorlovgivning. Vi kan bare se på hele processen omkring det at få vedtaget europæiske PNR-regler. Derfor glæder jeg mig også over denne betænkning og ordførerens arbejde. Jeg er dog ked af, at vi ved afstemningen i AFET nedstemte en række ECR-forslag, der kunne have gjort betænkningen endnu mere robust og endnu mere effektiv med hensyn til at forhindre finansiering af terrorisme. Især har den statslige sponsering af terrorisme, som vi ser fra visse lande i Mellemøsten, desværre ikke fået den rolle i betænkningen, som vi i ECR-Gruppen gerne havde set. Derfor håber jeg, at vi kan tackle de udfordringer, som statssponseret terrorisme forårsager, mere effektivt i forbindelse med vores anbefalinger fra udvalget vedrørende terrorisme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-094-0000" speaker_id="188445" name="André Elissen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, Europa is de afgelopen jaren opgeschrikt door talloze door de islam geïnspireerde en gelegitimeerde terroristische aanslagen. Volgens de EU-coördinator voor terrorismebestrijding zijn er meer dan 50 000 geradicaliseerde moslims in Europa. Toch komt het woord islam precies nul keer terug in het verslag, nul keer. Wat dit Parlement doet is niet meer dan een druppel op een gloeiende plaat. De titel van dat verslag is goed. De inhoud is volstrekt onvoldoende. Er wordt gesproken over onzinnige termen als islamofobie en zogenaamde aanvallen op moslims. Dit terwijl islamieten verantwoordelijk zijn voor 99 % van alle terroristische moorden in 2015 en 95 % van alle terroristische moorden in 2016. Voorzitter, dat zijn niet mijn gegevens, maar de gegevens van Europol. Critici krijgen een stempel opgedrukt islamofoob te zijn, terwijl de echte oorzaak, de islam, niet wordt benoemd. Het is de omgekeerde wereld. Voorzitter, wat ons betreft is er geen plaats in Europa voor jihadisten en geradicaliseerde moslims en worden de grenzen onmiddellijk gesloten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-095-0000" speaker_id="124870" name="Jeppe Kofod" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! I centrum af København står der store betonklodser overalt, og i de fleste andre europæiske storbyer ser man samme syn. De pynter ikke i bybilledet, men de er der af en grund: For at beskytte os mod terror, for at stoppe dem, der vil os det ondt!</p>
      <p sl="en">Ligesom vi sætter fysiske stopklodser for terrorisme i vores byer, skal vi også sætte reguleringsmæssige stopklodser for dem, der finansierer terror.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desværre er der alt for mange banker, som sætter profitter over principper. De holder ikke styr på, hvem der overfører penge til hvem, og hvilke lommer pengene havner i. Dertil kommer også, at europæiske banker uforvarende er med til at finansiere, til at medvirke til finansiering af terror og terrororganisationer via hvidvask, sjusk og svindel. Hvidvask nærer og muliggør terror, og begge næres bedst i mørke. Derfor er det på høje tid, at vi slår hårdt ned på de hvidvaskningsbanker, som ikke tager deres ansvar alvorligt. Tak for en god betænkning og den vigtige beslutning, vi træffer her i Parlamentet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-096-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Уважаема г-жо Председател, уважаеми колеги, последните години неведнъж сме обсъждали и коментирали заплахата за сигурността на европейските граждани, която поражда връзката на ислямистките организации, крайния радикален ислямизъм, с терористичните групи на европейска територия.</p>
      <p sl="en">Последните години коментирахме, обсъждахме и разглеждахме въпроса за финансирането на Ислямска държава, ДАЕШ, Ал Кайда, Ал Нусра и други подобни заплахи за нашия начин на живот. В хода на войната тези терористични организации загубиха над 90% от своите територии и много от бойците си от кървавите кампании за Рака и Мосул. Това принуди Ислямска държава да се върне към своята клетъчна структура, оформена и разработена в периода 2009 – 2011 г. Не бива да приемаме това като победа, а по-скоро като малка крачка към разгрома на джихадизма.</p>
      <p sl="en">Длъжен съм да отбележа, че заради териториалните загуби и търговията с петрол Ислямска държава вече се преориентира към разпространението на наркотици и оръжие. Тези стоки идват основно по канали от Африка и Азия. Трябва да отбележим финансирането на джихадистки групи от Република Турция, Саудитска Арабия и други държави в Персийския залив. Ние трябва да поставим твърди условия за прекратяване на това финансиране, защото е пряка заплаха за националната сигурност за всички държави и членове на Европейския парламент.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-098-0000" speaker_id="2002" name="José Ignacio Salafranca Sánchez-Neyra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, quisiera felicitar al señor Nart por este informe, que se sitúa directamente en el centro de las preocupaciones de nuestros ciudadanos y que, si tiene un mérito, es el de presentar un catálogo de propuestas concretas: por ejemplo, la plataforma estable de cooperación de los servicios de inteligencia financiera en el marco de Europol, el catálogo de empresas, bancos o entidades financieras que tienen deficiencias en lo que se refiere al blanqueo de dinero o la cooperación con países terceros a través del diálogo político, la asistencia financiera y el refuerzo de su capacidad antiterrorista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que tenemos que felicitarnos por esta colaboración entre el GAFI y el Consejo de Cooperación del Golfo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Me parece que este informe, señora presidenta, pone también claramente de manifiesto una serie de deberes a la Comisión para que haga las propuestas oportunas, al Consejo para que aplique con eficacia las sanciones, a los Estados miembros y al Servicio de Acción Exterior, para, como nos decía el comisario, poder dar una respuesta adecuada a esta lacra que amenaza nuestras sociedades.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-099-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Commissioner, dear colleagues, first of all, from 2014 to 2017 – in four years – we have seen 45 big terrorist attacks in Europe that caused hundreds of victims. This situation cannot continue, Commissioner. The security of EU citizens has to become the first priority of the European Union’s specialised institutions. I believe that law enforcement and prevention strategy are important, both among EU Member States and in the European Union’s external relations. The fight against Daesh and Al-Qaeda should remain at the top of the security agenda in Europe, but of course in the Middle East as well, and not be diverted, especially in the Middle East, to pursuing particular political and sectarian agendas of the regional actors. I strongly believe that, in our fight against terrorists, we need to focus our efforts on police and judicial cooperation and on exchanging information and data and good practices so as to strengthen synergies in the global …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-100-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, η μείωση των πηγών εσόδων των τζιχαντιστών θα γίνει βεβαίως όταν μπει στο στόχαστρο η χρηματοδότηση η δική τους και φυσικά η χρηματοδότηση της τρομοκρατίας. Για να γίνει αυτό, πρέπει φυσικά να ελέγξουμε τις χώρες οι οποίες στήριξαν τους τζιχαντιστές και ξέρουμε ποιες είναι. Είναι η Σαουδική Αραβία, το Κατάρ και η Τουρκία. Η Τουρκία έκανε λαθρεμπόριο καυσίμων στηρίζοντας τους ίδιους τους τζιχαντιστές. Επομένως, εκεί πρέπει να στραφούμε. Πρέπει να βρούμε τρόπους για να παγώσουν τα περιουσιακά στοιχεία αυτών, οι οποίοι πραγματικά λειτουργούν υπέρ των τζιχαντιστών, στην Τουρκία και στις άλλες χώρες. Είναι πολύ συγκεκριμένα τα μέτρα που πρέπει να πάρουμε. Επιπλέον, πρέπει να ελέγξουμε και τα τεράστια ποσά, το ξέπλυμα χρήματος που γίνεται στο ποδόσφαιρο. Πολλές αραβικές χώρες στηρίζουν ποδοσφαιρικές ομάδες, με στόχο την παραπέρα ριζοσπαστικοποίηση των φτωχών μουσουλμανικών πληθυσμών. Όλα αυτά πρέπει να τα δούμε για να μπορέσουμε να αντιμετωπίσουμε τους τζιχαντιστές.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-101-0000" speaker_id="125070" name="Λάμπρος Φουντούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, στο εξαιρετικά σημαντικό πρόβλημα της τρομοκρατίας και ειδικά δε στο πρόβλημα της ισλαμικής τρομοκρατίας, είμαστε εξαρχής κάθετοι και ξεκάθαροι. Καμία ανοχή στους τρομοκράτες, επιπλέον όμως καμία ανοχή και σε όσους υποστηρίζουν ή χρηματοδοτούν τις ενέργειές τους. Δυστυχώς, δεν έχει γίνει μέχρι τώρα κανένα σοβαρό βήμα ως προς την ημιεπίσημη κρατική χρηματοδότηση τρομοκρατικών οργανώσεων. Χαρακτηριστικό παράδειγμα είναι η περίπτωση της Τουρκίας, για την οποία αποτελεί πλέον κοινό μυστικό πως για μεγάλο χρονικό διάστημα χρηματοδοτούσε το Ισλαμικό Χαλιφάτο μέσω του λαθρεμπορίου πετρελαίου. Επίσης, όλοι σε αυτήν εδώ την αίθουσα γνωρίζουμε τον επιεικώς αμφιλεγόμενο ρόλο της Σαουδικής Αραβίας, του Κατάρ και άλλων κρατών του Κόλπου και την απροκάλυπτη ορισμένες φορές στήριξη που παρέχουν στις διάφορες ισλαμιστικές οργανώσεις που λειτουργούν ως συγκοινωνούντα δοχεία με τους τρομοκράτες. Ειδικά δε ο πόλεμος στη Συρία έχει υπάρξει εξαιρετικά αποκαλυπτικός όσον αφορά το ρόλο των κρατών αυτών. Θα πρέπει λοιπόν να ελεγχθούν οι ύποπτες χρηματοδοτήσεις που πολύ συχνά είναι καλυμμένες με τον μανδύα των φιλανθρωπικών ιδρυμάτων. Όταν και όπου διαπιστώνονται τέτοιου είδους συναλλαγές, θα πρέπει να επιβάλλονται πολύ αυστηρές κυρώσεις - όχι μόνο σε πρόσωπα αλλά και στα ίδια τα κράτη.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-102-0000" speaker_id="186884" name="Arndt Kohn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Ich möchte dem Auswärtigen Ausschuss für den Initiativbericht zur Bekämpfung der Terrorismusfinanzierung herzlich danken. Der Bericht ist ein wichtiger Anstoß für das Parlament, mit der Verordnung über die Einfuhr von Kulturgütern endlich voranzukommen. Letzte Woche wurden die Ergebnisse der Operationen Athena und Pandora 2 von Interpol und der World Customs Organization bekannt, bei der 41 000 illegal gehandelte Kunstobjekte – darunter viele antike – beschlagnahmt wurden. Der Handel mit Kunst und Kulturgütern ist mittlerweile genauso ausgeprägt wie der Drogen- oder Waffenhandel; den Zusammenhang mit der Terrorfinanzierung haben die VN bereits 2015 festgestellt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir dürfen nicht zulassen, dass durch fehlende Zollbestimmungen ein derartiges Businessmodell funktioniert und Anschläge in Europa und anderswo finanziert. Ich fordere das Parlament und alle Mitgliedstaaten auf, sich für bessere Zollkontrollen, bessere Weiterbildung der Zollbeamten und effektive internationale Kooperationen einzusetzen. Denn nur gemeinsam können wir illegalen Handel mit Kulturgütern bekämpfen und Anschläge verhindern …</p>
      <a text="(Die Präsidentin entzieht dem Redner das Wort.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-103-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospođo predsjednice, ukidanje izvora prihoda džihadističkim organizacijama temelj je učinkovite borbe protiv terorizma. Podržavam sve mehanizme kojima ćemo učinkovito suzbiti financiranje terorizma, uključujući i bolji nadzor vjerskih ustanova za koje postoje indicije da su uključene u širenje ekstremizma, ali ti mehanizmi moraju biti dovoljno selektivni da ne zahvate nedužne građane i negativno utječu na njihove slobode.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ne smijemo zaboraviti ni to da financijska i logistička pomoć teroristima, izravno ili neizravno, često dolazi i od nas samih. Naša licemjerna vanjska politika koja se odbija jasno odrediti prema nekim zemljama koje su dokazani sponzori međunarodnog terorizma i priznavanje te naoružavanje skupina koje nam nisu istinski partneri također doprinose jačanju džihadista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za svoje dobro moramo biti puno dosljedniji i oprezniji, što znači da konačno moramo imati pravu strategiju, a ne se voditi dnevnopolitičkim motivima.</p>
      <a text="(Govornica je pristala odgovoriti na pitanje postavljeno podizanjem plave kartice (članak 162. stavak 8. Poslovnika))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-104-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonașului albastru”. – Doamnă președintă, stimată colegă, în principiu sunt de acord cu ce ați spus dumneavoastră. Dar ați spus, între altele, că noi suntem de vină, că noi nu am luat măsuri suficiente. Puteți să ne spuneți ce ar trebui să facă Parlamentul, Uniunea Europeană, Comisia, pentru a pune capăt finanțării terorismului și a actelor de terorism? Pentru că e bine să criticăm, dar să venim și cu soluții.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-105-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">odgovor na pitanje postavljeno podizanjem plave kartice. – Kolegice, vi jako dobro znate da neke države članice trguju još uvijek s onima za koje je rečeno da ne smijemo trgovati. Dakle, jedno ovdje govorimo, drugo radimo. Ako se donesu zakoni da svi zajedno moramo raditi na suzbijanju korupcije, onda svi zajedno moramo raditi, a ne da neke države mogu, a neke ne mogu. Dakle, prema svima bi trebali biti isti zakoni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-107-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Julian King" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to express particular thanks to Mr Nart for the report and thank everyone for today’s important debate.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want to caution against the suggestion that in some way we have a defeated Daesh. We have made very welcome progress on the ground against the so-called caliphate, but Jihadi extremist terrorism remains active in a number of countries and the terrorist threat – including to us here in Europe – remains very high. They are still able to produce and spread poisonous propaganda. We will be announcing some new measures to tackle that aspect of the problem later today. They still have access to significant sources of funding and funds that they have previously raised.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why the work that you’ve been highlighting in this report to disrupt the sources of revenue of terrorist organisations, to limit their capacity to move and use funds and to support law enforcement in their efforts to detect financial movements of terrorists, in order to identify them and frustrate their plans and tackle the networks, is so important.</p>
      <p sl="en">I agree with those who’ve underlined the importance of making progress on information exchange and information-sharing. We have made some progress, there is still more that needs to be done. With the help and support of this House, I hope that this year we will be able to agree to further strengthen the key law-enforcement and information-sharing networks and databases and make sure that they work together effectively.</p>
      <p sl="en">In particular, we’re going to come forward with further proposals to strengthen the network of financial intelligence units and the ability of law enforcement to work with those units, and I hope you will support that.</p>
      <p sl="en">I agree with those who’ve spoken about the transnational character of the terrorist threat, and that is why we need a common European approach. That approach needs to be rooted in and complementary with actions taken at national level and international cooperation. That’s our objective. That’s the work that we’re pursuing, with your help and support, to continue to build an effective security union to better protect our citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-108-0000" speaker_id="125005" name="Javier Nart" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, una cuestión tan extraordinariamente sensible como importante: más de doscientas ochenta enmiendas, un consenso completo, los grupos satisfechos, el comisario King contento y yo también.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-109-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place shortly.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-110-0000" speaker_id="28257" name="Ivo Belet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftelijk. – De aanpak en preventie van terrorismefinanciering zijn cruciaal in de strijd tegen terreur. Zodra de geldbronnen opdrogen, wordt het een stuk moeilijker voor terroristen om hun activiteiten uit te voeren. Daarom moeten we zo snel mogelijk een beter zicht krijgen op die geldstromen, en schimmige transacties onderscheppen en bestraffen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dat is echter alleen mogelijk als ook de samenwerking op Europees niveau optimaal verloopt. Concreet moet de oprichting van een Europees inlichtingenplatform voor terrorismefinanciering de info-uitwisseling tussen de nationale inlichtingendiensten verder verbeteren. Het Parlement wil ook dat er een Europees financieel traceringssysteem komt om de betalingsverrichtingen van en naar terreurnetwerken efficiënt te kunnen opsporen.</p>
      <p sl="en">De nieuwe antiwitwasrichtlijn waarover de EU eind vorig jaar een akkoord bereikte, is al een belangrijke stap vooruit in de strijd tegen terrorismefinanciering. Zo moeten inlichtingendiensten makkelijker toegang krijgen tot bankregisters bij gegronde vermoedens van terroristische connecties. Maar inlichtingendiensten moeten die informatie ook onderling efficiënt uitwisselen. België speelt ter zake al een voortrekkersrol, met o.a. het verbod op anonieme prepaidkaarten. Laat ons zulke goede praktijken ook met andere lidstaten delen, om zo een doeltreffende en proactieve, op Europese leest geschoeide aanpak uit te werken.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-110-5000" speaker_id="23868" name="Monika Beňová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne – Účinný boj proti terorizmu a prevencia súvisiacich hrozieb si vyžaduje cielené opatrenia zamerané na zastavenie jednotlivých foriem jeho financovania. Odstrihnutie teroristických sietí od peňažných zdrojov je z pohľadu posilňovania bezpečnosti kľúčové. Nevyhnutnou súčasťou týchto snáh je ďalší rozvoj spolupráce spravodajských zložiek jednotlivých členských štátov Európskej únie. Cieľom nie je vytváranie nových inštitúcií či orgánov na európskej úrovni, ale posilnenie koordinácie v rámci existujúcich systémov výmeny informácií. Terorizmus je ohrozením pre slobodu európskych krajín a ich obyvateľov. Efektívny boj proti organizovaným skupinám, ale aj jednotlivcom ohrozujúcim bezpečnosť občanov je preto najvyššou prioritou. Nesmieme pripustiť, aby bol naďalej ohrozovaný systém práv a istôt, ktorý je dôležitou súčasťou európskeho integračného projektu. Hlavným cieľom všetkých extrémistov a radikálov bez rozdielu je šírenie zmätku, nárast strachu a chaosu v spoločnosti. Akékoľvek prijímané opatrenia preto musia byť komplexné a racionálne, a to aj z dôvodu, že vždy predstavujú istú mieru záťaže pre verejné rozpočty.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-111-0000" speaker_id="96697" name="Valdemar Tomaševski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Gerbiamas Pirmininke, pasaulis ir Europa nuo daugelio metų grumiasi su islamistinio pagrindo terorizmu. Vienas iš pagrindinių kovos su terorizmu elementų yra jo finansavimo, įskaitant naudojantis slaptomis sukčiavimo ir mokesčių slėpimo, pinigų plovimo ir mokesčių rojų grandinėmis, šaltinių atkirtimas. Teisėtos kilmės finansavimą gavėjas gali, deja, nukreipti trečiosioms šalims, individams, grupėms, įmonėms ar subjektams, susijusiems su teroristine veikla. Verta paminėti, kad terorizmas yra pasaulinio masto nusikaltimas, taigi veiksmingas atsakas taip pat turi būti pasaulinio masto ir visa apimantis, kartu vykdant tarptautinį finansų įstaigų, teisėsaugos institucijų ir teisminių institucijų koordinavimą, o keitimasis susijusia informacija apie fizinius ir juridinius asmenis ir įtartiną veiklą yra būtinas, turint mintyje, kad asmens duomenų apsauga ir privatumo užtikrinimas yra svarbios pagrindinės teisės. Dėl to verta paremti ataskaitoje esantį įrašą, raginantį ES Tarybą sugriežtinti tikslinių sankcijų ir kitų ribojamųjų priemonių taikymą visiems asmenims ir subjektams, kurie bet kuriuo būdu teikia ekonominius išteklius ISIS/„Da’esh“, „Al-Qaida“ ar kitoms džihadistų grupuotėms.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-111-5000" speaker_id="125104" name="Romana Tomc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pisno. – Podpiram predlog parlamenta, saj so preventivne strategije, ki temeljijo na izmenjavi najboljših praks in izmenjavi sumljivih ustreznih informacij med obveščevalnimi službami, bistvene v boju proti financiranju terorizma oz. terorističnih napadov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Onemogočanje virov financiranja terorističnih mrež naj bo prednostna naloga, saj je to učinkovito orodje za zmanjševanje uspešnosti teh mrež. Vzpostavitev mreže strokovnjakov za boj proti terorizmu v delegacijah EU, zagotovitev financiranja za programe, namenjene spodbujanju izmenjave najboljših praks med obveščevalnimi službami znotraj držav članic EU kot tudi tretjih držav, so nujno potrebni ukrepi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poziv državam članicam naj oblikujejo skupne preiskovalne enote z Europolom, ki bodo skrbele za nadzor sumljivih organizacij, ki se ukvarjajo z dejavnostmi, kot so nezakonita trgovina, tihotapljenje, ponarejanje in goljufive prakse, je zelo pozitiven. Nujno potrebujemo programe in sredstva držav članic, da bi lahko ti programi bili uspešni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-112-0000" speaker_id="96774" name="Jarosław Wałęsa" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I would like first to congratulate the rapporteur, Mr Nart, on a very good report with a catalogue of specific solutions. Combating the financing of terrorism is a demanding topic and I agree that it should be a key priority, as it constitutes a useful tool in hampering the effectiveness of terrorist networks. All Member States should make every effort, and should take joint action, to cut the flow of funds and other financial assets and economic resources to individuals and entities on the ISIL (Daesh) and al-Qaeda sanctions list.</p>
      <p sl="en">We repeatedly underline how extremely important it is that information sharing among financial intelligence units should be improved and speeded up. Therefore, it is a crucial aspect of the sharing of best practices among intelligence agencies. The report rightly pointed to the investigation and analysis of terrorists and of terrorist organisations’ methods of recruiting and the transfer of terrorist financing. There is no doubt that, as the EU, we must continue to oppose cruel and unacceptable acts of terrorism. We should remember that the fight against terrorism is fundamental to the security of European society. We are required to take appropriate measures in response to every type of threat against our citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. EU priorities for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-114-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the report by Izaskun Bilbao Barandica and Ángela Vallina, on behalf of the Committee on Women’s Rights and Gender Equality, on a European Parliament recommendation to the Council on the EU priorities for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women (2017/2194(INI)) (A8—0022/2018).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-115-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, señora comisaria, quiero comenzar esta intervención agradeciendo muy especialmente a Ángela Vallina su talante, sus ideas y entusiasmo para trabajar juntas en un informe que también agradece y saluda a las aportaciones de todas y todos los que han trabajado con nosotras. Creo que por primera vez en la historia de la humanidad hay un movimiento potente generalizado en favor de la igualdad que queremos ayudar a que progrese con trabajos como el que hoy presentamos.</p>
      <p sl="en">El texto que hoy debatimos va a ser la contribución que la Unión realizará este año al principal foro intergubernamental dedicado a promocionar la igualdad y el empoderamiento femenino: la Comisión de la Condición Jurídica y Social de la Mujer de las Naciones Unidas. Las instituciones comunitarias deben garantizar la plena participación del Parlamento y su Comisión de Derechos de la Mujer e Igualdad de Género en su 62.ª Asamblea, dedicada este año a mejorar la situación de las mujeres que viven en el medio rural y a poner especial atención a su acceso a las nuevas tecnologías y a los medios de comunicación.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Unión quiere asumir un papel protagonista en el impulso y fortalecimiento de un proceso que es justo, democrático y social y económicamente rentable. Es, por eso mismo, bueno para la humanidad en su conjunto y especialmente relevante para poder cumplir los Objetivos del Milenio, entre los que ocupa un lugar principal la lucha contra el hambre, la pobreza y la marginación. Y en ese proceso, las mujeres, su empoderamiento y su posición en pie de igualdad con los hombres son determinantes. Y lo son particularmente en el medio rural, en el que las mujeres de todo el mundo están llamadas a jugar un relevante papel si se propicia que sus capacidades y aportaciones se visibilicen y proyecten plenamente sobre las actividades productivas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Actualmente, en el mundo desarrollado, pero especialmente en los países en vías de desarrollo, las mujeres sufren una discriminación particularmente intensa en el medio rural. Informes de las Naciones Unidas estiman que cambiar esta situación incrementaría la productividad del sector primario en más de un 30 %, un progreso imprescindible para poder atender las previsiones de crecimiento demográfico para las próximas décadas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso, este informe plantea condiciones básicas para acabar con la discriminación y medidas específicas centradas en el medio rural y en el acceso a las nuevas tecnologías y los medios de comunicación, siguiendo el guion propuesto por las Naciones Unidas. Entre las condiciones generales, está la de intensificar el trabajo contra la violencia contra las mujeres y especialmente contra prácticas como los matrimonios forzados o la mutilación genital; además, avanzar en la formación, la educación y la dotación de servicios sociales universales y gratuitos para poder propiciar la igualdad de oportunidades entre hombres y mujeres. Un objetivo lastrado ahora por un evidente desequilibrio en el reparto de las tareas que están vinculadas a la logística doméstica y a los cuidados de niños y personas mayores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para propiciar en el mundo rural el desempeño profesional femenino, apostamos por un estatuto de la mujer profesional en el mundo rural, como el que ya está en vigor en el País Vasco. Sus pilares básicos son el acceso a la propiedad y titularidad o cotitularidad de las explotaciones y a los sistemas de seguridad social. Igualmente, el establecimiento de vías específicas de financiación para poder impulsar nuevas actividades y productos; una formación específica que incorpore habilidades digitales y modernice y dé otra dimensión al papel femenino en la creación de nuevos productos y su comercialización; la progresiva incorporación de las mujeres a los procesos de decisión, tanto en el ámbito público como en el sector privado, incluyendo desde las instituciones hasta las organizaciones de productores de cooperativas y empresas de producción y transformación; y una recopilación de datos estadísticos, sistemática y homogénea, que permita evaluar los resultados de las políticas en pro de la igualdad completa con este catálogo de medidas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estamos convencidas de que la consolidación de un estatuto de la mujer profesional en el ámbito rural que impulse, reconozca y proteja esta equiparación es una conquista, no solo de las mujeres, sino de la humanidad. Y esto va a ser especialmente visible si esta verdadera revolución en favor de la justicia y de la igualdad se acelera en los países en vías de desarrollo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, con su generosidad, deseo añadir solo una cuestión: lamento que, entre las noticias destacadas de este Parlamento, una vez más no se haya incluido un informe tan importante, cuando se trata de la igualdad de las mujeres en el mundo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-116-0000" speaker_id="125050" name="Ángela Vallina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, comisaria, en primer lugar, me gustaría agradecer, desde luego, a la señora Jourová, su participación en este debate, así como a mi colega, la coponente Izaskun Bilbao, su excelente trabajo y cooperación y todo el trabajo que hemos realizado conjuntamente en este informe; también quiero dar las gracias a los ponentes alternativos de los diferentes grupos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desde la Comisión de Derechos de la Mujer y de Igualdad de Género presentamos esta Recomendación del Parlamento al Consejo para el próximo periodo de sesiones de la Comisión Jurídica y Social de la Mujer de las Naciones Unidas, que comienza próximamente en Nueva York y en el que participará una delegación de este Parlamento, en la que estaremos nosotras.</p>
      <p sl="en">El tema prioritario de esta sesión es el empoderamiento de las mujeres y las niñas en el mundo rural, y en esta cuestión decidimos las coponentes centrar nuestro informe. Y es que se estima que más del 75 % de la población que vive en la extrema pobreza a nivel mundial se encuentra en las zonas rurales. El 90 % de los países en el mundo tiene al menos una ley que limita la igualdad económica de las mujeres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Millones de niñas en el mundo rural se ven privadas cada día del derecho a ir a la escuela porque, al no tener acceso ni al agua potable ni a la electricidad, son las responsables principales de ir a buscar agua o combustible para sus familias. Para ello, tienen que recorrer, en muchos casos, varios kilómetros, expuestas, además, a la violencia sexual en su trayecto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para romper el círculo de la pobreza es imprescindible impulsar el empoderamiento de las mujeres y las niñas rurales a través del acceso a la educación, a la sanidad y a los recursos productivos. Por eso, en nuestro informe, recomendamos al Consejo que, en el marco de la próxima sesión de la Comisión de las Naciones Unidas, promueva políticas destinadas a erradicar la pobreza y a garantizar un nivel de vida adecuado para grupos particularmente vulnerables, como las mujeres y las niñas, y especialmente a través del sistema de protección social; programas que garanticen que las mujeres y sus familias tengan acceso a sistemas universales de protección social que incidan en su futura situación de jubilación y contribuyan así a reducir la brecha de las pensiones de naturaleza pluridimensional; el derecho y el acceso a una atención sanitaria universal y de calidad, que se adecúe a las necesidades de las mujeres y las niñas rurales y, en particular, por lo que respecta a la salud y a sus derechos sexuales y reproductivos; el acceso universal a servicios adecuados de cuidado de la infancia y de las personas mayores en zonas rurales; que las mujeres y las niñas rurales puedan acceder fácilmente a créditos y recursos productivos y que reciban apoyo en sus iniciativas económicas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y le recomendamos asimismo que garantice los derechos de propiedad de las mujeres rurales, en particular su derecho a ser propietarias de explotaciones agrarias y a heredar tierras, lo que constituye una herramienta muy importante para su empoderamiento económico y les permite participar plenamente en el desarrollo de las zonas rurales y beneficiarse del mismo; que condene todas las formas de violencia contra las mujeres y garantice que no se prive a ninguna de las víctimas en zonas rurales y aisladas de un acceso igualitario a la asistencia y protección; que desarrolle políticas de empleo, servicios y programas dirigidos a atender situaciones precarias de aquellas mujeres rurales que, a menudo, trabajan en el sector informal y que pueden enfrentarse a múltiples formas de discriminación interseccional por sexo, edad, clase, religión, etnia, discapacidad o identidad de género; que proporcione asistencia y apoyo adaptados a las necesidades e intereses; que garantice los derechos humanos fundamentales de los trabajadores migrantes y estacionales y de sus familias, en especial de las mujeres y las niñas, y que promueva su integración en las comunidades locales; que promueva la incorporación de la perspectiva de género.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y solamente quiero añadir que en un momento crítico, en el que se está produciendo efectivamente un retroceso por primera vez en décadas en los derechos de la mujer y las niñas a nivel mundial, hacemos un llamamiento al Parlamento Europeo para que apoye esta Recomendación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-117-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, later this month the United Nations Commission on the Status of Women will hold its 62nd session in New York.</p>
      <p sl="en">This year the priority theme is the empowerment of rural women and girls, while the review theme is participation in, and access of women to, the media and information and communication technologies and their impact on, and use as, an instrument for the advancement and empowerment of women. I am happy that, as in previous years, there will be an EU delegation representing the team of Europe led by my colleague, Neven Mimica, with Members of the European Parliament as part of the EU delegation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The position of women and the full enjoyment of their human rights by women and girls are still areas of concern for us in 2018. Progress on these topics is by no means a given. In fact, we have seen attempts to go backwards and to call into question once again the rights of women and girls, including in Europe. We discussed these questions thoroughly, together with many stakeholders, during the Annual Colloquium on Fundamental Rights in November last year.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this global context, the EU is one of the world leaders in gender equality. We are by far the biggest investor. With the EUR 500 million EU-UN Spotlight Initiative, the latest commitment to collaborate with other international organisations in combating violence against women, a global alliance is being formed. And, to mitigate gender—based violence in humanitarian crises, the EU has taken over the leadership for the call to action on protection from gender-based violence in emergencies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, the EU will strive for the session to adopt agreed conclusions that take into account the particular reality of rural women and girls world-wide, that challenge social norms and gender stereotypes, that promote equal economic independence for women and men, that promote women’s participation in decision—making at all levels, and that strengthen the prevention of all forms of violence against women and girls and the protection of its victims.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank Parliament for drafting such a comprehensive document that captures the priorities related to this year’s priority team very well. The Members of the European Parliament have an important role to play, complementary to that of the Member States and the other EU institutions. I am very happy to be here today, and I welcome this opportunity to listen to your views on priorities for the upcoming session.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-118-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I am aware that there are a lot of people who would like to contribute to the debate in catch the eye. However, I think that catch the eye is not possible because of the time constraints. I apologise to colleagues who would like to contribute, so please contribute in writing. I would ask those who now take the floor to adhere to their time please.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-119-0000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime Kluba zastupnika PPE-a. – Gospođo predsjednice, ravnopravnost žena i muškaraca osnovna je vrijednost Europske unije, koja je sadržana i u Ugovoru o Europskoj uniji i promovira se kao temeljni prioritet u vanjskim aktivnostima Unije. Ova tema „Izazovi i mogućnosti u postizanju ravnopravnosti spolova i osnaživanju žena i djevojaka u ruralnim područjima” na 62. sjednici Vijeća Ujedinjenih naroda o položaju žena za mene je jako važna u cilju uklanjanja nejednakosti na temelju spola.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uzimajući u obzir porast urbanizacije velikog broja obitelji koje se sele iz ruralnih u gradska područja, vrlo je važno pružiti razne i dobro promišljene poticaje za mlade žene i obitelji da se razvijaju i napreduju u ruralnim područjima. Jedan od tih poticaja mora se usredotočiti na ravnopravnost žena i muškaraca budući da većina žena u svijetu živi u ruralnim područjima, a do sada se nije dovoljno raspravljalo o diskriminaciji žena u takvim područjima. Znamo svi da je obrazovanje važno i da ono igra ključnu ulogu u životu svake osobe. Potpuni pristup obrazovanju mora se pružiti svim ženama u ruralnim područjima za bolju kvalitetu života, ali i za uklanjanje razlike u plaćama između muškaraca i žena.</p>
      <p sl="en">Također moramo uzeti u obzir i klimatske promjene kojima svjedočimo, a koje najviše utječu na ruralna područja i na žene koje tamo žive. Čak i nakon desetljeća na međunarodnoj razini, a ne samo na razini Unije, jaz između muškaraca i žena ostaje velik, posebno u ruralnim područjima. Naša Unija mora predvoditi borbu protiv nejednakosti žena i muškaraca i zato ovu preporuku smatram dobrim materijalom i nadam se da ćemo u tom smjeru nastaviti dalje i da će Unija i dalje prednjačiti u borbi protiv nejednakosti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-120-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Ms Grapini has requested a blue card but as time is short in this debate I am afraid I am not going to be able to accept any blue cards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-121-0000" speaker_id="28298" name="Iratxe García Pérez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señora presidenta, comisaria, hoy traemos a debate una resolución que pretende fijar la posición de este Parlamento ante la posición que Europa —en este caso, el Consejo— debe llevar a la Comisión de la Condición Jurídica y Social de la Mujer de las Naciones Unidas. En esa asamblea se debatirá sobre muchas cuestiones y, sobre todo, acerca de la situación específica que viven en el mundo las mujeres del medio rural.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero agradecer el trabajo de la señora Bilbao y de la señora Vallina para generar un documento que ha surgido del debate y del trabajo de muchas y muchos de quienes participamos en estas actuaciones y que consideramos que es fundamental hablar de la condición de las mujeres en el medio rural.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablamos de una doble discriminación que sufren las mujeres en el medio rural. Hablamos de las dificultades de acceso al empleo, de las cuestiones referidas a la violencia de género, pero también de la necesidad de impulsar servicios públicos para garantizar el acceso de las mujeres a la educación o, por ejemplo, también a la sanidad y a los derechos de salud sexual y reproductiva. Y, en ese sentido, quiero recordar especialmente que hoy hace un año que se inició la plataforma SheDecides, donde cientos de miles de voces de mujeres y hombres clamaban contra la decisión de la Administración del señor Trump que, en esos momentos, planteaba el recorte de los fondos a las organizaciones que están trabajando en los derechos de salud sexual y reproductiva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablamos de la salud de las mujeres, hablamos de la salud de las niñas y no podemos correr el riesgo de obviar estos peligros. Por lo tanto, continuemos siendo muchas las voces a favor de los derechos de salud sexual y reproductiva de las mujeres en el mundo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-122-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Wśród priorytetów Unii Europejskiej na sesję ONZ w Nowym Jorku jest wzmocnienie ekonomicznej sytuacji kobiet mieszkających na terenach wiejskich. Myślę, że wszyscy doskonale wiemy, że kobietom na terenach wiejskich jest szczególnie trudno. Bardzo często wykonując tę samą ciężką fizycznie pracę co mężczyźni, otrzymują niższe wynagrodzenie. Mają trudniejszy dostęp do opieki zdrowotnej, edukacji, dokształcania.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bardzo dobrze, że dzisiaj właśnie o tych sprawach mówimy, bo możemy efektywnie poprawić sytuację kobiet poprzez ułatwienie dostępu do edukacji, usług zdrowotnych, usług medycznych, opieki społecznej. Musimy również mówić o tym, że kobiety powinny mieć zagwarantowane prawo do emerytury. Te kobiety, których życie skupia się na opiece nad osobami starszymi w rodzinie, nad chorymi, nad dziećmi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Będę więc popierała te wszystkie priorytety, które uważam za właściwe, dobre i słuszne. Bez zbędnej ideologii.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-123-0000" speaker_id="125040" name="Beatriz Becerra Basterrechea" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señora presidenta, señora Jourová, los medios de comunicación y las tecnologías de la información nos muestran cómo nos vemos a nosotros mismos, nuestra propia imagen como sociedad, y, al asomarnos a ellos, vemos que se mantienen demasiados estereotipos sobre hombres y mujeres, que seguimos ofreciendo a los jóvenes roles y visiones del pasado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las mejores iniciativas en favor de la igualdad de género se centran en combatir los prejuicios en los niños y jóvenes, en enseñar la igualdad y la no discriminación, en decir a las niñas que pueden ser lo que ellas quieran y que pueden querer lo mismo que los niños.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero estas iniciativas luchan con desventaja frente a la inercia de los medios, que siguen ofreciendo imágenes y relatos de mujeres y niñas altamente sexualizadas o en roles tradicionales. El público observa cómo mientras a un hombre se le valora en función de su experiencia o conocimiento, de una mujer lo principal suele ser su físico. Creo que esto tiene mucho que ver con la cultura organizativa de los medios y con la escasa presencia de mujeres en puestos de responsabilidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si esta brecha de representación está presente en todos los sectores, en el de la comunicación y las nuevas tecnologías tendrá consecuencias mucho más sensibles. Por eso, con el máximo respeto a la libertad de expresión, debemos favorecer una mayor implicación de los medios en la defensa de la igualdad, que es la lucha de todos, de toda la sociedad.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-124-0000" speaker_id="125049" name="Maria Lidia Senra Rodríguez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señora presidenta, señora comisaria: tres propuestas que nos preocupan hoy a las mujeres en el mundo rural.</p>
      <p sl="en">La primera cuestión: queremos protección frente a las corporaciones transnacionales que ocupan nuestra tierra, nuestros territorios, a menudo con mucha violencia y, además, para robar nuestros recursos naturales y también nuestras aguas.</p>
      <p sl="en">En segundo lugar: protección frente a la agricultura industrial que destruye nuestros puestos de trabajo, que contamina, que fumiga pueblos enteros y que, además, nos expulsa de nuestros mercados locales y de nuestros mercados de proximidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y una tercera cuestión: el reconocimiento legal de nuestros derechos como campesinas a través de leyes de titularidad compartida que nos otorguen el 50 % de los ingresos de la explotación, el 50 % de las ayudas, el 50 % de los derechos de producción, y que, además, nos garanticen una pensión digna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, en este sentido, quiero pedirle, señora comisaria —y termino—, que retiren el producto paneuropeo de pensiones individuales, que va a ocasionar una brecha mayor en las pensiones de las mujeres rurales.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-125-0000" speaker_id="128588" name="Linnéa Engström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Fru talman! Skulle du kunna tänka dig att föda barn i en bil, 50 mil från närmsta barnmorska? Det tvingas kvinnor i Sollefteå i norra Sverige att göra, på grund av att förlossningsavdelningen är nedlagd. Landsbygden måste leva. Det är ett stort problem att skillnaderna mellan land och stad ökar. I mitt hemland Sverige tvingas skräckslagna förstagångsföräldrar köra många mil till närmsta BB, och det är ovärdigt för ett välfärdsland som Sverige. Service som sjukvård och hälsovård måste finnas tillgänglig för alla oavsett var du råkar bo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Detta betänkande handlar om att lyfta behovet av jämställdhet på landsbygden och kvinnors behov där. Världen över möter kvinnor på landsbygden utmaningar som påverkar deras liv och möjlighet att skapa ett tryggt liv i frihet. Det är viktigt också att betänkandet lyfter behovet av klimaträttvisa och kvinnors situation i fattigare länder. De måste få sina rättigheter tillgodosedda vad gäller rätten till jorden de brukar och rätten till den egna kroppen. Detta är speciellt viktigt med tanke på att kvinnor är viktiga förändringsaktörer på lokal nivå när det gäller att tackla klimatförändringarnas konsekvenser.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-126-0000" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pone Komisijos nary, kolegos, iš tikrųjų Europos Sąjunga turi būti lyderė užtikrinant moterų teises, įgalinimą ir lygias galimybes. Ypatingai kalbant apie kaimo moteris mes privalome suteikti kiek įmanoma daugiau galimybių gauti joms tinkamą išsilavinimą, turėti saugų, gerai apmokamą darbą, užtikrinti teisę į aukštos kokybės sveikatos priežiūros paslaugas, ir, be abejo, kovoti su visų formų smurtu prieš moteris ir kartu užtikrinti, kad net atokiausiose vietovėse gyvenančios moterys turėtų vienodas galimybes gauti reikiamą pagalbą.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kaimo moterų darbas labai dažnai yra atlyginamas menkiau nei toks pat vyrų darbas ir jis net nėra oficialiai pripažįstamas, todėl tikrai raginu sudaryti sąlygas kaimo vietovių moterims pereiti iš neoficialiosios ekonomikos į oficialiąją ir pripažinti, kad kaimo moterys dirba įvairiose srityse ir dažniau skatina pokyčius, kuriant tvarų ir ekologišką žemės ūkį. Taip pat būtina užtikrinti visapusišką prieigą prie tinkamų vaikų priežiūros paslaugų gyvenant ir kaimo vietovėse.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-127-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this year the Commission on the Status of Women has chosen to focus on rural women, and rightly so. Women in rural areas are too often overlooked, despite their crucial role in their communities. They are more affected by climate change than men; they are more dependent on natural resources; and they play a significant role in ensuring food security for their communities. Their role in the fight against malnutrition is crucial, and their empowerment is necessary. I am happy to report that this report highlights the importance of women’s involvement in citizenship, but we must remember that fair political representation will never be achieved if girls’ human rights are not fulfilled. This means eliminating FGM, giving girls access to reproductive health and menstrual sanitary products, and fighting against rape culture, child marriage and all forms of gender-based violence. Later this month, I’ll join with colleagues to take our work to the United Nations in New York, but I am very concerned that Mr Trump’s administration has refused to grant visas to many women activists who planned to attend, and that this refusal is a way to silence the grassroots women’s movement. I therefore call on the EEAS and the Member States to use all diplomatic channels to help ensure that these attendees can obtain their visas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-128-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Commissioner Jourová, you have heard from women about the status of women, so I invite you to respond.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-129-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, it has been a pleasure to hear your views and recommendations for the Council on the upcoming meeting of the Commission on the Status of Women and I am happy to see such strong commitment and I hope our levels of ambition will be met.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-130-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, comisaria, gracias a todas por las aportaciones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podría terminar este debate insistiendo en las medidas que proponemos, desgranando estadísticas. Podría ser un discurso educado, correcto, pero creo que frío.</p>
      <p sl="en">La violencia contra las mujeres, la discriminación, la desigualdad merecen un tratamiento de choque. Por eso voy a hablarles de Ifé, una mujer que se asomó un día a mi blog personal en una entrada que dediqué a condenar el violento asesinato de una mujer como ella. Se llamaba Ada, sin hache, sin suerte y sin varita mágica …</p>
      <p sl="en">Ifé es una mujer subsahariana. Durante tres años seguidos lloró y se desesperó mientras trataba de sobrevivir en el primer mundo, mientras ahorraba para buscar un futuro mejor en el tercero. Porque aunque su piel brillante, tersa, negra reflejaba a veces el neón, su cada día eran las lámparas rojas que señalizaban su calvario. Era la semioscuridad. Era el contrato de bailarina que le permitió obtener un permiso de residencia. Era la siniestra coreografía de la dominación, del abuso, de la falta de respeto, de la deshumanización. Eran los billetes que guardaba y eran los que le quitaba aquel delincuente tras cada noche de «servicios».</p>
      <p sl="en">Ifé lloró mucho, pero cada lágrima le recordaba que la alternativa era casarse a los doce años con un hombre mucho mayor elegido por su padre, pegón, grosero; sufrir una espantosa mutilación para convertirla en un objeto al servicio del señor de la casa; recorrer diariamente decenas de kilómetros encorvada bajo el peso de quince litros de agua; respirar humo tóxico para transformar lo que aquí pasaría por desperdicios en una única comida al día; arar la tierra con las uñas; parir unos cuantos hijos y ver morir a la mitad; pasar hambre; sufrir, poco a poco, la pérdida de dientes, el brillo de los ojos, las grietas en la piel; apagarse; acabar arrinconada, a los veinticuatro, como un mueble desvencijado e inservible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un mundo justo, humano, con valores sigue ofreciendo a muchas mujeres rurales, como Ifé, la terrible disyuntiva de elegir entre lo malo y lo peor. Este informe es un grito de rebeldía contra esa realidad y un intento por cambiarla. Conseguirlo es responsabilidad de todos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-131-0000" speaker_id="125050" name="Ángela Vallina" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente. – Señora presidenta, me gustaría terminar recordando que las mujeres y las niñas en el mundo rural son agentes imprescindibles para lograr la erradicación de la pobreza en todo el mundo, terminar con el hambre, promover la agricultura sostenible y lograr la seguridad alimentaria.</p>
      <p sl="en">Muchas gracias por todas las aportaciones. Creo que estamos ante un informe de consenso, una coponencia entre el Grupo ALDE y el Grupo GUE/NGL en la que ambas coponentes hemos trabajado para acercar posturas, primero, entre nosotras y, luego, con el resto de los grupos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso, les manifiesto de nuevo mi agradecimiento por sus contribuciones. Y, en este momento, les pido un apoyo mayoritario y decidido al texto del informe como ha sido aprobado por la Comisión de Derechos de la Mujer e Igualdad de Género y que tiene como prioridad contribuir al empoderamiento de las mujeres y de las niñas en el mundo rural.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-132-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The vote will take place shortly.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-133-0000" speaker_id="124790" name="Doru-Claudian Frunzulică" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I welcome the recommendation on the EU priorities for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women and the provisions provided within. I strongly share the opinion that we have to put the spotlight on the empowerment of rural women, as they are often the primary care providers in their families and communities. However, they are confronting numerous difficulties in accessing childcare and elderly care for their families, which generates a disproportionate burden on women and hampers their integration into the labour market.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, as also pointed out in the report, the fifth UN Sustainable Development Goal (SDG5) consists in achieving gender equality and empowering all women and girls throughout the world. Therefore, the Union and its Member States must step up their efforts and be at the forefront of the empowerment of women and girls. I would remind you that we have a duty to work towards the achievement of full gender equality in the Union, and to promote this goal in all external relations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-133-5000" speaker_id="28377" name="Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">I support the recommendation of the European Parliament presented to the Council for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women. The EU could stand as one of the examples in terms of gender equality and therefore should be vocal in promoting those values across the world. We need to encourage all countries to further develop and implement policies to facilitate the lives of women and girls around the globe, and especially to prevent discrimination and domestic violence, to promote access to education and involvement in public life that mainly remain limited in rural areas, and to eliminate the gender pay gap and unfair conditions in employment.</p>
      <p sl="en">The entrepreneurial potential and economic benefit of full women’s participation in the labour market represents the underexploited source of economic development. We should urge the ratification and implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, with a special focus on article 6 relating to the rights of women with disabilities, the Marrakesh VIP Treaty, and to pursue policies to address the situation of women facing social exclusion and poverty. Furthermore, the EU should call on the 18 remaining members of the Council of Europe to ratify the Istanbul Convention.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-134-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în scris. – Egalitatea de gen și drepturile femeilor sunt lucruri pe care le discutăm la nivel european și la nivel național și, totuși, în acest secol avem încă discriminarea femeilor, mai ales în mediul rural. Așa cum s-a precizat în dezbaterea de azi, 75 % din populația săracă trăiește în mediul rural. Felicit raportoarele, dar cred că nu vom rezolva această problemă a egalității de gen dacă nu vom investi în educație, mai ales în mediul rural. Apoi ar trebui să avem măsuri specifice de finanțare a femeilor care doresc să dezvolte o afacere, dar și pentru asistența sanitară specifică pentru femei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Susțin raportul, dar este important să se supravegheze modul de implementare a normelor, regulilor și regulamentelor aprobate la nivel european și nivel național.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-134-5000" speaker_id="124763" name="Antanas Guoga" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Female empowerment is becoming more and more important on the agendas of international organisations such as the UN, which is a great success. However, there is still a lot of work that needs to be done. I congratulate the rapporteurs for their work on the report. They touched upon important issues such as women’ accessibility to formal and informal education, especially in rural areas, the promotion of digital skills and the use of ICT. I believe that in this digital age the promotion of digital skills is the main solution to help women, especially those living in rural areas, to increase gender equality, reduce the wage gap between men and women, as well as to give women equal opportunities. Therefore, I encourage the creation of informal programmes such as Coder Dojo that we have here in Europe which encourages boys and especially girls to learn digital skills such as coding. We firstly have to change the attitude that ICT technologies are ‘only for boys’. It should not be covered by gender prejudices. I believe that access to ICT is the most effective way forward for female empowerment.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-134-7500" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Jedno od temeljnih načela EU-a je poštovanje i rad na većoj ravnopravnosti žena i muškaraca. Tijekom posljednjih desetljeća društvene i gospodarske okolnosti i životni uvjeti znatno su se promijenili pa se tako radi na poboljšanju položaja žena i djevojčica, te suprotstavljanju rodnim stereotipima, u čemu bi EU trebao biti predvodnik.</p>
      <p sl="en">Treba stati na kraj svim oblicima diskriminacije žena i djevojčica u cijelom svijetu i zauzeti se za suzbijanje svih oblika nasilja koji predstavljaju teška kršenja njihovih temeljnih prava, a koja su izravna posljedica te diskriminacije. Sve vlade trebale bi izraditi programe namijenjene iskorjenjivanju spolnog i rodno uvjetovanog nasilja i štetnih praksi kao što su dječji, rani i prisilni brakovi te genitalno sakaćenje žena i trgovanje ljudima. S druge strane treba ulagati u obrazovanje, cjeloživotno učenje i strukovno osposobljavanje žena i djevojčica, osobito u ruralnim područjima, posebice u područjima znanosti, tehnologije, inženjerstva i matematike (STEM) te poduzetništvu i inovacijama, s obzirom na to da su ta područja važan alat za postizanje ciljeva održivog razvoja, te da promiču ravnopravnost u poljoprivrednom i prehrambenom sektoru, turizmu i drugim industrijama u ruralnim područjima.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-134-0001" speaker_id="28314" name="Anneli Jäätteenmäki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – Ehdotus Euroopan parlamentin suositukseksi neuvostolle EU:n painopisteistä naisten asemaa käsittelevän Yhdistyneiden kansakuntien toimikunnan 62. istuntoa varten on tärkeä. Istunnon teemana ovat sukupuolten tasa-arvon saavuttamista koskevat haasteet ja mahdollisuudet sekä maaseudun naisten ja tyttöjen voimaannuttaminen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tasa-arvo on yksi EU:n perustana olevista arvoista. EU:n on edistettävä naisten ja miesten välistä tasa-arvoa aktiivisesti sekä EU:n sisällä että kansainvälisesti. YK:n kautta tapahtuva vaikuttaminen on tällä sektorilla olennaista. Sukupuolten välisen tasa-arvon parantaminen edellyttää huomion kiinnittämistä useille eri sektoreille. Tasapuoliset, sukupuolesta riippumattomat mahdollisuudet saada terveydenhuoltoa, osallistua koulutukseen ja päätöksentekoon ovat esimerkkejä alueista, joihin keskittymällä sukupuolten tasa-arvoa voidaan parantaa. Koulutus on sukupuolten tasa-arvoa pitkällä aikavälillä tehokkaasti edistävä avaintekijä.</p>
      <p sl="en">On hyvä, että huomiota on kiinnitetty siihen, että ilmastonmuutoksella ja sen seurauksilla on suhteettoman suuri kielteinen vaikutus maaseudun naisiin ja tyttöihin. Ehdotuksessa todetaan, että sukupuolten epätasa-arvolla ja ympäristön pilaantumisen välillä on suora yhteys ja että maaseudun naiset voivat edistää kestävään ja ekologisesti terveeseen maatalouteen siirtymistä. Ympäristönäkökulma onkin yksi syy siihen, miksi sukupuolten välistä tasa-arvoa pitää edistää myös muualla kuin omassa lähiympäristössämme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Toimenpiteet naisten ja tyttöjen aseman parantamiseksi ovat välttämättömiä. Kansainvälisessä keskustelussa on vaadittava kohtuullisen elintason takaamista ja köyhyyden vähentämistä, koulutusmahdollisuuksien lisäämistä, sukupuoleen perustuvan syrjinnän ja väkivallan poistamista sekä sukupuolten palkkaeron tasaamista. Ihmisillä pitäisi olla tasavertaiset mahdollisuudet riippumatta sukupuolesta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-135-0000" speaker_id="125021" name="Agnes Jongerius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftelijk. – Voorzitter, tot in de jaren 1960 was het in Nederland gebruikelijk dat vrouwen stopten met werken als ze trouwden. Gehuwde vrouwen waren zelfs handelingsonbekwaam. Mijn eigen moeder moest er ook aan geloven: toen zij trouwde, mocht ze niet meer voor de klas staan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tegenwoordig is dit niet meer de norm, of de wet. Toch plukken we nog steeds de wrange vruchten van die tijd. Voorzitter, we leven nu in 2018, en toch doe ik hier een oproep om een einde te maken aan vrouwenongelijkheid. De cijfers liegen er niet om. Alleen al in Nederland is de inkomensongelijkheid tussen man en vrouw maar liefst 16,1 %. De pensioenongelijkheid is nog groter, een beschamende 44,9 %. We horen bij de slechte middenmoters, met een Europees gemiddelde van 39 %.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, ik pleit voor gelijk loon voor gelijk werk hier in Europa. Dit geldt niet alleen voor Oost- en West-Europa, dit geldt ook voor man en vrouw. Mannen en vrouwen hebben recht op hetzelfde loon voor hetzelfde werk, en daarmee ook op hetzelfde pensioen. Zo kan je vrouwen empoweren, door financieel zelfstandig te zijn. Dicht de pensioenkloof. Nederland en Europa kunnen zoveel beter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-135-0001" speaker_id="124793" name="Claudia Țapardel" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">Gender inequality poses serious threats to achieving a sustainable economy and reaching the goal of a non-discriminatory society. Moreover, the consequences of gender inequality are as serious as they are diverse, affecting girls and women in numerous ways, and especially women from rural areas. Figures show that the work of women from rural areas is often paid less than the work of men for the same output, and they encounter difficulties in getting access to adequate public health services. This situation is unacceptable for the Europe of the 21st century and calls for immediate action, which is why I support the recommendation of the European Parliament to the Council on the EU priorities for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women. We need to focus more on the challenges women from rural areas face, in all Member States, and the key EU priorities to increase the participation of women to media, information and communication technology are vital for the advancement and empowerment of women. My view is that we must make extra, but concrete, efforts to achieve gender equality and I fully support the use of digital technology as an instrument to sustain these efforts.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-135-5000" speaker_id="125090" name="Σωτήριος Ζαριανόπουλος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">γραπτώς. – Σε λίγες μέρες, 8 Μάρτη, είναι η Μέρα της Γυναίκας. Και πέρα από τα λόγια περί «ισότητας», πώς πραγματικά τη γιορτάζει η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση; Με την πρόσφατη απόφαση του Ευρωπαϊκού Δικαστηρίου που απελευθερώνει την απόλυση εγκύων γυναικών στα πλαίσια ομαδικών απολύσεων, αρκεί λέει, να μη γίνεται λόγω της εγκυμοσύνης, αλλά για οικονομικούς λόγους. Κοροϊδία. Βαρβαρότητα. Για την εργοδοσία, λόγος είναι ότι εγκυμοσύνη και μητρότητα δεν συμβαδίζουν με κέρδη, ανταγωνιστικότητα. Αγριεύει η εργασιακή ζούγκλα των «ιδιωτικών συμφωνητικών» με υποψήφιες εργαζόμενες πως δεν θα δημιουργήσουν οικογένεια, συμβάσεων που δεν ανανεώνονται όταν η εργαζόμενη μείνει έγκυος. Με ποσοστώσεις ανά φύλο δεν αλλάζουν οι νόμοι της καπιταλιστικής εκμετάλλευσης που αξιοποιούν για τα κέρδη τις διακρίσεις κατά των γυναικών σαν μέσο μείωσης μισθών, γενίκευσης της ευέλικτης εργασίας. Οι προτεραιότητες της Ένωσης εχθρεύονται τα εργασιακά, ασφαλιστικά, κοινωνικά δικαιώματα των γυναικών. Τα δικαιώματα των γυναικών κινδυνεύουν από δικαστικές αποφάσεις, κοινοτικές οδηγίες, εθνικές νομοθεσίες. Και κατακτώνται μόνο με συμμετοχή τους στο εργατικό, λαϊκό κίνημα.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Resumption of the sitting">
    <intervention id="2-140-0000" speaker_id="28229" name="Manfred Weber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich habe um das Wort gebeten, weil ich noch einmal eine Dringlichkeit aufrufen will, und zwar die Tatsache, die Sie gestern schon in Ihrem Statement angesprochen haben, nämlich die Tötung des slowakischen Journalisten. Wir haben heute in den europäischen Medien neue Fakten dazu gehört, dass nach dem Fall in Malta und nach dem Fall in der Slowakei jetzt leider Gottes zwei Journalisten in ihrem Einsatz für die Meinungsfreiheit ermordet worden sind. Ich möchte aufgrund der Dringlichkeit bitten, weil diese Woche keine CoP-Sitzung ist, dass wir als Parlament zum Ausdruck bringen, dass wir Wert darauf legen, dass es eine unabhängige Ermittlung im Fall der Slowakei gibt, dass die Fakten auf den Tisch gelegt werden, um die Unabhängigkeit zu erzielen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zum Zweiten: Nachdem heute auch in den öffentlichen Medien berichtet worden ist, dass EU-Gelder offensichtlich eventuell missbraucht worden sind, würde ich bitten, dass wir unseren CONT-Ausschuss beauftragen, eine eigene Untersuchungsmission in die Slowakei zu senden. Das Europäische Parlament muss die driving force sein, um Licht ins Dunkel der Vorfälle in der Slowakei zu bringen und die unabhängigen Journalisten zu beschützen. Ich bitte, dass wir das als Parlament auf den Weg bringen.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-141-0000" speaker_id="4267" name="Udo Bullmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich glaube, dass dieses Parlament – und das darf ich für meine Fraktion sagen – sich von niemandem übertreffen lassen wird, wenn es darum geht, den Rechtsstaat zu verteidigen und alle kriminellen Vorfälle – schlimme Vorfälle wie die Tötung von Journalisten – vorbehaltslos zu untersuchen, rückhaltlos zu untersuchen und allem auf den Grund zu gehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sind deswegen auch dafür, dass wir zu gegebener Zeit, wenn die Faktenlage das erlaubt, hier eine Aussprache dazu durchführen. Das ist, glaube ich, auch der Konsens unter den Kräften des Hauses. Ich will nur daran erinnern, dass diese Mission, die vom Kollegen Weber vorgeschlagen wurde auf der Agenda des TAXE-III-Ausschusses steht, also ohnehin für den neuen Untersuchungsausschuss, den wir heute auch in Gang bringen wollen, vorgesehen ist. Ich bitte den Präsidenten, sich mit den Verantwortlichen in TAXE III ins Benehmen zu setzen, damit keine Doppelarbeit erforderlich wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ansonsten möchte ich Herrn Weber daran erinnern, dass wir alles vorbehaltlos untersuchen. Das gilt für alle Staaten der Europäischen Union, unabhängig von der Frage, welcher Regierungschef gerade möglicherweise auch Mitglied der EVP ist. Das wird uns nicht hindern, in klarer und radikaler Weise alles zu untersuchen, was zu untersuchen ist. Das gilt auch für aktuelle Korruptionsvorwürfe, die in dem Zusammenhang laut geworden sind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-142-0000" speaker_id="96730" name="Sven Giegold" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to stress that the murder of journalists should never become a question of party politics. It is too serious a matter.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">This Parliament took tough action when this happened in Malta and we should do the utmost to take similar action when it happens in the Slovak Republic. Therefore I support the suggestion by Mr Weber to send an ad hoc mission to Slovakia, and to do so under the remit of the Conference of Presidents, because we cannot wait another few weeks until a secretariat has been created for the new committee: we have to act now. Journalists have the right to act freely in investigating corruption and taxation issues, and this Parliament should waste no time in safeguarding that right.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-143-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sono anch'io convinto che la libertà di stampa non sia né una questione di destra, né di centro, né di sinistra. La libertà di stampa è un valore fondamentale per tutta l'Unione europea e lo deve essere per tutti i governi, di qualunque colore siano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi credo che la soluzione migliore sia quella di avviare oggi stesso una procedura scritta attraverso i presidenti dei gruppi politici per decidere di inviare un gruppo di parlamentari, vediamo in quale formula, in Slovacchia per accertare cosa è accaduto, così coma la commissione "Panama Papers" andò a Malta per vedere quello che stava accadendo. Vi proporrò una procedura scritta nel pomeriggio, in modo che non si debba perdere altro tempo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Devo altresì dirvi che oggi sono state arrestate tre persone: si tratta di tre cittadini italiani che vivevano in Slovacchia. Però il problema è capire non soltanto chi sono gli esecutori materiali, ma chi sono i mandanti dell'omicidio. Ancora non abbiamo capito bene chi erano i mandanti dell'omicidio di Daphne Caruana Galizia. Come ho detto, continuerò a insistere su questo argomento perché non possiamo dare lezioni agli altri se prima non guardiamo dentro casa nostra.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi procederò rapidamente con una procedura scritta in modo che tutti i gruppi possano formalmente esprimere la loro volontà e sia possibile mandare quanto prima questa delegazione di parlamentari.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-144-0000" speaker_id="28429" name="Alessandra Mussolini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, parlando anche a nome del mio collega Alberto Cirio e di altri a proposito della Slovacchia, noi presentiamo questa interrogazione. Il Presidente Weber ha parlato di fondi, di un uso non corretto, ma c'è anche un uso non corretto della delocalizzazione, del dumping interno, e mi riferisco ai lavoratori dell'Embraco, che saranno licenziati, e l'azienda potrebbe passare dall'Italia alla Slovacchia. Questo è un uso improprio, è gravissimo che accada all'interno delle regioni dell'Unione europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-145-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mi sono occupato direttamente della vicenda perché ieri, accompagnati dal presidente della Regione Piemonte, sono venuti i lavoratori e i rappresentanti sindacali dell'impresa in questione. Mi sono già mobilitato per cercare di dare una risposta concreta e sono in sintonia con i sindacati, con il presidente della Regione e anche con le autorità italiane che stanno seguendo la vicenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-146-0000" speaker_id="113959" name="Martina Anderson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, you’re talking about Member States upholding the rule of law, and about the murder of journalists. And, given that we have Nils Muižnieks sitting here and going to address the House, I think it is important that we remember the murder, by loyalists, of human rights lawyer Pat Finucane and the fact it has been evidentially proven that there was British collusion in that murder. So here you have a Member State involved in the murder of a human rights lawyer – Pat Finucane.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-147-0000" speaker_id="28340" name="Patrizia Toia" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, sappiamo e apprezziamo quello che Lei ha fatto ieri e farà per questa situazione molto incresciosa sulla quale, come Lei sa, gli sforzi del governo italiano convergono nella stessa direzione: chiedere alle imprese multinazionali che abbiano un senso di responsabilità sociale. Quando vanno in un paese investono, lavorano, e non possono chiudere per motivi puramente finanziari, perché ne va della loro reputation e quindi diventa anche un danno per loro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le chiedo solo che nel corso di questa valutazione, che farà anche la commissione per il controllo dei bilanci con tutti gli strumenti che avremo, noi si valuti anche se i fondi regionali, i fondi europei che vanno alle regioni meno sviluppate per crescere, vengono invece utilizzati per fare questo da dumping del lavoro, sociale e fiscale. Penso che, accanto a tutte le azioni che faremo per quest'impresa, per i lavoratori che abbiamo ricevuto tutti insieme, ci sia anche questo aspetto dell'utilizzo dei fondi europei.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-148-0000" speaker_id="28306" name="Ana Gomes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I have the honour to lead the mission to Malta and I would like to concur that indeed there is still more work to be done. We are waiting for an answer from the Conference of Presidents but, of course, the work to be done should be done under the remit of the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs, and the new committee that is to be established following on from the Committee on Money Laundering, Tax Avoidance and Tax Evasion (PANA Committee).</p>
      <p sl="en">However, Mr President, what I wish to ask for now is that you should raise with the Vice-President of the Commission and High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy the situation in Ethiopia. Brutal repression is going on. The Government, including the Prime Minister, has resigned. A state of emergency has been re-imposed, and the statement made by the European Union is a shame by comparison with the one put out by the Americans condemning the reinstatement of the state of emergency.</p>
      <p sl="en">I ask you to bring this up with the Commission and with High Representative Mogherini. The European Union needs to take a position in the light of our values and the interests of democracy – which must be inclusive – in Ethiopia, as well as the re-establishment of the rule of law and respect for human rights.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-149-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Non stiamo facendo una discussione sui diritti umani. Ci sono state delle richieste di interventi per questioni urgenti, però abbiamo un ospite, credo sia anche nostro dovere. Possiamo intervenire prima della discussione.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-150-0000" speaker_id="28233" name="Rebecca Harms" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">I ask you Mr President to now come to the agenda.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">Because on the issue we are discussing it fits very well to listen to Mr Muižnieks.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-151-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">È quello che stiamo facendo, ma la vicenda del giornalista assassinato è una vicenda talmente grave che anche il Commissario per i diritti umani che abbiamo invitato, il signor Muižnieks, avrà ben capito l'importanza della questione. Lo ringrazio per aver pazientato per qualche minuto, ma si parlava anche qui di diritti umani.</p>
      <a text="(La seduta è sospesa alle 11.48. Il Parlamento si riunisce in occasione dell'allocuzione di Nils Muižnieks, Commissario per i diritti umani del Consiglio d'Europa.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Voting time">
    <intervention id="2-155-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca il turno di votazioni.</p>
      <a text="(Per i risultati delle votazioni e altri dettagli che le riguardano: vedasi processo verbale)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="8.1. Election of a Vice-President of the European Parliament (to replace Ryszard Czarnecki) (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-157-0000" speaker_id="2187" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca l'elezione di un Vicepresidente del Parlamento europeo in sostituzione dell'on. Czarnecki. Ricordo che ai sensi dell'articolo 20 del regolamento, il nuovo Vicepresidente prende il posto del Vicepresidente uscente che sostituisce nell'ordine di precedenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ho ricevuto le candidature dell'on. Krasnodębski, proposta dal gruppo ECR, e dell'on. Tarand, proposta da un numero di deputati pari almeno alla soglia bassa. I candidati mi hanno comunicato di accettare le candidature. Poiché il numero dei candidati è superiore al numero dei seggi da assegnare, dobbiamo procedere, conformemente all'articolo 17, paragrafo 1, del regolamento, a una votazione a scrutinio segreto. Procederemo pertanto all'elezione con il voto elettronico segreto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dopo la votazione:</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-158-0000" speaker_id="124971" name="James Carver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I voted for a candidate on three occasions, and on three occasions the vote has been registered and then has disappeared. The system is not working.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="8.2. Insurance distribution: date of application of Member States' transposition measures (A8-0024/2018 - Werner Langen)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-161-5000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Věra Jourová" is_mep="False" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">The Commission recalls that under the Interinstitutional Agreement on Better Law-Making of 13 April 2016 the European Parliament, the Council and the Commission agreed that in order to swiftly and correctly apply Union legislation in the Member States, the time limit for transposition of directives would be as short as possible and, generally, not exceed two years.</p>
      <p sl="en">In view of the particular timeframe for the application of Directive (EU) 2016/97 and of the Delegated Regulations adopted under this Directive, which resulted in difficulties for small and medium-sized insurance companies and insurance distributors to implement the required changes in time for the application date of 23 February 2017, the Commission exceptionally submitted a proposal to amend Directive (EU) 2016/97 by setting the date for application to 1 October 2016.</p>
      <p sl="en">The co-legislators have also agreed to postpone the transposition date for Directive (EU) 2016/97 to 1 July 2018. The Commission considers that this cannot be interpreted as creating a precedent, as it must be ensured that all Member States are treated equally, but notes that exceptionally it will not stand in the way of this agreement. The Commission expects Member States to fully comply with their obligation to bring their national transposition measures into force at this date at the latest, in order to give insurance companies and insurance distributors enough time to finalise their preparation and adaptation measures with the full knowledge of the European and national legislative frameworks.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem11" title="8.3. EU-USA Bilateral Agreement on prudential measures regarding insurance and reinsurance (A8-0008/2018 - Roberto Gualtieri)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="8.4. Nomination of a Member of the Court of Auditors - Annemie Turtelboom (A8-0027/2018 - Indrek Tarand)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-165-0000" speaker_id="97136" name="Indrek Tarand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, as a democrat I appreciate the decision of a parliament and very much welcome your vote in favour of the Belgian candidate.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem13" title="8.5. Appointment of a Member of the Single Resolution Board (A8-0030/2018 - Roberto Gualtieri)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="8.6. Setting up a special committee on financial crimes, tax evasion and tax avoidance (TAX3), its responsibilities, numerical strength and term of office (B8-0125/2018) (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8.7. Definition, presentation and labelling of spirit drinks and protection of geographical indications thereof (A8-0021/2018 - Pilar Ayuso)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-170-0000" speaker_id="4319" name="Pilar Ayuso" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, quisiera solicitar que el asunto se devuelva a la comisión competente con vistas a la celebración de negociaciones interinstitucionales, de conformidad con el artículo 59, apartado 4, del Reglamento interno.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="8.8. Mandatory automatic exchange of information in the field of taxation (A8-0016/2018 - Emmanuel Maurel)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="8.9. Objection pursuant to Rule 106: authorisation of genetically modified maize 59122 (DAS-59122-7) (B8-0122/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="8.10. Objection pursuant to Rule 106: authorisation of genetically modified maize MON 87427 × MON 89034 × NK603 and genetically modified maize combining two of the events MON 87427, MON 89034 and NK603 (B8-0124/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="8.11. Mobilisation of the European Globalisation Adjustment Fund: application EGF/2017/006 ES/Galicia apparel (A8-0033/2018 - Esteban González Pons)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8.12. Mobilisation of the European Globalisation Adjustment Fund: application EGF/2017/007 SE/Ericsson (A8-0032/2018 - Urmas Paet)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="8.13. Commission decision to activate Article 7 (1) TEU as regards the situation in Poland (B8-0119/2018, B8-0120/2018, B8-0121/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="8.14. Situation of fundamental rights in the EU in 2016 (A8-0025/2018 - Frank Engel)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="8.15. Prospects and challenges for the EU apiculture sector (A8-0014/2018 - Norbert Erdős)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="8.16. Banking Union - Annual Report 2017 (A8-0019/2018 - Sander Loones)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="8.17. Cutting the sources of income for Jihadists - targeting the financing of terrorism (A8-0035/2018 - Javier Nart)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="8.18. EU priorities for the 62nd session of the UN Commission on the Status of Women (A8-0022/2018 - Izaskun Bilbao Barandica, Ángela Vallina)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-183-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ceci clôt l’heure des votes.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem27" title="9. Composition of delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem28" title="10. Explanations of vote"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="10.1. Definition, presentation and labelling of spirit drinks and protection of geographical indications thereof (A8-0021/2018 - Pilar Ayuso)">
    <intervention id="2-188-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-жо Председател, Уважаеми колеги, днешният регламент относно определянето, представянето и етикетирането на спиртни напитки, използването на наименованията на спиртните напитки при представянето и етикетирането на други храни и защитата на географски указания е важна стъпка към развитието на сектора.</p>
      <p sl="en">Радвам се, че предложението ми за запазване на езиковото разнообразие на Съюза беше прието и правото на това многокултурно разнообразие ще бъде защитено. Радвам се, че първоначалното предложение на Комисията за условията за признаване на нова категория също беше преразгледано.</p>
      <p sl="en">Секторът на производство на алкохолни напитки е вече силно регулиран, затова смятам, че не трябва да бъде допълнително утежняван и затрудняван. Географските означения при спиртните напитки са също изключително важни. Затова смятам, че е необходимо законодателството при спиртните напитки да бъде възможно най-близко до това за селскостопанските храни и продукти. Това ще помогне на целия Европейски съюз да се наложи на световния пазар като защитник на местните традиции, производство и продукти.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-189-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, η προστασία των γεωγραφικών ενδείξεων για τα αλκοολούχα ποτά είναι κάτι πάρα πολύ σημαντικό, ιδίως για χώρες οι οποίες έχουν παραδοσιακά ποτά, όπως η Ελλάδα, ποτά όπως το ούζο, η τσικουδιά και το τσίπουρο. Πρέπει όμως η εμφιάλωση των παραδοσιακών αυτών ποτών να γίνεται εντός της συγκεκριμένης γεωγραφικής περιοχής. Επιπλέον, όπως επεσήμανα χθες στον κύριο Hogan, πρέπει στην Ελλάδα να διατηρηθεί ο μειωμένος ειδικός φόρος κατανάλωσης για την τσικουδιά και το τσίπουρο, διότι μόνο έτσι μπορεί να προστατευτούν αυτά τα παραδοσιακά ποτά. Στο πλαίσιο αυτό, θα πρέπει η Επιτροπή να αποσύρει την προσφυγή που έχει ασκήσει κατά της Ελλάδος, και όπου βρίσκεται σήμερα ενώπιον του Δικαστηρίου της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης, διότι πρέπει να διατηρηθεί, επαναλαμβάνω, αυτός ο ειδικός φόρος κατανάλωσης, μειωμένος τουλάχιστον κατά 50%, προκειμένου αυτά τα παραδοσιακά ποτά, δηλαδή η τσικουδιά και το τσίπουρο, να μπορέσουν πραγματικά να επιβιώσουν.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-190-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, some years ago I had a constituency case involving a fruit winemaker in Sussex. Fruit wine was redefined from being a spirit to a wine, so it suddenly fell within the EU’s directives on bottling. This guy – who employed, I think, eight other people – suddenly found that they had to change not just his bottles, but his labels, the cases, the prices and everything, because he was using 140 cl and 70 cl bottles rather than the mandated 150 cl and 75 cl bottles. Now, here’s the point: that winemaker was not exporting anything. There was no cross—border dimension. He was trading – like the majority of small and medium enterprises – in a fairly limited radius of where his business was situated. The problem with the way that the single market has evolved is that it no longer concerns itself only with issues of trade, but presumes to dictate to even the smallest and most local of businesses – and that reduces consumer choice and reduces economic growth.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-191-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já jsem tento návrh podpořil, i když musím říci, že i já vnímám za problematické, pokud se předepisují pravidla, která mají dopadat jednotně na velmi omezený trh. Je to skutečně mnohdy zatěžující pro male výrobce, pro místní regionální ekonomiku, pro místní producenty a zemědělce.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na druhou stranu, tato úprava si klade za cíl zamezit klamavým praktikám v obecném měřítku, zajistit ochranu spotřebitelů a zabránit nekalé hospodářské soutěži. To jsou hodnoty, které jsem poměřoval při svém hlasování, a nakonec jsem se rozhodl, že tuto zprávu podpořím, tedy i ten návrh té legislativy. Pro mě je velmi podstatné, že se budou jednotně uplatňovat pravidla týkající se lihovin a prováže se to s procesními pravidly týkajícími se geografického označování. I my v ČR máme např. žatecký chmel a chceme, aby i tato surovina byla takto chráněna.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-192-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, mar rapóirtéir den ghrúpa INTA, ghlacas páirt sa díospóireacht a bhí againn ar an ábhar seo aréir, agus bhí sí suimiúil agus dar ndóigh bhí sí tábhachtach. Bhí áthas orm gur glacadh leis an tuarascáil le móramh mór anseo inniu mar is ábhar an-tábhachtach é agus go háirithe go bhfuil fás mór ag teacht ar bhiotáille á easpórtáil timpeall an domhain, dá bhrí sin tá sé tábhachtach go mbeadh gach rud ceart againn ó thaobh lipéad agus mar sin de.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tá blas draíochta ag baint leis na táirgí seo, go háirithe ó mo thír féin, agus táim an—bhródúil as sin. Rud amháin a vótálas ina choinne ná beoir alcóil a bheith glactha mar bhiotáille. Is dóigh liom gur cheart idirdhealú a dhéanamh idir an dá rud agus bhí an Coimisiún ar an ábhar agus ar an bhfocal céanna aréir.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-193-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, me sumo a mis colegas a la hora de destacar la importancia de este Reglamento. Estoy satisfecha con lo que hemos aprobado y con el mandato que vamos a llevar del Parlamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que se ha tenido sensibilidad con los métodos tradicionales; en el caso de mi país, con el método de la «solera» en el brandy de Jerez, que es muy importante. Estaba recogido en la legislación española y temíamos que no pudiera trasladarse ahora a la legislación europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que se ha mostrado respeto a los métodos tradicionales, de lo que me felicito.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero quiero decir que he votado en contra de la introducción de los perfiles nutricionales en este Reglamento. Eso no quiere decir que esté en contra de que haya que debatir y avanzar en perfiles nutricionales en bebidas alcohólicas, pero, desde luego, este no era el reglamento y no es el momento oportuno. De ahí mi voto negativo específicamente a esas enmiendas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estoy satisfecha con lo aprobado, en líneas generales, en relación con este Reglamento.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem30" title="10.2. Mandatory automatic exchange of information in the field of taxation (A8-0016/2018 - Emmanuel Maurel)">
    <intervention id="2-208-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, doar în 2017, companiile multinaționale au exportat profituri de peste 600 de miliarde de euro. Paradisurile fiscale profită de mobilitatea sporită a capitalurilor și a persoanelor pe piața internă. Am ajuns în situația de a avea acorduri care facilitează evaziunea fiscală transfrontalieră și permit indivizilor și corporațiilor să își mute profiturile în paradisuri fiscale. Dacă autoritățile fiscale nu vor colabora între ele, atunci nu vom rezolva această situație.</p>
      <p sl="en">De asemenea, recomand autorităților fiscale să folosească milioanele de documente și de informații din ceea ce au descoperit jurnaliștii de investigații - și mă refer la Lux, Panama, „Paradise Papers”, „Laundromat”-ul Azerbaidjan și așa mai departe -, fiindcă toate se referă la paradisuri fiscale și identifică politicieni sau alte persoane care și-au ascuns banii acolo. Deci, statele își pot recupera banii folosind aceste informații.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-209-0000" speaker_id="125047" name="Paloma López Bermejo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">No descubro nada nuevo a este Parlamento si les digo que estoy convencida de la necesidad de las normas que obligan a gobiernos y empresas a dar de forma transparente toda la información económica. Por eso hemos apoyado este texto, porque va en la dirección correcta.</p>
      <p sl="en">La existencia de acuerdos fiscales secretos entre empresas y Estados miembros o las políticas de dumping fiscal como forma de competir entre unos Estados miembros y otros no contribuyen a generar ninguna riqueza, solo contribuyen al fraude y a la evasión y a los paraísos fiscales, como estamos viendo de forma permanente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estoy convencida de que las propuestas en la línea en la que se hacen en esta consulta sí son el camino para luchar contra la desigualdad fiscal. Necesitamos más información obligatoria, publicidad en los acuerdos entre Estados miembros y empresas transnacionales. Hay que tapar las goteras de la fiscalidad con transparencia y con información actualizada en el corto plazo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estas propuestas, hechas desde la Comisión ECON y apoyadas de forma casi unánime, responden a todos los ciudadanos europeos que esperan que reaccionemos ante su indignación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-210-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já jsem podpořil také tuto směrnici, protože mám pocit, že právě v boji proti daňovým únikům mohou jednotlivé daňové orgány jednotlivých národních států velmi intenzivně spolupracovat a je třeba, aby zde Evropa v rámci svého evropského práva přijala pro to jasná pravidla, pro přeshraniční spolupráci daňových orgánů.</p>
      <p sl="en">Už to tady kolegové říkali, problém úniku peněz do daňových rájů je velkým problémem EU a my tedy musíme na to reagovat dostatečně kvalitní legislativou. Proto jsem také tuto směrnici podpořil a doufám, že v praxi bude využívána, že bude implementována do jednotlivých národních právních úprav a přispěje k tomu, aby mezi jednotlivými daňovými orgány členských států docházelo k povinné výměně informací a aby také ti, kteří se snaží založit např. provozovnu v daňovém ráji, tyto skutečnosti povinně hlásili příslušné daňové autoritě.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-211-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, both in the report and in the debate we are being too loose in our language. When we talk about tax havens, and paradis fiscal, we are running together two things. One is something which is secret and therefore illegal, which not a single Member of this Chamber is going to defend. Of course it would be wrong for people to escape their legal responsibilities. The other is places that simply have lower tax rates than we would like – and those places, I would argue, are providing a service by providing some constraint on the appetites of less continent governments. This running together of tax avoidance and tax evasion, which runs through so many of these reports, is conflating two very different things. One is a serious criminal offence; the other is something that people do in the UK every time they buy an ISA or premium bonds, or any other legal device that reduces their tax exposure. If we in this House make that elision, how can we expect citizens to respect the difference?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-212-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pro mě je důležité, že bude docházet k výměně informací a bude se tak předcházet daňovým podvodům. Daňové podvody jsou mnohdy prováděny kriminalitou bílých límečků, tzn. velmi inteligentními lidmi, kteří využívají každé mezery, přesouvají své zdanitelné zisky do daňových rájů, takže výměna informací právě v tom přeshraničním styku je velmi důležitá. Také je důležité právě zachování otázky transparentnosti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nicméně sjednocovat přímé daně, pro to já bych určitě nebyl, takže pokud šlo o tuto zprávu, o tuto směrnici, mohl jsem ji podpořit, protože podporuji předcházení daňovým deliktům v různých členských státech, ale pokud by měly sjednocovat přímé daně členské státy, tak proti tomu bych se určitě postavil. V tomto smyslu jsem tedy mohl podpořit tento návrh směrnice.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem31" title="10.3. Commission decision to activate Article 7 (1) TEU as regards the situation in Poland (B8-0119/2018, B8-0120/2018, B8-0121/2018)">
    <intervention id="2-225-0000" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Głosowałam przeciwko rezolucji Parlamentu w sprawie decyzji Komisji o uruchomieniu art. 7 Traktatu w odniesieniu do sytuacji w Polsce. Decyzja ta jest nie tylko wyrazem podwójnych standardów stosowanych w Unii, ale jeszcze jednym atakiem na wybrany w demokratycznych wyborach polski rząd, który zgodnie z wyborczymi obietnicami przeprowadza spóźnione o przynajmniej dwadzieścia lat reformy. Chodzi tu zwłaszcza o reformę sądownictwa, do którego większość społeczeństwa nie ma zaufania.</p>
      <p sl="en">Reforma funkcjonowania wymiaru sprawiedliwości zgodnie z traktatami należy do kompetencji państw członkowskich. Tak zatroskana o praworządność w Polsce opozycja mimo wieloletnich rządów nie przeprowadziła żadnych reform, a utrwalała tylko poprzednie patologie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proponowane przez polski rząd rozwiązania stosowane są także w innych państwach członkowskich, a różne poziomy wieku emerytalnego są tylko wyrazem szacunku dla kobiet i docenieniem ich pracy jako żon i matek wychowujących dzieci.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-226-0000" speaker_id="96661" name="Krisztina Morvai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Természetesen nemmel szavaztam a Lengyelországgal szembeni gyalázatos határozat vonatkozásában, amelyet az az Európai Unió, vagy Európai Parlament hozott, amely egyébként a tömeges rendőri brutalitásokkal, szemkilövésekkel szemben soha nem óhajtott fellépni. Azért is szavaztam így, mert egyetértettem a Magyar Országgyűlésnek a február 21-i határozatával, amelynek a címe: a Lengyelország melletti kiállásról, Brüsszel nyomásgyakorlásával szemben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Idézek belőle: A vasfüggöny mögött eltöltött negyven év alatt elegünk lett a diktátumokból. Magyarországot és Lengyelországot számos jogtalan és igaztalan támadás érte az Európai Unió intézményei részéről a közelmúltban. Lengyelország és Magyarország az Európai Egyesült Államok eszméje helyett az Európai Nemzetek Közösségében hisz. A nyílt társadalom eszméjének terjesztése helyett keresztény kultúránk megőrzését tekintjük feladatunknak. Az Országgyűlés megalapozatlannak tartja, hogy az Európai Parlament és az Európai Bizottság Lengyelországgal szemben az uniós alapszerződés 7. cikke szerinti eljárás megindítását kezdeményezte, illetve arról döntött.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-227-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Chciałabym podziękować wszystkim głosującym przeciwko tej haniebnej rezolucji, która ma uderzyć w Polskę. Polska jest wolnym i demokratycznym krajem, szanujemy prawa demokracji i to w demokratycznych wyborach Polacy wybrali większość parlamentarną. Ta większość parlamentarna, idąc za programem wyborczym, mówiła o naprawie niesprawiedliwego systemu sprawiedliwości w Polsce, który był opresyjny wobec słabych i bezsilny wobec silnych. Obiecywaliśmy Polakom, że ten system niesprawiedliwości stanie się systemem sprawiedliwości.</p>
      <p sl="en">Proponowane przez nas rozwiązania są tożsame z tymi, które funkcjonują w wielu państwach członkowskich. To haniebne, że Parlament Europejski chce angażować się w sprawy, których kompletnie nie rozumie. My system sprawiedliwości odziedziczyliśmy, Pani Przewodnicząca, po PRL-u, po sowieckim komunistycznym bycie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-228-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Dlaczego w sytuacji, w której Parlament Europejski i tak będzie musiał odnieść się do ewentualnego wniosku Rady Europejskiej o podjęcie kroków przeciwko Polsce z art. 7, ale odnieść się przewidzianą przez traktaty większością dwóch trzecich głosów, odbywa się dzisiaj ta debata? W jakim celu? Chyba tylko po to, żeby kroki formalne zastąpić czystą demonstracją polityczną. Chyba po to, by ukryć, że tak naprawdę rządy państw europejskich wzbraniają się przeciwko dalszemu dzieleniu Europy w sytuacji, gdy Europa ma już tyle problemów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Naprawdę jest coś groteskowego w tym, że w momencie gdy tyle mówimy o populizmie, w miejsce formalnej procedury określonej przez traktaty przeprowadzamy czystą polityczną demonstrację, aby pokazać istnienie większości, która nie jest większością przewidzianą prawem, czyli wymaganą większością 22 rządów państw Unii Europejskiej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-229-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, what bothers me about this motion is not just the intrusiveness and the presumption about telling a sovereign country how to organise its internal affairs, it is the asymmetry that we see over and over again in this Chamber. Whenever a government is criticised for some domestic policy, you can bet that it is a government that is unpopular in this Chamber because it is patriotic, or because it stands up for its national interests, or because it refuses to endorse the goal of the United States of Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is a classic example: there were judicial reforms made by the previous Polish Government that resulted effectively in the packing of the bench, with not a peep of protest from this Chamber. But when the current Government undoes those reforms to try and restore a measure of balance to the judiciary, the sky falls in. All of you who voted for this measure know in your hearts that, if this had been a goody—two—shoes federalist government, this motion would never have come before the House.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-230-0000" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, pourquoi veut-on punir la Pologne? Parce qu’elle a limité la durée du mandat des juges de la Cour suprême, comme le font beaucoup d’États. Parce que la Pologne – et c’est un crime aux yeux de la majorité de ce Parlement – respecte la vie de l’enfant à naître. Parce que la Pologne a un gouvernement conservateur, ce qui est bien son droit. Parce que la Pologne, qui a été victime de l’agression allemande, veut que les camps de concentration qui se trouvaient sur son territoire soient qualifiés peut-être de «camps se trouvant en Pologne» mais pas de «camps polonais», c’est bien la moindre des choses me semble-t-il.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et on voit bien que la majorité de ce Parlement, appuyant les manœuvres de la Commission, donne l’exemple, finalement le plus cynique qui soit, de la mise sous tutelle à laquelle l’eurocratie voudrait procéder contre les libertés des peuples d’Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je m’écrie comme naguère, au temps de Napoléon III, un Français au passage du Tsar: «Vive la Pologne, vive la Pologne libre».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-231-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, if we cannot protect our principles inside the EU we will lose the moral right to criticise non-EU countries’ decisions. We should create independent evaluation mechanisms and strengthen sanctions for violations of EU fundamental principles within the Union. We have no choice. We have to understand whether we have common values or not.</p>
      <p sl="en">If not, the only possible decision is to dissolve the European Union. If yes, we must establish discipline among Member States and have the means to enforce it. Therefore, I welcome this motion for a resolution and I hope such discipline will be consistently applied. It is only through consistency in our policies on fundamental rights that we can achieve legitimacy in the eyes of our EU citizens. I voted in favour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-232-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já jsem tento návrh usnesení podpořil. Podle mého názoru se o právním státu, o demokracii nevyjednává. Ten má jasně daná pravidla – demokratický právní stát.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já si velmi dobře vzpomínám, když jsme projednávali, je to už řada měsíců, situaci v Polsku, které se účastnila přímo polská premiérka, ta už není ve funkci, byla dotazována, zdali bude respektovat polská vláda nález, který vydá Benátská komise Rady Evropy pro posouzení ústavnosti zamýšlených změn právě v souvislosti se sporem o Ústavní soud. Paní premiérka se vyhnula přímé odpovědi, jestli bude respektovat tento názor odborného stanoviska jiné organizace, Rady Evropy, ne EU. Ten odsudek byl naprosto zdrcující poté, co jej vydala Benátská komise, takže já jsem přesvědčen, že máme mít společné hodnoty, že je to klíčové alespoň v těch základech. O právním státu se nevyjednává, a proto mi nezbývalo nic jiného, než podpořit tento návrh usnesení.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-233-0000" speaker_id="124879" name="Janusz Korwin-Mikke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I voted against.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Głosowałem przeciwko, aczkolwiek zgadzam się, że partia rządząca nie ma pojęcia, co to są rządy prawa. Tutaj, na sali profesor Legutko powiedział, że muszą usunąć sędziów, którzy głosowali za komuny i skazywali opozycję. Ale oni wykonywali prawo, i tak samo dzisiaj głosowaliby, tak jak chce PiS. Jednak oni nie chcą sędziów, którzy stosowaliby prawa, tylko chcą sędziów, którzy głosowaliby zgodnie z zachciankami partii rządzącej. Sędziowie w nowym prawie będą karani i nagradzani za to, jak głosują, i to jest oczywiście przeciwko wszelkim zasadom rządów prawa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ale głosowałem przeciwko, ponieważ każda ingerencja Unii Europejskiej wymierzona w PiS, umacnia PiS. Każdy atak Unii Europejskiej na rządy PiS-u umacnia rządy PiS-u. Dlatego jestem przeciwny tej rezolucji i głosowałem przeciwko. A poza tym sądzę, że Unia Europejska musi być zniszczona.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem32" title="10.4. Situation of fundamental rights in the EU in 2016 (A8-0025/2018 - Frank Engel)">
    <intervention id="2-248-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I voted in favour of this very important report. There is nothing more important than the upholding of the fundamental rights of citizens across the European Union. I want to speak today though, about a group of people who do not always see their fundamental rights upheld, and that is people with a terminal illness who sometimes find themselves facing a real challenge and difficulty in upholding their fundamental right to work.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yesterday we launched a new group in Parliament, of MEPs from across the House, to campaign for stronger legal protection for people with terminal illness in the workplace, and I am grateful for support from colleagues across the House for that group and for that cause. I would also call today on Parliament itself to sign our voluntary charter, to properly protect and support people in the workplace with a terminal illness, so everybody, across the EU, has that fundamental right to work properly upheld.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-249-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, luni, jurnalistul slovac Ján Kuciak și logodnica lui, Marina, au fost împușcați. Aveau doar 27 de ani. Ján era jurnalist de investigație și lucra împreună cu alți colegi la investigarea unor crime transfrontaliere referitoare la droguri și la legăturile cu Slovacia. În octombrie, Daphne Caruana Galizia a fost aruncată în aer cu o bombă. Avem două crime de jurnaliști de investigații, violente, în inima Europei. De ce? Pentru că acei jurnaliști au rămas neclintiți, pentru că au vrut să spună adevărul lumii despre corupții care ne guvernează și despre toate relele și ilegalitățile pe care le comit și au plătit cu viața. Practic, mafia s-a organizat ca să elimine pe oricine vorbește liber și le expune corupția.</p>
      <p sl="en">Foarte pe scurt, aș vrea să spun că trebuie să facem o misiune de fact finding în Slovacia, cum am făcut și în Malta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-250-0000" speaker_id="96661" name="Krisztina Morvai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Mi magyarok ismét kaptunk üzenetet az Európai Uniótól. Szeretném továbbítani honfitársaimnak így az április 8-i választásokra készülődve. Azt mondja ez az alapvető jogok helyzetéről szóló jelentés: Hangsúlyozza, hogy az Európai Uniónak - 29. pont, a tolmácsok kedvéért mondom - teljes területén befogadási és integrációs politikát kell előmozdítania, valamint elfogadhatatlannak tartja, hogy bizonyos tagállamok azt állítsák, hogy nem érzik érintettnek magukat a migráció jelensége által.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tessenek elképzelni, az én otthoni honfitársaim, hogy majd azok a baloldali, illetve liberális jelöltek, akik most azt állítják, hogy ők igenis meg fogják tartani a kerítést a határon, ők igenis távol fogják tartani a tömeges migrációt, hogyha egyszer a magyar nép ezt követeli. Hogy fognak majd az itteni pártjaiknak, pártfrakcióiknak nekimenni, nekifeszülni, komolyan gondolják, hogy majd ők lesznek itt a nagy ellenállók? Nehogy már bedőljenek az ilyesminek!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-251-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">J’attire votre attention, mes chers collègues, sur le fait que nous devons terminer à 13 h 30 et qu’il y a encore beaucoup d’explications de vote à formuler. Donc nous serons probablement obligés de ne pas tenir compte des dernières, en tout cas oralement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-252-0000" speaker_id="28178" name="Miroslav Mikolášik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca, so správou o situácii v oblasti základných práv v Európskej únii v roku 2016 prišiel do pléna ďalší dokument, ktorý v mnohých ohľadoch vnáša prax rodovej identity v rozpore zo zásadou subsidiarity a proporcionality. Správa opätovne zneužíva tému základných práv na ideologický nátlak na určité členské štáty, na verejnú mienku a na presadzovanie absurdného sociálneho inžinierstva. Poukazujem na problematický článok 70, ktorý vyzýva členské štáty, aby ratifikovali Istanbulský dohovor. Ratifikáciou by sa podľa článku 6 zmluvné strany vrátane Slovenska definitívne zaviazali citujem: “začleniť rodovú perspektívu do implementácie a vyhodnocovania vplyvu ustanovení tohto dohovoru“ koniec citátu. Bojovať proti násiliu páchanému na ženách je jednoznačná povinnosť samozrejme, ale dá sa to efektívne aj inak než obetovaním iných základných hodnôt, akceptovaním právnych formulácií, ktoré sú nezlučiteľné so základnými hodnotami a predovšetkým s právnym systémom niektorých členských štátov, na ktorý máme ako zvrchované a demokratické štáty podľa práva EÚ nárok.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-253-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! To sprawozdanie wzywa – teoretycznie całkowicie słusznie – by unikać wszelkich nadużyć mogących prowadzić do tyranii większości. Tylko problem polega na tym, że my żyjemy pod tą tyranią większości. Ani rodzina, ani życie, ani wychowanie nie są traktowane jako wspólnoty i dobra, których natury nie ma prawa zmieniać władza polityczna. To samo dotyczy wolności narodów. Wbrew tej wolności i wbrew traktatom obecne władze Unii Europejskiej powołują się na, jak to mówi pan przewodniczący Timmermans, wolę zdecydowanej większości rządów i tego Parlamentu.</p>
      <p sl="en">O co więc chodzi w tym apelu? Czy naprawdę o tyranię większości czy może o to, żeby znieść ostatnią zaporę, która ochroni naszą wolność, czyli o to, żeby zniewolić opinię publiczną naszych narodów?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-254-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já jsem pro tuto zprávu nakonec nehlasovala. Přesto bych chtěla poděkovat kolegovi Franku Engelovi za to, že se snažil tu zprávu udržet ve věcné rovině a zaměřil ji na podstatné věci, jako je boj proti diskriminaci, nesnášenlivosti, rasismu a násilí všeho druhu, a samozřejmě také kladl důraz na ochranu dětí na internetu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Problém ovšem představují ty části, které navrhují větší podporu sexuálním a reprodukčním právům s tím, že tato práva souvisí se základními lidskými právy. Také za problematické považuji návrhy levice, které nakonec byly prohlasovány a které vybízí k plošnému uznávání sňatků homosexuálů. Musím říci, že jsem hlasovala pro vypuštění těchto částí, ale byla nás menšina, a proto jsem nakonec nemohla pro tuto zprávu hlasovat, protože se domnívám, že o těchto věcech mají rozhodovat členské státy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-255-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! 1 marca to szczególny dzień dla Polaków – to Narodowy Dzień Pamięci Żołnierzy Wyklętych. To dzień, w którym przywracamy pamięć żołnierzom drugiej konspiracji, którzy po drugiej wojnie światowej nie złożyli broni, tylko stanęli do heroicznej walki z komunistycznym okupantem.</p>
      <p sl="en">W latach 1944–56 wymordowano w Polsce blisko 50 tysięcy żołnierzy podziemia niepodległościowego, a do więzień wsadzono 250 tysięcy ludzi. Kolejne tysiące wywieziono na Syberię i w inne miejsca Rosji. Inwigilowano w latach stalinowskich blisko 5 milionów Polaków. Niestety te działania okazały się na tyle skuteczne, że komunistyczna władza przetrwała aż do 1989 roku i to ta władza ukształtowała system sprawiedliwości w Polsce, który dzisiaj rząd Prawa i Sprawiedliwości chce reformować, a niestety dyktatura większości w Parlamencie Europejskim mu to utrudnia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-256-0000" speaker_id="1164" name="Bruno Gollnisch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, le rapport Engel est un rapport véritablement totalitaire qui consiste à qualifier de «discours de haine» toute plainte émanant de la minorité et de «discours d’amour, de justice, de charité, de bienveillance» le discours de la majorité oppressive de ces institutions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais ne ferait-on pas mieux de balayer devant sa porte? Ne ferait-on pas mieux d’assurer le respect des droits les plus élémentaires au sein de cette institution, de ce Parlement européen? Je prends mon exemple personnel: sur la requête du Secrétaire général Welle, fonctionnaire issu des milieux politisés de cette Assemblée, je suis taxé de près de 300 000 euros, somme faramineuse. Je suis ponctionné des trois-quarts des émoluments qui devraient me servir à assurer mon mandat pour le motif parfaitement grotesque que mon assistant, pendant six ans, a travaillé non seulement avec moi, mais aussi avec mon collègue Jean-Marie Le Pen. Ni mon assistant ni moi-même, à aucun moment, n’avons été entendus ni par le Secrétaire général Welle, ni par les questeurs, ni par le Bureau dont vous faites partie. Commencez par respecter les droits de l’homme à l’intérieur du Parlement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-257-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I voted in favour of the report on the situation on fundamental rights in the EU in 2016. However, I would like to raise your attention to one thing: the rights of minorities in the EU are only a marginal topic in this report. I believe this is not a shortcoming of the report drafted by our colleague Frank Engel but rather a shortcoming of our policies. We actually do not have a real European approach to minorities, and we leave it to the discretion of Member States to protect them, but in some Member States minorities belong to really vulnerable groups.</p>
      <p sl="en">To give you one example, the Russian-speaking minority in Latvia is in decline due to emigration and to the negative birth rate. The death rate among Russian speakers in Latvia is much higher than the average in the country. The reasons for that are their unfavourable social conditions and the absence of rights for civil and political participation. These people are in a situation of total cultural insecurity and the reproduction of their identity is at high risk.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-258-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, vótáil mé i bhfabhar na tuarascála seo, cinnte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madam President, our fundamental rights must be rigorously upheld, and this report has carried out a thorough investigation and evaluation of that. The issues of hate speech, discrimination, migration and integration are especially relevant in our society, and we must learn how to combat division and animosity through the core values of the Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">I respect reports focused on protecting citizens and asylum seekers alike from violence and discrimination. We must continue to take into account the rights of minorities and communities throughout the EU, from ethnic groups to members of the LGBT+ community.</p>
      <p sl="en">The increased emphasis in the fight against organised crime and human trafficking is to be praised. I would also like to mention in that regard that we in the European Union should be making more noise and do more to bring attention to the appalling act of kidnapping by Boko Haram of 100 girls, and we must do everything we can to get them back.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-260-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">J’ai le regret de vous signaler que nous ne pourrons pas prendre oralement les explications de vote sur les rapports de M. Sander Loones, de M. Nart et de Mmes Bilbao Barandica et Vallina. Explications de vote, évidemment, qui pourront être déposées par écrit. Nous avons un problème de temps et nous ne pouvons pas les prendre.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem33" title="10.5. Prospects and challenges for the EU apiculture sector (A8-0014/2018 - Norbert Erdős)">
    <intervention id="2-274-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, what is in a jar of honey? In this jar – I am confident – it is pure honey produced by buzzing Suffolk bees and harvested by members of the West Suffolk Beekeepers’ Association that I had the pleasure of meeting last week. But honey is the third most adulterated product in the world. Twenty percent of samples taken on imported honey do not respect our high standards. Honey fraudsters add sugar syrup to their product or harvest it early and artificially dry it out to cut time and costs. They con consumers and endanger legitimate beekeeping with knock—on effects for the number of pollinators.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why I support this fight back with improved testing procedures, better labelling and higher penalties for fraudsters. Producing honey is hard work. This little jar of liquid gold represents the nectar from two million flowers so let us swarm to the defence of our hardworking bees and beekeepers.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-275-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já bych chtěla zdůvodnit, proč jsem předložila tuto zprávu o budoucnosti evropského včelařství. Z několika důvodů, především včely a opylování rostlin mají pro udržitelnou zemědělskou produkci zásadní význam. Nehledě na to, že včelařské produkty jsou v EU velmi žádané. Domnívám se, že je nutné zaměřit se na ty problémy, které jsme schopni ovlivnit vhodnými opatřeními také na evropské úrovni. Jedná se především o identifikaci případů padělání medu, které evropským včelařům působí velké škody a pro spotřebitele představují vážná zdravotní rizika. Zároveň je třeba eliminovat množství dováženého medu do EU z Číny a třetích zemí. V této souvislosti zcela podporuji návrh na zrušení klamavého označení směs medu ze zemí EU a mimo EU a jeho nahrazení jasným označením konkrétní země původu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-276-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Eugenia Aguilera García" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, quiero mostrar mi posición favorable a este informe de propia iniciativa, al gran trabajo que se ha hecho, especialmente por mi compañero Nekov, en nuestro Grupo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Creo que se ha hecho un informe muy exhaustivo, y espero que la Comisión Europea lo aproveche con la finalidad de atajar el grave problema que hay de la mortalidad en las abejas. Es un grave problema y, por tanto, hay que abordarlo en serio, con medidas serias, para tener una buena respuesta y no causar problemas al medio ambiente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero quiero destacar en mi intervención que la enmienda que proponía un grupo de colegas sobre la prohibición total de neonicotinoides creo que no es oportuna. No podemos tomar decisiones políticas basadas solo en el influjo, en no se sabe qué. Es decir, las decisiones políticas deben estar basadas en los resultados del análisis científico y, por tanto, estoy muy de acuerdo con la opinión de la EFSA, que prohíbe parcialmente algunos neonicotinoides.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-277-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Уважаеми колеги, пред европейските пчелари днес има много предизвикателства и е крайно време на тях да бъде отговорено. Радвам се, че приехме днешния доклад, защото е крайно време нашите пчелари да бъдат чути.</p>
      <p sl="en">Основната функция на пчелите е опрашването. Тази екологична услуга трябва да бъде справедливо възмездена и в новата ОСП да се въведат преки субсидии за опрашването, извършвано от пчелите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Пълна забрана за използването на неоникотиноидите, защото е крайно време това да стане факт. Здравето на пчелите се влошава от 90-те години, в много региони те умират, а европейското земеделие става монокултурно. Тази тенденция трябва да спре.</p>
      <p sl="en">Предлагаме 50% увеличение на финансовата помощ за националните програми за пчеларството, и това да бъде минимумът, като това трябва да се направи наистина много бързо. Вносът от трети страни също е голямо предизвикателство. Нискокачествен или евтин мед от страни като Китай, Украйна или Аржентина задушава европейските производители.</p>
      <p sl="en">Докладът е прогресивен и дава доста правилни насоки за развитието на сектора.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-278-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Já jsem s radostí podpořil tuto zprávu svých kolegů, kteří ji z vlastní iniciativy předložili. Na první pohled to může vypadat, že téma včelařství je téma, které je okrajové. V žádném případě to tak není. Už to tady moji kolegové říkali, ten dopad tohoto sektoru do celé zemědělské politiky je mimořádně významný nejen podílem a tím, že zaměstnává naše spoluobčany, ale právě tím, že opylování je klíčová věc, kterou právě včely zajišťují.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je dobře, že ta zpráva popisuje aktuální problémy od řekněme nemocí včelstev, které vedou k destrukci včelstev, až po problémy spojené s jednotným trhem. Otázka pašování produktů, které se nazývají medem a medem nejsou, do Evropy je myslím problém, který právě má řešit EU. Měly by to řešit jaksi odpovědné orgány EU, Evropská komise by se tím měla zabývat. Mě velmi překvapila informace, že med je 2. – 3. nejčastěji falšovanou komoditou na trhu. Je dobře, že zpráva byla přijata.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-279-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, fáiltím agus vótáil mé ar son na tuarascála seo mar is tuarascáil an-tábhachtach í.</p>
      <p sl="en">The fact that 76% of European food production depends on bee pollination shows how integral the species is to core aspects of humanity’s future. The destruction of European bee pollination by disease is of key concern. Therefore, it is essential that we support, educate and train more producers and the public, and commit to researching the challenges facing bees and the apiculture industry today.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must support current beekeepers, many of whom have faced, or are facing, shutdown in business due to fake honey or decimated bee populations, and therefore I praise the recommendations for the revision of EU support for beekeepers. I especially hope this will be an integral part of the next common agricultural policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">The trends for beekeeping within the Union have been positive in recent years, and it is essential we maintain this upward momentum in order to preserve the apiculture sector for generations to come. Our future and the future of the planet depend on it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-281-0000" speaker_id="39724" name="Csaba Sógor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Meglehetősen méltánytalan helyzetben vannak az Unió méztermelői, mivel a jelenlegi uniós agrárpolitika nem támogatja kellőképpen a tevékenységüket, továbbá jelentős mértékű hamisított mézzel is meg kell küzdeniük a belső piacon. Ez a hamisított mennyiség nagyrészt EU-n kívüli országokból származik, és nemcsak a termelőinket lehetetleníti el, hanem a fogyasztók megtévesztését is jelenti. Elsősorban a saját termelőink számára kell kedvező feltételeket teremtenünk annak érdekében, hogy az uniós fogyasztók egészséges és minőségi mézhez jussanak, továbbá meg kell változtatnunk a jelenlegi tisztességtelen versenyhelyzetet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ennek érdekében a 2020 utáni Közös Agrárpolitikában külön figyelmet érdemelnek a méztermelők, akik számára egy új, közvetlen támogatási rendszer kialakítása, valamint adómentesség bevezetése szükséges. Az uniós polgároknak pedig joguk van tudni, hogy az általuk mézként vásárolt termékek milyen arányban tartalmaznak európai termelőktől származó mézet, s ennek megfelelően kell átalakítani a termékek címkézését.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-282-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this is not fair. We waited and we prepared to speak and I think you should stay until the end. There are two more files for which we prepared to speak. It is less than ten minutes. It is on the list and now you cancel it. Really it is not fair for us.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-283-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame, j’ai indiqué à deux reprises que nous avions une contrainte horaire importante et que donc nous serions obligés de nous arrêter à 13 h 30. Nous arrêtons à 13 h 36 et je crois avoir prévenu effectivement. Mais vos explications sont les bienvenues. Elles seront recueillies à l’écrit dans le procès-verbal de cette séance, il n’y a aucun problème. Je suis désolée, mais nous avons cette contrainte importante et nous ne pouvons pas la dépasser.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem34" title="11. Corrections to votes and voting intentions : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem35" title="12. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem36" title="13. Transfers of appropriations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem37" title="14. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem38" title="15. Dates of forthcoming sittings : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem39" title="16. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem40" title="17. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="2-307-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Je déclare interrompue la session du Parlement européen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
