<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20181129.EN" lang="en" date="2018-11-29" place="Brussels" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting">
    <intervention id="2-004-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Good morning. My apologies for the slight delay. I think some people had difficulty with traffic this morning, so thank you for your patience. The sitting is now open.</p>
      <a text="(The sitting opened at 9.06)"/>
      <p sl="unknown">Before we move to the first item on the agenda, there is a point of order from Mr Corbett.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-005-0000" speaker_id="2309" name="Richard Corbett" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, under Rule 162(3) and (6), Parliament has decided that this debate we are about to start on Brexit will only have a round of speakers from the leaders of each of the political groups. That has a consequence, Madam President. There will be three British voices in that debate, each and every one of them from those who support Brexit. Parliament will not hear a single British voice from those who oppose Brexit, which according to the latest opinion polls actually represents the majority view of the British population.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-006-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Thank you, Mr Corbett. Your point is noted. It was a decision of the political groups to have this format. I’m in the hands of the decision of the political groups, but I think your point is well taken by the plenary.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. The Cum Ex Scandal: financial crime and the loopholes in the current legal framework (motions for resolutions tabled): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. The UK’s withdrawal from the European Union (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-009-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the debate on the Council and Commission statements on the UK’s withdrawal from the European Union 2018/2958(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-010-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karoline Edtstadler" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President-in-Office of the Council">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, Chief Negotiator Barnier, ladies and gentlemen, the European Council endorsed the agreement of the withdrawal of the UK from the EU and Euratom. The European Council then invited the Commission, the European Parliament and the Council to take the necessary steps to ensure that the agreement can enter into force on 30 March 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Council also approved the political declaration setting out the framework for the future relationship between the EU and the UK. On that occasion, the Union’s determination to have as close as possible a partnership with the UK in the future was restated in line with that declaration. This outcome would not have been possible without the commitment and the determination of Mr Barnier and his team, to which the European Council paid tribute. No less important was the sense of unity, shared purpose and responsibility amongst the EU’s 27 Member States, as well as amongst the EU institutions.</p>
      <p sl="en">On this particular occasion, I should like to express my appreciation for the constant involvement and timely contribution of the Brexit Steering Group and, more broadly, the European Parliament. In the coming months we will have to secure the conclusion of the withdrawal agreement. The Council is doing its utmost to adopt its decision on signature in the coming weeks, which should allow the EP to complete its consent procedure in good time, before the end of March 2019.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-011-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">négociateur en chef sur le Brexit. – Madame la Présidente, Madame la Secrétaire d’État, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, bonjour à chacune et chacun d’entre vous. Je vous remercie de me donner l’occasion de m’exprimer au nom de la Commission européenne et vous prie d’excuser le président Jean-Claude Juncker, qui participe en ce moment au sommet du G20.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, nous sommes à un moment important et grave, dix-sept mois après le début des négociations, que j’ai eu l’honneur et que j’ai l’honneur de conduire sous l’autorité et avec la confiance du président Jean-Claude Juncker et avec le soutien de toute la Commission européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dimanche, comme vous l’avez rappelé, Madame la Secrétaire d’État, le Conseil européen a approuvé notre projet d’accord de retrait. Il a approuvé aussi la déclaration politique qui fixe le cadre de notre future relation. À ce stade, je veux de mon côté remercier le Conseil européen, son président, Donald Tusk, toutes ses équipes, mais aussi les présidents successifs avec lesquels j’ai travaillé et bien travaillé, la Présidence autrichienne aujourd’hui, mais aussi la Bulgarie, l’Estonie et Malte. Puis, nous continuerons avec la Roumanie dans les mois qui viennent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mesdames et Messieurs, le temps des négociations sur l’accord de retrait et sur la déclaration politique est terminé. C’est maintenant le temps de la ratification par le Parlement britannique, par votre Parlement et par le Conseil.</p>
      <p sl="en">Compte tenu des circonstances difficiles de cette négociation et de l’extrême complexité de tous les sujets de ce retrait britannique, l’accord qui est sur la table – le projet de retrait ordonné et la déclaration politique – est le seul et le meilleur possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons réussi cette première grande étape ensemble et, du côté européen, grâce à l’unité très forte des vingt-sept États membres et de toutes les institutions entre elles.</p>
      <p sl="en">En particulier, Madame la Présidente, l’accord de retrait et cette déclaration politique doivent beaucoup à vos quatre résolutions et à la vigilance attentive dont vous avez fait preuve depuis le début de cette négociation, évidemment, pour préserver les droits des citoyens que vous représentez – c’était votre priorité, c’était ma priorité –, pour préserver les intérêts de l’Union européenne, l’intégrité du marché unique et l’indivisibilité des quatre libertés, et l’autonomie de décision de l’Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ces deux documents, nous les avons co-construits ensemble tout au long du processus. Madame la Présidente, à travers vous, je veux aussi remercier le président Tajani et vous me permettrez de dire un mot plus personnel à Guy Verhofstadt, coordinateur de votre assemblée pour le Brexit, et à tous et à chacun des membres du groupe de pilotage sur le Brexit, Danuta Hübner, Elmar Brok, Roberto Gualtieri, Gabriele Zimmer et Philippe Lamberts qui ont suivi avec toutes leurs équipes, que je remercie, les négociations jour après jour au sein de ce groupe de pilotage. Je remercie aussi les présidents de groupe, les présidents de commission et Cécilia Wikström, sachant que nous ne sommes pas au bout d’une longue route qui restera difficile.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’accord trouvé dimanche est aussi le résultat d’une méthode que nous avons décidée ensemble et avec vous. Nous avons mis les choses dans l’ordre, en commençant – comme c’était logique – par négocier l’accord de retrait, un retrait ordonné, avant de discuter du cadre de notre future relation avec le Royaume-Uni. Nous avons insisté pour régler en amont certaines questions qui étaient et qui sont toujours prioritaires pour votre Parlement, à savoir les droits des citoyens, la paix et la stabilité en Irlande, et le règlement financier. Mesdames et Messieurs, dès le départ, nous avons surtout travaillé en toute transparence, c’est-à-dire en toute confiance, et nous continuerons.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette méthode nous a permis d’expliquer les enjeux de chaque sujet, de montrer ce qui était possible et ce qui ne l’était pas compte tenu des principes fondamentaux de notre Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Depuis le début, nous avons expliqué comment nous pouvions et devions respecter nos principes et, en même temps, prendre en compte les lignes rouges officiellement indiquées par le Royaume-Uni. Finalement, nous avons trouvé un terrain d’entente. En un mot, le cadre que nous avons posé a donné une stabilité et une prévisibilité à cette négociation. Personne ne peut être objectivement surpris par le contenu de notre accord.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mesdames et Messieurs, il est peut-être utile de rappeler à ce stade que l’Union européenne n’a pas souhaité le Brexit. À ce jour, personne d’ailleurs n’a été capable de me démontrer la valeur ajoutée du Brexit, mais nous respectons le vote démocratique et souverain des citoyens britanniques et nous avons donc, comme le gouvernement britannique l’a demandé, mis en œuvre ce processus pour une sortie ordonnée. Simplement, les deux documents agréés dimanche permettent de limiter les conséquences négatives du Brexit des deux côtés mais aussi, en particulier, pour les vingt-sept États membres de l’Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’accord de retrait apporte de la sécurité juridique à toutes les personnes, aux entreprises, aux régions inquiètes des conséquences de la décision britannique de quitter l’Union européenne: évidemment, les citoyens européens, 4 millions et demi de personnes qui vivent au Royaume-Uni et les citoyens britanniques établis dans l’un des pays de l’Union; les habitants et les entreprises d’Irlande et d’Irlande du Nord, Madame la Présidente, qui participent à toutes les dimensions humaine, sociale, économique de la coopération Nord-Sud. La solution de dernier recours sur laquelle nous nous sommes mis d’accord pour éviter le retour d’une frontière physique en Irlande tout en protégeant le marché unique fait partie intégrante de l’accord de retrait. Sans cette solution pour l’Irlande, il n’y a pas d’accord de retrait. Les collectivités ensuite, les universités et les entreprises qui portent tant de projets financés par les politiques et les budgets européens, y compris avec les partenaires britanniques, les universités, les laboratoires extrêmement dynamiques au Royaume-Uni. Les agriculteurs qui bénéficient de la politique agricole commune et qui souhaitaient légitimement protéger leurs droits de propriété intellectuelle, et bien plus que cela, à travers les indications géographiques. Et puis, tous ceux dont les données personnelles ont été échangées avec des organismes ou des entreprises basées au Royaume-Uni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voilà les personnes et les secteurs pour lesquels nous avions le devoir de remettre de la sécurité là où le Brexit a créé de l’insécurité. C’est l’objet de cet accord de retrait très dense – j’en conviens – parce qu’il s’agit d’un traité juridique, précis et complet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quant à la déclaration politique, elle fixe le cadre dans lequel nous allons, dès que possible, négocier notre relation future.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, dans cette négociation, l’Union européenne continuera à défendre ses intérêts et à appliquer exactement les mêmes principes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans cette négociation qui va s’ouvrir, l’Union adoptera, tout comme votre négociateur, la même attitude. Il n’y aura jamais et il n’y a jamais eu d’agressivité. Il n’y aura jamais et il n’y a jamais eu d’esprit de revanche. Il n’y aura jamais et il n’y a jamais eu de ma part un quelconque esprit de punition. Nous continuerons à travailler avec le Royaume-Uni, et non pas contre lui, pour bâtir ce partenariat futur et nous continuerons à travailler avec le respect qui est dû à un grand pays qui restera en toute hypothèse notre ami, notre partenaire et notre allié.</p>
      <p sl="en">La vérité, s’agissant de cette relation future, c’est que, compte tenu de la décision britannique de quitter l’Union européenne et le marché unique, cela ne peut pas être le statu quo à l’avenir. Cela ne peut pas être «business as usual» et notre devoir est de le dire, notamment aux entreprises, qui doivent se préparer. Mais notre intérêt mutuel, c’est bien de bâtir un partenariat ambitieux sur les biens, les services, le numérique, la mobilité, les transports, les marchés publics, l’énergie, la sécurité intérieure – évidemment – pour la stabilité de notre continent, la politique étrangère avec ce pays qui restera actif au sein du Conseil de sécurité des Nations unies, la défense et dans bien d’autres domaines.</p>
      <p sl="en">Plus ce partenariat sera ambitieux, plus nous serons, de notre côté, attentifs et exigeants sur le cadre des conditions de concurrence entre nous. Au total, si nous concrétisons cette déclaration politique dans toutes ces dimensions, permettez-moi de vous dire – et je dis bien si nous concrétisons cette déclaration politique dans toutes ces dimensions –, le partenariat avec le Royaume-Uni sera sans précédent par l’étendue et le nombre des sujets de coopération.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comme l’a souhaité le président Juncker et comme l’ont souhaité les États membres et votre Parlement, nous nous préparerons et nous serons prêts à lancer cette négociation sur la future relation, une fois le Royaume-Uni devenu pays tiers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais avant cela, Madame la Présidente, il reste évidemment une étape décisive, celle de la ratification de notre accord de retrait. Le temps est maintenant venu pour chacun de prendre ses responsabilités. Les parlementaires britanniques auront dans les semaines qui viennent à se prononcer sur cet accord de retrait et sur le texte de la déclaration politique et ce vote engage l’avenir de leur pays. Nous devons respecter – et je respecterai – ce débat et ce temps de débat parlementaire et démocratique au Royaume-Uni. De notre côté, nous devons laisser ce temps de la ratification au Parlement européen qui a été et qui restera étroitement associé à chacune des étapes de cette négociation, et qui aura le dernier mot.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, merci pour votre confiance et votre attention.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-012-0000" speaker_id="97058" name="Guy Verhofstadt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Parliament's Brexit coordinator) on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, first of all, I would like to welcome the withdrawal agreement and the political declaration. I think that we can say easily today that both have been built around the principles of the European Union – that means the integrity of the Single Market, that means the four freedoms which underpin that Single Market and that means the ability, the capacity of the European Union to decide in an autonomous way.</p>
      <p sl="de">But I have to tell you, and I think it’s important in these debates, that also two other elements have been taken into account. The first are naturally the positions – maybe I have to say the red lines – of the UK Government following the decision to end the membership of the European Union. Then, a second important point that underpins this agreement or these agreements, and that is something often underplayed and not fully understood, is the 1998 Good Friday Agreement, though the European Union is in fact not a direct party in this. The 1998 Agreement was only possible among EU Member States, between EU Member States, and it shows, in my opinion, that the European Union is about that, about reconciliation, about the end of violence, about peace. The result of all this is the withdrawal agreement, and I think the only and best agreement possible, considering these three elements that I have just described.</p>
      <p sl="de">In achieving this, I would like to thank, naturally, and congratulate – it’s not the first time that I’m doing this – Michel Barnier personally. He has done a tremendous job in close cooperation with the European Parliament and with the Brexit Steering Group, and this also gives me the possibility to congratulate all the members of the Brexit Steering Group for the good cooperation beyond the lines of the political parties. I think that it worked very well.</p>
      <p sl="de">Now, the result, Michel, is an agreement that, in my opinion, does three things. The first is to minimise the disruption for both sides, in particular for the economy, and to allow for an orderly withdrawal and allow for a timeframe between two and four years to conclude the negotiations on the future relationship. The second result is to avoid a hard border on the island of Ireland, to safeguard the Good Friday Agreement and to secure peace. Then the third thing – and I think this was the first priority of the European Parliament – is to safeguard the rights of all citizens. Here the European Parliament has, with the help and with the support of our negotiators, significantly improved the agreement and the text. Moreover, we are also committed – and I want to tell you this today – to ensuring that, before we start the consent procedure in the European Parliament, we receive from our British counterparts the necessary guarantees that all these citizens’ rights will be fully implemented.</p>
      <p sl="de">I believe that this framework – withdrawal agreement and political declaration – provides for the possibility to establish in the future a really close relationship between the European Union and the United Kingdom and the basis, therefore, as you have seen in the agreement, in the political declaration, is an association agreement, as the European Parliament has proposed from day one. Why an association agreement, on which also the British Government has agreed? Well, it will be applicable, once concluded, in a provisional way after approval at the European level. Secondly, it will be ratified in one round of ratification by the Member States, so as to avoid – if I may say so – the complexity of, for example, our relationship with Switzerland, which is based not on one association agreement, but on a patchwork of agreements.</p>
      <p sl="de">The Brexit Steering Group, along with the whole European Parliament, will further scrutinise the deal, the withdrawal agreement and the political declaration on the future relationship, as part of the consent procedure.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-013-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">(Exclamations by certain members of Parliament) Colleagues, I am in the Chair, so I will call time, with due respect. Thank you for your guidance, but you will respect the Chair please.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-014-0000" speaker_id="97058" name="Guy Verhofstadt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ALDE Group">
      <p sl="de">Madam President, Parliament will, in this respect, look very carefully into how the so—called Joint Committee will work. We want to ensure that the decisions that are taken by the Joint Committee are legitimate and, where necessary, also require the approval of the Parliament. I hope that, before we start the consent procedure, we can have an agreement with the Council.</p>
      <p sl="de">Let’s be clear that there will be no winners in this. I think that the departure of the UK from the Union is a failure for everybody – for the UK and for the EU. Last Sunday – we have to tell our colleagues this – was a sad day for both. So let us make the best of it in the knowledge that in the near future there will be a new generation in Britain who will – and I’m pretty sure about this – decide to come back into the great political European family.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-015-0000" speaker_id="1263" name="Elmar Brok" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, Frau Ratspräsidentin, Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Der Brexit ist eine schlechte Angelegenheit, für uns in der Europäischen Union und für Großbritannien – mehr für Großbritannien wegen der unterschiedlichen Größe als für uns, aber auch für uns. Deswegen war der Sonntag, wie Guy Verhofstadt – dem ich für die Zusammenarbeit danke – richtig analysiert hat, ein trauriger Tag. Aber aufgrund der Verhandlungskunst von Michel Barnier und seines Teams, seiner Geduld und seiner Informationspolitik innerhalb der Europäischen Union ist es gelungen, den bestmöglichen Deal herauszuholen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich muss sagen, in Großbritannien ist die Regierung gespalten, die Regierungspartei ist gespalten, die Opposition ist gespalten, das Land ist gespalten. Diese Europäische Union, die angeblich am Ende ist, war einig, mit 27 Ländern, mit Rat, Kommission und Parlament, und auch das Parlament war einig. Diese Europäische Union hat eine große Zukunftschance; das hat sie in diesen Brexit-Verhandlungen bewiesen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen sehen, dass wir diesen Schaden für Großbritannien möglichst gering halten, der etwa durch die Äußerung der Bank of England gestern noch einmal deutlich geworden ist: Es wird in Großbritannien größere Wachstumsverluste durch den Brexit als durch den Finanzschaden von 2008 geben. Das ist die Erklärung der Bank of England von gestern. Da kann Herr Farage, der ja der Redenschreiber von Herrn Trump ist, erklären, was er will, sein Land weiter belügen. Das wird an den Fakten nichts ändern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen sehen, dass dies aber bedeutet – und ich glaube, das Europäische Parlament unterstützt das –, dass es keine weiteren Verhandlungen gibt. Es ist dieser Deal und kein anderer. Es geht nicht noch mal, nicht nach der Methode „noch einmal ablehnen, dann verhandeln wir noch mal, und dann gibt es wieder einen neuen Deal“. Dies ist eine Vereinbarung, die steht, die muss man so nehmen, die ist lange verhandelt worden. Und aus diesem Grund muss klar sein, dass der Austrittsvertrag eine Bedingung ist für eine Übergangsregelung. Ich habe den Eindruck, das ist manchen in Großbritannien nicht klar. Wenn der Austrittsvertrag nicht kommt, gibt es keine Übergangsregelung. Der Bruch wird donnerartig sein – für beide Seiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen sehen, dass mit diesem Vertrag auch deutlich gemacht werden muss, dass es eine schwierige und risikoreiche Angelegenheit der Remainer ist, wenn sie jetzt meinen, diesen Vertrag abzulehnen und vielleicht dann noch vor dem 29. März etwas anderes, einschließlich eines Referendums, hinzubekommen. Dies halte ich für ein sehr gefährliches Unterfangen. Man sollte aus Sicherheitsgründen, damit der Schaden gering bleibt, diesen Deal nehmen. Deshalb appelliere ich an beide Seiten in Großbritannien in diesem Spiel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben festgestellt, dass damit die Übergangsregelung durch diesen Vertrag kommt , dass die Rechte der Bürger gewährleistet sind, die sich von beiden Seiten auf den Bestand der Europäischen Union verlassen haben in ihrer persönlichen Lebensplanung, dass es keine harte Grenze mit katastrophalen menschlichen und ökonomischen Konsequenzen zwischen Nordirland und der Republik Irland geben wird, und dass wir dabei einen Backstop vereinbart haben, der, solange die Übergangsperiode läuft, überhaupt nicht in Kraft tritt, und dass wir dann eine Verhandlung durchführen über den zukünftigen Vertrag, ohne dass er in Kraft tritt. Ziel des Backstops ist es, dass er nicht in Kraft tritt. Das muss deutlich sein, und deswegen darf dieses nicht missbraucht werden, auch nicht in den Diskussionen in Großbritannien.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich meine, dass wir die zukünftigen Beziehungen im gemeinsamen Interesse – ich wiederhole mich –, um den Schaden gering zu halten, mit großem konstruktivem Bewusstsein für eine Lösung führen müssen. Großbritannien will keine Zollunion, weil sie eigene Handelsverträge machen wollen. Sie wollen nicht Mitglied des Binnenmarkts sein, weil sie die vier Freiheiten nicht erfüllen wollen. Aber alles, was danach möglich ist, sollten wir möglich machen. Und deswegen sollten wir einen Freihandelsvertrag machen, der sehr weitgehend ist. Theresa May hatte Recht, als sie im Frühjahr sagte: Je mehr wir in unseren Standards ähnlich sind, je mehr level playing field wir haben, desto mehr Marktzugang gibt es. Das sollte man in dem Zusammenhang sehen, um auf die Art und Weise den Schaden möglichst gering zu halten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sollten aber deutlich machen, dass dieses Partnerschaftsabkommen, das ja vom Europäischen Parlament initiiert worden ist, das jetzt in der Vereinbarung drinsteht – wir haben es noch Assoziierungsabkommen genannt –, dass das diesen Handelsvertrag weitgehend beinhalten soll, aber auch Fragen der inneren und äußeren Sicherheit. Es ist im beiderseitigen Interesse, dass wir Vereinbarungen treffen im Kampf gegen den Terrorismus, dass wir eine Beteiligung Großbritanniens in einem bestimmten möglichen Sinne auch bei der Gemeinsamen Sicherheits- und Verteidigungspolitik haben. Beide Seiten wollen dies. Dafür setzt dieser Austrittsvertrag die entsprechenden Rahmenbedingungen, um das in einem weiteren Vertrag zu verhandeln, um die Sicherheit unserer Völker sicherzustellen. Das gilt auch für andere Bereiche wie Forschung, wenn ich die Situation der englischen Universitäten sehe und wie sehr sie im Forschungsprogramm sein wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lassen Sie mich eine letzte Bemerkung machen: Herr Farage schreibt Herrn Trumps Reden, und Herr Trump hat vorgestern gesagt, er würde nicht einmal dieses Withdrawal Agreement machen, weil er so mit Großbritannien nicht verhandeln will. Herr Trump möchte, dass alle europäischen Länder geteilt, vereinzelt werden, damit er sie sich einzeln vornehmen kann, einzeln in die Breschen schlagen kann und sie fertigmachen kann. Diese Trump-Rede ist die beste Begründung, dass wir in Zukunft eine Europäische Union brauchen, damit sich unsere Völker gemeinsam gegen die Trumps und Putins und Xis. verteidigen können. Das werden wir uns auch durch Herrn Farages Reden, die er für Herrn Trump schreibt, nicht zerstören lassen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-016-0000" speaker_id="96892" name="Roberto Gualtieri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, after long and difficult negotiations, the agreement reached on Sunday sets the basis for an orderly withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union, and we are ready to ratify it.</p>
      <p sl="en">On behalf of the S&amp;D Group, I would like to thank Michel Barnier for the outstanding work he and his team have done in dealing with this historic challenge. At the same time, I cannot hide my profound sadness about the UK’s choice to leave the Union. Our Group respects this decision, but we deeply regret it. We consider it an historic mistake. In our eyes, it will always be a lose—lose situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Despite the disappointment and the frustration, the EU – and all of us – have acted, since the very beginning of the process, with responsibility and respect. We have worked tirelessly for more than two years to protect those most affected by the decision and to alleviate its worst possible consequences. This was achieved thanks to the guidance of our lead negotiators and thanks to the unity within, and between, the EU institutions. I would also like to thank Guy Verhofstadt and all the members of the Brexit Steering Group. We have been – and we shall be – always united.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU has been responsible towards the UK by providing the basis to deliver an orderly withdrawal without any feelings of revenge or resentment. We have also been responsible towards ourselves and our citizens not to endanger the European project and the integrity of our Union. This sense of responsibility shall continue to guide us going forward.</p>
      <p sl="en">One thing must be clear, though. There is no alternative deal to the one agreed on Sunday. Considering the United Kingdom’s red lines, this is the best, and the only possible, agreement. It is a deal that protects citizens’ rights, safeguards the integrity of the single market and the customs union and, crucially, prevents a hard border on the island of Ireland, respecting the Good Friday Agreement in all its parts.</p>
      <p sl="en">We know that on citizens’ rights, which have been our priority from the start, our work is far from being finished and we will remain vigilant with respect to the implementation of this part of the agreement. We will never allow EU citizens to fall victim to the same disgraceful hostile—environment policies that saw members of the Windrush generation wrongly deported.</p>
      <p sl="en">The political declaration accompanying the withdrawal agreement establishes the framework and basis for an ambitious, broad and deep partnership. This unprecedented partnership, which should take the form of an association agreement, shall fully respect the integrity of the single market and the autonomy of our legal order. We also welcome all the interpretative declarations adopted by the Council and consider them legally binding, including with regard to Gibraltar. On the future relationship, the UK has made its red lines clear throughout the process – just as we have – and we respect this.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the negotiations we have shown a high degree of flexibility and we have stretched the deal as much as we could in order to take into account the position and the constraints of the United Kingdom. We have always said – and we repeat it now – that if the UK changes its mind our arms are, and will remain, open. But insofar as you want to leave the single market and no longer apply the principle of free movement of persons, this is the only possible way to leave the European Union in an orderly manner, avoiding the severe disruption of a no—deal scenario. There is no other deal that could respect such limits without compromising or endangering our European project. This Parliament is the very symbol of our common project and of the links between countries and people. This is why we will continue to play a responsible and proactive role in safeguarding the integrity of the Union and ensuring a positive future relationship with the United Kingdom.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-017-0000" speaker_id="4513" name="Geoffrey Van Orden" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, (inaudible) … lot of experts on domestic British policy these days. Look, Brexit was always about much more than the economy. In a way, because the European Union strayed so far into many other areas, into our national lives, it is why the British people voted for Brexit. They were increasingly unhappy with this tendency. You say you didn’t want Brexit, but you did nothing to avoid it.</p>
      <p sl="en">But of course the economic aspects are central. A bad deal for Britain or no deal will have repercussions in many European countries as well as Britain. Much time seems to be spent here on predicting events in London and the consequences of Brexit for Britain. Perhaps we should look at the impact of a bad deal or a sour relationship on the European Union. Certainly, the British government entered into negotiations in a spirit of goodwill, aiming for a positive future partnership. There’s been astonishment in Britain over the legalistic inflexibility that has been shown quite often. But we all know that the EU will bend or break any of its own rules when it suits it, and instead of defending the long-term interests of EU countries, it seems to have chosen to pursue a narrow ideological course defending a particular view of the EU project, which is increasingly repudiated by citizens across Europe; it may appeal to the leaders of a couple of the larger countries in the European Union. Instead of listening to citizens, your answer to everything is just more Europe. And by the way, I think a lot of people have been very cross in Britain about the discourteous way in which our Prime Minister seems often to have been treated.</p>
      <p sl="en">Because of your insistence on a bizarre sequencing arrangement, you’ve wasted two years when you could already have made progress on a free trade agreement. All other issues would then have fallen into place – it wasn’t necessary to do it in the way you did. This makes it all the more important to move quickly into negotiating our future relationship and reaching rapid but correct conclusions, but we need some reassurance and flexibility – indeed, guarantees – from the EU over concerns that have been expressed. We need an atmosphere of trust and goodwill from your side if we are to have that future positive, stable relationship that is surely the least that all our citizens demand.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-018-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, dear colleagues, at the EU Council last Sunday, many asked me if I felt sad. Actually rather than sadness, I felt gratitude first to Michel Barnier and his outstanding team. Not only did they negotiate the agreement, keeping in mind the common interests of the EU without ever losing their nerve, they did so – and that is one of Michel’s defining qualities – involving the Council and Parliament on an equal footing, keeping the EU team together in more than one way. Of course, this agreement is not perfect; as far as we Greens/EFA are concerned, we would have liked to see something more than non-regression clauses on social and environmental matters as a condition for the UK staying in the customs union, and the political declaration should, again, have been more explicit about conditioning our future relationship on the UK not becoming a tax haven or a money laundering country. The countdown has to be tough on these issues as we move forward.</p>
      <p sl="en">I also felt relieved: relieved that, after 18 months of very hard work, an agreement could be found. Had that not been the case, the worst-case scenario of the UK crashing out of the European Union would have become the likeliest, causing major damage not just to business but above all to people. Relief that the EU could reach this agreement with the UK without compromising on its integrity. Relief that the British government had finally come to terms with reality.</p>
      <p sl="en">The ball is now clearly in the UK’s court. The Prime Minister has come to terms with reality, but it remains to be seen whether she will find a majority supporting the deal in the House of Commons.</p>
      <p sl="en">To the dissatisfied Brexiteers I will say this: if a negotiated Brexit is what you want and unless you would also consider keeping the country inside the single market, no other deal is available. Whoever negotiates on behalf of the UK will face the same legal constraints as Theresa May did, and I hope no one of you is seriously considering leaving without an agreement. Because if the UK did that, it would be in breach of the Good Friday Agreement, because at once a border would be re-erected in Ireland. It would also be in breach of its financial commitments taken under the EU Treaties during its membership period, because leaving a club, my friends, does not free you from paying your outstanding debt.</p>
      <p sl="en">In other terms, crash Brexit would make the UK a rogue state, a country whose signature with any other partner would amount to just nothing. The real choice, therefore, is only between Brexit under the terms negotiated, and no Brexit at all.</p>
      <p sl="en">That choice will have such an impact on the future of the country that as a Democrat I would find it normal that we would ask the people, especially as the major parties seem to be very divided on the issue.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">I will agree with remainers that your country finds itself in a less enviable position now than it was as a Member State, because indeed, European Union is a boost to sovereignty. In this world, if we want to have impact, we need to act together. And I think many British citizens realise that.</p>
      <p sl="en">Are they a majority? We don’t know. Can we find a way to ask them? If there is one, it is very narrow.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">But I’m certain, though, that if the UK wants to renounce its intention to leave, we should embrace it back with pleasure. Equally – and that is my final word, Madam President – I think it would be a utterly, utterly irresponsible to end up with the UK crashing out of the European Union, either voluntarily or inadvertently.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-019-0000" speaker_id="28248" name="Gabriele Zimmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Der Rat hat in seiner Sitzung am vergangenen Wochenende dem Scheidungsabkommen, das zwischen EU und UK ausgehandelt wurde, zugestimmt. Und trotzdem kann in diesem Moment niemand sagen, ob damit ein geregelter Brexit wahrscheinlicher wird. Es ist deshalb richtig, sich seitens der EU und der Mitgliedstaaten auf den schlimmsten Fall vorzubereiten: auf eine No-Deal-Situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unsere Mitwirkung als Fraktion in der Brexit Steering Group und auch die Mitarbeit an der allerersten Entschließung des Parlaments vom vergangenen Jahr – April 2017 – war nicht von vorneherein selbstverständlich. Die Entscheidung, dass wir diese Plattform mittragen, dass wir als linke Fraktion in die Arbeit der Brexit Steering Group einsteigen, war richtig. Und ich möchte in diesem Zusammenhang auch sagen, dass die Kooperation mit Michel Barnier Maßstäbe gesetzt hat für die künftige Kooperation zwischen den Institutionen in der Europäischen Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schon jetzt aber muss auch klar gesagt werden: Das Scheidungsabkommen lässt uns nicht jubeln. Wir sind besorgt, dass gerade bei den Bürgerrechten und in Bezug auf Nordirland eine Reihe unserer Forderungen nicht so verankert sind, dass sie tatsächlich ausreichend Rechtssicherheit für die vom Brexit Betroffenen schaffen könnten. Was im Withdrawal Agreement nicht wasserdicht ist, kann auch durch Absichtserklärungen nicht behoben werden. Wir atmen auf, weil im Withdrawal Agreement, also im Rückzugsabkommen, im Scheidungsabkommen, der Backstop, die Notfalllösung, vereinbart wurde, um damit ein Horrorszenario in Irland zu vermeiden. Dennoch leistet der Backstop nicht, was noch im Joined Report vom Dezember letzten Jahres versprochen wurde: Die Grenze, die Irland teilt, wird härter werden, die grenzüberschreitende Wirtschaft wird beeinträchtigt, Rechte, die im Good Friday Agreement verankert sind, werden minimiert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uns macht ebenfalls besorgt, wie sich Theresa May um die Stimmen von Zweiflern, Kritikern aus ihrem Lager für das Withdrawal Agreement, das Scheidungsabkommen, bemüht. Sie versichert ihnen nunmehr, das jumping von Migranten aus den EU-Mitgliedstaaten nach Großbritannien zu stoppen. Offenbar hat die britische Regierung – und mit ihr nicht nur die Regierung, sondern auch einige der Kollegen, die hier drüben sitzen – bis heute nicht begriffen, worin das Wesen der European citizenship besteht. Sie vergessen, dass sie auch ihren eigenen Bürgern Rechte entziehen, und sie erwecken den begründeten Verdacht, dass EU-Bürger, die nach dem Brexit in Großbritannien leben, arbeiten, studieren wollen, gegenüber Menschen aus anderen Ländern der Welt benachteiligt und diskriminiert werden könnten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am Wochenende versicherten die Regierungschefs – auch das wurde hier heute mehrfach angesprochen –, dass auch nach der Trennung Großbritannien und die EU eine möglichst enge Partnerschaft betreiben wollen. Das unterstützen wir. Wenn dies aber nicht nur leere Worte sein sollen, liegt noch viel Arbeit auf beiden Seiten vor uns. Als Europäisches Parlament sollten wir uns deshalb – hier stimme ich Guy Verhofstadt voll und ganz zu – weiterhin vor allem den Interessen der Bürger und Bürgerinnen in Großbritannien, aber auch innerhalb der Europäischen Union verpflichtet fühlen. Wir fühlen uns auch den Interessen der UK-Bürger innerhalb der EU verpflichtet. Das möchte ich auch noch mal sehr deutlich sagen. Das werden wir auch weiterhin in den Vordergrund stellen, genauso wie die Frage Nordirlands.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-020-0000" speaker_id="4525" name="Nigel Farage" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the EFDD Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I’m in no doubt that this withdrawal agreement is a good deal. It’s a good deal because it involves large transfers of money. It’s a good deal because it maintains free movement of people. It’s a good deal because it keeps Britain in the customs union and stuck with the EU’s rulebook. And crucially, the key point, as Mr Barnier said this morning: there is the backstop, which means of course the United Kingdom can be held effectively as a hostage for many years to come.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s a good deal for the European Union; for the UK, I think it’s probably the worst deal in history. Something, Mr Brok, that President Trump has noticed – and, by the way, he is a great respecter of the great nation states of Europe, and certainly no enemy of any single one of them. No, Mr Barnier, I have to say I wish you were on our side really, because it’s game, set and match to you. You probably can’t even believe your luck that you came up against a British Prime Minister who met every single demand of yours whilst at the same time trying to deceive the British public, and you took it to the big summit on Sunday, and in 38 minutes it was all agreed, done and dusted, and off to lunch.</p>
      <p sl="en">Well, I have to say, we will be leaving on 29 March next year, but any illusion at home that we’re going to be an independent country, I’m afraid, has been shattered. And before the ink was even dry last Sunday, President Macron of France stood up and decided to start to threaten us. Now, I understand the French do catch 90% of the haddock in the west of the English Channel and we get 10; I understand their interests. But I fear that we’re very much now open and at your mercy over the course of the next few years, and the truth of it is, in the political declaration, you haven’t got to give us anything. You don’t need to give us a thing, and that is why this is going to fail in Parliament, and probably fail by a very big margin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now, Mr Barnier, you say this is the only possible deal. But this deal isn’t going to be accepted. So perhaps we all need to grow up and recognise that there is a strong chance now of the UK leaving on 29 March with a WTO no deal. We need a negotiated deal, to deal with sensible border issues. I wonder, Mr Barnier, are you prepared for that? Because you seemed this morning to assume that the British Parliament is going to ratify this. It isn’t.</p>
      <a text="(Applause from certain quarters)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-021-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Madame la Présidente, le peuple britannique a décidé il y a deux ans de quitter l’Union européenne. Il faut respecter sa décision souveraine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour le groupe Europe des nations et des libertés, que je représente aujourd’hui, le respect de la souveraineté de chaque nation est un principe fondamental. Il est choquant, à cet égard, qu’une demande de remise en cause du Brexit ait été déposée devant la Cour de justice de l’Union, qui statuera le 4 décembre. J’estime, en effet, qu’aucun tribunal n’est compétent pour remettre en cause les effets d’un référendum. En France, le Conseil constitutionnel l’a compris et refuse de contrôler les référendums. Je souhaite vivement que la Cour de justice de l’Union adopte la même position. Si elle venait à interpréter l’article 50 du traité sur l’Union européenne dans un sens défavorable au Brexit, il faudrait lui résister. La souveraineté n’est pas un ensemble de compétences qu’on peut ligoter par des traités ou abandonner à la subjectivité des juges. C’est un pouvoir métajuridique qui permet à chaque nation de décider librement de son destin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vive le peuple britannique. Vive le Brexit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-022-0000" speaker_id="124971" name="James Carver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, last week Angela Merkel said, and I quote, ‘what’s been important to us it that the UK cannot decide unilaterally when the customs union ends but rather has to define that timeframe jointly with the EU.’</p>
      <p sl="en">The European institutions took control in 1973 and, ironically, continue that control through this 2018 Brexit betrayal deal. This deal means that we remain a nation of supplicants. We’ve lost the freedom teasingly dangled before us through the 2016 referendum results, when a British establishment and political class were rudely reminded that the British people want to take back their sovereign control.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ataturk’s wise words now seem more appropriate than ever when he said ‘sovereignty is not given, it is taken’. This is a terrible deal: bad because the EU continues to hold my country over a barrel and the British politicians who sign up to it need to understand that history will be their judge, and believe you me it will judge them all very badly.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madam President, a number of friendly pro-European colleagues within this Parliament have openly admitted to me that they cannot believe their luck in how bad a deal this is for the UK, and it surely cannot be allowed to proceed on such a one-sided basis.</p>
      <a text="(Applause from some quarters)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-023-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Michel Barnier" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">négociateur en chef sur le Brexit. – Madame la Présidente, merci à ceux qui se sont exprimés, en particulier Guy Verhofstadt, Elmar Brok, Roberto Gualtieri, Philippe Lamberts et Gabriele Zimmer pour dire, au nom de leur groupe, leur appréciation sur le travail que nous avons fait. J’y suis sensible. C’est un travail vraiment collectif. Cela n’a pas été un travail solitaire ou personnel, c’est un travail collectif. J’étais heureux d’y participer parce que je connais cette assemblée – j’y ai été élu à un certain moment –, je connais aussi le Conseil européen et évidemment la Commission, et il me paraissait très important de travailler comme un ouvrier – j’espère qualifié – à cette unité entre les Vingt-sept et entre les institutions. L’appréciation porte sur le travail de mon équipe, la task force 50, et je la transmettrai évidemment à mon adjointe, Sabine Weyand, à Stéphanie Riso et à toute l’équipe qui a mérité cette appréciation et qui la recevra comme un encouragement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cependant, nous sommes dans un moment grave et triste, comme vous l’avez dit les uns et les autres. Aussi, je dis à Monsieur Farage et à d’autres que je n’ai pas envie de faire des polémiques. Je n’en ai jamais fait et je ne vais pas commencer aujourd’hui. Nous écoutons tout le monde, nous répondons à tout le monde, nous dialoguons avec tout le monde et nous continuerons. Il reste, comme l’a dit Gabriele Zimmer, le moment de la ratification et, dans les mois qui viennent, il faut préparer la future négociation dont nous avons besoin, sur d’autres bases juridiques d’ailleurs, pour le partenariat avec le Royaume-Uni. Nous devons être vigilants, comme Guy Verhofstadt l’a rappelé, aussi sur la mise en œuvre de ce qui est dans ce traité, notamment sur les droits des citoyens et les garanties qui doivent être confirmées et concrétisées pour que les procédures pour les citoyens européens au Royaume-Uni soient peu coûteuses et les plus simples possibles. Par conséquent, il faut de la vigilance et de la détermination.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce vote, qui est attendu de part et d’autre, engage l’avenir de l’Union. Il engage l’avenir du Royaume-Uni. Je le dis avec le respect évoqué tout à l’heure pour le temps du débat démocratique au Royaume-Uni, que nous respectons. Le Royaume-Uni, par sa culture, par son histoire, par sa solidarité, en particulier dans les grands moments tragiques que l’Europe a traversés au XXe siècle, sa solidarité totale, par son économie, par la qualité de sa diplomatie, est un très grand pays. J’ai pour ce pays définitivement du respect et c’est pourquoi je souhaite que le plus tôt possible nous puissions travailler à un vrai partenariat sans précédent par l’étendue des sujets de coopération pour consolider notre alliance au-delà de ce que nous faisons déjà pour beaucoup de pays dans l’Alliance atlantique évidemment ou bilatéralement pour renforcer notre partenariat dans un autre cadre et pour consolider notre amitié aussi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur Farage, dans cette négociation, on m’a parfois demandé si l’Union allait faire des concessions. Non, il n’a jamais été question dans mon esprit qu’il y ait un gagnant ou un perdant. Le Brexit, c’est «lose-lose». Il n’y a pas de valeur ajoutée. Par conséquent, il s’agit de tenir compte de votre décision souveraine – je dis bien souveraine, Monsieur Lebreton. Nous respectons cette décision souveraine d’une majorité de citoyens britanniques et nous la mettons en œuvre selon les indications, les demandes et les lignes rouges exprimées par le gouvernement de Londres.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’ai travaillé tout au long de cette année et demie avec le gouvernement de Theresa May et selon ce qu’elle disait accepter ou ne pas accepter. Comment voulez-vous que je fasse autrement? Nous avons négocié avec le gouvernement de Londres, qui a exprimé la volonté de quitter l’Union européenne à la suite du référendum, ensuite de quitter le marché unique, parce que vous ne voulez plus respecter le cadre réglementaire, parce que vous ne voulez plus respecter la liberté de circulation des personnes, parce que vous ne voulez plus reconnaître le rôle de la Cour de justice et que vous ne voulez plus payer. De plus, vous quittez l’union douanière parce que vous ne voulez plus être dans une politique commune de commerce. Voilà les lignes rouges qui sont les vôtres et nous les respectons. Mais vous devez respecter notre détermination à préserver les fondations de l’Union européenne et notamment ce marché unique. J’ai eu l’honneur d’en être le commissaire pendant cinq ans. Ce marché unique, il doit beaucoup au Royaume-Uni. Vous avez eu un très grand degré d’influence dans sa construction et dans son évolution, mais vous le quittez parce que vous ne voulez plus respecter ces quatre libertés qui sont indivisibles. Je veux dire avec beaucoup de respect à Geoffrey van Orden:</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s not inflexibility, it’s not inflexibility; it is just responsibility. We have a duty, a responsibility, to work for an orderly withdrawal, to create security and stability where Brexit creates insecurity. It’s only an orderly withdrawal which creates a basis of trust for the deep and ambitious partnership we all want.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voilà ce que je voulais dire. Cette négociation est une négociation parce que vous quittez l’Union européenne. Vous avez décidé de quitter l’Union européenne et nous le regrettons. C’est une négociation évidemment négative, sans valeur ajoutée. Voilà pourquoi nous avons ce sentiment de gravité, ce qui n’interdit pas la lucidité de notre côté aussi pour tirer les leçons de ce Brexit. Il y a, comme l’ont dit Guy Verhofstadt et Elmar Brok, des leçons à tirer pour nous-mêmes, à savoir comprendre les raisons de ce vote et, le cas échéant, changer un certain nombre de choses qui devraient l’être pour répondre mieux aux préoccupations, aux demandes et parfois aux angoisses des citoyens.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voilà, nous avons travaillé à cette unité qu’ont voulue les dirigeants européens dans le contexte géopolitique très grave dans lequel nous sommes. À l’ouest, à l’est, au sud, on voit bien que nous sommes interpellés de tous côtés et nous avons travaillé avec cette unité entre les vingt-sept États membres et entre les institutions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce que je peux simplement formuler comme vœu à ce stade de ce processus qui n’est pas terminé, car la route est longue et est encore très escarpée – nous attendons le vote du 11 décembre et le processus de ratification du côté britannique sur cet accord qui est le seul et le meilleur possible –, je souhaite simplement et humblement que cette unité que nous avons forgée ensemble dans cette négociation négative, les dirigeants européens dont vous faites partie décident de la mettre au service d’un agenda positif.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-026-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Thank you, Mr Barnier, and could I thank you on behalf of the Parliament and President Tajani for your work with Parliament on this issue, your transparency and, above all else, your patience.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">If I may say on a personal note, the word ‘rubbish’ has been bandied about. Mr Coburn, you use it frequently. It is not the view of the majority of this House.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The debate is closed.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Written statements (Rule 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-027-0000" speaker_id="125024" name="Barbara Kappel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – Die EU-Mitgliedstaaten stimmten letzte Woche dem Austrittsabkommen und der politischen Erklärung zu den künftigen Beziehungen zwischen der EU und Großbritannien zu. Dieser sogenannte „Brexit-Deal“ muss noch im Dezember vom britischen Parlament genehmigt werden. Ziel ist es, auch weiterhin eine erfolgreiche wirtschaftliche und politische Zusammenarbeit zwischen der EU und Großbritannien zu gewährleisten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Bank of England und das britische Finanzministerium haben nun im Vorfeld der Parlamentsdebatte im britischen Unterhaus Studien veröffentlicht, in denen aufgezeigt wird, dass ein No-Deal-Szenario eine tiefe und schädliche Rezession im Vereinigten Königreich auslösen könnte. Ein No-Deal-Brexit würde die britische Wirtschaft in einen heftigen Angebotsschock versetzen, der dazu führte, dass die Nachfrage nach Gütern und Dienstleistungen das Angebot übersteigt, was die Inflationsrate erhöhen würde. Das britische Bruttoinlandsprodukt könnte im nächsten Jahr um bis zu 8 % sinken, die Arbeitslosenquote von derzeit 4,1 % auf 7,5 % ansteigen, während die Zinssätze bei einer Inflation von 6,5 % ebenfalls ansteigen würden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der zwischen der EU und Premierministerin May ausverhandelte Brexit-Deal hilft, dieses Szenario zu vermeiden, weiterhin enge Handelsbeziehungen zu unterhalten und in den nächsten fünf Jahren ein BIP-Wachstum von 1,75 % zu erreichen. Auf diese Weise blieben sowohl das Ergebnis des demokratischen Referendums als auch die wirtschaftlichen Interessen gewahrt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-027-5000" speaker_id="111027" name="Светослав Христов Малинов" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">в писмена форма. – Днес Мишел Барние докладва за напредъка по оттеглянето на Обединеното кралство. Споразумението за Брекзит предстои да бъде одобрено от Британския парламент. Пред очите ни евродепутатите от Великобритания се скараха. Очевидно разделението в страната е станало още по-дълбоко. Анализите на британския бизнес показват негативни тенденции за британската икономика. Няма добър сценарий! Най-малко лошият е Британският парламент да одобри споразумението. На 11 декември ще бъде гласуването, но ако трябва да сме откровени, на този етап няма мнозинство, за да бъде прието. В такъв случай се пораждат много рискове за бизнеса и най-вече за гражданите, включително за българите, които са там. Ще си позволя един практичен съвет към тях. Ако споразумението не бъде прието от Британския парламент, най-вероятният сценарий е Обединеното кралство да напусне без сделка. Не разчитайте на идеите за втори референдум или за предсрочни избори. На практика това означава, че ще бъде изключително трудно, макар и не невъзможно, за част от хората, които нямат пълната документация, да докажат своите права и да поискат право на уседналост. Затова моят съвет е още отсега да започнете да събирате документи си за легално пребиваване, работа, доходи, платени университетски такси, наеми за жилище и здравни осигуровки. Така ще сте подготвени и за най-лошия сценарий.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-028-0000" speaker_id="124781" name="Alfred Sant" is_mep="True" mode="written">
      <p sl="en">On the one hand, it is clear that the Brexit deal just signed is the only one possible in the circumstances. On the other hand it is equally clear that while the EU has safeguarded all its imperatives, the UK has retreated along all lines of engagement. In part this was because for various reasons, its negotiating positions and strategies were not so coherent. However the EU should be wary of driving its negotiating advantages as of now, to the extreme. This might lead to very serious unintended and unforeseeable consequences. In any agreement, a party that goes away with the feeling it has been given a raw deal, will later be tempted or driven to exact some form of compensation or retribution. Witness the Versailles treaty, or the Russian position over recent years in reaction to how post-Soviet arrangements in Europe were played out. Secondly, should there be any other EU government wishing to exit, it will have learnt the lesson of not doing it the British way under article 50 procedures. It could for instance first do its best to cause havoc from the inside in order to leverage and strengthen its position during exit negotiations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-028-5000" speaker_id="124929" name="Ivan Štefanec" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne. – Rokovania o brexite ukázali, že Európska únia dokáže spolupracovať aj na tej najvyššej úrovni rýchlo a efektívne. Európska rada schválila dohodu o odchode Spojeného Kráľovstva z Európskej únie a vydala vyhlásenie, v ktorom stanovuje rámec pre budúce vzťahy medzi Európskou úniou a Spojeným kráľovstvom. Naším cieľom je zachovať čo najužšie partnerstvo so Spojeným kráľovstvom aj v budúcnosti. Uvedomujeme si, že brexit nie je v konečnom dôsledku výhodný ani pre jednu stranu. Spojené kráľovstvo odmieta colnú úniu, pretože chce mať vlastné obchodné dohody a už nechce byť ani súčasťou spoločného jednotného trhu, pretože nechce zachovať princíp štyroch slobôd. Aj napriek tomu nesmieme zabúdať, že existuje mnoho sfér, v ktorých je naša spolupráca nevyhnutná pre obe strany. Takými oblasťami sú napríklad bezpečnosť, obchod alebo veda a výskum. V dobe, keď si Rusko viditeľne posilňuje svoj vplyv v krajinách bývalého Sovietskeho zväzu, je spolupráca so Spojeným kráľovstvom práve v oblasti bezpečnosti pre našu budúcnosť kľúčová.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-028-7500" speaker_id="124726" name="Henna Virkkunen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – On harmillista, että vuoden 2016 Brexit-äänestys perustui pääosin puutteelliselle ja väärälle tiedolle sekä täysin katteettomille lupauksille, joita brittihallitus ei käytännössä pysty lunastamaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Britannian lähestyvä EU-ero on suuri tragedia, joka voitaisiin vielä välttää. Sinänsä nyt neuvoteltu erosopimus vastaa niitä vähimmäisehtoja, joita EU-parlamentti sille asetti. Erosopimus turvaa Britanniassa asuvien EU-kansalaisten oikeudet, vahvistaa Britannian tulevat maksuvelvoitteet EU:lle sekä välttää kovan rajan syntymisen Irlannin ja Pohjois-Irlannin välille. Silti on selvää, että sekä Britannia että EU tulevat kärsimään Brexitistä. Tällä sopimuksella pyritään lähinnä pienentämään erosta syntyviä vahinkoja. On myös aivan selvää, ettei Britannia voi EU:n ulkopuolella saada parempia etuuksia kuin jäsenmaat. Alustavien päälinjojen mukaan Britannia haluaisi kuitenkin olla mukana lähes kaikessa EU-toiminnassa myös jatkossa. Tämä herättää kysymyksen siitä, miksi Britannia ylipäänsä haluaa erota?</p>
      <p sl="en">Nyt neuvoteltu erosopimus siirtymäaikoineen on toiseksi paras vaihtoehto, mihin voimme päästä. Paras ratkaisu olisi, jos Britannia päättäisi perua eronsa. Se olisi vielä täysin mahdollista. Oikein ja kohtuullista olisi, että Britannian kansa saisi ainakin mahdollisuuden äänestää uudelleen erosta nyt, kun tiedossa on, mitä ero käytännössä merkitsee. Tämä luonnollisesti on nyt täysin brittien käsissä.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. The preparation of the Marrakech Intergovernmental Conference of 10-11 December on the UN Global compact for Migration (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-031-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Erklärungen des Rates und der Kommission zur Vorbereitung der Regierungskonferenz am 10. und 11. Dezember in Marrakesch zu dem Globalen Pakt für Migration der Vereinten Nationen (2018/2959(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-032-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karoline Edtstadler" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President-in-Office of the Council">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, High Representative, ladies and gentlemen, thank you for this opportunity to discuss the issue again after the debate we had in Strasbourg earlier this month. I’m aware that the delegation from Parliament will be present in Marrakech and that you attach great importance to this conference where the Global Compact of safe, orderly and regular migration is due to be politically endorsed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Since the first draft of the Global Compact was put on the table, Member States engaged in intensive discussions on this document in the Council, both during the Bulgarian and the Austrian Presidency. They also actively engaged in the discussions in New York. Indeed, since the adoption of the New York declaration for refugees and migrants in September 2016, the EU has actively engaged in providing input at the various stages of preparation of the first draft of the Global Compact.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you are aware the Council does not have a common position on this text. Member States have decided or are in the process of deciding their national position on the Global Compact. The political endorsement of the Global Compact in the intergovernmental conference in Marrakech followed by the adoption of this document by the UN General Assembly will open the way for the implementation phase.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, I would recall that cooperation with third countries and regions remains a crucial element of the EU’s migration policy. The dialogues and the support we provide to our partners through a variety of instruments, including through the EU Trust Fund for Africa, are testimony to our commitment to a policy that recognises the specific responsibilities, needs and concerns of countries of origin, transit and destination.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can assure you that the Council and the Presidency will continue to contribute to that purpose.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-033-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Federica Mogherini" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">haute représentante de l’Union pour les affaires étrangères et la politique de sécurité/vice-présidente de la Commission européenne. – Monsieur le Président, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, merci à vous tous pour l’attention constante que vous portez à ce débat sur le travail que font les Nations unies, mais aussi sur le thème de l’immigration, qui est un thème crucial de notre temps et de notre travail, en tant qu’institution européenne, avec les États membres, la Commission et le Parlement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I believe there are two mistakes we must not make when discussing the Global Compact, and one additional that I will mention later.</p>
      <p sl="en">The first one is to pretend that there is a clash between our national interests and the idea of a Global Compact. The opposite is true. If our national interest is to govern migration, and I believe it is – of all of us – to make it orderly, humane and sustainable, then the Global Compact is the most powerful tool we have to serve our national interests.</p>
      <p sl="en">The second mistake would be to tackle migration as a fight between the north and the south of the world: the developed and the developing countries. Again, the opposite is true. Let me mention just the fact that most of the countries are, at the same time – for instance, in Africa – countries of origin, of transit and of destination. Again, as I said, the opposite is true. It’s not north against south or south against north; we all share an interest in managing migration. We all have an interest in investing in sustainable development in the regions that need it the most, and we all have an interest in creating regular pathways for human mobility. The earlier we realise that it’s partnership and cooperation that we need, the better for us all, because we are all in this together. No country can address it on its own, neither in Europe nor elsewhere in the world, and all countries have an interest in addressing this effectively. We all support it. The UN Secretary—General Ban Ki-moon’s initiative to hold a high—level meeting on migration – that was back at the UN General Assembly in 2016. Then, we all, collectively and unanimously, adopted the New York Declaration that launched the work on the two Global Combats on refugees and on migration.</p>
      <p sl="en">And that was an important achievement for us Europeans, because in the middle of the migration crisis in Europe – I add ‘in Europe’ because we have to remind ourselves there are migration crises every single day in every single part of the world – but at that specific moment, after the summer of 2016, in the middle of the European migration crisis, Europe – us – we called for the international community to engage, to build partnerships, and we received a positive response. And there the Global Compact process started.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union took an early lead in the discussions on the Global Migration Compact. We also participated from the beginning, actively, in the work leading to the clear common positions that are now in front of us, and this has allowed us to bring forward a Global Compact that largely reflects European objectives and that respects all our key concerns. I know that Commission Stylianides said it very clearly in the European Parliament in the plenary session in Strasbourg a couple of weeks ago. We regret the decision by some European Union Member States not to join or to support the Global Compact on Migration. We do believe that all Member States’ interests are best served in supporting the proposed framework that will establish a basis for international cooperation and dialogue – that basis that was missing up to now and that we asked for: dialogue and cooperation that lie already at the basis of the first results that would need to be consolidated, that we have achieved as Europeans, in the past years: reducing irregular arrivals, offering alternatives to migrants, bringing smugglers to justice and also tackling difficult topics, including return and readmission. Results that were achieved by way of cooperation, partnership and mutual respect and understanding, with a strong role of the United Nations – all elements that are the basis of the Global Compact.</p>
      <p sl="en">There are some misconceptions in the debate on the Global Compact, as I said already. I would like to underline one that is self—evident to me, but maybe we need to repeat it in view of the national debates that are going on. It is not a legally-binding framework. I think national parliaments in particular, but also the European Parliament, have to acknowledge that from the very beginning: it is not legally binding. It will not create any legal obligation for the states. It is a menu of policy actions; it is a menu of best practices from which states may draw to implement their national migration policies in a cooperative way and in any international manner. It provides a framework. The Compacts are built on this basis and are grounded on the respect of the principle of national and sovereign rights of states to determine their national migration policies. But they do provide that framework that is missing today, and that is definitely needed, as we Europeans asked for it.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will continue to work to improve migration management worldwide, which is already done today on the European side, on the basis of the work strands that are developed under the Global Compact. We will, notably, continue our engagement with the International Organisation for Migration, who will lead the implementation and follow—up of the Compact, which will entail sharing experiences, helping countries to overcome shortcomings, and searching for solutions to an issue that is global, by definition. We will also continue to support partnerships at bilateral, regional and global level in the area of migration. With our partners in the world, the Migration Compact will be an important basis for cooperation along what has been agreed as the common European Union approach to migration. And that, as I said, is largely reflected in the Compact.</p>
      <p sl="en">So here, our common work and your contribution as the European Parliament will be essential. Mr Avramopoulos will be leading the Commission delegation to Marrakech on 10 and 11 December, and I’m very happy to see that Members of the European Parliament will join the European Union delegation to the Intergovernmental Conference at Marrakech. I believe the role of Parliament is going to be crucial. I very much appreciate the European Parliament’s strong interest and engagement and confirm our full commitment to work very closely with you in this joint endeavour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-035-0000" speaker_id="185341" name="Željana Zovko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba PPE. – Poštovani predsjedavajući, poštovana uvažena povjerenice, kao članica Odbora za vanjske poslove i Odbora za razvoj obišla sam krizna žarišta u svijetu susrećući se s brojnim izbjeglicama te sam uvidjela kako oni svi imaju jedan zajednički cilj - pronaći sigurno utočište za sebe i svoju obitelj.</p>
      <p sl="en">2015. godine vidjeli smo kako je dovoljna samo jedna iskra da se osjetljivi mir na Zapadnom Balkanu poremeti izbjegličkim valom koji se kretao prema Europi. Hrvatska, koja ima najdužu kopnenu granicu prema Zapadnom Balkanu, to vrlo dobro zna. Italija i Španjolska s morskim granicama prema Africi bile su najizloženije izbjegličkim valovima i nisu mogle dizati zidove. Države članice Europske unije, a ni države članice Ujedinjenih naroda ne bi smjele pristupati ovom problemu individualno, već sudjelovati i zajednički djelovati u kreiranju sveobuhvatnih rješenja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Žalim što Globalni sporazum o migracijama nailazi na kontroverze, ali se nadam da će se pronaći srednji put, kao što je to učinio Europski parlament u svojoj rezoluciji o Globalnom sporazumu, na kojoj sam radila kao pregovaračica u ime Europske pučke stranke, koji će poslužiti kao putokaz kako postupiti u ovom pitanju na human i prihvatljiv način.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-036-0000" speaker_id="96911" name="Tanja Fajon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">v imenu skupine S&amp;D. – Gospod predsednik, današnjo razpravo smo zahtevali, ker se je vse več evropskih vlad umaknilo od globalnega dogovora za varne, urejene in nadzorovane migracije in ker ne smemo ostati tiho.</p>
      <p sl="en">Politiki smo odgovorni, da verodostojno pojasnimo odločitve. Evropski parlament je aprila globalni dogovor podprl z veliko večino, saj ta poudarja pomen človekovih pravic, ki so univerzalne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vsem, ki pravijo, da gre z globalnim dogovorom za uvoz migrantov, za nacionalno izdajo ali izdajo suverenosti in uničevanje zahodne civilizacije, kar so obtožbe desnice tudi v slovenski javnosti, naj povem, da je takšno ustrahovanje ljudi napačno in zavajajoče.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gre za politično deklaracijo, ki temelji na sodelovanju, suverenosti držav, delitvi odgovornosti, ki temelji na svetovnem, evropskem in nacionalnem pravnem redu, ki ne izenačuje migrantov z begunci in ne prinaša novih pravnih obveznosti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Globalne izzive lahko rešujemo le skupaj. Ravno sem se vrnila iz države Niger. Tam je boj za dostojno življenje del vsakdana, saj bogate zahodne države zlorabljajo naravne vire in ljudi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dokler bo tako, bo Evropa privlačna celina. Zato je globalni dogovor še kako pomemben, da bodo migracije lahko varne, nadzorovane in urejene in da bo to globalna skrb vseh nas, kar Evropejci od nas tudi pričakujejo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-037-0000" speaker_id="124875" name="Anders Primdahl Vistisen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">for ECR-Gruppen. – Hr. formand! Marrakesherklæringen er en skamstøtte af kulturradikale og liberale idéer, der har ført Europa ud i det morads, vi ser i dag, hvor medlemsstaterne er vendt mod hinanden, fordi man ikke længere kan kapere den enorme ulovlige indvandring, der finder sted. Hvad er løsningen så, hvis man spørger FN? Det er at anerkende et koncept som ”klimaflygtninge”, det er at give migranter sociale rettigheder, og det er at tale om integration i stedet for hjemsendelse af flygtninge, hvis ophold pr. definition skal være midlertidigt, indtil de får beskyttelse. Heldigvis nærmer vi os ti EU-medlemsstater, der ikke vil være med til at skrive under på det her vanvittige dokument, inklusiv fornuftige lande uden for EU som Schweiz, USA og Australien. Men det er beskæmmende, at mit eget hjemland Danmark endnu ikke har taget beslutningen om ikke at underskrive Marrakesherklæringen, selv om regeringens egne politiske holdninger er i direkte modstrid med indholdet. Derfor en opfordring til min egen regering i Danmark om at følge de fornuftige i EU, lad være med at tage til Marrakesh, lad være med at underskrive dette FN-vanvid!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-038-0000" speaker_id="96815" name="Judith Sargentini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de Verts/ALE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, wat een schizofrenie! Aan de ene kant spreekt mevrouw Edstädtler, staatssecretaris in de Oostenrijkse regering, namens de Europese Raad. Ze praat er omheen, maar de Oostenrijkse regering wil niet tekenen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aan de andere kant zit mevrouw Mogherini, die niet alleen de Europese Commissie maar ook de Raad vertegenwoordigt. Zij omarmt gelukkig wel het Mondiaal Pact voor veilige en geordende migratie.</p>
      <p sl="en">We staan als Europa echt voor gek! Dat Donald Trump niet mee ging doen, was vrij logisch. Maar wij, in het Europa van de zachte krachten, gingen aan de wereld laten zien dat je met zijn allen ook tot afspraken kunt komen om ervoor te zorgen dat kinderen van migranten naar school gaan, dat er een terugkeerbeleid gevoerd wordt, en dat kinderen niet zonder papieren komen te zitten maar een bestaan kunnen hebben. Dit was ons moment om ervoor te zorgen dat wij niet langer gegijzeld werden door de migratiecrisis vanaf 2015.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar wat doen wij? We maken het tot een intern spelletje en we vergeten dat we hiermee normen stellen die ook gelden voor Afrika en Azië.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-039-0000" speaker_id="124992" name="Malin Björk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för GUE/NGL-gruppen. – Herr talman! Jag tycker att det är häpnadsväckande att flera EU-länder nu, under tryck av nationalism och rasism, drar sig ur den globala överenskommelsen om migration. Från vänsterns sida ser vi stora problem med texten inför Marrakech, men vi stöder helt och fullt ut att det måste finnas globala målsättningar och processer som kan hantera migration inom FN:s ram.</p>
      <p sl="en">Migration är inte ett problem. Det är utnyttjandet av migranter, till exempel på den europeiska arbetsmarknaden, som är ett problem. Vi måste se över vår utrikespolitik, vapenhandeln i Europa, våra klimatutsläpp, som gör att människor söker sig iväg och måste flytta och migrera. Det är detta som måste ändras. Vi måste också ha dessa förhandlingar på en mer jämlik bas mellan nord och syd.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jag kan tycka att detta misslyckande med all tydlighet också visar att EU är på fel väg, att vi inte lyckats komma överens om någonting här hemma, att vi inte tar emot flyktingar med värdighet, att vi låter döden på Medelhavet fortsätta, att vi sätter upp 10 000 gränsvakter i stället för att prata om hur vi ska hantera migration och flyktingar på ett värdigt och människorättsbaserat sätt. Den kriminalisering av NGO som pågår nu är fruktansvärd. Jag ser inte varför vi …</p>
      <a text="(Talmannen avbryter talaren.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-040-0000" speaker_id="190518" name="Jörg Meuthen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der EFDD-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Wir reden erneut über den Global Compact for Migration, weil sich die links-grün-utopistische Migrationslobby erhofft, dass von diesem Hause aus ein bejahendes Signal für eine Welt grenzenloser Migration gesetzt wird. Das Gegenteil ist der Fall. Gestern hat endlich auch die Regierung von Italien entschieden, dem Pakt nicht zuzustimmen. Es reiht sich damit ein in eine immer länger werdende Liste von Staaten, die sich dieser absurden Agenda verweigern. Die USA lehnen den Pakt ab, ebenso Australien und Israel, in der EU Ungarn, Österreich, die Slowakei, Polen, Tschechien und Bulgarien. Belgien hat deswegen eine Regierungskrise. Auch in Deutschland zeichnet sich eine Krise ab, denn den bisherigen Befürwortern dämmert inzwischen, in was für einen weiteren Irrsinn Frau Merkel unser Land als nächstes hineintreiben will.</p>
      <p sl="en">Behaupte also niemand, das EU-Parlament stünde auch nur halbwegs geschlossen hinter der Unterzeichnung dieses hinterhältigen Pakts. Denn das stimmt nicht, es stimmt sogar ganz und gar nicht. Lassen Sie diese Fake News! Es reicht. Stoppen wir diesen suizidalen Pakt – bevor es zu spät ist!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-041-0000" speaker_id="125001" name="Harald Vilimsky" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ENF-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, meine sehr geehrten Damen und Herren! Ein guter Tag beginnt mit einem weiteren Land, das dem UN-Migrationspakt nicht beitritt, so gestern Italien. Danke an Matteo Salvini, der hier der Impulsgeber war, genauso wie in Österreich Heinz-Christian Strache Impulsgeber dafür war, dass Österreich diesem Pakt nicht beitritt. USA, Australien, Ungarn, Polen, Tschechien, Bulgarien, Slowakei, Slowenien – immer mehr sagen „Nein“ dazu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und wenn Sie sich die Hauptziele der Vereinten Nationen ganz ehrlich ansehen, hat das nichts mit dem UN-Migrationspakt zu tun. Die Hauptziele sind Abrüstung, Frieden, Sicherheit und Freundschaft zu gewährleisten, Menschenrechte zu gewährleisten, und auch ein Ort der Begegnung zu sein. Aber die Vereinten Nationen haben mit Sicherheit nicht das Ziel, weltweit die Frage der Migration zu lösen und damit in die Entscheidungshoheit nationaler Parlamente und von deren Volksvertretern entsprechend einzugreifen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dieser Pakt ist etwas Schlechtes; immer mehr Länder erkennen es. Ich bin froh über jedes weitere Land, das diesem Pakt nicht beitritt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-042-0000" speaker_id="124832" name="Udo Voigt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich bin schon sehr überrascht, Frau Mogherini, wie Sie sagen können, dass dieser Pakt kein verpflichtendes Recht für die Nationen ist, wenn doch die Nationen nach vier Jahren dahingehend überprüft werden sollen, ob sie die Maßnahmen dieses Paktes umgesetzt haben. Und wenn ich mir auf der einen Seite vorstelle, dass Integration jetzt das neue Zauberwort wird und über die Rückführung gar nicht mehr nachgedacht wird, dass man gar nicht mehr daran denkt, was eigentlich die Genfer Flüchtlingskonvention sagt, nämlich, dass diejenigen Migranten zurückgeführt werden sollten, wenn wieder Frieden in ihrer Heimat ist. Alles dieses ist nicht berücksichtigt. Integration soll das künftige Zauberwort sein statt Rückführung. Die Völker Europas sind durch diesen Migrationspakt bedroht, und viele Völker haben jetzt die Antwort gefunden, dieses nicht zu unterschreiben. Ich denke, auch die Migranten haben mit diesem Pakt keine wirkliche Zukunft. Denn die Zukunft sollte nicht darin liegen, nach Europa zu kommen …</p>
      <a text="(Der Präsident entzieht dem Redner das Wort.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-043-0000" speaker_id="96674" name="Anna Maria Corazza Bildt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Global Compact is important as it recognises that migration is a global challenge that requires a global response and solidarity.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is nothing binding. Richer countries have to share responsibility and, for example, do more resettlement. I regret that Trump turned them back but, even worse, that some Member States walked out. To just say ‘go home and stay home’ is no solution. No state can deal with migration alone. A common European response and global cooperation is the way forward to safe and legal migration because Europe must work with third countries, from prevention to combating trafficking, and to implement return.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is also crucial to invest in Africa in the long term. I was in Agadez in Niger with the European Parliament delegation and, thanks to the EU’s effective action, we have reduced migration, we have saved lives, and we are combating trafficking: more of those partnerships. I look forward to participating, on behalf of the PPE Group, in the European Parliament …</p>
      <a text="(The President cut off the speaker)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-044-0000" speaker_id="124723" name="Péter Niedermüller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök úr! A Global Compact fontos hozzájárulás a migráció, a menekültügy globális kihívására adandó válaszokhoz. A tervezet pontosan megfogalmazza a kereteket, és világossá teszi, hogy a menekültek védelme, a menedékjog kérelme olyan emberi jog, amelyet nem lehet kétségbe vonni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Több mint sajnálatos, hogy van néhány olyan EU-tagország, amelynek vezetői önös politikai okokból és indokokból nem hajlandók a Global Compact elfogadására. Tudnunk kell, hogy azok, akik elutasítják ezt a nyilatkozatot, nem érdekeltek a probléma megoldásában, sőt, éppen ellenkezőleg, abban érdekeltek, hogy a menekültek, a bevándorlás kérdése ne rendeződjön, hiszen ebből kovácsolnak maguknak politikai tőkét. Mérhetetlen felelőtlenség, szégyenletes, erkölcstelen és embertelen politika ez, aminek a következményei mindannyiunkat sújtani fogják. Éppen ezért kell fel emelnünk a hangunkat – a közös felelősségvállalás mellett – a gyűlölet és félelemkeltő politika ellen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-045-0000" speaker_id="4465" name="Raffaele Fitto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la vicepresidente Mogherini ha poc'anzi detto che il Global compact non ha alcun impatto giuridicamente vincolante per i paesi. Allora, io mi chiedo se il 10 e 11 dicembre a Marrakech ci sarà un grande convegno dove discutere di questo.</p>
      <p sl="en">La verità è che sull'immigrazione – grande fallimento delle politiche europee di questi anni – si sta giocando una partita culturale e politica con il Global compact ed è assolutamente giusto che non si firmi e non si partecipi a una iniziativa nella quale l'incertezza è assoluta e soprattutto si sta tentando esclusivamente di mettere in campo un'azione politica mirata per poter continuare su una strada sbagliata.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ho ascoltato diversi colleghi che hanno parlato del ritiro dell'Italia: l'Italia discute da qualche giorno di Global compact grazie all'azione di Giorgia Meloni di Fratelli d'Italia, che si è inserita all'interno di un governo nel quale la situazione è poco chiara: Salvini ha detto di non andare e di non partecipare a Marrakech; il Presidente del Consiglio Conte ha detto il contrario. Staremo a vedere cosa accadrà. Noi lavoreremo con decisione, perché l'Italia non partecipi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-046-0000" speaker_id="21817" name="Mario Borghezio" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io non cito Salvini, cito Papa Francesco che, nell'Aula del Parlamento europeo, ha ammonito l'Europa, affermando testualmente: "se sarà in grado di proporre con chiarezza la propria identità culturale e difendere, oltre al diritto all'accoglienza, anche i diritti dei cittadini, aiutando questi popoli nel loro paese". Tranne le invocazioni, che sembrano cadere nel vuoto, del Presidente Tajani a un piano Marshall, l'Europa su questo piano non risponde.</p>
      <p sl="en">In questo testo la parola identità non esiste: si dice che si tutela la sovranità degli Stati ma poi si precisa che deve essere subordinata agli accordi internazionali e quindi è una sovranità limitata. Io credo che noi dobbiamo ispirarci agli insegnamenti di chi ha una certa idea dell'Europa, come Papa Francesco. Se l'avesse scritta Papa Francesco, io, a scatola chiusa, la firmerei subito! Credo che questa sia anche l'impostazione del governo italiano, che non è insensibile ai diritti di chi fugge dalle persecuzioni, eccetera, ma che intende mettere fine all'osceno commercio dei migranti che servono solo …</p>
      <p sl="en">(Il Presidente interrompe l'oratore).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-047-0000" speaker_id="124801" name="Cécile Kashetu Kyenge" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io sarò a Marrakech con la delegazione del Parlamento. Il Global compact fornisce un risvolto globale al tema della migrazione, dando continuità al nostro lavoro iniziato con la risoluzione sull'approccio olistico alla migrazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Troppi gli Stati membri che hanno deciso di sabotare la conferenza intergovernativa: a questi paesi, soprattutto al mio, l'Italia, dico: andateci! Orban, Salvini e tutti i leader dei paesi che hanno deciso di fare questo passo: andate a Marrakech, venite con me, venite con noi!</p>
      <p sl="en">Opporsi al patto globale significa non solo opporsi a delle soluzioni per una migrazione più sicura e regolare, ma ben peggio: opporsi alla dignità e ai diritti umani dei migranti! Non restate al di fuori della storia: questa è la storia! E le immigrazioni non si fermeranno. Le immigrazioni continuano. Dobbiamo essere responsabili nell'affrontare le cause profonde dell'immigrazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ancora una volta emerge l'ipocrisia del governo italiano che predica la responsabilità di affrontare il fenomeno migratorio in maniera solidale e poi si oppone a delle proposte</p>
      <p sl="en">(Il Presidente interrompe l'oratrice).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-048-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Für das nun folgende Catch-the-eye-Verfahren muss ich Ihnen sagen, dass ich doppelt so viele Meldungen habe wie Zeit vorgesehen ist. Wir werden heute eine sehr lange Abstimmung haben. Deshalb bitte ich um Nachsicht, wenn ich nicht alle Kolleginnen oder Kollegen berücksichtigen kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Spontane Wortmeldungen</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-049-0000" speaker_id="96933" name="Milan Zver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spoštovani gospod predsedujoči, jaz sem eden tistih, ki nasprotuje marakeški deklaraciji, predvsem zaradi tega, ker ne predstavlja globalnega dogovora, ni niti globalen niti dogovor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Od njega so že odstopile velike države, veliki svetovni akterji, kot so ZDA, Avstralija, Izrael, več kot deset evropskih držav članic, in to zagotovo ni splošen dogovor. V Sloveniji je 70 odstotkov javnosti proti njej. Še niti politične elite se niso mogle oglasiti okoli njega, kaj šele evropska in svetovna javnost.</p>
      <p sl="en">Predvsem sem proti temu, ker je besedilo slabo, zato ker temelji na napačnih predpostavkah, in tudi ni res, da ni zavezujoče, še kako je zavezujoče, če ga temeljito preberete, to delo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Skratka, nasprotujem temu dogovoru, zato ker bo v prihodnje še poslabšal situacijo pri upravljanju z migracijami.</p>
      <p sl="en">Evropska unija bi morala veliko več vložiti, več napora in denarja v države izvora, od koder prihajajo migracije, nikakor pa ne na ta način reševati ta problem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-050-0000" speaker_id="125018" name="Eugen Freund" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ganz offensichtlich haben diejenigen, die den Migrationspakt ablehnen, ihn nicht gelesen. Denen geht es nur um Populismus und um Parteipolitik. Denn was wird abgelehnt, was in diesem Migrationspakt steht? Zum Beispiel, dass man Daten erhebt, um damit eine Grundlage für die Migrationspolitik zu haben, oder dass man schaut, jene Triebkräfte zu verhindern, deretwegen die Menschen ihre Heimat verlassen, oder dass man korrekte und zeitnahe Informationen in allen Phasen der Migration erhebt – abgelehnt, ebenso wie, dass Menschenleben gerettet und internationale Maßnahmen koordiniert werden, wenn es vermisste Migranten gibt. Abgelehnt wird auch der grenzübergreifende Kampf gegen Schleuser oder ein integriertes, sicheres und koordiniertes Grenzmanagement. Unsere Regierung will nicht einmal, dass Möglichkeiten geschaffen werden, um für schnellere, sichere und kostengünstigere Rücküberweisungen von Migranten in ihre Heimatländer zu sorgen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-051-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, potreba da se na globalnoj razini stvori okvir za migracije postoji jer je evidentno da veliki broj država ne poštuje međunarodni poredak i otvoreno propušta migrante prema njihovim finalnim odredištima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deseci tisuća ljudi u ovom trenutku bez dokumenata, s lažnim identitetom i bez prave provjere prelaze granice i odlaze prema nekoj od zapadnih država, dok oni koji ih propuštaju okreću glavu od problema i tako ugrožavaju sve nas. Migracije moraju biti sigurnije i za migrante, ali i za domicilno stanovništvo. U Europu je ušlo puno ljudi za koje dan danas ne znamo tko su i koje su im stvarne namjere.</p>
      <p sl="en">UN-ov kompakt o migracijama ne predstavlja taj okvir za rješenje ovog globalnog izazova jer ga odbijaju Amerikanci, Australija, Izrael i niz europskih država. To znači da ga uglavnom podržavaju one države iz kojih ljudi odlaze, ali ne i one koje bi ih trebale primiti. Tako se problem ne rješava, nego samo pogoršava.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-052-0000" speaker_id="125003" name="Igor Šoltes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spoštovani gospod predsedujoči, tak globalni dogovor seveda bi potrebovali že mnogo prej in mnogo lažje bi ob sodelovanju vseh držav reševali mnoge probleme, s katerimi se danes soočamo.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dejstvo je, da ta globalni dogovor tudi pomeni učinkovito upravljanje migracij, kar je tudi obramba suverenosti in varnosti držav, kar skušajo oporekati nasprotniki tega dogovora. Pa tudi varnost za tiste najšibkejše v karavanah bežečih.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ta deklaracija, ta dogovor ima seveda velike ambicije in če preberemo vse cilje, ki so povzetek same vsebine, vidimo, da ponuja rešitve, za katere do danes nismo našli ustreznega dogovora.</p>
      <p sl="en">In mislim, da je res nerazumno zavračati tovrstne pobude, dejstvo pa je, da rešitev lahko najdemo vsi skupaj, zelo težko pa vsaka država posebej, in tu ne pomagajo nobene visoke ograje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-053-0000" speaker_id="125071" name="Γεώργιος Επιτήδειος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, το παγκόσμιο σύμφωνο για τη μετανάστευση είναι ένα κείμενο όχι μόνο άχρηστο, αλλά και επικίνδυνο. Πρώτα απ’ όλα, αναγνωρίζει το δικαίωμα της μαζικής κινητοποίησης και μετακίνησης για οικονομικούς λόγους σε οποιονδήποτε από τρίτη χώρα θέλει να εισέλθει ή ακόμη και να εισβάλει -κυρίως- στην Ευρώπη και τις Ηνωμένες Πολιτείες. Κατά δεύτερο λόγο, δημιουργείται σύγχυση μεταξύ του ποιος είναι νόμιμος και ποιος παράνομος μετανάστης. Αυτό έχει ως αποτέλεσμα τα κράτη να μην μπορούν να ακολουθούν μία ανεξάρτητη εθνική μεταναστευτική πολιτική και να προστατεύουν τα σύνορά τους.</p>
      <p sl="en">Επιπλέον, υπάρχει κίνδυνος, στο μέλλον, οι μη δεσμευτικοί -αυτήν τη στιγμή- στόχοι που αναφέρονται στο σχέδιο να γίνουν δεσμευτικές διατάξεις και, λαμβάνοντας υπόψη τις αγκυλώσεις και την εμμονή της Αριστεράς, δεν θα προκαλέσει εντύπωση εάν οποιαδήποτε επίκριση για το φαινόμενο της παράνομης μετανάστευσης γίνει ποινικό αδίκημα. Αυτός ακριβώς είναι και ο λόγος για τον οποίον πολλά κράτη δεν επιδιώκουν πλέον να υπογράψουν το εν λόγω κείμενο.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-055-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Federica Mogherini" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission / High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I want to underline the fact that I am speaking here on behalf of the Commission. It’s for the Austrian Presidency to express the position of the Council.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has a very clear position on the Global Compact. As I explained, this is the result of a process that we Europeans have initiated in the UN Framework, asking for partnership and asking to have a political global framework for managing together, on the basis of what we had already started to do with our African friends, with our Asian friends, and with friends from Latin America and everywhere. We initiated this process in the UN Framework, asking for a global approach – political, not legally binding – to establish partnerships because we Europeans found out – in my view quite late, in 2015-2016, but still we did – that we needed to build strong partnerships with the countries of origin, of transit and of destination, supporting a common system and a common approach to manage migration, fight traffickers, offer opportunities and also to tackle, as some of you have said, difficult issues like returns, in an effective manner. It’s a difficult process, but it’s a process that is now reflected in a Compact that, starting from a European approach, has moved to a global level.</p>
      <p sl="en">As I said, the Compact largely reflects the positions of the European Union and the work that we are currently doing, together with our partners, on migration, starting from the work we’re doing with the International Organisation for Migration (IOM) and the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNNHCR). I can tell you this: the Commission will not only be represented in Marrakesh with a delegation, as I said, led by Commissioner Avramopoulos, but will continue to actively engage with the UN and with the UN system on its implementation. Technically, as you might know – but maybe not – after the Conference in Marrakech, there will be a vote in the General Assembly, where Member States of the UN will take a vote, but the Commission will continue to work with the UN system, with the UN agencies and with our partners globally to implement this agenda because we have seen that, in the first couple of years of work that we have done, along the lines that are reflected in the Global Compact, these have started to bring results.</p>
      <p sl="en">So we will continue to work in this direction, investing in the Global Compact’s implementation as a political, non—binding, cooperative framework that will guide our work over the coming decades.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-056-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Karoline Edtstadler" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President-in-Office of the Council">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, High Representative, honourable Members, it was useful to have this discussion today in view of the conference next month and of the forthcoming adoption of the Global Compact in New York. I would like to conclude by reiterating what I already stated at the beginning, and that is the fact that migration in general and more specifically cooperation with third countries will remain high on the agenda of the Council and the Presidency. Therefore we will continue to contribute to that purpose. I would like to thank you for sharing your doubts, your questions, your concerns, and also your thoughts in this regard.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-057-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-058-0000" speaker_id="28150" name="Kinga Gál" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Ha az ENSZ globális migrációs csomagját alaposan átolvassuk, nyilvánvaló válik, hogy nem Európa érdekeit tükrözi, sőt Európára káros és veszélyes. A dokumentum pozitív jelenségnek tünteti fel a migrációt, egybemossa az illegális gazdasági migrációt a valódi menekültek kérdésével, illetve a legális migrációval, és az illegális migrációt mintegy alapvető jogként állítja be. Arra kötelezné az országokat, hogy tájékoztassák a migránsokat a migrációs útvonalakról, és indítsanak tájékoztató kampányokat nekik. Továbbá megkönnyítené a migránsok családegyesítését, és ugyanolyan szolgáltatásokat kéne nyújtani a migránsoknak, mint az adott ország polgárainak. A dokumentumban nyolcvan alkalommal szerepel a kötelezettség szó, így messze nem igaz az az állítás, hogy csak ajánlásokat fogalmaz meg. A csomag elfogadásának ezért a jogértelmezés és szokásjog kialakulása miatt visszafordíthatatlan következményei lennének, hiszen ezek hivatkozási ponttá és a nemzetközi bíráskodás alapjává válnának. Ez ellentétes az európai emberek érdekeivel. Magyarország példáját követve már nyolc ország döntött amellett, hogy kilép a csomag elfogadásának folyamatából, és számos más tagállam fontolgatja a migrációs kompakttól való elállást. Úgy látom, kezd visszatérni a józan ész kontinensünkre, és egyre többen veszik észre, hogy ez egy nemzeti érdekeket sértő, a mi Európánkra veszélyes dokumentum, ami egyértelműen megosztja az Uniót.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-058-5000" speaker_id="124749" name="Marijana Petir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – SAD, Austrija, Bugarska, Češka i Mađarska države su koje su odustale od potpisivanja Marakeške deklaracije, dok Slovačka, Poljska, Estonija, Australija, Izrael i Švicarska imaju izražene rezerve prema Deklaraciji te navode da neće sudjelovati u ratifikaciji Deklaracije. Odustajanje navedenih država od ratifikacije Deklaracije treba nas pozvati na određeni oprez.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mene najviše, u okviru teksta Deklaracije, brine činjenica da se brišu granice između legalnih i ilegalnih migracija. Bez obzira što Deklaracija predstavlja neobvezujući dokument, države članice mogu ga uvrstiti u svoje zakonodavstvo, što može stvoriti dugoročne probleme po pitanju migracija i po pitanju suvereniteta u budućnosti.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU je pogriješio u samom pristupu migracijama, nije ih rješavao na mjestu gdje su nastajale, već je svojom usvojenom politikom dodatno poticao migrantske valove. Smatram da je važno pomoći ljudima koji bježe od rata i svojom humanošću im pokazati da smo uz njih, ali kada je riječ o ekonomskim migracijama, potrebno je stvoriti socijalne, gospodarske i političke uvjete u državama iz kojih migranti dolaze, kako bi mogli ostati i pristojno živjeti u svojoj domovini.</p>
      <p sl="en">Smatram kako EU ne smije vršiti pritisak na države članice, već one same moraju odlučiti hoće li pristupiti Marakeškoj deklaraciji te im treba dati mogućnost da same odluče mogu li i koliko primiti migranata u svoju državu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-059-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne. – Globálny rámec o bezpečnej, riadenej a legálnej migrácii považujem za vážny politický dokument, ktorý mal byť pre všetky štáty, ktoré sú zastúpené v OSN, zárukou toho, aby problém migrácie vo svete bol koordinovaný, aby mal jednotnú platformu a aby štáty spoločne čelili problémom migrácie, ktoré sú všade vo svete. Bohužiaľ, dokument prináša okrem dobrých návrhov aj body, ktoré sú kontroverzné, a preto aj neprijateľné pre mnohé štáty. Aj keď sa v preambule v článku 7 uvádza, že globálny právny rámec predstavuje nezáväzný rámec, vzápätí sa v článku 9 uvádza, že tento globálny rámec stanovuje naše spoločné chápania, spoločné povinnosti, zdieľané zodpovednosti a jednotu účelu v súvislosti s migráciou, aby bola prospešná pre všetkých. Dokument má 23 cieľov, s niektorými môžeme súhlasiť, ale niektoré sú neprijateľné. Určite všetci súhlasia s tým, aby sa minimalizovali nepriaznivé podnety a štrukturálne faktory, ktoré nútia ľudí, aby opustili svoju krajinu. Na druhej strane je bod o integrácii migrantov a ich začleňovaní, ich vzdelávaní, o ich finančnej podpore, ktorý by si mali osvojiť iba krajiny, ktoré pre svoju ekonomiku potrebujú migrantov. OSN by si mala uvedomiť, že nejednotnosť pri hodnotení dokumentu je vážny moment, preto by v čo najkratšom čase mala hľadať kompromisné návrhy, lebo problémy migrácie je potrebné riešiť spoločne.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. The situation of women with disabilities (debate)">
    <intervention id="2-061-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung an die Kommission über die Situation von Frauen mit Behinderungen von Rosa Estaràs Ferragut im Namen des Ausschusses für die Rechte der Frau und die Gleichstellung der Geschlechter (O-000117/2018 – B8-0418/2018) (2018/2685(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-062-0000" speaker_id="96811" name="Rosa Estaràs Ferragut" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autora. – Señor presidente, hablamos hoy en nombre de los más de 46 millones de mujeres con discapacidad; ellas representan el 16,6 % de la población total de la Unión Europea. Hoy, con este debate, vamos a hacerlas más visibles. Vamos a ser su altavoz. Hoy vamos a crear una imagen que favorezca de verdad que puedan ejercer sus derechos. Ellas son, ante todo, seres humanos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Son ciudadanas que no pueden ser definidas por su discapacidad y, de hecho, no quieren serlo. Se enfrentan día a día a los mismos problemas que el resto de mujeres: son madres, hijas, amigas, trabajadoras; tienen multitud de talentos y multitud de habilidades y enriquecen nuestra sociedad haciéndola más diversa. Es crucial la contribución que ellas pueden hacer, y por eso hay que promoverla y asegurar que los planes que tienen estas mujeres van a ser escuchados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hoy, con este debate, vamos a crear una concienciación positiva sobre la diversidad y vamos a hacer que la cultura de la diferencia se imponga, porque es la que genera más ventajas sociales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esas mujeres se enfrentan día a día al reto de que las hacemos invisibles. Las mujeres que no ven, que no oyen, que viven de otra manera, que no tienen movilidad; en definitiva, las mujeres con discapacidad, son mujeres que la sociedad excluye. Se trata muchas veces de barreras mentales: las invisibiliza, y se generan así muchísimas discriminaciones en todos los sectores en todos los países.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablaremos de educación —la educación inclusiva—, que significa que todos participamos libremente en la sociedad y todos aportamos y contribuimos a la misma. Cuando se discrimina en educación se hace culpable al alumno diverso de esta exclusión; eso no puede pasar. El trabajo y la educación inclusivas y accesibles son los instrumentos para poder vincularnos a una sociedad y para poder participar en todos los sectores; solamente un 18,8 % de las mujeres con discapacidad están empleadas en la Unión Europea, un porcentaje menor que sus homólogos hombres o que, indudablemente, el resto de personas que no tienen discapacidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Necesitamos hablar también de alfabetización digital, porque un colectivo importante de estas mujeres son mayores de sesenta años y por eso deberemos elaborar una estrategia para la mujer mayor y discapacitada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablaremos también de la necesidad de la plena participación en todos los asuntos de las mujeres con discapacidad; no pueden quedar al margen de nada; y, por supuesto, garantizar el sufragio activo y pasivo de estas mujeres. Recientemente se ha hecho una modificación legislativa en España en este sentido.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablaremos de la igualdad de trato: la necesidad de que todos seamos iguales —uno de los valores de la Unión Europea—. Para eso habrá que crear políticas activas y públicas para poder romper todas las barreras a esa igualdad y, sobre todo, dar información veraz, simple y eficaz a estas mujeres para que puedan desarrollar sus derechos.</p>
      <p sl="en">La accesibilidad es el requisito previo para poder tener participación e igualdad. Es verdad que el 8 de noviembre nos han comunicado que Consejo y Comisión han acordado ya que salga adelante esta Acta Europea de Accesibilidad, que es más de lo que teníamos y menos de lo que pedíamos, pero que es un paso adelante para trabajar en una Europa sin barreras.</p>
      <p sl="en">La accesibilidad significa que todo se haga en todos los lenguajes, en todas las formas, en todos los formatos. Piensen ustedes que, por ejemplo, en las revisiones ginecológicas, las mujeres con discapacidad tienen problemas de accesibilidad para ir a hacerse una mamografía o una revisión ginecológica. Hay dificultad en la accesibilidad a muchos servicios de salud, a muchos servicios contra la violencia de género, a servicios de apoyo, a los de maternidad, a la protección, a la comunicación. Hay que romper esas barreras. El pilar social es una oportunidad para poder incluir a las mujeres con discapacidad y hacerlas también protagonistas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y hablaremos también de dignidad. Hay que salir del silencio del acoso que sufren estas mujeres: una de cada tres mujeres con discapacidad ha sido o va a ser maltratada y víctima de violencia de género. Por eso necesitamos una estrategia de apoyo y respeto en este sentido.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y hablaremos también de otra forma de discriminar, como la esterilización forzosa, el aborto coercitivo o excluirlas del derecho a la adopción o a la maternidad. Es también una discriminación en toda regla y supone un trato inhumano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y también hablaremos de la necesidad de tener indicadores para saber cuál es la situación de estas mujeres; indicadores de género; indicadores de discapacidad en la propia Estrategia Europea sobre discapacidad y en todos los departamentos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y acabo diciéndoles que el objetivo 5 de los Objetivos de Desarrollo Sostenible hablaba de empoderar a las mujeres. Empoderar a las mujeres con discapacidad es empoderar a la humanidad. Hoy tenemos una oportunidad para aprender, para sentir, para vivir y para crear. «Ser mujer —dice una discapacitada y buena amiga— me encanta; tengo una discapacidad y tengo muchísimas capacidades como cualquier otra persona, pero ante todo soy un ser humano, con todos los derechos que me corresponden; espero no tener nunca más que volver a justificar el porqué».</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-063-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members of Parliament, fundamental rights, inclusive growth and social fairness are at the core of this Commission’s agenda. We are working hard to make sure that no one is left behind, and I would like to think Madam Estaràs Ferragut and the FEMM Committee for putting forward this question on the situation of women with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission has undertaken important legislative initiatives for fostering the participation of persons with disabilities in society and for promoting gender equality.</p>
      <p sl="en">Just to give you two examples: the European Accessibility Act, on which there has recently been a provisional agreement among co-legislators, will break down barriers to key products and services. The Accessibility Act will, in particular, be a key tool to bridge the digital divide.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, the Commission has proposed a work-life balance package in order to enable carers – mainly women – to better balance work and caring responsibilities. This is a key initiative to contribute to bridging the existing employment gap, pay gap and pension gap between men and women, and I hope the ongoing trilogues will produce results soon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me now respond to the three questions you’ve put forward.</p>
      <p sl="en">Together with all of our Member States, the European Union has committed to implement the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities. The European Disability Strategy is the main instrument to support the Union’s implementation of the Convention until 2020. It is part of the wider efforts under the Europe 2020 strategy to succeed in creating smart, sustainable and inclusive growth. Indeed, full economic and social participation of people with disabilities is essential to fulfil the objectives of the European 2020 strategy.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is currently preparing an evaluation of the implementation of the current European Disability Strategy. The evaluation will cover all aspects of this ability. This includes, in particular, the situation of women and girls with disabilities and the challenges stemming from inter-sectional discrimination. And of course, as part of our preparations, we will consult as many stakeholders as possible. We will take into account the European Parliament’s views, such as last year’s resolution on the concluding observations of the UN Committee.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now on the gender-disaggregated data. Reliable and accurate data are essential for policy development. The Commission already disaggregates by gender the disability-related data it collects, including within the European semester. These data provide us with an objective basis for identifying intersectional discrimination. Our data show, for instance, that in the areas of poverty risk and employment, women with disabilities are disadvantaged compared to men with disabilities. In the area of education, however, we observe a higher percentage of early school-leaving with boys with disabilities than with girls.</p>
      <p sl="en">Attention to gender equality is also paid in the Union’s external action activities. We notably provide support to partner countries to improve data collection disaggregated by sex and disability. There is also the obligation to complete a gender analysis for each development cooperation project or programme.</p>
      <p sl="en">As a last point, I want to address the question on what the Commission is doing to enable participation of women with disabilities in the European elections.</p>
      <p sl="en">My colleague, Commissioner Jourová, has delivered a statement on the participation of people with disabilities in the European elections at the European Parliament’s plenary session on 5 July this year, and she pointed out the Commission’s recommendation of February 2018, which addresses the exchange of best practices with a view to promote the exercise of electoral rights of under-represented groups, including persons with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">In April this year we followed up with a dedicated session on this topic, involving our network of Member States experts in electoral matters, and this week, on 26 and 27 November, we dedicated the annual colloquium on fundamental rights to democracy and the European Union, including the promotion of broad participation as a condition for inclusive democratic societies.</p>
      <p sl="en">And finally, I want to mention that the directive on the accessibility of public sector bodies’ websites, which came into effect last September, will contribute to assuring the accessibility of information issued by public bodies across the Union about political participation and elections. Thank you again for these questions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-064-0000" speaker_id="124889" name="Agnieszka Kozłowska-Rajewicz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy PPE. – Panie Przewodniczący! Pani Komisarz! Przede wszystkim gratuluję Rosie Esteraz znakomitego tekstu rezolucji na temat sytuacji kobiet niepełnosprawnych.</p>
      <p sl="en">W Europie żyje 80 mln osób z niepełnosprawnościami, z czego 46 mln to kobiety. Tylko 18% z nich posiada zatrudnienie. Niepełnosprawnymi osobami opiekują się głównie kobiety. 80% z nich robi to nieformalnie i nieodpłatnie. To zamknięte koło nierówności, niekończącego się wysiłku i niesprawiedliwości.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlaczego tak mało niepełnosprawnych kobiet dostaje się na rynek pracy? Jakie przepisy lub ich brak stoją na przeszkodzie do ekonomicznej samodzielności niepełnosprawnych kobiet? To nie tylko kwestia pieniędzy, niewykorzystanych talentów i kompetencji. To także kwestia ludzkiej godności związana z faktem bycia osobą niezależną i w pełni włączoną do życia społecznego i ekonomicznego. Przecież dzisiejsze technologie, na co rezolucja zwraca uwagę, dają osobom niepełnosprawnym duże możliwości do prowadzenia normalnego życia i samorealizacji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pani Komisarz! Należy jak najszybciej wdrożyć w praktyce zalecenia Konwencji ONZ ds. praw osób niepełnosprawnych oraz europejską strategię w sprawie niepełnosprawności. Apeluję także do Komisji i państw członkowskich o rewizję i pełne stosowanie przepisów na rzecz osób niepełnosprawnych, o włączenie do tych przepisów zasad projektowania uniwersalnego oraz o lepsze wykorzystanie technologii cyfrowych i postępu medycyny, tak aby zwiększyć samodzielność, zatrudnialność, oraz poczucie wolności i godności niepełnosprawnych kobiet i mężczyzn.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-065-0000" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">S&amp;D frakcijos vardu. – Gerbiamas Pirmininke, apie neįgalių žmonių teises, jų tarpe neįgalių moterų teises ir jų gyvenimo kokybės gerinimą, turėtume kalbėti ir ieškoti sprendimų ne tik neįgalių žmonių dienos išvakarėse, bet prie šio klausimo turime dirbti nuolatos – kartu su Komisija, valstybėm narėm, žinoma, įtraukiant ir neįgaliųjų visuomenines organizacijas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mes vis kalbame apie Europos socialinių teisių ramstį, apie Europos strategiją dėl negalė, bet deja nesugebame sumažinti neįgaliųjų, ypač neįgalių moterų, diskriminacijos, niekaip nesugebame užtikrinti paprasčiausių dalykų, atrodo, šitiems žmonėms, t.y. darbo, pajamų, įtraukimo į pilietinį ir politinį gyvenimą.</p>
      <p sl="en">Neįgaliųjų nedarbo lygis išlieka nepriimtinas, dėlto jiems gresia žymiai didesnė skurdo ir socialinės atskirties rizika. Be to, neįgalios moterys susiduria su didesnėm kliūtim norėdamos patekti į darbo rinką, o dėlto joms sunkiau gyventi įprastą ir nepriklausomą gyvenimą, nes darbas yra ne tik pajamų šaltinis, bet ir socialinės įtraukties priemonė, padedanti užmegzti ryšius su platesne visuomene. Neįgalių moterų darbas dažnai apmokamas nepakankamai, o ką jau kalbėti apie jų senatvės pensijas, sulaukus senatvės amžiaus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dar viena problema yra ta, kad duomenų apie negalę turinčių moterų darbo pobūdį ir užimtumo situaciją apskritai yra nedaug. O neturint konkrečių duomenų suskirstytų pagal lytį, labai sunku spręsti diskriminacijos atvejus, todėl, ponia komisare, raginu visą Komisiją nustatyti konkrečias priemones minėtoms problemoms spręsti, užtikrinti pakankamą finansavimą, per Europos Sąjungos struktūrinius fondus.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-066-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Nasza wrażliwość na potrzeby osób niepełnosprawnych objawia się w przededniu Międzynarodowego Dnia Osób Niepełnosprawnych. Dla mnie trąci to trochę jednak hipokryzją, że oto w związku ze zbliżającym się Dniem Osób Niepełnosprawnych w Parlamencie Europejskim podejmujemy tematykę osób, które powinniśmy wspierać i którym powinniśmy stwarzać szanse i możliwości na edukację, rozwój zawodowy, dostęp do dóbr kultury. Warto dzisiaj postawić pytanie, dlaczego Parlament Europejski działa akcyjnie. Ponad podziałami politycznymi powinniśmy podejmować działania, które pozwolą osobom niepełnosprawnym po prostu godnie żyć.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szkoda, że do tego dokumentu wrzucacie Państwo – tutaj zwracam się do lewej strony sali parlamentarnej – tematy związane ze zmianą płci. Uważam, że to godne pożałowania, aby w tak ważnej …</p>
      <a text="(Przewodniczący odebrał mówczyni głos)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-067-0000" speaker_id="193292" name="Tilly Metz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident, werte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Respektieren wir wirklich die UN-Konvention für die Rechte von Menschen mit einer Behinderung? Nein! Noch immer werden Menschen mit einer Behinderung diskriminiert, und vor allem Frauen mit einer Beeinträchtigung – das im Bereich der Ausbildung, im Bereich der Arbeit, aber auch im Bereich der persönlichen, privaten Entwicklung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber jeder hat das Recht darauf, glücklich zu sein. Jeder hat das Recht darauf, ein selbstbestimmtes Leben zu leben – ein Leben, wo Sexualität kein Tabu ist, ein Leben, wo ich meine Sexualität ausleben kann, wo aber auch „Nein“ sagen „Nein“ heißt, das Recht darauf, eine Familie zu gründen, das Recht darauf, aber auch zu heiraten oder mit meinem Partner oder meiner Partnerin zusammenleben zu können. Und genau in diesen Bereichen brauchen gerade Frauen mit einer Beeinträchtigung unsere Unterstützung und unsere Begleitung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es geht hier nicht um Mitleid, es geht um ein fundamentales Menschenrecht.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-068-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, a União Europeia não se pode demitir de responsabilidades na degradação da situação socioeconómica das pessoas com deficiência, onde as mulheres são duplamente discriminadas. As políticas de austeridade que promove, o recorte de direitos sociais e laborais, o condicionamento ao investimento nos orçamentos dos Estados em áreas como a saúde, a educação ou os apoios sociais não se dissociam do retrocesso social desta franja da população.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todos os dias, os direitos fundamentais são negados às pessoas com deficiência. Nas dificuldades de acesso ao emprego com direitos, nas limitações e desadequação da formação profissional, na perpetuação da pobreza e exclusão, na insuficiente proteção social, na falta de meios humanos, materiais e pedagógicos na escola pública para o adequado acompanhamento e inclusão efetiva de crianças e jovens, nas dificuldades no acesso a cuidados de saúde, medicamentos e terapias direcionadas, nas persistentes limitações à mobilidade e no acesso à cultura e ao desporto, entre outros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma realidade que exige o reforço de políticas e de respostas públicas que deem resposta cabal às necessidades das pessoas com deficiência.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-069-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, zajištění rovných podmínek pro ženy s postižením, ať už v oblasti vzdělávání, ve zdravotnictví nebo na pracovišti by mělo být samozřejmé. Přesto tomu tak v některých oblastech není. Zdravotně postižené ženy mají např. v praxi často problém vyhledat pomoc i běžných lékařů. Tyto ženy se potýkají se zatíženým přístupem i v jiných službách a čelí různým podobám násilí. Tento návrh usnesení obsahuje řadu důležitých výzev, které by měly tuto situaci žen zlepšit. Na tyto problémy upozorňuje a doufá, že pro státy bude toto usnesení impulzem pro zajištění kvalitnějších služeb.</p>
      <p sl="en">Přesto musím upozornit na témata, se kterými nesouhlasím. Nesouhlasím s doporučením na přijetí Istanbulské úmluvy, se začleněním problematiky sexuálního a reprodukčního zdraví a se specifickou zdravotní péčí pro transgender osoby. Domnívám se, že tyto výzvy nemají místo v takto pojaté rezoluci, a proto, obávám se, nebudu moci ji podpořit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-071-0000" speaker_id="26837" name="Λευτέρης Χριστοφόρου" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, είναι γεγονός ότι, μέσα από τη συζήτηση για τις διακρίσεις κατά των γυναικών και κατά των ατόμων με αναπηρίες, αναδεικνύεται ένα μείζον θέμα για την Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση: ότι δεν είναι μόνον οι γυναίκες με αναπηρίες που τυγχάνουν δυσμενών διακρίσεων, αλλά οι δυσμενείς διακρίσεις παρατηρούνται εις βάρος όλων των γυναικών, σε όλα τα επίπεδα. Πιστεύω ότι η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση έπρεπε να είναι πρωτοπόρα και πρωταγωνίστρια, και να εφαρμόζει πλήρως και απόλυτα την αρχή της απαγόρευσης των διακρίσεων μεταξύ ανδρών και γυναικών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ισότητα των φύλων στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση ήταν, είναι και παραμένει μια βασική, ατράνταχτη και απαραβίαστη αρχή που οφείλουν όλοι να την εφαρμόζουν, και ιδιαίτερα η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή. Δεν γίνεται μόνο με λόγια και διακηρύξεις. Οι διακηρύξεις είναι εδώ και υπάρχει σήμερα η δυνατότητα να δεσμευτούν η Ευρωπαία Επίτροπος και η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή για την πλήρη και απόλυτη εφαρμογή όσον αφορά την ισότητα των φύλων και για την επιβολή κυρώσεων σε όσα κράτη μέλη δεν εφαρμόζουν την αρχή της ισότητας των δύο φύλων. Μόνον έτσι θα γίνει πράξη η πλήρης και απόλυτη εφαρμογή της αρχής της ισότητας των δύο φύλων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-072-0000" speaker_id="125105" name="Helga Stevens" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, allereerst wil ik graag de rapporteur bedanken om via deze ontwerpresolutie aandacht te vragen voor de situatie van vrouwen met een beperking. Vrouwen met een beperking worden vaak geconfronteerd met interseksuele discriminatie vanwege hun geslacht en hun beperking. Zij hebben twee tot vijf keer meer kans om geweld en seksueel misbruik mee te maken dan vrouwen zonder handicap, vooral wanneer ze een verstandelijke beperking hebben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zij zijn bovendien ondervertegenwoordigd op de arbeidsmarkt en in de politiek. Hierdoor voelen veel vrouwen met een handicap aan dat zij uitgesloten zijn in de samenleving. Ik hoop oprecht dat de Commissie gendergelijkheid dit expliciet zal meenemen bij het ontwerp van de EU-strategie inzake handicaps 2030 zodat discriminatie van vrouwen en meisjes met een handicap krachtig kan worden aangepakt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gelijkheid, non-discriminatie, respect en gelijke kansen voor vrouwen met een handicap. Geen woorden maar daden, nu!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-073-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, νομίζω ότι η συζήτηση έχει αποκαλύψει ότι πραγματικά υφίστανται, δυστυχώς, διακρίσεις κατά των γυναικών με αναπηρία. Και αυτό που χρειάζεται είναι να μην λέμε πολλά λόγια· να μην βρίσκουμε σαν αφορμή το γεγονός ότι στις 3 Δεκεμβρίου είναι η Παγκόσμια Ημέρα των Ατόμων με Αναπηρία για να κάνουμε αυτή τη συζήτηση. Πρέπει να πάρουμε συγκεκριμένα μέτρα και έχουμε πει επανειλημμένως σε παρεμβάσεις μας στην ολομέλεια του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου ότι πρέπει να εφαρμοστεί η σύμβαση του ΟΗΕ για τα άτομα με αναπηρία.</p>
      <p sl="en">Επίσης, δεν πρέπει να υπάρχουν διακρίσεις. Δεν πρέπει να υπάρχουν διακρίσεις κατά των γυναικών οι οποίες είναι ΑΜΕΑ. Αυτό το βλέπουμε να συμβαίνει· υπάρχει δυσκολία στην πρόσβασή τους στην αγορά εργασίας. Πολύ δε περισσότερο στην Ελλάδα, όπου εκεί οι διακρίσεις είναι πολύ έντονες και, λόγω των μνημονίων, έχουν μειωθεί και τα αναπηρικά επιδόματα. Επομένως, χρειάζονται μέτρα συγκεκριμένα για να μπορέσουμε να αντιμετωπίσουμε αυτό το κοινωνικό πρόβλημα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-075-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this debate shows once more the relevance of the strategic and long-term approach we have chosen for both the specific issues of gender equality and disability. I should mention here that gender equality, equal opportunities and the inclusion of persons with disabilities are also among the principles of the European Pillar of Social Rights, which was jointly proclaimed just over a year ago by all three European political institutions.</p>
      <p sl="en">There is no doubt that the considerable input of the European Parliament over the past years will feed into the reflection about the form and the content of future European disability policies. The Commission is also committed to ensure the involvement of people with disabilities and their representative organisations in this reflection. I count on the European Parliament and, of course, also on the Member States to be strong allies in putting the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities into practice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gemäß Artikel 128 Absatz 5 der Geschäftsordnung wurde ein Entschließungsantrag eingereicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet heute, 29. November 2018, statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-5000" speaker_id="23868" name="Monika Beňová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písomne. – Ženy a dievčatá so zdravotným postihnutím sú obzvlášť zraniteľné z hľadiska hrozby diskriminácie a násilia. Z dostupných štatistík vyplýva, že v porovnaní so zdravou populáciou existuje až niekoľkonásobne vyššia pravdepodobnosť, že hendikepovaná žena bude vystavená násiliu alebo nejakej forme zneužívania. Práve preto potrebujeme vytvárať efektívne normy na ochranu občanov so zdravotným postihnutím a fungujúci systém ich aktívneho zapájania do bežného života. Veľmi dôležitá je tiež podpora zjednodušovania a lepšieho prístupu hendikepovaných ľudí k novým technológiám. Pre plné začlenenie žien a dievčat so zdravotným postihnutím do spoločnosti je nevyhnutná pomoc a participácia rodiny, kolegov či zamestnávateľa. Základ zmeny tak spočíva v konaní okruhu ich najbližších ľudí. Z pohľadu nadchádzajúcich európskych volieb je nezastupiteľný aktívny prístup Európskej komisie smerom k hendikepovaným občanom. Tak, aby ženy so zdravotným postihnutím mohli nielen voliť, ale predovšetkým sa jednoduchšie uchádzať o dôveru ľudí vo voľbách.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-6250" speaker_id="124851" name="Nicola Caputo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – Tutte le persone con disabilità devono avere la possibilità di beneficiare pienamente dei propri diritti sulla base dell'inclusione e della piena partecipazione alla società. La partecipazione sociale ed economica delle donne con disabilità è essenziale per il successo della strategia economica e sociale globale dell'Europa. Ad esse deve essere garantito il pieno godimento dei diritti per quanto riguarda un'istruzione di qualità, accessibile e a prezzi abbordabili, l'assistenza sanitaria, comprese cure sanitarie specifiche per le persone transgender e per la salute sessuale e riproduttiva e i diritti ad essa connessi, l'occupazione, la mobilità, la vita familiare, l'autonomia fisica, la sessualità e il matrimonio, nonché le salvaguardie che garantiscono tali diritti. Chiedo alla Commissione di presentare una proposta di strategia europea sulla disabilità 2020-2030 che integri pienamente le disposizioni della Convenzione delle Nazioni Unite sui diritti delle persone con disabilità nella legislazione, nelle politiche e nei programmi futuri dell'UE e che sia coerente con la Convenzione delle Nazioni Unite sui diritti del fanciullo e con l'impegno strategico a favore della parità di genere 2016-2019, al fine di assicurare che le donne e le ragazze con disabilità possano godere pienamente dei propri diritti come ogni altra persona.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-6875" speaker_id="124900" name="Beata Gosiewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Kobiety niepełnosprawne w zależności od wieku, miejsca zamieszkania, statusu społecznego czy wreszcie rodzaju niepełnosprawności doświadczają różnych trudności związanych z codziennym funkcjonowaniem. Są to problemy dwojakiego rodzaju: z jednej strony dotyczą uzyskania odpowiedniego wykształcenia czy znalezienia wymarzonej pracy, z drugiej zaś indywidualnych cech związanych z samoakceptacją oraz poczuciem własnej wartości. Ponadto bariery komunikacyjne oraz architektoniczne powodują, że w życiu codziennym proste czynności stają się dla nich bardzo skomplikowane lub wręcz niewykonalne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zgadzam się z założeniami rezolucji o promowaniu inicjatyw wspierających aktywizację zawodową i zapewnieniu równego dostępu do edukacji i pracy. W przeciwnym wypadku może to skutkować ubóstwem i wykluczeniem społecznym. Należy egzekwować usunięcie wszelkich barier i przeciwdziałać dyskryminacji społecznej, której te osoby doświadczają. Konieczne jest wdrożenie polityki zapobiegania, leczenia, rehabilitacji i integracji w odniesieniu do osób niepełnosprawnych, a także zapewnienie wsparcia ich rodzinom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uważam, że dyskutując na temat osób niepełnosprawnych, nie powinniśmy wprowadzać do debaty różnic ideologicznych. Moim zdaniem rezolucja powinna być pozbawiona jakichkolwiek światopoglądowych zapisów, a szczególnie tych dotyczących orientacji seksualnej i aborcji. Włączenie tych tematów powoduje, że rezolucja staje się przedmiotem sporów ideologicznych i nie służy niepełnosprawnym. Miejmy na uwadze, że zagadnienie pomocy kobietom niepełnosprawnym jest bliskie większości eurodeputowanych, a kwestia dostępności aborcji czy zmiany płci już nie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-076-7500" speaker_id="135540" name="Czesław Hoc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Przyjęło się stwierdzenie, że stosunek do osób niepełnosprawnych jest miarą dzisiejszej cywilizacji. Podejście do niepełnosprawności ewoluowało od traktowania osób niepełnosprawnych jako przedmiotu działań charytatywnych do postrzegania ich jako obdarzonych prawami. W nowoczesnym ujęciu niepełnosprawności, w pełni uznając wagę człowieczeństwa i godność osób niepełnosprawnych, wskazuje się na prawa im przysługujące na równi z innymi ludźmi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nie możemy już patrzeć na osoby niepełnosprawne przez pryzmat ciągłej opieki i pomocy. Dzisiaj niepełnosprawni nie oczekują litości i superprzywilejów. Pragną traktowania ich w świetle praw człowieka, a także osiągnięć naukowych prowadzących do postępów w leczeniu, rehabilitacji i edukacji, która gwarantowałaby wyrównywanie szans i ochronę przed dyskryminacją. Pragną poczucia bezpieczeństwa i postawy solidarnościowej. Najpierw należy widzieć osobę, potem ewentualnie jej wózek inwalidzki. W szczególności dotyczy to niepełnosprawnych kobiet i dziewcząt, które są trzykrotnie bardziej narażone na przemoc niż kobiety pełnosprawne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Musimy pilnie doprowadzić do likwidacji istniejących przeszkód i barier, w tym barier architektonicznych, aby stworzyć równość praw i szans udziału kobiet i dziewcząt w życiu rodzinnym, politycznym, kulturalnym, społecznym i zawodowym.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-077-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Riječ „invaliditet” obuhvaća mnogo različitih privremenih, kratkoročnih ili dugoročnih osobnih situacija koje zahtijevaju prilagođene političke odgovore i uključuju psihičke poteškoće. Sve osobe s invaliditetom trebale bi moći u potpunosti uživati u svojim pravima na temelju uključenosti i u potpunosti sudjelovati u društvu.</p>
      <p sl="en">To je moguće samo uz provedbu aktivnih i javnih politika te uz uklanjanje svih prepreka za sudjelovanje. U EU-u danas živi oko 46 milijuna žena i djevojčica s invaliditetom koje čine oko 16 % ukupnog broja žena u Uniji i 60 % ukupnog stanovništva s invaliditetom, a samo je 18,8 % žena s invaliditetom u EU-u zaposleno. Žene i djevojčice s invaliditetom izložene su dvostrukoj diskriminaciji zbog kombinacije spola i invaliditeta i često mogu biti izložene višestrukoj diskriminaciji koja proizlazi iz kombinacije spola i invaliditeta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ovaj Prijedlog rezolucije poziva države članice da provedu politike za prevenciju, liječenje, rehabilitaciju i integraciju osoba s invaliditetom i za pružanje potpore njihovim obiteljima te da preuzmu odgovornost za efektivno ostvarenje njihovih prava, ne dovodeći u pitanje prava i dužnosti roditelja ili skrbnika.</p>
      <p sl="en">Također, poziva na razvoj pedagogije kojom se društvo osvješćuje o dužnosti poštovanja i solidarnosti u pogledu osoba s invaliditetom u cilju borbe protiv socijalne diskriminacije kojoj su te osobe izložene.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-078-0000" speaker_id="96829" name="Ádám Kósa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – 2013-ban 33 igen és 6 tartózkodás mellett fogadta el az EMPL bizottság a fogyatékossággal élő nőkről szóló véleményt, amelynek én voltam az előadója. 5 évvel később is fontos hangsúlyozni: a fogyatékosságon és nemi alapon történő megkülönböztetés valamennyi formáját tiltani kell. A fogyatékossággal élő nők csoportja nagyobb kirekesztettségnek, többszörös megkülönböztetésnek van kitéve. Fel kell használni az Európai Szociális Alapot a fogyatékossággal élő nők az élet minden fontos területén – munkaerőpiachoz, képzéshez és (általános) oktatáshoz való szabad hozzáférés terén – való nagyobb bevonásának hatékony eszközeként. A nők inaktivitási rátája magasabb, kevesebb készséget igénylő, kevesebb felelősséggel és alacsonyabb fizetéssel járó munkát végeznek, nagyobb társadalmi elszigeteltségben élnek, pénzügyileg jobban függnek a családtól és gondozóktól. A népesség elöregedésével egyre nagyobb a fogyatékossággal élő idősek aránya, akik közt több a nő a hosszabb várható élettartamuk miatt. Nagyobb figyelmet kell fordítani a jelnyelvet használó siketekre, különösen a gyengén halló idősekre (az ő számuk, arányuk a társadalmon belül növekszik). Az Uniónak és tagállamoknak meg kell osztani az innovatív tervezés példáit és együtt kell működjenek a szabványosítás területén. A sztereotípiákkal való szembeszállás a fogyatékossággal élő nők valós, inspiráló példája révén is megvalósítható, bemutatva, hogy képességeik hogyan kompenzálják fogyatékosságukat és teszik lehetővé, hogy sikeresek legyenek a szakmai és családi élet terén.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-078-1250" speaker_id="129073" name="Urmas Paet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjalikult. – ELis on üle 80 miljoni puuetega inimese, neist 60% on naised. Vananeva ühiskonna üks probleem on ka suurenev puuetega inimeste hulk kõrgemas vanuses. 45% tööealistest puuetega naistest ei ole tööturul aktiivsed. Halvenenud on ka puuetega naiste olukord, kes töötavad, võrreldes meestega – seda nii sissetuleku kui ka sotsiaalse tõrjutuse osas. Puuetega inimeste hooldajaks on 2/3 juhtudest naised; 80% puuetega inimeste hooldajatest palka ei saa; 75% neist on naised.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kõike eeltoodut arvestades tuleb võtta rohkem meetmeid selleks, et puuetega inimeste, aga eriti naiste olukord paraneks. Tehnoloogia areng annab palju võimalusi suurendada puuetega inimeste kaasatust tööturul. Kõik puuetega inimesed peavad saama kasutada oma õigusi ning olla täieväärtuslikult ühiskonda kaasatud. Puuetega naiste puhul tuleb suuremat rõhku panna tervishoiu ning seksuaal- ja reproduktiivtervisega seonduvatele õigustele ning aidata kaasa naiste suuremale iseseisvusele. Samuti tuleb murekohti teadvustada poliitilisel tasandil ning teha kõik, et kaotada barjäärid puuetega inimeste täisväärtuslikule elule ning aidata kaasa nende õiguste ja võimaluste edendamisele ühiskonnaelus.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-078-2500" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – YK:n vammaisten henkilöiden oikeuksien sopimuksen tarkoituksena on taata vammaisille henkilöille täysimääräisesti ja yhdenvertaisesti kaikki ihmisoikeudet ja perusvapaudet sekä edistää heidän ihmisarvonsa kunnioittamista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vammaisten ihmisten oikeudet eivät toteudu itsestään, vaan ne vaativat paitsi tekoja päättäjiltä, myös osallistamista ja aktiivista vuoropuhelua. Saavutettavuusdirektiivin tarkoituksena taas on, että kaikilla olisi tasavertaiset toimintamahdollisuudet yhteiskunnassa, myös digitaalisessa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meillä kaikilla on oikeus tarvitsemiimme peruspalveluihin. On tärkeää tunnistaa yksilöiden, erilaisten ihmisten, erilaiset tarpeet. Myös naisten ja miesten erilaiset tarpeet on tärkeä tunnistaa. Tasa-arvon saavuttamiseksi sen edellytysten pitää olla kunnossa. Olennaista on esimerkiksi laajentaa syrjimättömyys myös työpaikan ulkopuolelle hyväksymällä jäsenmaiden käsittelyssä jumissa oleva yhdenvertaisen kohtelun direktiivi. Euroopan sosiaalisten oikeuksien pilarissa esitetyt periaatteet sukupuolten tasa-arvosta ja naisten ja miesten yhdenvertaisista mahdollisuuksista tulee toteuttaa käytännön tasolla.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-078-5000" speaker_id="96718" name="Olga Sehnalová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písemně. – V příštím týdnu budeme slavit Mezinárodní den osob s postižením. Je velmi důležité si tyto dny připomínat – nicméně na to, že lidé s postižením mají stejná práva jako kdokoliv jiný, bychom měli myslet v průběhu celého roku. Lidé s postižením jsou pro společnost často neviditelní, obzvláště to bohužel platí pro ženy. Považuji za skutečně nepřijatelné, že žen s postižením je zaměstnán zhruba jenom poloviční počet v porovnání s muži. Nemůžeme se proto divit, že jsou nejvíce ohroženy chudobou a sociálním vyloučením. Kromě toho, že mají nižší příjmy i důchody, také častěji než muži zůstávají doma, aby se bez nároku na odměnu staraly o další rodinné příslušníky. Tuto praxi musíme změnit. Ženy s postižením musí mít možnost plně se zapojit do veřejného života a přihlásit se o svá práva. Jedním ze základních způsobů, jak toho dosáhnout, je i možnost volit a vybrat si své zástupce. Doufám proto, že příští volby do Evropského parlamentu, a nejen ty, budou plně přístupné pro všechny, včetně lidí s postižením. Ráda bych také vyzvala své kolegy, aby při své legislativní činnosti a při přípravě veškerých návrhů konzultovali organizace zastupující lidi s postižením, protože jenom tak můžeme dosáhnout toho, že na jejich práva bude skutečně brán zřetel.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Welcome">
    <intervention id="2-084-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Chers collègues, je voudrais vous indiquer que nous avons le plaisir d’accueillir aujourd’hui dans la tribune des visiteurs une délégation du Majlisi Oli, présidée par Sharif Rahimzoda. La délégation est ici à Bruxelles pour participer à la septième commission de coopération parlementaire Parlement européen-Tadjikistan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous sommes très heureux d’accueillir cette importante réunion qui renforcera notre dialogue et notre coopération. C’est un honneur de vous voir ici, au cœur de la démocratie européenne, signe de notre engagement commun à promouvoir les droits de l’homme, le pluralisme politique à travers l’état de droit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Au nom de l’ensemble du Parlement européen, Mesdames et Messieurs, je vous souhaite une réunion fructueuse et un bon séjour en Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-085-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to say to my colleagues that, in the</p>
      <p sl="en">context of today’s historic address by two Nobel Peace laureates – one to another, because the EU itself won the Peace Prize in 2012 – I want to inform you that yesterday. 28 November, was the seventh anniversary of the Brussels Declaration – a Pledge to Peace, signed here in this House in the European Parliament under the patronage of Gianni Pittella, then First Vice—President.</p>
      <p sl="en">The pledge encourages projects and actions aimed at promoting peace in its most universal meaning, based on the significance of each individual person. It’s inspired by the universal ideas of human dignity, freedom, equality and solidarity enshrined in the preamble of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union and confirmed by the Lisbon Treaty in 2009. So let’s remember, folks, that the European Union is, and always will be, a peace project.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Voting time">
    <intervention id="2-087-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour appelle l’Heure des votes.</p>
      <a text="(Pour les résultats des votes et autres détails les concernant: voir procès-verbal)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="8.1. Application of the Euro 5 step to the type-approval of two- or three- wheel vehicles and quadricycles (A8-0346/2018 - Daniel Dalton)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="8.2. Trade in certain goods which could be used for capital punishment, torture or other cruel treatment or punishment (A8-0387/2018 - Lidia Joanna Geringer de Oedenberg)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="8.3. Asylum, Migration and Integration Fund: Re-commitment of remaining amounts (A8-0370/2018 - Miriam Dalli)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-092-0000" speaker_id="124970" name="Miriam Dalli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Fil-fatt, abbażi tal-Artikolu 59, paragrafu 4, nixtieq nitlob li din il-materja tiġi rreferuta lill-Kumitat biex inkunu nistgħu nagħtu bidu għan-negozjati interistituzzjonali.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem12" title="8.4. Accession of Samoa to the EU-Pacific States Interim Partnership Agreement (A8-0376/2018 - David Martin)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="8.5. Appointment of the Chair of the Supervisory Board of the European Central Bank (A8-0380/2018 - Roberto Gualtieri)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="8.6. Mobilisation of the European Globalisation Adjustment Fund: application EGF/2018/003 EL/Attica publishing (A8-0377/2018 - Eider Gardiazabal Rubial)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8.7. Temporary reintroduction of border control at internal borders (A8-0356/2018 - Tanja Fajon)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-099-0000" speaker_id="96911" name="Tanja Fajon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Madam President, I request that the matter be referred back to committee for interinstitutional negotiations, pursuant to Rule 59(4).</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="8.8. Common rules for the operation of air services (A8-0150/2018 - Claudia Țapardel)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="8.9. Objection pursuant to Rule 106: Sodium dichromate (B8-0548/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="8.10. The Cum Ex Scandal: financial crime and the loopholes in the current legal framework (B8-0518/2018, B8-0519/2018, B8-0520/2018, B8-0521/2018, B8-0525/2018, RC-B8-0551/2018, B8-0551/2018, B8-0552/2018)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="8.11. Role of the German Youth Welfare Office (Jugendamt) in cross-border family disputes (B8-0546/2018)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-106-0000" speaker_id="96677" name="Cecilia Wikström" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I have a point of order. I’d like to take my name off the resolution by the Committee on Petitions (PETI) on Jugendamt. The text that we have just voted is not the draft text that I proposed. It has been substantially changed by the vote in the committee, and therefore I’d like to take my name off the text. This is not my text and should not be recorded as such.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-107-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame, nous enregistrons effectivement le retrait de votre nom.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8.12. WTO: the way forward (A8-0379/2018 - Bernd Lange, Paul Rübig)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="8.13. 2018 Report on Serbia (A8-0331/2018 - David McAllister)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="8.14. 2018 Report on Kosovo (A8-0332/2018 - Igor Šoltes)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="8.15. 2018 Report on the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (A8-0341/2018 - Ivo Vajgl)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="8.16. 2018 Report on Albania (A8-0334/2018 - Knut Fleckenstein)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-114-0000" speaker_id="96840" name="Knut Fleckenstein" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Wir hätten gerne einen mündlichen Änderungsantrag. Das heißt: Ziffer 21a:</p>
      <p sl="en">‘Notes with concern that women living in rural and remote areas and Roma and Egyptian women continue to have limited access to primary health care and sexual and reproductive health services and are often unaware about the availability of such services, calls on the Albanian authorities to ensure better information about such services and ensure that they are accessible, affordable and of quality’.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem25" title="8.17. 2018 Report on Montenegro (A8-0339/2018 - Charles Tannock)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="8.18. Defence of academic freedom in the EU's external action (A8-0403/2018 - Wajid Khan)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem27" title="8.19. The situation of women with disabilities (B8-0547/2018)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="2-120-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ceci clôt l’heure des votes.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem28" title="9. Explanations of vote"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="9.1. The Cum Ex Scandal: financial crime and the loopholes in the current legal framework (B8-0518/2018, B8-0519/2018, B8-0520/2018, B8-0521/2018, B8-0525/2018, RC-B8-0551/2018, B8-0551/2018, B8-0552/2018)">
    <intervention id="2-126-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Niezwykle istotne przy tej rezolucji jest wskazanie państwa, w którym doszło do tak poważnych problemów z nadużyciem kwestii finansowych: to są Niemcy. Jest to bardzo smutny obraz, że tak ważne państwo w Unii Europejskiej dopuściło lukami prawnymi do tak poważnej afery.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przypomnę, że niemieckie prawo pozwoliło na to, aby fiskus stracił 55 miliardów euro w 11 państwach członkowskich Unii Europejskiej. Wszystko to dzięki nieuczciwym bankierom, prawnikom, maklerom giełdowym. To kwota, która z pewnością pokryłaby większość potrzeb niemieckiej Bundeswehry. Zwrócę uwagę na istotność tej rezolucji w dwóch elementach, po pierwsze w tym zaniepokojeniu dotyczącym możliwości doprowadzenia do takiej luki i drugie: wezwania, które zostało sformułowane przez, mojego kolegę, Dariusza Rosatiego, za co chciałem bardzo serdecznie podziękować i podkreślić znaczenie tego wezwania.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-127-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, scandalul Cum-Ex a demonstrat încă o dată faptul că acolo unde autoritățile închid ochii, jurnaliștii de investigație aduc adevărul la suprafață. Ei au descoperit cum au fost furate 55 miliarde de euro de la oamenii cinstiți care își plătesc taxele. A durat zece ani până când Germania a modificat legislația și a interzis returnarea frauduloasă a taxelor pe dividende. Cu această problemă se confruntă și Franța și Danemarca și Olanda și multe alte țări. Autoritățile se împiedică însă de proceduri greoaie, de colaborare nefuncțională și, practic, rezultatul este că cei care ne fură, infractorii, rămân nepedepsiți. Cum-Ex este cea mai mare escrocherie din istoria Europei și ne demonstrează că este nevoie de un răspuns european, ferm, rapid, acum, ieri, pentru a opri acest furt din banii publici.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-128-0000" speaker_id="132366" name="§Pirkko Ruohonen-Lerner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, EU:n jäsenvaltiot ovat menettäneet cum ex -osinkokikkailujen takia ainakin 55 miljardia euroa. Tämäkin veroskandaali tuli päivänvaloon tutkivien toimittajien työn ansiosta. Jälleen kerran viranomaiset ovat istuneet tiedon päällä, eikä tieto ole kulkenut toivotulla tavalla jäsenvaltioiden välillä.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cum ex -skandaali antaa myös hyvän esimerkin pyöröovi-ilmiön ongelmallisuudesta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Frankfurtin veroviraston entinen johtaja, verolakimies Hanno Berger, palkattiin pankkimaailman puolelle monimutkaisia osinkokikkailumalleja kehittämään. Bergerin näkemyksen mukaan aggressiivinenkin osinkojen pesu on ollut laillista. On vaikea käsittää, miten esimerkiksi järjestelyt, joissa useat henkilöt hakevat samaa veronpalautusta, vaikka veroa ei ole maksettu edes yhteen kertaan, ovat voineet joissain maissa olla laillisia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Skandaali osoittaa, että paljon on vielä tehtävää veronkierron ja aggressiivisen verosuunnittelun vastaisen työn saralla. Tämän johdosta oli helppo äänestää päätöslauselman puolesta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-129-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Cum-Ex tax fraud scheme, as has been mentioned, has cost EU countries a reported 55 billion: a huge sum of money. Through complex share deals with no economic purpose other than to receive tax reimbursements from the state and no actual tax being paid, European citizens have, to put it bluntly, been robbed. The EU has made significant progress in tackling money laundering and tax fraud. However, the Cum-Ex scandal has shown that there is still a gap in effective implementation, enforcement and administrative cooperation between Member States. This scandal has, naturally, caused outrage across Europe. Urgent coordinated action at EU level is needed. This kind of large-scale tax fraud needs to be clamped down on, and we must assess the strength of the laws we have in place to this end.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-130-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, you might say that once the scandal was unveiled, the system worked. Investigative journalists did their job, legislation was changed. I’m struggling to understand why the rest of us are now piling in to opine on what is essentially a German domestic matter. Germany is not a failed state; on the contrary, it’s a country whose rule of law is beyond question and whose authorities operate according to impartial rules. A little bit of me wonders whether this isn’t part of this Chamber’s constant obsession with trying to have a common fiscal policy, which would really be about reducing competition rather than about cracking down on avoidance.</p>
      <p sl="en">But I have to say – perhaps I’m the only person in the House who feels this – isn’t it slightly odd to hear all of these outraged squeals about tax avoidance from Members of the European Parliament, who are exempt from paying national income tax?</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem30" title="9.2. Role of the German Youth Welfare Office (Jugendamt) in cross-border family disputes (B8-0546/2018)">
    <intervention id="2-143-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, ψήφισα υπέρ της έκθεσης, διότι η γερμανική υπηρεσία κοινωνικής μέριμνας παιδιών και νέων, η περίφημη «Jugendamt», έχει πραγματικά ξεπεράσει τα όρια με τη δράση της αυτά τα χρόνια. Είναι άπειρες οι καταγγελίες που έχουν γίνει στην Επιτροπή Αναφορών. Οι γονείς διαμαρτύρονται, και κυρίως αυτοί που είναι εγκατεστημένοι στη Γερμανία και δεν είναι Γερμανοί πολίτες, αλλά είναι Έλληνες, Γάλλοι, Κροάτες. Έχουμε λάβει επανειλημμένα πάρα πολλές καταγγελίες και από Πολωνούς. Η Jugendamt ακολουθεί την εξής λογική: εάν ο ένας εκ των γονέων είναι Γερμανός, πάντοτε τον υποστηρίζει· πάντοτε υποστηρίζει τους Γερμανούς. Και αυτό είναι πλέον μια διοικητική πρακτική που εφαρμόζεται χρόνια ολόκληρα. Παρεμβαίνει η Jugendamt στη λειτουργία του οικογενειακού δικαίου με διακριτικό τρόπο εις βάρος όσων δεν είναι Γερμανοί.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-144-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Działalność niemieckich Jugendamtów od lat budziła sprzeciw i bardzo często bezskutecznie musieliśmy rozmawiać o tym, żeby szanowały one prawa każdego rodzica, szczególnie w przypadkach rozbitych rodzin. Dobrze, że temat ten – choć późno – został w końcu podjęty przez Parlament Europejski.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zawsze musimy pamiętać, że prawa człowieka najpierw dotyczą wiary, rodziny, wychowania, godności ludzkiej, tożsamości narodowej. Prawa walczących o władzę polityków są dopiero pochodną. I dobrze, że dzisiaj wyraźnie o tym w tej rezolucji mówimy. Mam nadzieję, że jej efektem będzie większa otwartość na krytykę liberalnego państwa, świadomość tego, że inżynieria społeczna nie może niszczyć najbardziej elementarnych praw ludzkich i że ludzie, po prostu ludzie będą dzięki temu bezpieczniejsi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-145-0000" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Głosowałam za sprawozdaniem, które zwraca uwagę na dyskryminację rodziców przez niemiecki Jugendamt, który powołany do dbania o dobro dzieci w rzeczywistości działa przeciwko nim, odbierając dzieci rodzicom, szczególnie obcokrajowcom. Dyskryminacja rodziców, którzy nie są narodowości niemieckiej, odbieranie dzieci z błahych powodów, dotyczy także Holandii i innych krajów, w których dochodzi do łamania artykułu 24 Karty praw podstawowych, gdzie napisano, że każde dziecko ma prawo do utrzymania stałego osobistego związku i bezpośredniego kontaktu z obojgiem rodziców, jeśli nie jest to sprzeczne z jego interesami.</p>
      <p sl="en">W petycjach wpływających do Komisji są liczne dowody na łamanie praw dziecka, tożsamości, wolności, bezpieczeństwa osobistego i na zakaz porozumiewania się w języku ojczystym, następczą germanizację, co prowadzi do rozbicia rodziny i jest powodem wielkiej traumy dzieci, choroby sierocej, a nawet może skutkować śmiercią dzieci odłączonych od matek. Jugendamt otrzymujący ogromne zasiłki na dzieci, w wysokości kilku tysięcy euro, wkracza praktycznie w każdą sferę życia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-146-0000" speaker_id="135540" name="Czesław Hoc" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Zagłosowałem za rezolucją w sprawie Jugendamtu, gdyż temat ten wywołuje wiele kontrowersji, sprzeciwu i emocji, o czym świadczy ogromna liczba petycji wpływających do Parlamentu Europejskiego. Na tę kwestię należy spojrzeć przede wszystkim z perspektywy autentycznych dramatów ludzkich, szczególnie dramatów dzieci, a nie z uwagi na tzw. poprawność polityczną.</p>
      <p sl="en">Z informacji przekazywanych przez Polskie Stowarzyszenie Rodziców Przeciw Dyskryminacji Dzieci w Niemczech wynika, że tylko w 2016 roku Jugendamt odebrał rodzinom 77 tysięcy dzieci, z czego co najmniej 20 tysięcy to polskie dzieci. Rodzice często latami nie mają kontaktu ze swoimi dziećmi, a w czasie nadzorowanych wizyt nie mogą porozumiewać się z nimi w języku ojczystym.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pamiętajmy, że kilka lat temu Komisja Petycji Parlamentu Europejskiego także przyjęła krytyczne sprawozdanie dotyczące Jugendamtów, jednak nie było żadnej pozytywnej reakcji, refleksji nad poprawą czy empatii ze strony Jugendamtów. Zatem najwyższy czas, by niemieckie Urzędy ds. Dzieci i Młodzieży zaczęły działać tylko i jedynie w imię dobra dziecka i wzmacniania potencjału rodziny biologicznej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-147-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, dar ndóigh tá obair an-mhaith á déanamh ag Coiste PETI, agus thug mé féin cúpla agóid ós a chomhair agus thug siad moladh an-mhaith faoi na hagóidí sin. Ach sa chás seo, cé go nglacaim go hiomlán gur cheart do thuismitheoirí go háirithe a bheith in ann cumarsáid a dhéanamh lena mic agus lena gclann ina dteanga dhúchais féin, ag an am céanna vótáil mise agus mo ghrúpa i gcoinne na tuarascála, mar dáiríre baineann sé seo le tír amháin agus tá sé de dhualgas ar an tír sin é a réiteach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Freisin, fuair Coiste PETI agóidí ó thrí thír eile, dá bhrí sin, ba chóir dúinn féachaint orthu go léir le chéile gan díriú ar thír amháin. Fós féin, aontaím go hiomlán leis an bprionsabal atá anseo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-148-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this is an area where we have to tread very sensitively. We’re talking about the most intimate and important matters: relations between parents and children. I’ve come across a number of heart-breaking cases both on the Petitions Committee and indeed as constituency cases in the UK, and yet I have to come down on the same side as my EPP friend Sean Kelly. This is fundamentally – precisely because of its sensitive nature – the sort of issue that should be determined by each country through its national democratic mechanisms and procedures. For the second time in a row I find myself rising in defence of German sovereignty. That’s not to say that there isn’t a problem. But the people to sort that problem out are those most directly involved, namely the authorities of the Member State in question.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem31" title="9.3. WTO: the way forward (A8-0379/2018 - Bernd Lange, Paul Rübig)">
    <intervention id="2-161-0000" speaker_id="124953" name="Jude Kirton-Darling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the multilateral rules—based system is under threat as never before. It is our collective responsibility to uphold it in these trying times, especially under the attack of the current US President. In a world of raw power politics, neither the EU nor any of its Member States, individually, stands a chance of promoting a progressive future.</p>
      <p sl="en">The keystone of the global order is the WTO. It is to date the most advanced of all the multilateral institutions. Its dispute settlement mechanism is one of the very few instruments at international level with the power to resolve conflicts peacefully. In the past, we know as a continent that economic conflicts often lead to military conflicts. But the WTO is far from perfect. It’s high time we broadened its scope to make it a real instrument for development, workers and the environment.</p>
      <p sl="en">So to save the WTO we must make it more efficient and accountable, and that’s why I supported the report today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-162-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Niezwykle ważne jest źródło wczorajszej debaty, jak i również samego sprawozdania. Przypomnę – to porażka, to jednak porażka, która zaczęła się w 2008 roku, czyli w czasie kiedy przyjęto pierwszą rezolucję popierającą konieczność dokonania przeglądu WTO. Dlaczego? Bo utknęły w martwym punkcie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dla mnie bardzo istotne jest, że od tego 2008 roku do 2018 nie tyle nic nie zrobiono, ile nie zrobiono zbyt wiele. Przypomnę, że po ostatniej konferencji ministerialnej WTO w Buenos Aires w grudniu dokładnie ubiegłego roku okazało się, że funkcja negocjacyjna organizacji została kompletnie sparaliżowana. Stało się to jeszcze w związku z tym pilniejszym zadaniem i stąd nasza debata. Jeszcze raz podkreślam, że nie można powiedzieć, że w ostatnim okresie 10 lat zrobiono niewiele albo nic. Zrobiono sporo, ale jest to kompletnie niewystarczające dla sprawnego funkcjonowania tej instytucji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-163-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, commercial property values plunging by almost half, house prices down 30%, sterling down by 25%, living standards hit, GDP down 8% on what was forecast – just some of this week’s forecasts on the hits the UK economy would take in the event of a no—deal Brexit.</p>
      <p sl="en">We heard earlier in this House some advocating a no—deal Brexit and trade purely and only on WTO rules. Those who advocate that position never seem to be able to answer the most obvious question: that if WTO rules are so perfect, why do countries spend so much time and energy to secure FTAs over and above WTO arrangements? Those advocating a hard deal / no—deal Brexit today must answer the question, why do they want to see people across the UK made poorer? Talk of a no—deal Brexit must be dismissed today for what it is, which is dangerous, preposterous nonsense.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-164-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I welcome this report into how we make the WTO more relevant. WTO rules are, for the first time in my memory, being talked about in everyday conversation in Britain. The hard—line Brexiteers tell us a no—deal Brexit is simply about adopting WTO rules. But what would that mean in practice for British businesses that export to Europe? An end to zero tariffs, a big change from today. It would result in a 12% tariff to export the fish that we capture around Suffolk shores and in Luton van parts will be taxed at 10% every time they cross the border between the UK and the EU and a 21% tariff to sell the tomatoes grown in Essex into Europe. Plus, unlike today, there will be quotas limiting the amount that we could sell into the EU and that’s before we even start to think about renegotiating and starting the 124 new trade agreements currently handled through the EU with the rest of the world.</p>
      <p sl="en">President, it seems to me that our proud exporting nation would be decimated.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-165-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the WTO remains an example of a rules—based multilateral institution that brings a certain degree of order into the house of post—modern states. It is a precious platform for the EU to promote the values of multilateralism. However, it is becoming even more difficult considering the free—riding behaviour of some states, like the USA.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am glad to see that the report calls for the eradication of poverty and removing barriers to women’s participation in trade. I believe that our task is to make commerce as inclusive as possible. I also welcome the fact that the report calls for more transparency in international trade as a way to increase stability.</p>
      <p sl="en">My special attention goes to the provisions on developing countries. I believe that both these and the EU, in compliance with WTO principles, should avoid a situation of donor—charity—receiver. To allow our partners to grow we need to treat them as equals and demand the same level of trade compliance from developing countries as from our developed countries.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-166-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I welcome the approval drafted by Mr Lange and Mr Rübig regarding the modernisation of the World Trade Organization and the way in which it operates. I welcome this report, as I believe this change is essential in order to make the WTO more relevant and adaptive to a changing, more globalised world, while strengthening the effectiveness of the organisation itself. I believe this legislation will help to overcome the difficulties and the failure of the Ministerial Conference held in Buenos Aires last December and deliver on some of the issues of the DDA. This legislation, if passed, will address the current gaps in the rule book, which create an uneven playing field in regards to subsidies and state—owned enterprises as well as regulatory barriers to services and investments. This legislation also looks at creating the necessary framework to cope with technological developments, including e-commerce, global value change and SMEs.</p>
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, is jab maith é, comhghairdeas le Lange agus Rübig.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-168-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, to consider the miracle – the power – of free trade, consider the story of Hong Kong. After the Second World War its GDP was a third of that of the UK. By 1997 it had drawn level; now it’s 30% higher. Based on what? What natural resources does that island have? It has to import its drinking water, its food, its electricity – it is utterly reliant on things it brings in from elsewhere. Its magic was simply to remove all obstacles to trade and not to make it contingent on what any other country did. There was a unilateral removal of tariff and non-tariff barriers that led to this extraordinary flowering of prosperity. Similar thing in Singapore: went from half of our level of wealth in the 1950s to twice what it is today. And Britain outside the customs union as a WTO member will have the opportunity to do something similar to return to what first raised us above the run of nations in the 19th century, which is to remove barriers between businesses and their customers. That’s all you need to do; the magic follows.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-169-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já chci souhlasit se svým předřečníkem, že ekonomové se skutečně shodují na tom, že pro obchod je nejdůležitější odstranění všech bariér, nicméně takhle bohužel mezinárodní politika a vztahy mezi státy nefungují.</p>
      <p sl="en">Důležitou roli skutečně plní tato organizace, která se snaží vnést pořádek do obchodních vztahů a vlastně i řešení obchodních sporů, nicméně v poslední době sledujeme jakousi paralýzu této organizace, minimálně už ve více než 10 letech a ty obchodní spory narůstají. Čína vstoupila do této organizace, nicméně neplní ideje nebo ducha této organizace.</p>
      <p sl="en">V zásadě stojíme i díky rozporuplným opatřením Trumpovy administrativy na prahu obchodní války, takže je důležité, aby se Evropa ujmula své aktivní role, proto já jsem toto usnesení podpořil, protože ono skutečně počítá se stabilitou, s transparentností v této organizaci, s pravidly pro rozvojové země anebo s pravidly pro nové technologie. Toto všechno je potřeba, Evropa musí být aktivní. Pojďme do toho.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem32" title="9.4. 2018 Report on Serbia (A8-0331/2018 - David McAllister)">
    <intervention id="2-182-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Przypomnę, że Serbia rozpoczęła oficjalne negocjacje w 2014 r. Od tego czasu mamy 35 rozdziałów, z tego otwartych 14, czyli nawet nie połowa. Zamkniętych zostało zaledwie 2. Chcę na ten fakt zwrócić uwagę ze względu na to, że w tym tempie perspektywa przyjęcia Serbii do Unii Europejskiej to 40 czy nawet 50 lat, jeżeli oczywiście to tempo zostanie utrzymane.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dla mnie niezwykle ważne jest, że samo sprawozdanie dotyczące tej problematyki jest bardzo dobre i zostało pozytywnie ocenione, natomiast postęp Serbii, jeżeli chodzi o wdrażanie tych elementów, do których sama się zobowiązała, niestety jest niesatysfakcjonujący. Podkreślę zwłaszcza, że z tych 35 rozdziałów największe uchybienia czy brak postępu odnotowano przede wszystkim w zakresie praworządności i wolności słowa. A przypomnę, że uznano te kwestie za niezwykle istotne.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-183-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, Srbsko je hrdá země s dlouhou, bohatou historií. Ta moderní historie je poměrně překotná. Od rozpadu státu, války, přes ukrývání některých válečných zločinců, já chci ocenit pokrok, byť je skutečně malý, na straně této země, který učinila, a předpokládám, že skutečně směřuje do toho demokratického společenství Evropy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je důležité ale, aby si tato země plnila ty úlohy, které si předsevzala. Je skutečností, že pro ČR a myslím, že i pro celou Evropu je podstatné, abychom skutečně dokázali balkánským zemím dát naději. Některé státy na Balkáně toho ale dokázaly daleko více, budeme o tom mluvit možná v následujícím bodě.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mírová budoucnost a spolupráce, hospodářská prosperita, pokud skutečně o ně Srbsko usiluje, myslím, že musí zabrat. Zpráva to skutečně popisuje, myslím, že věrohodně, a já jsem ji podpořil. Tím ale dávám najevo, že by i Srbsko, pokud to myslí vážně, mělo více zabrat.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem33" title="9.5. 2018 Report on Kosovo (A8-0332/2018 - Igor Šoltes)">
    <intervention id="2-202-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Kosowo otrzymuje od Unii Europejskiej bezcenne porady, jak walczyć z terroryzmem. Otóż Unia Europejska zaleca, żeby terrorystów rehabilitować, poddawać edukacji i integracji społecznej. No, naprawdę, już widzę, jak terrorystom uginają się teraz ze strachu kolana i ojciec terrorysta mówi synowi, uważaj, bo jak się złapią, to zostaniesz poddany w Unii Europejskiej takiej edukacji, rehabilitacji i integracji, że naprawdę pożałujesz.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ludzie drodzy, terroryzm zwalcza się przez przywrócenie kary śmierci. To co wy mówicie, ta edukacja, rehabilitacja i integracja, to jest nagroda a nie kara. Na edukację trzeba sobie zapracować, na integrację sobie trzeba zasłużyć, a wy chcecie dawać to ludziom za darmo w imię walki z terroryzmem za to, że byli terrorystami. To broń Boże Kosowo przed takimi doradcami jak Unia Europejska.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem34" title="9.6. 2018 Report on the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (A8-0341/2018 - Ivo Vajgl)">
    <intervention id="2-220-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem podpořila zprávu o Makedonii, protože udělala značný pokrok směrem k možnému vstupu do EU. Mezi kandidátskými státy patří k nejpokročilejším, i když přetrvávají problémy s demokratickým charakterem politiky, s dodržováním zásad právního státu, včetně problémů korupce a začleňování menšin. Proto také dostává značný příspěvek od EU, aby mohla provádět reformy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Velmi pozitivní je skutečnost, že se podařilo nalézt dohodu mezi Makedonií a Řeckem o názvu země, kterou již schválil makedonský parlament. V této zprávě je také zmínka o tom, že bývalý premiér Gruevski uprchl z Makedonie do Maďarska, kde žádá o azyl. Já předpokládám, že bude bývalý premiér vydán Makedonii, kde by měl nastoupit jako pravomocně odsouzený ke svému trestu, že tedy bude vydán.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-221-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία πρόεδρε, τα Σκόπια συνεχίζουν να καπηλεύονται το όνομα της Μακεδονίας μας και την ιστορία μας. Ταυτόχρονα, ακόμη και με το νέο Σύνταγμα που υιοθέτησαν, συνεχίζουν την αλυτρωτική τους πολιτική, καθώς στο άρθρο 36 συνεχίζουν να αναφέρονται σε δήθεν «Μακεδονία» και σε δήθεν «μακεδονικό λαό». Ταυτόχρονα, στο προοίμιο του Συντάγματος, αναφέρονται στην απόφαση της ASNOM, του 1944, όπου αναφέρεται ρητά ότι υπάρχει το δικαίωμα αυτοδιάθεσης του δήθεν «μακεδονικού έθνους» και αυτοδιάθεσης του δήθεν «μακεδονικού λαού». Επομένως, παραβιάζεται από την πλευρά των Σκοπιανών ακόμη και αυτή η κατάπτυστη συμφωνία των Πρεσπών, και άρα η συμφωνία των Πρεσπών είναι νεκρή και δεν δικαιούται καν η ελληνική κυβέρνηση να την καταθέσει στο ελληνικό κοινοβούλιο. Είμαι, λοιπόν, αντίθετος με οποιαδήποτε μελλοντική ένταξη των Σκοπίων στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και, φυσικά, καταψήφισα τη συγκεκριμένη έκθεση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-222-0000" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław Piotrowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! W przegłosowanym sprawozdaniu Parlament pochwala znaczne wysiłki Macedonii i Grecji, dzięki którym znaleziono przyjęte za obopólną aprobatą rozwiązanie kwestii nazwy kraju. Macedonia boryka się jednak z podobnymi problemami jak inne kraje tego regionu. W ustępie 32. wzywamy władze do podjęcia działań w celu rozbijania siatek przestępczych zaangażowanych w handel ludźmi, bronią i środkami odurzającymi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podobnie jak w przypadku Albanii i Czarnogóry w sprawozdaniu dotyczącym Macedonii wykazuje się nadmierną troskliwość wobec osób LGBTI. W ustępie 43. Parlament domaga się karania za przemoc na tle homofobicznym i transfobicznym, cieszy się natomiast z ustanowienia międzypartyjnego koła parlamentarnego do spraw praw społeczności LGBTI. Zapisy te uważam za zbędne, dlatego głosowałem przeciwko temu sprawozdaniu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-223-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, as a member of the Joint Parliamentary Committee of this House and that of the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, I am pleased to support this report. There’s clearly much work yet to be done before Macedonia can accede to this Union, but it should be clear to anyone whose eyes are open that significant progress has been made.</p>
      <p sl="en">Settling disputes like the name dispute between Macedonia and Greece requires politicians of courage, who are prepared to tell the truth to the people that they seek to lead. The simple truth here is that the Prespa Agreement might not be perfect but nobody – not the nationalists in Macedonia nor the nationalists in this place – have suggested any alternative to the Prespa Agreement other than stagnation and stalemate. So let’s praise the courage of those members of the Sobranie who supported the constitutional changes and look forward to progress on media freedom, and political and civil administration.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-224-0000" speaker_id="124704" name="Stanislav Polčák" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, Makedonie má status kandidátské země od roku 2005 a od té doby skutečně učinila velmi významný pokrok. Ostatně změna ústavy, ke které má dojít na základě dohody z Prespy, na základě toho hlasování z 19. října, je opravdu obrovský kus práce, který byl odveden. Nacionalisté žádné jiné řešení nenabízí. Já chci toto úsilí ocenit. Chci podpořit ty proudy, které směřují k usmíření mezi těmi dvěma státy, a myslím si, že pokud někdo kvůli tomu mění ústavu, tak myslím, že to úsilí tímto demonstruje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je ale třeba také učinit mnoho z toho, co tíží minulost této země, např. ve zprávě se zmiňuje otázka zvláštního státního zástupce, který má došetřit trestné činy z minulosti. Tím myslím kriminální závažné delikty, to je myslím důležitý úkol, který si bude muset Makedonie splnit, ale ta cesta je myslím, že dobrá.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem35" title="9.7. 2018 Report on Albania (A8-0334/2018 - Knut Fleckenstein)">
    <intervention id="2-240-0000" speaker_id="125069" name="Νότης Μαριάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, έχω δηλώσει επανειλημμένα, εδώ στο Σώμα, ότι είμαι αντίθετος με οποιαδήποτε μελλοντική ένταξη της Αλβανίας στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση. Πολύ δε περισσότερο καθώς συνεχίζεται η καταπίεση της ελληνικής εθνικής μειονότητας της Βορείου Ηπείρου. Είχαμε πρόσφατα, πριν από έναν μήνα, τη δολοφονία του Κωνσταντίνου Κατσίφα από την αλβανική αστυνομία. Συνεχίζει, λοιπόν, η Αλβανία να αρπάζει τις περιουσίες των Ελλήνων, να γκρεμίζει τις εκκλησίες, να αλλοιώνει τον πληθυσμό στη Βόρειο Ήπειρο και, αυτή τη στιγμή, προβαίνει και σε νέα αντίποινα. Κόβει το ρεύμα και εκφοβίζει όλους τους Έλληνες που βρίσκονται στη Βόρειο Ήπειρο, και όλα αυτά για να περάσει το μήνυμα ότι δήθεν θα συνεχίσει αυτή την πολιτική της· την πολιτική της καταπίεσης. Της λέμε, λοιπόν, ότι αυτά δεν περνάνε και ότι συνεχώς θα την καταγγέλλουμε -εδώ, στο Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο- μέχρις ότου αναγνωρίσει και εφαρμόσει τα δικαιώματα της ελληνικής εθνικής μειονότητας της Βορείου Ηπείρου. Γι’ αυτό και καταψήφισα τη συγκεκριμένη έκθεση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-241-0000" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław Piotrowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! W przegłosowanym sprawozdaniu Komisja zaleca otwarcie negocjacji akcesyjnych z Albanią. Mają one, jak podkreślono w dokumencie, umożliwić ściślejszą kontrolę ze strony Unii i przeprowadzenie reform.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podobnie jak w innych krajach kandydujących zwracamy uwagę na powtarzającą się niebezpieczną tendencję handlu ludźmi. Mowa jest o tym w punkcie 18, gdzie nasz Parlament wzywa władze albańskie do podjęcia zdecydowanych działań w celu rozbijania siatek przestępczych zaangażowanych w handel ludźmi, a także bronią palną i środkami odurzającymi. Niepotrzebnie jednak w punkcie 23 w specyficzny sposób promuje się ideologię gender, umieszczając zapisy dotyczące LGBTI. Dlatego też głosowałem przeciwko temu sprawozdaniu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-242-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Albania has made significant progress, and this needs to be acknowledged and rewarded. That’s why I very much like the idea of supporting the accession negotiations with Albania next year. While being aware of the progress that has been made, especially in the juridical reform, we have as well to point out the things that still remain to be done. The electoral reforms remain a concern. The issues of corruption, organised crime and good neighbourhood relations – the reforms in these areas are painful, but they have to be done; they are essential. The rule of law, respect for human rights and the fight against corruption have to be improved. With this goal, we should all ensure the opening of the negotiations and avoiding further backsliding.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-243-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Chciałem odnieść się do skandalicznej sytuacji polegającej na tym, że na posiedzeniu plenarnym wnosi się ustną poprawkę niebędącą jedynie ortograficznym sprostowaniem, lecz zaśmiecaniem unijnych dokumentów jakimiś seksistowskimi bajdułami o kobietach na wsi, którym trzeba coś – oczywiście na koszt pozostałych podatników – zapewniać. Taką formułę należy ocenić krytycznie, podobnie jak skandaliczną treść samej poprawki. Ponadto z przykrością stwierdzam, że nie znalazło się czterdziestu sprawiedliwych posłów, którzy sprzeciwiliby się dołożeniu tej poprawki w czasie sesji. Tylko kilku posłów powstało, żeby się temu sprzeciwić. Naprawdę jest to smutne i żałosne, że boicie się wystąpić w tak oczywistej sprawie.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem36" title="9.8. 2018 Report on Montenegro (A8-0339/2018 - Charles Tannock)">
    <intervention id="2-254-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, chtěla bych vysvětlit, proč jsem podpořila zprávu o Černé Hoře, která usiluje o přistoupení do EU. Považuji ji za zemi, která sdílí naše evropské kořeny a usiluje tedy o vstup do EU, což prokazuje svojí snahou o splnění kodaňských kritérií.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ve zprávě se uvádí, že Černá Hora udělala pokrok ve vyjednávání s EU, především ve své domácí politice. Došlo ke zlepšení stavu nezávislosti soudů, elektronické správy. Dalším pozitivním ukazatelem byly i nedávné prezidentské volby v dubnu tohoto roku, kdy nebyly zjištěny žádné závažné přestupky v otázce svobodného rozhodování občanů. Jisté znepokojení máme o svobodu médií a zde budeme samozřejmě i jako EP sledovat další vývoj.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-255-0000" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław Piotrowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Głosowałem przeciwko tego temu sprawozdaniu. Wczoraj wieczorem zabierałem głos na ten temat. Chcę zwrócić uwagę na pewne iunctim łączące sprawozdania w sprawie Macedonii i Albanii. Tutaj również, w sprawozdaniu w sprawie Czarnogóry w punkcie 22 Parlament ubolewa nad brakiem postępu w zwalczaniu handlu ludźmi. To się powtarza w każdym sprawozdaniu. Tam handluje się ludźmi, a także tutaj dodatkowo wskazuje się, że zmusza się dzieci do żebractwa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mówiłem wczoraj, że jest to proceder haniebny i żaden kraj aspirujący do członkostwa w Unii Europejskiej nie powinien tego tolerować, ale jest druga też tendencja, gdzie Parlament nasz zbytnio troszczy się o tak zwane mniejszości. W punkcie 34 piszemy, że niepokoimy się trudnościami z akceptacją różnorodności seksualnej w czarnogórskim społeczeństwie. Uważam te zapisy za zbędne. Dlatego, powtarzam, głosowałem przeciwko temu sprawozdaniu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-256-0000" speaker_id="134243" name="Jasenko Selimovic" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I thank Mr Tannock for his excellent and detailed report. Montenegro remains a frontrunner in the Western Balkans, with Chapter 31 open, and we would like the process to continue on that path.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, certain things have to be pointed out, like the fact that media freedom remains an issue in that country. The Olivera Lakić case is one that should never happen in a country wishing to join the EU. Freedom of expression needs to be guaranteed and attacks on journalists need to be condemned.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would also like to urge Montenegrin officials to launch public awareness—raising campaigns to fight discrimination and violence against LGBT and Roma people and to safeguard investigations and prosecutions in cases of crimes committed against them.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem37" title="9.9. Defence of academic freedom in the EU's external action (A8-0403/2018 - Wajid Khan)">
    <intervention id="2-266-0000" speaker_id="185637" name="Alex Mayer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I welcome this debate and would make three points. Firstly, postgraduate research in the field is vital and risk can never be entirely eliminated, but it is vital that the safety of European students studying abroad remains paramount. Second, we must be vigilant when European universities host foreign branch campuses in countries where governments restrict freedom of speech. Thirdly, it is vital that we get our own house in order.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Hungary, gender studies courses are being cancelled after a government ban, and the attacks on the CEU continue. Last week I met Professor Betegh, a visiting professor from the CEU, who told me that the university is a hub for state universities and attracts high calibre speakers who Hungarian students would not otherwise come into contact with, and that its move to Vienna would be a huge blow. Academic freedom is not an abstract notion. The right to question all and search for truth is fundamental.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-267-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, academic education is a starting point of political awareness. If we want our efforts in promoting democracy to be successful, we need to ensure that the population of the countries we engage with is able to make an informed political choice. The more freedom we give to academia, the more democratic a society we achieve. A democratic society is always a more peaceful and balanced society.</p>
      <p sl="en">I particularly appreciate the plenary amendments tabled by S&amp;D group that require academic freedom to become a part of the Copenhagen criteria. If a country restricts free academic research we must take it as the first symptom of illiberalism and encourage our partners to refrain from political manipulation of universities and schools. A failure in education brings about a failure in all spheres of public life, and in addition it results in a huge loss in economic opportunities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, I support this report and hope that its provisions are fully implemented.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-268-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I want to congratulate my colleague, Wajid Khan, for bringing forward this important report. I think my generation grew up perhaps taking for granted, and benefiting immensely, from freedoms secured by previous generations – democracy, the rule of law, media freedom and indeed academic freedom as well.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this era today, where all those things are being challenged, in this era of populism, of fake news and of other challenges as well, those of us who believe in those freedoms must stand up and defend them.</p>
      <p sl="en">Academic freedom is crucial and set against those things are populism and fake news, fake facts – almost a poisoning in places of our public discourse. We must protect that space of free, unfettered scholarship and academic freedom. So I welcome this report. I was pleased to vote for it and I hope we can enact the proposals that it has brought forward.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-269-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am delighted to support the work of my colleague, Wajid Khan, in this report which is regrettably necessary. Those of us who have taught or researched understand that academic freedom is something that must be cherished. The notion that the state should in any way dictate what is studied in academic institutions is entirely unacceptable, and I believe incompatible with European values.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should be prepared to defend academic freedom fiercely. If a Member State or third country are acting to contain this essential freedom of inquiry then they should not be able to benefit from Union funding or collaborative programmes under Horizon Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we should also be prepared to defend academic freedom from the pressures of the market. It is rumoured that three institutions in my region are under threat for financial reasons. We need to understand that many of the greatest gains for humanity have been made from research with no obvious economic output at the time it was undertaken. We need to defend that pure research ability.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem38" title="9.10. The situation of women with disabilities (B8-0547/2018)">
    <intervention id="2-278-0000" speaker_id="124987" name="Liadh Ní Riada" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, tuigimid ar fad, is dócha, mar mhná go bhfuil go leor constaicí agus dúshlán ann ach, samhlaigh a bheith mar bhean atá faoi mhíchumas agus feictear ansin agus tuigtear na dúshláin ollmhóra atá acusan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Léiríonn an tuarascáil seo é sin go maith. Feicimid an t-idirdhealú abair, 18.8% de mhná faoi mhíchumas fostaithe san Aontas Eorpach i gcomparáid le 35% de na fir. Níor chóir dúinn glacadh leis seo, níl sé sásúil agus mar sin, is dóigh liom gur chóir dúinn fáilte a chur roimh na huirlisí atá sa tuarascáil seo. Ach, is faoi na Ballstáit iad sin a chur i bhfeidhm.</p>
      <p sl="en">Agus caithfimid tosú ag cur tacaíocht faoi leith ann, ionas go mbeidh deiseanna comhionannais ann i dtaobh oideachais, i dtaobh cúrsaí sláinte, i dtaobh spóirt agus a chinntiú go mbeidh mná faoi mhíchumas in ann páirt iomlán a ghlacadh inár saol ó thaobh cúrsaí toghcháin, ó thaobh vótála agus ní dóigh liom go bhfuil na tacaíochtaí sin ann faoi láthair.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mar sin, cuirim fáilte mhór roimhe seo, ach arís, tá sé chomh tábhachtach go gcuirfeadh na Ballstáit na huirlisí seo i bhfeidhm agus go ndéanfaidís é láithreach.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-279-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, přestože považuji rovný přístup zdravotně postižených žen za velmi důležitý a souhlasím s tím, že by v této oblasti měly členské státy vyvíjet větší úsilí, nemohla jsem podpořit návrh zprávy kvůli zásadním výhradám, které mám k některým doporučením.</p>
      <p sl="en">Týká se to především těch doporučení, která přesahují kompetenci EU a zasahují do rozhodování členských států, zejména v oblastech etických a zdravotní péče. Usnesení totiž doporučuje značná rozšíření v oblasti reprodukčního zdraví, což je jen jiný název pro potraty. Já se domnívám, že bychom měli chránit život, a to život všech, jak žen, tak nenarozených dětí. Kriticky se také stavím k výzvě k zajištění specifických podmínek ve zdravotnictví pro transgender osoby. Domnívám se, že to je plně v kompetenci členských států stejně jako rozhodování o změně pohlaví.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-280-0000" speaker_id="28334" name="Urszula Krupa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Głosowałam za rezolucją dotyczącą kobiet niepełnosprawnych, która szeroko omawia sytuację kobiet i dziewcząt ocenianych na 46 milionów, co stanowi 60 % całkowitej populacji osób z niepełnosprawnością. Pomimo licznych międzynarodowych konwencji i przepisów prawa europejskiego, europejskich strategii w sprawie niepełnosprawności osoby dotknięte jakimś rodzajem niepełnosprawności nadal mają problemy z korzystaniem z praw obywatelskich, socjalnych, a szczególnie opieki zdrowotnej czy też praw wyborczych. Kwestie te z różnych przyczyn ciągle wymagają rozwiązania.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poruszone w dokumencie tematy orientacji seksualnej, przynależności płciowej, klasy czy nawet religii wydają się nie do zaakceptowania i mają drugorzędne znaczenie, jednak w związku z rolą dokumentu głosowałam za. Warto natomiast przypomnieć, że stosunek do osób słabszych, w tym dzieci, osób starszych, chorych, niepełnosprawnych, świadczy o poziomie rozwoju osobowego poszczególnych osób, ale także o stopniu poczucia odpowiedzialności i poszanowania praw obywatela ze strony państw, narodów czy instytucji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-281-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I support this report and want to underline that the strength of a society is assessed based on its attitude towards fragile groups. Even though European countries have achieved better social standards than the majority of our international partners, the issue of female disability is far from being solved. If you look at the figures, there is good reason to be disappointed and even ashamed. We have 46 million women and girls with disabilities in the EU, but only 18% of them are employed. 34% of them have experienced physical or sexual violence by a partner.</p>
      <p sl="en">These women and girls not only face discrimination in the labour context, but also in education, in the social spheres of public life. As a result, their choice of profession and lifestyle is restricted. They become victims of poverty and social exclusion, and this all creates a situation where cruelty almost seems to be socially acceptable.</p>
      <p sl="en">On those grounds, I voted in favour.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-282-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca, oceňujem snahu riešiť problémy žien so zdravotným postihnutím v našej spoločnosti. Podpora a doplnenie politík členských štátov v oblasti sociálneho zabezpečenia a sociálnej ochrany patrí k úlohám únie. Ak však chceme naozaj posilniť práva žien a dievčat so zdravotným postihnutím, musíme predovšetkým chrániť ich ľudskú dôstojnosť. Žiaľ, v uznesení o nej nenájdeme jedinú zmienku. Namiesto toho propaguje neobmedzený prístup k zariadeniam a službám v oblasti sexuálnych a reprodukčných práv, ktoré zahŕňajú aj prístup k potratom. Kompetenciu v tejto oblasti pritom majú členské štáty, a nie Európska únia. To som nemohla podporiť. Ľudský život, jeho dôstojnosť, ale aj princíp subsidiarity patria k základným hodnotám Únie. Mali by ich rešpektovať aj uznesenia jej Parlamentu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="2-283-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! To jest kolejna skandaliczna, seksistowska inicjatywa Parlamentu. Nie rozumiem w ogóle, co to ma oznaczać? Jak daleko zabrnęliście w tym szaleństwie Państwo? Jakie inne prawa mają mieć niepełnosprawne kobiety niż niepełnosprawni mężczyźni? Co to w ogóle ma być? Wydajemy rezolucję na temat tylko niepełnosprawnych kobiet, czyli będą osobne podjazdy dla niepełnosprawnych kobiet, a osobne dla mężczyzn? Czy jeśli mowa tu, na przykład, o usuwaniu barier do głosowania, czy ten problem jakoś bardziej dotyczy kobiet niż mężczyzn?</p>
      <p sl="en">A już w ogóle szczytem przewrotności jest punkt 7, w którym się stwierdza, że ze względu na to, że kobiety żyją dłużej częściej są niepełnosprawne i dlatego należy je jakoś uprzywilejować. No przecież, jeśli kobiety żyją dłużej, a mężczyźni żyją krócej, to dla mężczyzn jest gorzej, to mężczyzn należałoby w tym momencie jakoś wynagradzać za ich ciężkie życie, które szybciej się kończy, a nie traktować tego jako powód do uprzywilejowania kobiet, które już z tego powodu, że żyją dłużej, w jakiś sposób są uprzywilejowane. Więc jest to absolutnie chora i przewrotna logika.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem39" title="10. Corrections to votes and voting intentions : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem40" title="11. Transfers of appropriations and budgetary decisions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem41" title="12. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem42" title="13. Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem43" title="14. Dates of forthcoming sittings : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem44" title="15. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem45" title="16. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="2-307-0000" speaker_id="28141" name="Elnök asszony" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Bejelentem az Európai Parlament ülésszakának megszakítását.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
