<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20190328.EN" lang="en" date="2019-03-28" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Emergency situation in Venezuela (motions for resolutions tabled): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Recent developments on the Dieselgate scandal (motions for resolutions tabled): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Establishing the Creative Europe programme (2021 to 2027) (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-008-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour appelle le débat sur le rapport de Silvia Costa, au nom de la commission de la culture et de l’éducation, sur la proposition de règlement du Parlement européen et du Conseil relatif à la mise en place du programme «Europe créative» (2021 à 2027) (COM(2018)0366 – C8-0237/2018 – 2018/0190(COD) (A8-0156/2019)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-009-0000" speaker_id="96917" name="Silvia Costa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io ringrazio molto i colleghi relatori ombra della commissione per la loro preziosa collaborazione e per avere arricchito la mia relazione e averla votata a larghissima maggioranza in commissione CULT.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il nuovo programma "Europa creativa" si inserisce in un contesto completamente mutato rispetto a sette anni fa, sia per la rivoluzione digitale sia per l'esigenza di rispondere a una grande crisi di identità e di appartenenza all'Europa e al suo progetto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ritengo un grande risultato di questa legislatura la nostra forte iniziativa per ottenere finalmente un quadro europeo di politiche culturali, a partire dall'Anno del patrimonio culturale, dal rafforzamento delle imprese culturali e creative, dalla strategia delle relazioni culturali internazionali e del dialogo interculturale, che oggi sono pienamente inserite nella nuova agenda per la cultura.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un quadro che vede anche il settore creativo e audiovisivo finalmente inserito in un'economia digitale, in un ecosistema digitale, in cui la direttiva sui servizi di media audiovisivi e quella approvata martedì sul copyright determineranno nuove regole e anche maggiori disponibilità finanziarie per il settore.</p>
      <p sl="en">Come relatore sono soddisfatta degli elementi di novità nel testo, a partire dal raddoppio del bilancio da 1,4 a 2,8 proposto al Parlamento e mi auguro che la nostra indicazione sia difesa dal futuro Parlamento e accolta dal Consiglio dei ministri e che quindi non si torni indietro. Abbiamo arricchito le tre sezioni del programma – cultura, media e transettoriale – di importanti novità, a partire da un nuovo obiettivo generale, accanto a quello della cooperazione e della competitività, ovvero il riconoscimento del valore intrinseco della cultura e del ruolo centrale degli artisti e dei professionisti culturali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo reintrodotto l'articolo sul valore aggiunto europeo, incoraggiando anche una narrativa delle radici comuni europee, dell'unità e della diversità e abbiamo previsto un'azione strutturata, anche con centri di eccellenza europei, per la definizione, finalmente, di indicatori qualitativi e quantitativi di impatto delle politiche culturali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono felice altresì che sia stata recepita la mia proposta, avanzata in qualità di ex relatore del precedente programma "Europa creativa", di inserire un nuovo programma di mobilità europea e internazionale per gli artisti e gli operatori culturali. Il settore dedicato alla cultura è oggi finalmente rafforzato e articolato in quattro specifici ambiti, che diventeranno linee finanziare dedicate: la musica, il patrimonio culturale, l'architettura, l'editoria e il design.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il settore media sosterrà azioni transnazionali di rafforzamento delle competenze dei curricula in ambito audiovisivo e digitale, la produzione indipendente, le coproduzioni europee, le reti europee delle sale cinematografiche e di operatori video on demand (VOD), la vendita all'estero, la promozione di nuovi modelli di produzione e il coinvolgimento del pubblico.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diamo speciale attenzione alle fiction, ai documentari, ai film per bambini e di animazione, nonché alle opere interattive fra cui i videogiochi narrativi di qualità e i contenuti multimediali. È interessante notare che il programma sosterrà la valorizzazione dei talenti artistici ma anche artigianali e, soprattutto, per la prima volta si inserisce uno specifico riferimento alla promozione del riconoscimento del ruolo delle donne nel campo culturale e artistico. Sono ancora troppo poche quelle nei consigli di amministrazione delle istituzioni culturali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo introdotto una nuova linea sull'alfabetizzazione mediatica, un'importante azione contro le fake news a sostegno della qualità del giornalismo e, accanto alle sovvenzioni di cofinanziamento per i progetti, abbiamo sviluppato importanti sinergie, sia con il nuovo programma InvestEU, mantenendo però la specificità e le condizioni dell'attuale strumento esistente di garanzia per il settore, sia con i fondi di sviluppo regionale e con il nuovo strumento finanziario dell'azione esterna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma soprattutto vogliamo che il programma sia più accessibile e coinvolga maggiormente i giovani. Faccio solo due esempi conclusivi: la nuova linea di sostegno - che ho voluto inserire e, che tutti i colleghi hanno sostenuto, e ne sono molto felice - a reti di radio e media universitari che raccontino l'Europa ai giovani, nel ricordo di Antonio Megalizzi e Bartek Orent-Niedzielski, i due giovani giornalisti di Europhonica barbaramente uccisi nell'attentato di Strasburgo lo scorso dicembre.</p>
      <p sl="en">E il secondo esempio: abbiamo previsto un oggetto di sostegno diretto, accanto all'importante European Film Academy di Berlino, alla European Union Youth Orchestra, fondata quarant'anni fa dal maestro Claudio Abbado e da Lionel Bryer.</p>
      <p sl="en">Continuiamo a sostenere l'Europa della cultura.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-010-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, good morning. It’s a pleasure for me to be here to replace Commissioner Navracsics for this important plenary debate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Promoting cultural and linguistic diversity in Europe and boosting our cultural and creative sectors to ensure they remain world class are essential elements of the European project. Creative Europe has played a major role in this, which is why we want to build on and strengthen this programme after 2020. We want more Europeans to be able to enjoy the wealth of our diverse cultures, benefiting from their undisputed power to embody our common values and promote our shared European identity. I know that the rapporteur, Ms Costa, and her shadow rapporteurs fully support these goals. My sincere thanks go to you, Ms Costa, for the high—quality work you have done on this proposal and the excellent working relations we have enjoyed with you.</p>
      <p sl="en">To live up to our ambition, the Commission’s intention is to continue linking up professionals from different European countries through cooperation projects, partnerships and networks; to keep on connecting Europe’s beautiful audiovisual works with large international audiences; and to continue investing in cross—sectoral innovation. We will do all this because we believe it is the best way to enlarge the horizons of both creators and audiences, while at the same time developing good solutions to cultural issues of common concern across borders.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we also want to support our cultural and creative sectors in adapting to new challenges and making the most of opportunities that are opening up in times of rapid change. This is why we have proposed some new features: a new international window; individual mobility for artists and cultural operators; support for specific cultural sectors, such as music books and publishing; architectural and cultural heritage; a stronger focus on Europe’s audiovisual talents, especially women; encouraging creative spaces for script writing; initiatives to enhance promotion and marketing for European books in Europe and beyond; new innovative cross—sectoral actions, encompassing new technologies such as virtual reality and artificial intelligence for content creation, distribution and promotion; and also a scheme to promote a diverse and pluralistic media environment in Europe, including through media literacy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear Members of Parliament, I am pleased that you welcome these novelties and, more generally, that you agree on the ambition, the architecture and the objectives we propose. As you know, the Commission and also the Council Presidency were keen to reach a partial first-reading agreement before the end of this legislature. This would have sent a clear signal to the European citizens about the importance we attach to this programme and to the cultural diversity and richness that makes Europe unique and defines our identities. It would also have helped us to put everything in place to be able to start implementing the new programme in time before it starts in 2021. The Commission therefore regrets that this programme is among the few where negotiations will not have started before the elections.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are very much looking forward to the future negotiations and our continued excellent cooperation. I am confident that we can find a swift agreement on the issues where our institutions hold slightly diverging views, as we all agree on the importance and the general thrust of the programme. The European Parliament and the Committee on Culture and Education (CULT) in particular have always been an ally for the Commission when it came to working together for the benefit of our cultural and creative professions and professionals in Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on Budgets">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I’m pleased to say that the Committee on Budgets recognised the Creative Europe programme as an important investment budget, acknowledged the importance of the creative industries, and substantially increased the MMF envelope over the Commission’s original proposal. I hope – and I believe – that this creates room in Creative Europe to support projects in regional languages and dialects, because they are an inherent part of Europe’s cultural diversity. Catalan or Cornish, Breton, Basque or Sámi: identities that are as important to many citizens as their legal nation-state identities. Language and dialect is central to folk traditions, and suppression is always a mistake. They belong in Creative Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">In 1982, I came to a South-East England constituency as an economic migrant from Thatcherite unemployment, but I remain proud of my Northumbrian heritage. So perhaps if you’ll indulge me in what may be my last speech in this Chamber, I will conclude with a few words of Geordie: Wen the tarkins ower, if the reivers an candymen o Brexit have hoyed us oot and the Brits are nee mair, divvint bother yersels ower much, cos wor bairns’ll put it t reets and tek us yem t’Europe afor lang. (In standard English: When the talking’s over, if the bandits and henchmen of Brexit have taken us out and the Brits are no longer there, don’t worry too much, as the next generation will put things right and bring us home to Europe before long.)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-012-0000" speaker_id="28299" name="Bogusław Sonik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy PPE. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Chciałbym podziękować pani poseł Silvii Coście za owocną współpracę przy nowej edycji programu „Kreatywna Europa”. Oczywiście najważniejszym punktem tego sprawozdania jest dwukrotne zwiększenie budżetu tego programu do 2,8 mld EUR. My dziś mówimy zdecydowane „tak” dla wsparcia europejskiego kina, europejskich twórców i artystów. Mam nadzieję, że przedstawiciele państw członkowskich podtrzymają tę decyzję budżetową w czasie prac nad kształtem przyszłego budżetu na lata 2021–2027, gdyż nasze cele są bardzo ambitne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podprogram MEDIA tak jak dotychczas będzie służył wspieraniu rozwoju, dystrybucji i promocji europejskich filmów i programów telewizyjnych. W nadchodzących latach zwiększone zostaną inwestycje w międzynarodową produkcję i dystrybucję europejskich dzieł i innowacyjnych sposobów opowiadania historii, w tym dzieł opartych na rzeczywistości wirtualnej. Stworzony zostanie internetowy katalog filmów europejskich, aby zwiększyć dostępność i widoczność europejskich dzieł.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podprogram KULTURA z kolei ma wspierać promocję europejskiego sektora kultury i sektora kreatywnego. To w ramach tego podprogramu powstaną projekty, sieci i platformy współpracy łączące utalentowanych artystów z całej Europy i ułatwiające twórcom współpracę międzynarodową. Nowym elementem tego komponentu będzie wspieranie sektora muzyki. Jest to ogromny sukces projektu pilotażowego „Muzyka dla Europy”, który zostanie włączony do tego programu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jako były dziennikarz cieszę się, że nowością części międzysektorowej jest finansowanie sektora mediów i dziennikarstwa śledczego. Warto podkreślić, że każdy komponent programu będzie miał specjalny zestaw wskaźników ilościowych i jakościowych. Będzie to służyło do zbierania odpowiednich danych statystycznych i do pomiaru i analizy wpływu polityki kulturalnej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, arts and culture are the heart and soul of Europe and Creative Europe is the key mechanism that enables artists and audiences from across Europe and beyond to engage in creative exploration of what it means to live in Europe today. The programme is one of the EU’s finest projects and promotes excellent synergies across other sectors – for example STEAM, which recognises science, technology, art, engineering and maths. I am personally proud to have pushed for this acknowledgment over the course of my mandate.</p>
      <p sl="en">The new programme ensures that the sector will reach its economic potential contributing to sustainable growth, jobs and social cohesion. It will enable Europe’s culture and media sectors to access new international opportunities, markets and audiences and that’s why it’s essential, if the tragedy of Brexit is to happen, that the UK remains part of such a project. I will be spending this weekend in the city of Hull with artists and media professionals from all across Europe who absolutely defy that Brexit will separate us. We will remain European.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014-0000" speaker_id="195454" name="Ralph Packet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, Creative Europe is eigenlijk een subsidieprogramma van de Europese Commissie ter bevordering en ondersteuning van de internationale samenwerking in de culturele en creatieve sector. Wat cultuur betreft zouden toneelhuizen en dansscholen bijvoorbeeld subsidies kunnen krijgen om samen met hun tegenhangers uit andere Europese landen een project op te zetten. Wat media betreft kunnen Vlaamse distributeurs subsidies krijgen om buitenlandse films naar Vlaanderen te halen en omgekeerd kunnen zij ook films in het buitenland verspreiden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar het kan natuurlijk niet de bedoeling zijn dat de Europese Unie zich gaat bemoeien met lokaal cultuurbeleid of met nationaal cultuurbeleid en daarom ben ik blij dat het Parlement in de tekst de klemtoon heeft gelegd op projecten met een Europese toegevoegde waarde, zodat in de eerste plaats grensoverschrijdende projecten en samenwerking over de landsgrenzen heen gesteund worden. Wat ik niet steun, is de verdubbeling van het huidige budget naar 3 miljard, dat kunnen we vandaag echt niet verantwoorden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015-0000" speaker_id="124805" name="Mircea Diaconu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului ALDE. – Doamnă președintă, deoarece doamna Silvia Costa a amănunțit subiectul, mie îmi rămâne - din fericire pentru mine, firește - o privire de ansamblu. Mai ales că suntem la final de mandat, cred că e important să ne uităm la întregii cinci ani pe care i-am parcurs - mă refer în clipa asta la Comisia pentru cultură și educație - și trebuie să mărturisesc acum, la bilanț, că senzația mea este că s-a comportat - Comisia pentru cultură și educație - ca o ființă unitară, lucrând și cu dreaptă și cu stânga în egală măsură.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dovadă este că, finalmente, ne aflăm în punctul acesta, în care acest program e ca un fel de dovadă că, în sfârșit - așa cred eu, cel puțin - cultura, patrimoniul nu mai sunt privite ca o Cenușăreasă a bugetelor, ba, dimpotrivă, cresc pe zi ce trece. Acest program e o dovadă și, firește, la asta am contribuit cu toții, toți membrii Comisiei pentru cultură și aș zice - pentru că doamna președintă a remarcat cu plăcere prezența domnului Gérard Deprez în sală, o fac și eu, este unul dintre oamenii pe care i-am simțit alături în clipe mai grele, mai ales că, fiind în Comisia pentru bugete, acest lucru contează, pentru că e imposibil să lucrăm numai în comisii, numai cu subiectele noastre, ci să privim în ansamblu, să ne facem prieteni, să lămurim pe toată lumea și în dreapta și în stânga și mă refer în clipa asta chiar la această sală, sau la politica europeană însăși.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finalmente, ca să nu lungesc vorba prea mult, aș zice că acest program, ca un fel de încununare a muncii noastre, a tuturor, conține chiar un fel de filozofie și focalizez pe un singur subiect care m-a impresionat în mod special - eu fiind actor de film - noțiunea de sală de cinema, de cinema proiectat în sală, a căpătat greutate, a fost înțeleasă pe deplin ca o funcție socială fundamentală și nu … (Președinta a retras cuvântul vorbitorului)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-016-0000" speaker_id="28240" name="Helga Trüpel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! In Vielfalt geeint – das ist nicht ohne Grund unser großer Einigungsslogan. Und wir wissen alle: Wenn wir es nicht lernen, mit Vielfalt, mit kultureller Vielfalt in Europa umzugehen, dann werden unsere Gesellschaften gewalttätiger werden. Deswegen ist gerade unser Programm für kulturelle Vielfalt, auch mit kulturellen Unterschieden, mit verschiedenen kulturellen Traditionen zu leben und unser kulturelles Erbe und die Zukunft der gemeinsamen Kulturproduktion wertzuschätzen, entscheidend wichtig für die Zukunft der Europäischen Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sehen das jetzt auch bei den Künstlern und jungen Leuten im Vereinigten Königreich: Die wollen dieses Creative-Europe-Programm behalten, weil sie alle wissen, was sie davon haben. Das ist ein Programm, das nur bei Antieuropäern umstritten ist, sonst wissen alle um den Wert und darum, dass es bei dem einzelnen Bürger und der einzelnen Bürgerin ankommt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deswegen ist es richtig, das Budget zu verdoppeln. Wir haben ein neues Programm Music Moves Europe, weil Musik wirklich auch die Seelen der Menschen erreicht und nicht nur die Köpfe. Wir tun mehr für den europäischen Film, seine Vielfalt, auch für die Filme aus kleinen europäischen Ländern und insbesondere für den interkulturellen Dialog.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhora Presidente, valorizamos o aumento significativo que a proposta do Parlamento consagra a este programa. Esse aumento não faz esquecer, contudo, o que tem sido o desinvestimento nos apoios à cultura e a profunda precarização das relações laborais do setor, deixando os artistas numa situação de enorme dependência.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uma realidade que não se desliga das políticas de austeridade que a União Europeia tem imposto. Mas esta proposta anima um conjunto de aspetos que não acompanhamos, amarra a possibilidade de apoios a um dito valor acrescentado europeu e, subsequentemente, às políticas da União Europeia e à sua visão para a democracia ou as relações externas. Enferma, simultaneamente, de uma visão mercantilista da cultura suportado na concorrência, o que rejeitamos. O exemplo da Orquestra Europeia de Juventude e a referência à necessidade de diversificar receitas e fontes de financiamento é paradigmático desta visão.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abordagens que contribuem para uma normalização e colonização culturais que são contrárias à promoção da liberdade e da independência criativa e à democratização da cultura.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018-0000" speaker_id="124831" name="Isabella Adinolfi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Europa creativa è l'unico programma che sostiene chi vuole fare impresa nel settore della cultura e della creatività. Molto spesso si tratta di microimprese, piccole e medie imprese o di creatori e artisti indipendenti. Essi rappresentano la vera spina dorsale della diversità culturale europea, in grado di innovare, intraprendere e narrare le storie e le tradizioni dei territori locali.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Unione europea deve concentrare su di loro i propri sforzi e le proprie risorse. Sono quindi particolarmente soddisfatta che siano state approvate le mie proposte per includere un supporto specifico per le piccole produzioni audiovisive indipendenti, così come per i giovani artisti musicali emergenti, che potranno accedere a finanziamenti specifici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voglio ricordare che la cultura è tale se aperta a tutti: è fondamentale aver inserito dei finanziamenti per l'adattamento in formati accessibili di libri e film o per le persone disabili, come avevo proposto. È un'azione concreta che permette a tutti di godere del diritto fondamentale all'accesso alla cultura.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nei momenti di crisi economica si taglia il superfluo e, purtroppo, la cultura è considerata il superfluo. Il programma "Europa creativa", grazie al nostro lavoro, rappresenta un primo passo nella direzione di valorizzare l'immenso patrimonio europeo e di permettere a tutti i cittadini di goderne.</p>
      <a text="(L'oratrice accetta di rispondere a una domanda &quot;cartellino blu&quot; (articolo 162, paragrafo 8, del regolamento))"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">otázka položená zvednutím modré karty. – Paní kolegyně, nemusíte se obávat, já si Vaší spolupráce vážím, ale chtěla jsem se zeptat na jednu věc. Kreativní Evropa v tom loňském roce podpořila aktivity pro Evropský rok kulturního dědictví a já si vzpomínám na debatu, kdy Vy jste se obávala, že to bude jenom propagace, že to bude jenom zase evropská nálepka, ale nepůjde to až k lidem do regionů.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chtěla jsem se Vás zeptat, jestli jste se Vy osobně seznámila s nějakým úspěšným projektem? Protože já takový projekt znám. Je to Art and Contemporary Me, který velmi dobře oslovuje mladou generaci. Tak jen taková všetečná otázka.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020-0000" speaker_id="124831" name="Isabella Adinolfi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">risposta a una domanda "cartellino blu". – Sì, io ho contestato perché c'era uno spostamento di budget, quindi portavamo una parte di budget da Europa creativa verso quest'altro programma e quando c'è uno spostamento di budget non credo mai che sia una cosa positiva. Se veramente noi credevamo e se la commissione credeva nel progetto, doveva aggiungere dei finanziamenti, non spostarli da qualcosa che già non aveva finanziamenti a sufficienza.</p>
      <p sl="en">E poi contestavo perché vedevo questo progetto come molta comunicazione piuttosto che sostanza e, ahimè, io sono una persona che preferisce la sostanza e la concretezza piuttosto che l'apparenza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Madame la Présidente, si les industries culturelles pèsent tant dans l’économie européenne, c’est que la culture est si intimement liée à notre continent qu’elle en constitue presque la marque de fabrique. Une communauté culturelle dans le sens le plus élevé de ce terme, reconnaissait même Robert Schuman, apôtre du marché unique désincarné. Aussi est-il regrettable qu’Europe créative, qui aura soutenu des œuvres aussi estimables que La vie des autres ou Le discours d’un roi se trouve à son tour galvaudée au profit des lubies idéologiques de la mode.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je passe sur l’obsession des fake news, à l’heure où l’imminence des élections européennes semble plonger la Commission dans un insondable désarroi. Car le plus contestable est l’ouverture à l’infini du programme du Kosovo à la Tunisie, sans compter l’inévitable topo de l’intégration des migrants.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans sa mission confiée par les traités de promotion de la diversité culturelle, Bruxelles semble donc n’avoir privilégié qu’une diversité toujours plus exotique. Il en résulte immanquablement un programme à son image, sans racines, sans passion et sans âme.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, kultura spojuje Evropu a každý občan v Evropské unii přirozeně cítí, že i bez nařízení je kulturní dědictví pro všechny společné, že by nevzniklo bez vzájemné spolupráce. Že nám přináší obohacení.</p>
      <p sl="en">Samotný program Kreativní Evropa je pro to, abychom toto dědictví uchovali, rozvíjeli, abychom přispěli k jeho znalosti, k vytváření nových kulturních akcí a uměleckých děl. Složka média, kultura a meziodvětvová složka budou zachovány a rozpočet je mírně navýšen na 1,85 miliardy EUR. To nás úplně neuspokojuje, protože stále mnoho projektů nebude realizováno. Snažili jsme se o to, aby program byl efektivní, aby se zaměřil také na nové aktivity. Já osobně podporuji důraz na mediální a filmovou výchovu. K většímu zviditelnění by pomohla také lepší spolupráce a networking oceněných kulturních míst, jako je European Heritage Label.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kultura nás spojuje a o tom jsme se přesvědčili také při práci ve Výboru pro kulturu. Já bych chtěla velmi poděkovat mým kolegyním a kolegům. Cítím se velmi obohacena z této spolupráce a osobně chci poděkovat Silvii Costové, Helze Trüpelové, kolegovi Diaconu a také kolegyni Adinolfiové a dalším, kolegovi Zdrojewskému. Je to pro mě velké obohacení z této spolupráce.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023-0000" speaker_id="124788" name="Luigi Morgano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, con soddisfazione il programma quadro "Europa creativa" per il periodo 2021-2027 continuerà, rafforzato, a promuovere e a salvaguardare la diversità linguistica e culturale europea e a incrementare la competitività dei settori culturali e creativi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Progetti di cooperazione transnazionale, reti di supporto ai settori culturali e creativi, traduzioni di opere letterarie, piattaforme di operatori culturali, fondi per coproduzioni di film, fiction, documentari, film per bambini, sottotitolaggio e doppiaggio, videogiochi interattivi, festival cinematografici, così come le capitali europee della cultura e il marchio del patrimonio europeo, i premi europei per la letteratura, l'architettura, la tutela del patrimonio, il cinema e la musica: tutto questo è “Europa creativa”, una vera peculiarità europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma per evitare che troppi progetti continuino a non poter essere realizzati per mancanza di fondi, è imperativo raddoppiare la dotazione di bilancio, coerentemente con la relazione intermedia del quadro finanziario pluriennale. Altrettanto importante è che il programma, nel prossimo settennio, garantisca una maggiore accessibilità a beni e servizi culturali, concretamente, per tutti i cittadini europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alla collega e amica Costa, il plauso per l'eccellente lavoro!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-024-0000" speaker_id="124827" name="Joachim Starbatty" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Jean Monnet wird der Satz zugeschrieben: Wenn ich noch einmal mit der europäischen Integration beginnen könnte, dann nicht mit Kohle und Stahl, sondern mit Kultur. Und was wir heute gehört haben, das erinnert mich an die Politik, die Jean Monnet mit Kohle und Stahl gemacht hat, mit den Vorgaben, mit den Mittel und den Subventionen. Das kann man sozusagen übertragen auf die Kultur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich lese mal einen Satz vor, der mich als Ökonom so wunderbar erregt und belustigt hat, das ist der Buchstabe c in Artikel 3a: „die Skaleneffekte, das Wachstum und die Arbeitsplätze, die mittels der Unterstützung durch die Union gefördert werden, wodurch eine Hebelwirkung für zusätzliche Mittel entsteht“ . Ich habe noch nie einen Satz gelesen, der so viel Unsinn auf einmal enthält. Skaleneffekte, das bedeutet: Größendegression bei wachsender Ausprägung. Was soll das bei der Kultur sein? Wachstum, Arbeitslosigkeit und Hebel! Ja mein Gott, was verspricht man sich von diesem Programm? Das ist ja geradezu lächerlich! Ich finde es lächerlich – nicht, weil ich gegen Europa bin, ich finde es lächerlich, weil ich Europäer bin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-025-0000" speaker_id="124940" name="Patrick O’Flynn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, there’s an old saying that he who pays the piper calls the tune, and it certainly seems to apply to the creative sector where the European Union is concerned. More than a billion euros has been spent on the current creative Europe programme, and in return I must note the creative sector overwhelmingly backed EU membership during the UK referendum. We certainly had our artists for Brexit who did not, but those at the commanding heights of our cultural institutions were generally in favour of staying in. Fortunately, the Great British public had other ideas and did not follow the direction of those we refer to somewhat sarcastically as the great and the good.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now there’s no doubt that the creative sector is an area in which Europe has a competitive advantage. Were you to ask people the world over which continent has the richest cultural heritage, it is difficult to imagine Europe not coming top. We’ve had most of the greatest painters, classical composers, writers and architects the world has ever seen. It’s also true that down the ages many writers, artists and musicians have depended on wealthy patrons to further their careers. The Royal Court of the Habsburg Empire was a noted sponsor of art and music, for instance, so it’s perhaps no surprise to find the court of the Juncker empire following suit. The danger is, though, that yes, indeed he who pays the piper calls the tune.</p>
      <p sl="en">The various strands of creative Europe naturally place a high value on funding activities that elevate the European collective identity above national identities. In this, the attention, I think, is to promote the creation of a European demos which trumps national affinities, and such a demos is certainly required to make sense of the EU’s mania for ever-closer union, but there’s little sign of its emergence. The danger is that subsidised culture becomes dull culture, lured towards safe and politically correct choices that won’t rock the boat with the sponsor.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the case of the Habsburgs, it was the uninspiring Salieri who retained the lucrative position of court composer, and not the genius Mozart. I’m sure in the years ahead the next creative Europe programme will help some talented creatives with their careers. Whether it will prove to be value for money is doubtful and whether it will foster the miraculous birth of the long-awaited European demos, more doubtful still.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! W Komisji Kultury jesteśmy zgodni w odniesieniu do dwóch tematów: do programu Erasmus+ i właśnie do „Kreatywnej Europy”. Staramy się zawsze, na każdym posiedzeniu, przy każdej okazji podkreślać wagę i znaczenie tych dwóch programów, jak również ich skuteczność w realizacji istotnych, dobrze określonych celów. Dziś chciałbym podziękować pani Sylvii Coście, dlatego że nie tylko przygotowała dzisiejszy dokument, ale także przewodnicząc wcześniej Komisji Kultury, wspierała właśnie te dwa tematy, o których mówiliśmy często i zazwyczaj bardzo – podkreślam to – bardzo dobrze.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zwrócę uwagę natomiast na dwa elementy. Po pierwsze, zaczęliśmy kadencję tego Parlamentu od wątpliwości innych grup politycznych i innych komisji dotyczących znaczenia programu Erasmus+. Zaczęliśmy także od monitorowania programu „Kreatywna Europa”, po to żeby sprawdzić jego efektywność, jak również satysfakcję tych, którzy w nim uczestniczą. I muszę podkreślić, że w odniesieniu do „Kreatywnej Europy” mamy jeden poważny problem: Zaledwie 20 % projektów aplikujących do tego programu uzyskuje satysfakcję, uzyskuje wsparcie. To oznacza, że 80 % projektów dobrze przygotowanych, cennych i wartościowych – krótko mówiąc – ląduje w koszu. To jest najważniejszy argument na rzecz zwiększania finansowania tego programu. I dziś mogę apelować, aby przynajmniej dojść do 50-procentowej efektywności w tym programie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca. Program Kreatívna Európa je programom pre všetkých a som veľmi rada, že kreatívny priemysel v Európskej únii zaznamenáva rast, pretože výrazne pomáha napríklad filmovému priemyslu, kultúrnemu dedičstvu, prekladaniu kníh, ale je aj pre tých, ktorí sú konzumentmi takto podporenej kultúry. Z tohto dôvodu je dôležité, aby rozpočet o viacročnom finančnom rámci na roky 2021 až 2027 nebol podfinancovaný, pretože miera neúspešnosti žiadateľov je veľká a to odrádza mnohé subjekty od účasti na ňom. Aj keď Kreatívna Európa je financovaná aj z ďalších finančných nástrojov Európskej únie, súhlasím so spravodajkyňou, že je potrebné navýšenie rozpočtu pre program Kreatívna Európa. Na druhej strane je potrebné oceniť návrh Komisie, ktorá zaviedla možnosť, na základe ktorej môžu kreatívne a kultúrne projekty, ktoré dostali vysoké hodnotenie, získať certifikát excelentnosti, čo by im uľahčilo prístup k financovaniu. Želám programu Kreatívna Európa, aby mal podporu aj v novom zložení Európskeho parlamentu po májových voľbách.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029-0000" speaker_id="28400" name="Francisco José Millán Mon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, el patrimonio cultural europeo es muy importante, y yo celebro mucho que ocupe un lugar tan relevante en el informe de la señora Costa y en el programa Europa Creativa. Debemos preservar y recuperar este patrimonio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Especial satisfacción me produce que el informe de la señora Costa apoye claramente una cooperación más estructurada y ambiciosa con el Consejo de Europa sobre el programa de rutas culturales europeas. Estas rutas, ahora ya 33, ponen de manifiesto en su gran mayoría la enorme riqueza y diversidad de la cultura europea. Pero también son testimonio de los estrechos vínculos históricos y culturales y artísticos que nos unen a los europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Somos una auténtica comunidad cultural que desborda las fronteras nacionales. La Unión Europea es más que una unión económica y comercial surgida tras la Segunda Guerra Mundial para preservar la paz. Eso sí es importante, desde luego, pero también es cierto que esta Europa es una comunidad con profundas raíces culturales e históricas comunes, y esto lo evidencia nuestro patrimonio cultural. Por eso debemos preservarlo, cuidarlo. Es un gran testimonio de esa unidad de base europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, doamnă comisar, stimați colegi, cultura, patrimoniul cultural și diversitatea culturală sunt bogății ale pieței unice. Sigur, avem identitate națională, dar avem un patrimoniul cultural european de care trebuie să ținem cont.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mă bucur foarte mult că există programul „Europa creativă”, pentru că acest program contribuie, de fapt, la competitivitate, la coeziune socială, la dezvoltare locală și regională. Sunt surprinsă că unii nu înțeleg această legătură între „Europa creativă” și creșterea și dezvoltarea economică. Stimulează crearea de proiecte inovatoare, acest proiect, și cunoașterea proiectelor de succes, cunoașterea reciprocă. Cultura, de fapt, asigură durabilitate economică și socială și ar trebui să fie un element central al strategiilor politice de dezvoltare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Avem nevoie de promovarea educației culturale, pentru că educația culturală, până la urmă, este un pilon important al democrației. Mă bucur mult că există un buget consistent, sper să nu fie scăzut acest buget și, sigur, sper să existe un sistem de indicatori de performanță cantitativi și calitativi pentru că, da, și în acest domeniu avem nevoie de calitate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-032-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to thank honourable Members for this good discussion, which clearly shows how important culture and creativity are for our societies, for our personal lives, for our relations with each other and, not least, for the European project and its values. Thank you also for your support in making the new programme even more ambitious and innovative.</p>
      <p sl="en">We intend to consolidate and build on the current success and we plan to experiment with novel ideas, responding in an innovative way to the emerging needs of the cultural and creative sectors. Let me stress once again that the Commission is ready to engage in interinstitutional negotiations as quickly as possible to ensure a smooth transition to the new programme in 2020.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-033-0000" speaker_id="96917" name="Silvia Costa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissaria Thyssen, vorrei subito rispondere a quanto detto in apertura dalla Commissaria, dicendo che apprezzo il suo contributo in merito alla nostra relazione e la grande collaborazione che abbiamo avuto. Noi pensiamo che, proprio perché questo nuovo programma è così ambizioso – e noi condividiamo questa ambizione – e propone tante nuove linee di finanziamento, di spesa e di azione, sia assolutamente necessario accompagnare il negoziato alla conoscenza e alla capacità di valutare le risorse disponibili.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo noi riteniamo che sia stato importante avere una prima lettura, approvarla oggi in Parlamento, chiudere un testo che sarà alla base del prossimo negoziato. Tuttavia, senza capire quali saranno le risorse disponibili, il negoziato rischierebbe di essere un po' al buio e ridurrebbe anche la possibilità di sviluppo di tutte le azioni previste.</p>
      <p sl="en">Siccome questo è un programma sottofinanziato, con un indice di successo dei progetti che nella cultura è del 15% e nella media è del 40%, noi rischiamo di alimentare aspettative senza poi averne le risorse. Quindi riteniamo che il prossimo Consiglio e il prossimo Parlamento dovranno assolutamente garantire questa coerenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda il tema delle risorse, do delle risposte molto brevi. Non cito tutti i colleghi ma li ringrazio moltissimo per essere intervenuti, in modo anche molto gentile nei miei confronti, ma penso che abbiamo fatto un bellissimo lavoro insieme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prima di tutto: le risorse. Qualcuno dice che sono troppe, qualcuno che sono troppo poche: è interessante. Sono senz'altro troppo poche, però vorrei dire che qualcosa abbiamo fatto, perché adesso c'è una sinergia più forte e più certa con altri programmi: parlo dei Fondi strutturali, parlo della politica di cooperazione internazionale, anche con il seal of excellence, e poi abbiamo finalmente una maggiore capacità anche sul fronte degli investimenti, con la garanzia europea prevista da InvestEU.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'altra notazione riguarda il fatto che abbiamo voluto tenere insieme – lo sappiamo che questa è una grande sfida – la libertà e la diversità culturale, non certo sostituendoci ad esse, ma favorendole e sostenendo anche uno spazio culturale europeo, del confronto, del dialogo e dei partenariati. Abbiamo voluto rafforzare anche e soprattutto – e lo dico in riferimento all’affermazione del collega che non c'è più e che forse non ha letto il testo – un terzo obiettivo, accanto alla cooperazione e alla competitività, che non si riferisce ad un approccio commerciale, ma piuttosto, al valore intrinseco della cultura, dell'arte e della società degli artisti. Dunque, rifiuto questo tipo di commento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi teniamo insieme, quindi, la parte culturale e artistica, la progettazione di uno spazio culturale condiviso e anche, naturalmente, l'industria culturale, artistica e audiovisiva, che deve essere rafforzata anche attraverso la direttiva sul copyright, che abbiamo citato prima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Concludo dicendo che noi abbiamo veramente questa grande responsabilità, che è stata riconosciuta da molti colleghi, in particolare quella di avere fatto di questo programma uno strumento, che oggi ha una maggiore centralità, ma non è uno strumento solitario, bensì si colloca all'interno di una strategia culturale – il cui sviluppo in questi anni è da attribuire alla commissione CULT– che vede oggi una maggiore centralità della cultura e della dimensione culturale in tutte le politiche europee.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa è la grande novità con la quale, io mi auguro, si confronteranno il nuovo Parlamento, il nuovo Consiglio e la nuova Commissione e in merito alla quale, spero, non saranno fatti passi indietro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le débat est clos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le vote aura lieu jeudi, le 28 mars 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">Déclarations écrites (article 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-034-5000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">napisan. – Kreativni i kulturni sektori čine 7,5 % radne snage EU-a, što je više od 12 milijuna radnih mjesta s punim radnim vremenom. Ovi sektori stvaraju dodanu vrijednost od približno 509 milijardi eura te su nakon sektora građevinarstva i hrane i pića najveći poslodavci u Uniji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kreativna Europa jedini je izravni program Unije za kulturni, kreativni i audiovizualni sektor te se uz praksu razmjene i dijaloga između kulturnih institucija država članica nadovezuje na prethodne programe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Komisija je odlučila povećati proračun Programa za 17 % te je novi prijedlog proračuna od 1,85 milijardi eura, u okviru VFO-a za razdoblje 2021. – 2027., podijeljen u tri potprograma: medije, kulturu i međusektorsku aktivnost. Za medije će biti izdvojena 1,081 milijarda eura te će se financirati audiovizualni projekti i poticati konkurentnost u audiovizualnom sektoru u Europi. Za potprogram kulture bit će dodijeljeno 609 milijuna eura za promicanje europskih kulturnih i kreativnih sektora, dok će za potprogram međusektorske aktivnosti 160 milijuna eura biti namijenjeno za mala i srednja poduzeća koja rade u kulturnim i kreativnim sektorima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Potrebno je naglasiti da se kulturni i audiovizualni operatori suočavaju s mnogim izazovima i preprekama, uključujući napredak digitalne tehnologije, fragmentaciju tržišta i poteškoće u pristupu financiranju. EU ima velike ambicije za kulturu, a snažan program Kreativna Europa će omogućiti da se one pretvore u stvarnost.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. 'Erasmus': the Union programme for education, training, youth and sport (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-036-0000" speaker_id="96952" name="La Présidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L’ordre du jour apppelle le débat sur le rapport de Milan Zver, au nom de la commission de la culture et de l’éducation, sur la proposition de règlement du Parlement et du Conseil établissant «Erasmus»: le programme de l’Union pour l’éducation, la formation, la jeunesse et le sport (COM(2018)0367 – C8-0233/2018 – 2018/0191(COD) (A8-0111/2019)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037-0000" speaker_id="96933" name="Milan Zver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">poročevalec. – Spoštovana predsedujoča, dragi kolegi poslanci, spoštovana komisarka Thyssen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erasmus+ predstavlja simbol evropskega povezovanja, simbol Evrope, ki skrbi za mlade, Evrope, ki ji je mar za državljane in je prava evropska zgodba o uspehu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Od leta 1987 je v programu sodelovalo več kot 9 milijonov študentov, učencev, vajencev, učiteljev, mladinskih delavcev, odraslih in športnikov. Program iz leta v leto podira rekorde, vsako leto financira več projektov, udeležba je vse večja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vse kaže, da se bo v tem obdobju udeležilo raznih oblik sodelovanja v Erasmusu okrog 4 milijone Evropejcev. Za obdobje 2021–2027 pa je napovedano kar 12 milijonov udeležencev. Te številke zvenijo lepo, a vemo, da bo med letoma 2014 in 2020 Erasmus lahko podprl le 3,7 % mladih v Evropi.</p>
      <p sl="en">V Erasmusu je povpraševanje torej ogromno, denarja pa je vedno premalo. Tako za mobilnost, kot za mnoge druge projekte. Če bi študenti dobili višje štipendije, bi se jih na izmenjave prijavilo veliko več. Če bi bilo več sredstev na voljo, nam ne bi bilo treba zavrniti toliko dobrih, kvalitetnih mladinskih projektov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato sem za obdobje 2021–2027, torej za naslednji finančni proračun, perspektivo, predlagal trikratno povečanje sredstev, s 15 na 45 milijard evrov.</p>
      <p sl="en">Če želimo potrojiti število udeležencev, če želimo dodati tri velike nove pobude in če želimo narediti program bolj dostopen, potem podvojitev sredstev, kar je predlagala Evropska komisija, ne bo dovolj.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pri pripravi poročila o novem Erasmusu sem predvsem želel okrepiti in izboljšati tradicionalne aktivnosti oziroma podprograme, med njimi mobilnost in različne projekte. Obenem pa sem želel zavarovati tri velike nove pobude, tj. pobuda Odkrij Evropsko unijo, Mreža evropskih univerz in Centri poklicne odličnosti, ki bodo del programa po letu 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">V primerjavi s predlogom Komisije smo v Parlamentu predlagali precejšnje povečanje sredstev za poklicno izobraževanje, šole, šport in odrasle. Naj naštejem še nekaj novosti, ki smo jih v Parlamentu podprli in nadgradili.</p>
      <p sl="en">V novem Erasmusu bo več možnosti za manjše projekte in manjše organizacije, ki so do sedaj imele težave pri dostopanju do programa. Novi Erasmus bo prinesel več možnosti za učenje tujih jezikov, za mobilnost šolarjev in profesorjev v šolah, pa za mobilnost predšolskih vzgojiteljev ter več možnosti za mobilnost in projekte za odrasle. Novost bo tudi mobilnost za športne trenerje in za posamezne športnike.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kot je razvidno iz poročila, je bila ena od mojih glavnih prioritet, da program v naslednjem ciklu postane bolj enostaven za uporabnike ter vključujoč, dostopen in pravičen za vse skupine mladih in starejših, ne glede na ekonomsko situacijo in druge okoliščine, npr. invalidnost.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za tiste, ki imajo težave pri dostopanju do programa, ljudi z manj priložnostmi, smo predlagali vrsto specifičnih ukrepov. Na eni strani boljše informiranje, na drugi strani pa finančno podporo, če je to potrebno.</p>
      <p sl="en">V poročilu smo bolj poudarili pomen evropske dodane vrednosti, kar pa seveda ne pomeni, da morajo biti vse aktivnosti nadnacionalne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zahtevali smo tudi večjo vlogo Parlamenta, da ne bo le Evropska komisija določala in odločala o vsakoletnih prioritetah.</p>
      <p sl="en">Novi Erasmus bo poleg finančne mobilnosti omogočil tudi virtualno in mešano sodelovanje, kar seveda podpiramo. Obenem pa želimo transparentnost, da se vodi ločene evidence za fizično, torej realno mobilnost, in virtualne mobilnostne aktivnosti. Ne želimo namreč, da bi se napihovalo številke s tem, koliko ljudi v Evropi je mobilnih, ko bi mnogi v resnici sedeli doma za računalnikom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ob koncu naj se iskreno zahvalim poročevalcem v senci za konstruktivno sodelovanje. Naša pogajanja niso bila lahka, a je končni rezultat zato toliko boljši.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am pleased to join you today for this debate on the future Erasmus programme. I think we all agree that Erasmus is the European Union’s most iconic programme and one of its biggest success stories. Erasmus is a true expression of what the European Union stands for and what it can do for our people. It has changed the lives of millions of Europeans and changed them for the better.</p>
      <p sl="en">With this in mind, the Commission has tabled an ambitious proposal for a new Erasmus programme. We propose to double the budget and build on the success of the current programme. At the same time, we propose to add some promising new elements.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me first of all thank the rapporteur, Mr Zver, and his shadow rapporteurs, as well as all the Members of the Committee on Culture and Education (CULT) and, of course, of the other committees that give an opinion, and all those who have contributed to this report. The Commission is fully aware that the programme and its participants from universities, FET colleges, apprentices and high schools, are just as dear to you as they are to us. I would therefore like to take this occasion to wholeheartedly thank you for your enthusiasm and for your support for the Commission’s proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is also happy to see that our two institutions have largely converging positions on most features of the future programmes. We share the Parliament’s objectives to make the programme even more inclusive, to make it simpler for our beneficiaries and to further exploit the potential for synergies with other sources of EU funding. Fundamentally, we want Erasmus to reach more people and especially people from diverse socio—economic backgrounds. We want Erasmus to become more open to smaller organisations, notably by cutting the paperwork. We also want to boost mobility for school pupils, learners in vocational education and training, and for youth exchanges. This will strongly diversify the profile of Erasmus participants.</p>
      <p sl="en">I know that this House takes a lot of interest in synergies and complementarities between EU funding programmes, and I can assure you that Erasmus will benefit from this. For example, the future European Social Fund Plus could top up individual mobility grants to support people with fewer opportunities or skill up the results of successful Erasmus projects. For this to become a reality, we need to involve all actors, including at national and regional level. What matters most is that we put funding to its best and most efficient use.</p>
      <p sl="en">The future Erasmus programme will also be instrumental in creating a genuine European education area by 2025, where learners can move freely across borders and between disciplines, and where education and training systems are inclusive, innovative and geared towards lifelong learning. I appreciate that you support the Commission in this effort.</p>
      <p sl="en">In order to help turn this vision into reality, the future Erasmus programme will support ambitious new initiatives, such as the European Universities Initiative or the Centres of Vocational Excellence. They have the potential to become new flagships of the programme, together with the new DiscoverEU initiative. The idea for DiscoverEU, namely to offer 18-year-old young people a ticket to travel Europe, has enormous potential, especially if it is reinforced with a strong learning dimension, as you rightly request.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s now important that we negotiate the new programme quickly so that it will soon be a reality. The Commission therefore regrets that the Parliament is not willing to start negotiations for Erasmus before the elections, while the Commission and the Presidency would have been keen to do so. We would consider it a pity if this well-known and successful programme risked delays in kicking off due to a late start of the negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission believes that this report provides a good basis to reach an agreement between the institutions swiftly. I am convinced that the European Parliament will again be a powerful ally in creating a strong and vibrant new Erasmus programme. Rest assured that the Commission will be an honest broker in this process.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039-0000" speaker_id="124856" name="Ignazio Corrao" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatore per parere della commissione per lo sviluppo. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissaria Thyssen, io sono contento, a fine legislatura, di poter parlare di Erasmus perché dieci anni fa ho avuto l'opportunità io stesso di parteciparvi e di trascorrere un anno di studio in Galizia, in Spagna. È stato sicuramente uno degli anni migliori della mia vita. Chi ha avuto l’opportunità di fare l’Erasmus, ha potuto veramente vivere un'esperienza straordinaria.</p>
      <p sl="en">Probabilmente, in un'Unione europea che è percepita come opaca e lontana dai cittadini, il programma Erasmus rappresenta il più grande successo, il miglior esperimento di cittadinanza europea. Per questo, dal punto di vista dalla commissione DEVE, speriamo di poter incrementare la partecipazione e la cooperazione con altri paesi extra UE, al fine di creare una sempre maggiore integrazione e cooperazione. Quindi ben vengano maggiori fondi per l'Erasmus!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040-0000" speaker_id="124773" name="Jean Arthuis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur pour avis de la commission des budgets">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je voudrais à mon tour féliciter la Commission pour son initiative.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erasmus est un programme qui parle aux Européens, c’est évidemment une grande réussite. C’est celui qui contribue au meilleur investissement que nous puissions faire, c’est-à-dire permettre aux jeunes de se donner les moyens de comprendre le monde, sans doute d’accéder à une capacité professionnelle, et c’est aussi former des talents pour la compétitivité des entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, Madame la Commissaire, je formulerai trois observations, trois souhaits, au nom de la commission des budgets.</p>
      <p sl="en">D’abord, c’est d’augmenter les crédits. Et, si la discussion avec le Conseil a du mal à démarrer, c’est parce que nous ne connaissons pas la position du Conseil. Doubler les crédits par rapport au MFF 2014-2020 ne suffit pas et nous risquerions d’avoir en 2021 des crédits en-deçà des crédits Erasmus de 2020. Il faut donc augmenter les crédits.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxième préoccupation: simplifier les procédures.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et enfin: démocratiser Erasmus. Aujourd’hui, pour la mobilité longue, celle qui est profitable parce qu’il y a une immersion, ce sont surtout les étudiants qui en bénéficient. Ce que nous souhaitons, c’est que les apprenants professionnels, les apprentis et les stagiaires professionnels puissent bénéficier de bourses Erasmus et avoir de longues mobilités. Il faudra aussi suggérer aux États membres d’utiliser les fonds de cohésion, Fonds de développement régional et Fonds social européen, pour mettre en place des centres d’excellence.</p>
      <p sl="en">Merci, Madame la Commissaire, pour tout ce que vous avez réalisé au service de la mobilité et de l’emploi des jeunes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041-0000" speaker_id="129256" name="Emilian Pavel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Raportor pentru aviz, Comisia pentru ocuparea forței de muncă și afaceri sociale. – Doamnă președintă, vreau să vă mulțumesc și eu pentru munca la acest dosar, raportorilor și tuturor colegilor și colegelor care au contribuit. Programul Erasmus+ a reușit ceva greu de calculat în bani: a contribuit la formarea, în rândul tinerilor mai ales, a unei identități europene de care avem mare nevoie. Aceasta este, cred eu, menirea programului Erasmus+ și acesta este secretul succesului său de până acum.</p>
      <p sl="en">Totuși, pentru a continua la același nivel, cred în continuare că programul are nevoie de mai multă finanțare. Noi, atât în Comisia pentru ocuparea forței de muncă, cât și în Comisia pentru cultură, am propus o triplare și sper că și Consiliul va veni și va sprijini acest demers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cred, de asemenea, că este nevoie de îmbunătățirea comunicării dintre beneficiari, Comisia Europeană și organismele naționale. Nu în ultimul rând, în era digitală e nevoie de o simplificare, de creșterea accesibilității și de reducerea birocrației. Și nu trebuie să uităm că Erasmus+ trebuie să devină mai incluziv, trebuie să asigure acces și celor defavorizați și celor care suferă de o dizabilitate și trebuie clar să asigure egalitate între femei și bărbați.</p>
      <p sl="en">Și să nu uităm, insist, insistați și dumneavoastră pentru o triplare, pentru că avem componente noi, ne dorim o triplare a beneficiarilor. Dacă nu avem această triplare, va fi greu să le realizăm, astfel încât, probabil că va trebui să scădem din calitate. Vă mulțumesc, susțineți Erasmus+!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-042-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Paní předsedající, děkuji kolegovi Zverovi za jeho dlouhodobou práci pro tento program. On také zde jasně vysvětlil nové změny, které v programu najdeme. Erasmus je nejznámějším a nejúspěšnějším evropským programem právě proto, že ho mladí lidé oceňují, že ho vyhledávají. Má potenciál zasáhnout velký počet mladých lidí, ovlivnit jejich budoucí kariéru a také jejich představy o Evropě. Je to důležité právě v dnešní době, kdy se lidé uzavírají a kdy se šíří různé dezinformační kampaně.</p>
      <p sl="en">Slíbili jsme, že uděláme maximum pro zvýšení rozpočtu tohoto programu. Předkládáme tedy Radě návrh na ztrojnásobení rozpočtu oproti dnešnímu stavu. Tento návrh je ambiciózní, ale jsme přesvědčeni o tom, že je to potřebné. Za důležité považuji zjednodušení administrativních procesů a také větší flexibilitu pro konkrétní podmínky členských států.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dámy a pánové, dnes, 28. března, je výročí narození Jana Ámose Komenského, známého jako Comenius, Učitel národů. Jsem přesvědčena o tom, že by tento program uvítal. V této souvislosti chci apelovat na to, aby program Erasmus v budoucnu ještě více pamatoval na učitele, kteří si zaslouží více příležitostí a ocenění. Na závěr chci poděkovat paní komisařce Thyssenové a panu komisaři Navracsicsovi za jeho přístup a podporu k výraznému navýšení tohoto rozpočtu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-043-0000" speaker_id="96837" name="Petra Kammerevert" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Mein langfristiges Ziel ist es, jedem jungen Menschen zu ermöglichen, eine Erasmus-Erfahrung zu machen, ohne dabei Abstriche in Sachen Qualität und Länge zuzulassen. Die echte Mittelverdreifachung, die das Parlament fordert, ist ein absolut notwendiger Schritt, diesem Ziel näher zu kommen. Wir akzeptieren nicht, dass das Prinzip „Masse statt Klasse” gilt, womöglich Aufenthalte verkürzt und durch virtuelle Begegnung ersetzt werden. Das wäre die Konsequenz aus dem Vorschlag der Kommission, mit einer Verdoppelung der Mittel eine Verdreifachung der Teilnehmerzahlen zu erreichen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Durch einen stärkeren Fokus auf die berufliche Aus- und Weiterbildung, die Erwachsenenbildung und die Schulbildung ermöglichen wir mehr jungen Menschen einen besseren Zugang zum Programm. Der Studierendenaustausch bleibt das Herzstück des Programms und wird unter diesen Neuerungen nicht leiden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir fordern außerdem die Rückkehr zur breiteren Nutzung von Pauschalbeträgen. Die Antragsverfahren müssen endlich einfacher und verständlicher werden. Anträge, die länger als zehn Seiten sind, müssen endlich der Geschichte angehören.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei allem Respekt für den Umgang mit Geld: Man beantragt hier nicht Forschungsgelder in Milliardenhöhe, sondern möchte sich im Austausch mit jungen Menschen aus anderen Ländern weiterbilden. Das muss bei Beantragung und Abrechnung endlich auch gebührend berücksichtigt werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schließlich fordern wir eine ehrgeizige Inklusionsstrategie, die die diskriminierungs- und barrierefreie Teilhabe wirklich aller jungen Europäerinnen und Europäer realisieren kann. Auch die Teilnahme an einem Erasmus-Programm, an einer Erasmus-Maßnahme darf nicht vom Geldbeutel der Eltern abhängen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mein Appell geht heute an den Rat: Geben Sie sich einen Ruck und schließen Sie sich der Forderung des Parlaments nach einer Verdreifachung der Mittel an! Man kann nicht immer über die Bedeutung von Erasmus schwadronieren und dann nicht bereit sein, den Geldbeutel zu öffnen. Schließlich geht es darum, Menschen in Europa zusammenzubringen und der Jugend Europas einen guten Weg in die Zukunft zu ebnen. Das sollte uns allemal 41 Milliarden Euro wert sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noch ein Satz zum Vorwurf der Kommission, wir seien nicht bereit zu verhandeln: Die Kommission hat das Programm ein halbes Jahr zu spät vorgelegt, und der Rat ist nicht bereit, uns irgendein commitment zu geben, was das Geld angeht. Insofern folgt hier der Inhalt dem Geld und nicht umgekehrt. Und deshalb sind wir bereit, nach der Europawahl zu verhandeln, aber nicht vorher.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ECR. – Poštovana predsjedavajuća, program Erasmus pokazao se kao istinska dodana vrijednost. Omogućio je milijunima studenata da se školuju u najboljim europskim visokoobrazovnim ustanovama, razmjenjuju znanja i vještine, ostvaruju poslovne kontakte i upoznaju druge države i njihove običaje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podržavam povećanje proračuna za ovaj program i dijelim mišljenje da bi određenim korekcijama u načinu financiranja trebalo osigurati bolji pristup isključenim skupinama. U mojoj zemlji, Hrvatskoj, studenti lošijeg materijalnog stanja uz postojeću stipendiju često nemaju izbora i odustaju od Erasmusa, što je velika šteta i za njih osobno, a i za ovaj program.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ciljevi programa moraju biti obrazovne, kulturološke i poslovne prirode, a ne političke. Izgradnja europskog identiteta ne bi smjela biti među službenim ciljevima Erasmusa. Sasvim je moguće da bi se taj proces sam od sebe događao uz ovakav program, ali ne bi trebao biti potican od institucija jer to bi to značilo da glavni motiv za Erasmus nije istinska briga za budućnost mladih nego nešto sasvim drugo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-045-0000" speaker_id="135491" name="María Teresa Giménez Barbat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ALDE. – Señora presidenta, estimados compañeros, quisiera dar las gracias a mi compañero Milan Zver y a los demás ponentes alternativos con los que hemos trabajado durante meses en este nuevo Reglamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">El programa Erasmus ha contribuido decisivamente a la difusión de una identidad auténticamente europea, a la creación de una generación de personas que han crecido reforzando el sentido de pertenencia europeo. A la vez se trata de un proyecto en curso, pues el objetivo último no es otro que lograr una Europa federal, superando los egoísmos nacionales, el populismo y los intereses particulares.</p>
      <p sl="en">En relación con este Reglamento, estas son algunas de nuestras propuestas concretas para el informe parlamentario: aumentar la financiación hasta triplicar el presupuesto actual; aumentar el número de los participantes y conseguir una mayor participación de personas de entornos desfavorecidos; impulsar la iniciativa sobre redes universitarias europeas orientada a construir un espacio europeo de educación.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nuestro objetivo es proponer alianzas transnacionales que constituirán las universidades europeas del futuro, promoviendo los valores y la identidad europea y revolucionando la calidad y la competitividad de nuestra educación superior.</p>
      <p sl="en">El programa integra además una importante dimensión internacional, persiguiendo un doble objetivo: por un lado, facilitar a los jóvenes los desplazamientos y la movilidad internacional, favoreciendo la docencia y la investigación; y, por el otro, apoyar el diálogo entre países y fomentar las relaciones culturales entre la Unión y terceros países, creando proyectos de desarrollo y modernización de los mecanismos educativos en los países asociados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por todos estos motivos, consideramos que el programa Erasmus+ es un programa ganador de la Unión Europea; el programa Erasmus es la iniciativa de mayor éxito en el ámbito de la educación: más de 10 millones de personas han participado en este programa desde su lanzamiento en 1987.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gracias a esta nueva etapa legislativa, en los próximos años, aún más ciudadanos europeos podrán disfrutar del programa Erasmus, así que, participen, únanse y no se lo pierdan.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-046-0000" speaker_id="4550" name="Jill Evans" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am delighted to have played a role in this update of the excellent Erasmus+ programme 2021-2027. I congratulate the rapporteur and thank him for his positive and constructive approach. Many thousands of students and young people in Wales, like elsewhere, have benefited from the opportunities that Erasmus offered. Our universities in particular have had the pleasure of hosting young people from across the European Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission said we have to have ambition to empower young people. I believe we’ve achieved that here. From the start, one of the priorities of my group, the Greens/EFA Group, was to support the tripling of the budget to meet the target of tripling the number of people taking part, because that is ambition. I believe the new programme will be simpler, more open to all individuals from all education sectors and phases, and will help tackle many of the problems we face.</p>
      <p sl="en">And finally, if we leave the EU, the loss of Erasmus to Wales would be a huge blow. That is why I am pleased that this report allows for the continued participation of third countries. You can be sure that given the opportunity, Wales will still be an active and enthusiastic partner, and that’s the positive message that I would like to leave with you. Diolch yn fawr iawn. (Google Translate)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047-0000" speaker_id="26851" name="Νικόλαος Χουντής" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, και η δική μας η εκτίμηση είναι ότι το Εrasmus+ είναι ένα πρόγραμμα που έχει αγκαλιαστεί από τους νέους της Ευρώπης. Κατά συνέπεια είναι σημαντικό να δώσουμε τις δυνατότητες σε περισσότερους νέους να έχουν την ευκαιρία να έρθουν σε επαφή με διαφορετικά εκπαιδευτικά συστήματα, με διαφορετικούς πολιτισμούς, με διαφορετικές συνήθειες, με διαφορετικές κουλτούρες. Προτείνουμε κι εμείς τον τριπλασιασμό του προϋπολογισμού αυτού του προγράμματος, ούτως ώστε να αγκαλιάσει περισσότερους και να μην είναι ένα πρόγραμμα για λίγους.</p>
      <p sl="en">Όμως θέλουμε να πούμε ότι είμαστε αντίθετοι με τον εργαλειακό τρόπο που αντιμετωπίζει η Επιτροπή και το πρόγραμμα αυτό, προκειμένου να περάσει νεοφιλελεύθερες απόψεις στον τομέα της εκπαίδευσης. Πρώτον, η σύνδεση όλο και περισσότερο της εκπαίδευσης με τον ιδιωτικό τομέα, δεύτερον, ο ανταγωνισμός μεταξύ των ιδρυμάτων στο πλαίσιο της αριστείας, τρίτον, η διαμόρφωση των προγραμμάτων σπουδών με βάση μόνο τις επιταγές της αγοράς εργασίας είναι δυστυχώς ορισμένα απ’ αυτά τα χαρακτηριστικά της εργαλειοποίησης. Επομένως, ναι στη συνεργασία και στην ανταλλαγή, όχι στην εκμετάλλευση του μέλλοντος των νέων!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048-0000" speaker_id="124831" name="Isabella Adinolfi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo EFDD. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario, l'Erasmus è il programma di maggiore successo dell'Unione europea e, da oltre trent'anni, offre la possibilità, a giovani e non, di compiere esperienze di studio e lavoro all'estero e a tante organizzazioni di fare rete e di realizzare progetti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il testo approvato in commissione CULT rafforza ulteriormente la proposta della Commissione, visto che si aumentano sia il budget che la platea dei beneficiari. Sono molto contenta che le mie proposte di coinvolgere maggiormente gli adulti in percorsi di istruzione siano state accolte. Infatti, gli adulti potranno così partecipare alle azioni di mobilità individuale, così come gli insegnanti potranno ricevere opportunità di formazione e aggiornamento professionale.</p>
      <p sl="en">È stato fatto un ottimo lavoro anche per quanto riguarda l'inclusione: non vogliamo, infatti, che la partecipazione al programma Erasmus resti un'esperienza elitaria riservata soltanto a pochi privilegiati. Si tratta di un'opportunità unica di crescita che va resa accessibile a tutti, quindi anche a chi ha meno opportunità. Per questo motivo, anche grazie alle mie proposte, il programma prevede specifiche misure di sostegno finanziario, in sinergia con altri programmi europei, per dare a tutti la stessa possibilità: nessuno deve rimanere indietro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-049-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ENF. – Madame la Présidente, renforcer le sentiment d’appartenance à l’Europe chez les citoyens, tel est le prétendu objectif que la Commission assigne au programme Erasmus, qui est devenu Erasmus+ ou qui veut redevenir Erasmus, on ne sait plus très bien. Cela serait d’autant plus urgent naturellement suite au Brexit. Ce ne sont là que des vœux pieux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certes, la mobilité Erasmus, par la découverte d’autres espaces, cultures et langues, est une magnifique occasion pour se rendre compte de ce que nous avons en commun et de ce qui nous distingue. Malheureusement, rien n’est fait pour approfondir ces découvertes lors de la mobilité. En effet, la mobilité au-delà de l’Europe est toujours plus encouragée. L’on voit mal, par exemple, en quoi le fait que la Tunisie soit la première destination hors Europe chez les Français renforce l’identité européenne. De plus, la Commission, plutôt que d’encourager les agences nationales à faire découvrir le patrimoine local aux bénéficiaires de la mobilité, préfère offrir des pass interrail à ceux qui viennent d’avoir 18 ans, soit ceux qui vont voter pour la première fois. Elle ne cherche pas à favoriser la découverte des autres cultures, ce que permet davantage un long séjour que de traverser le continent en train. Je pense que tout le monde est d’accord là-dessus. Mais simplement, on veut influencer le vote des citoyens.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, ce rapport s’intéresse certes à l’apprentissage des langues, mais ne rend toujours pas obligatoire l’apprentissage de la langue du pays d’accueil. Au lieu de cela, on facilite l’apprentissage par le numérique et nul doute que ce sera l’anglais qui sera choisi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bref, pour la Commission, notre identité est à chercher ailleurs et seuls les migrants, auxquels on offre des cours de langues, ont le droit de s’enraciner. On comprend mieux dès lors la nécessité de tripler le budget, 41 milliards, qu’il faudra bien aller chercher dans la poche des citoyens.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bienvenue dans l’Europe du monde au lieu d’une Europe des nations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050-0000" speaker_id="96729" name="Santiago Fisas Ayxelà" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, en la anterior legislatura, cuando el presupuesto de la Unión se redujo, logramos desde el Parlamento incrementar el presupuesto para Erasmus en un 43 %. Y ahora me congratulo de que se pida triplicar el presupuesto actual, lo que permitirá a muchos jóvenes disfrutar de esta gran experiencia que contribuye a mejorar su futuro laboral, a la vez que incrementa su sentimiento de pertenencia a la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">En mi opinión, el programa Erasmus ha hecho más por la unión de Europa que cualquier Tratado que se haya firmado. En el informe del que fui ponente en el año 2011, sobre la dimensión europea del deporte, se solicitaba la creación de un Erasmus deportivo. Me congratulo de que la Comisión lo haya propuesto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este capítulo persigue objetivos tan esenciales como la lucha contra la violencia, la intolerancia y la discriminación y promueve el voluntariado y la inclusión social, sin olvidar la importancia de la actividad física para la salud. Una persona que practica deporte, que se ajusta a las reglas y al espíritu de superación, muy posiblemente será un mejor ciudadano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finalmente, estoy muy satisfecho de que el presupuesto destinado a deportes haya aumentado hasta un 2 % y espero que lo siga haciendo en los próximos años, lo que permitirá que estos importantes valores se sigan promocionando entre los ciudadanos europeos. Y quiero felicitar, por supuesto, a mi querido colega Milan Zver por el estupendo informe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051-0000" speaker_id="96917" name="Silvia Costa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, dopo più di trent'anni, Erasmus si conferma il più grande successo dell'Unione europea, l'esperienza più significativa di cittadinanza europea praticata, non solo per le nuove generazioni, ma anche per l'educazione degli adulti, per lo sport e l'associazionismo giovanile. Per questo vogliamo che il nuovo Erasmus+ cresca, triplicando le risorse e diventando più accessibile, ma vogliamo anche che diventi sempre più il pilastro del nuovo spazio europeo dell'educazione, che dovrebbe partire dal 2025, con il riconoscimento automatico e reciproco dei diplomi, dei periodi di studio all'estero e delle competenze formali e informali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le proposte del Parlamento rendono Erasmus+ più accessibile ai soggetti svantaggiati, compresi quelli di background migratorio, e prevedono la mobilità degli studenti delle scuole superiori e dei docenti della scuola e della formazione professionale, ma anche dell'associazionismo giovanile. Vogliamo che si moltiplichino i partenariati fra le università, anche con le istituzioni culturali, e che si offrano master congiunti, anche attraverso la nuova rete delle università europee e dei centri di eccellenza. Poniamo le basi di un vero statuto dello studente, con la eCard degli studenti, una mia proposta che è stata finalmente inserita nel programma e che partirà dal 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Permettetemi di dire solo un'ultima parola, in conclusione, ricordando in quest'Aula le tredici studentesse Erasmus che, nel marzo di tre anni fa, hanno perso la vita in un tremendo incidente in Spagna: ecco, penso che noi dobbiamo assumerci tutti una grande responsabilità e impegnarci per garantire che i ragazzi e le ragazze che svolgono questa importante esperienza lo facciano in condizioni di sicurezza e di qualità dei servizi prestati.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052-0000" speaker_id="24942" name="Ana Miranda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, ¿qué decir del programa Erasmus? Yo misma lo disfruté en el año 1993 en Alemania: una estudiante de una universidad gallega que estudiaba y trabajaba para pagar sus estudios era difícil que tuviera una oportunidad de salir al extranjero y, gracias a Erasmus y a esa oportunidad, posiblemente hoy sea eurodiputada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Después de esta breve introducción personal, quisiera valorar positivamente la propuesta de la Comisión, porque el fomento del acceso y de la inclusión social en los entornos más desfavorecidos y la posibilidad de que personas con menos recursos puedan acceder a programas de este tipo es, desde luego, uno de los éxitos europeos que contribuye, además, a la relación y el intercambio entre pueblos, entre universidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay miles de jóvenes que han podido hacer realidad ese intercambio y realizar prácticas y estudios. Pero es cierto que no debería quedarse solo en los universitarios, sino ampliarse también a la formación profesional para darle un aspecto mucho más amplio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y qué decir, por supuesto, del tema del presupuesto. El presupuesto, hay que incrementarlo, y también la contribución, porque algunos Estados miembros no contribuyen suficientemente, y los estudiantes que van tienen que trabajar también para poder estudiar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053-0000" speaker_id="28299" name="Bogusław Sonik" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Marzenia się spełniają, choć pewnie nie zawsze tak szybko, jakbyśmy chcieli. Moje pokolenie lat 70. bardzo pragnęło, mając dwadzieścia lat, móc wyruszyć w daleką podróż, by poznać Rzym, Paryż czy Wiedeń i wiele innych sławnych miejsc naszego kontynentu. Jeśli udało się uzyskać paszport od władz komunistycznych, wyruszaliśmy autostopem z plecakiem na europejskie autostrady. Chłonęliśmy te sławne miejsca, które tak bardzo działały na naszą wyobraźnię: zabytki, muzea, krajobrazy. Pukaliśmy do bram europejskich uniwersytetów, by podjąć studia na zachodnioeuropejskich uczelniach, często spotykając się z odmową lub koniecznością opłat, na które nie było nas stać.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dzisiaj Europa stoi otworem dla studentów poszukujących wiedzy. To jest europejska inwestycja w przyszłość naszego kontynentu. Dlatego wierzę, że „Erasmus+” znajdzie się w centrum uwagi szefów państw członkowskich, którzy będą decydować o wielkości budżetu na ten program. Cieszę się, że Komisja Kultury i Edukacji Parlamentu Europejskiego opowiedziała się za potrojeniem środków na program dla studentów i stażystów „Erasmus+”, które mogłyby wynieść 45 mld EUR.</p>
      <p sl="en">Według nowych reguł program ma wspierać osoby, które mają mniejsze możliwości. „Erasmus” daje młodym Europejczykom możliwość studiowania, szkolenia się i odbywania wolontariatu za granicą. Priorytetem mają być też wymiany zawodowe w sektorze edukacji, zwłaszcza w regionach przygranicznych – zwiększyliśmy budżet na ten cel. Z programu „Erasmus+” może być również finansowany sport amatorski, a w jego ramach mobilność młodych sportowców, trenerów, kadry sportowej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">г-жо Председател, Еразъм + е една от малкото програми, които са доказали своята европейска добавена стойност. В този смисъл тройното увеличение на бюджета ще спомогне за постигане на амбициозните цели на програмата, а именно достигане до по-голям брой млади хора и повече одобрени финансови проекти.</p>
      <p sl="en">Сегашните нива на бюджета показват сериозен дисбаланс между високите нива на търсене и реалното предлагане. С други думи, редица качествени проекти биват отхвърляни заради липса на достатъчни средства, което има своя негативен ефект.</p>
      <p sl="en">Освен с по-голям бюджет, следващата програма трябва преди всичко да е достъпна и приобщаваща. Младите хора със скромни финансови възможности и хората с увреждания трябва да имат равен достъп до възможностите за мобилност.</p>
      <p sl="en">Не на последно място, следвайки същата логика, споделям виждането, че периметърът на програмата трябва да се разшири към професионално образование и обучение и към мобилността на учениците.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055-0000" speaker_id="28240" name="Helga Trüpel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Das Europäische Parlament fordert mit Mehrheit, dass das Budget für Erasmus auf 41 Milliarden verdreifacht wird. Das ist eine richtige Forderung, weil Bildung ganz maßgeblich darüber entscheidet, welche Chancen Menschen im Leben haben. Gerade auch für Migranten und Benachteiligte ist das der entscheidende Punkt. Deswegen müssen wir auch bei den kleinen Kindern schon anfangen. Sie müssen die jeweilige Sprache des Landes lernen. Deswegen liegt der Schwerpunkt im neuen Erasmus-Programm auf den Auszubildenden. Es geht eben nicht nur um die sowieso schon besser gestellten Schülerinnen im Gymnasium oder Studierende.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber natürlich, insgesamt wollen wir mehr für Bildung tun, und es geht immer um Ausbildung, aber natürlich geht es generell um Bildung und Persönlichkeitsbildung, dass man den Horizont erweitern kann, dass man in Europa und darüber hinaus unterwegs ist. Hier sind genug, die selber Erasmus-Studierende waren, und alle sagen, wie sehr sie davon profitiert haben. Unser Anliegen ist einfach, möglichst vielen jungen und auch nicht mehr so jungen Menschen diese Chance zu geben. Denn Europa tut ewas für seine Bürgerinnen und Bürger!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056-0000" speaker_id="119436" name="Ivana Maletić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, pozdravljam povjerenicu i zahvaljujem kolegi Zveru koji je izvjestitelj na ovom važnom izvješću o programu Erasmus. Zadali smo vrlo, vrlo ambiciozni cilj, a to je stvaranje europskog područja obrazovanja do 2025.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jako je bitan jer nije samo riječ o priznavanju kvalifikacija i diploma u državama članicama, nego i o razmjeni znanja i najvažnijih i najnovijih dostignuća, kako oni manje razvijeni ne bi trebali ispočetka sve otkrivati, već kako bi mogli napraviti razvojne skokove, a ne stalno, korak po korak, polako se razvijati. Dakle, to je važno i za ujednačeni razvoj čitave Europske unije.</p>
      <p sl="en">Upravo zbog toga moramo biti ambiciozni i zato podržavam i stajem snažno uz naš prijedlog koji je u izvješću, a to je da iznos sredstava bude tri puta veći. To je ono što treba mladima i profesorima i sportašima.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057-0000" speaker_id="118858" name="Marlene Mizzi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sinjura President, l-Erasmus huwa wieħed mill-aktar proġetti ta' suċċess tal-Unjoni Ewropea, proġett li għen miljuni ta' żgħażagħ sabiex jibbenefikaw minn opportunitajiet ta' tagħlim u mobilità. Fis-seba' snin li ġejjin nistgħu nistennew li l-Erasmus ħa jkompli jikber u jespandi. Imma biex dan iseħħ għandu bżonn baġit li jipprovdi fondi suffiċjenti. Il-proposta tal-Kummissjoni biex tirdoppja l-baġit mhix biżżejjed. Hemm bżonn li l-istess baġit jiżdied bi tliet darbiet aktar biex inkunu nistgħu nwasslu l-Erasmus+ li huwa aktar inklużiv u aċċessibbli għal kulħadd. Huwa għalhekk li nappoġġa l-proposta li l-fondi tal-Erasmus+ 2021-2027 jiżdied bi tliet darbiet. B'dan il-mod inkunu qed nagħtu lok biex aktar nies jieħdu sehem u jkun hemm aktar fondi biżżejjed għall-ħtiġijiet tal-parteċipanti. Il-programm għandu jiffoka fuq l-inklużività u b'mod partikolari fuq il-provvediment ta' aċċess aħjar għal persuni b'inqas opportunitajiet u dawk bi bżonnijiet speċjali. Kulħadd għandu jkollu l-istess prospetti, imma s'issa mhux kulħadd kellu l-possibbiltà jibbenefika mill-Erasmus. Għandha bżonn aċċess nondiskriminatorju u mingħajr ostakli biex verament ikollna Erasmus miftuħ għal kulħadd.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-058-0000" speaker_id="28346" name="Mercedes Bresso" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'Erasmus+ sarà uno strumento essenziale per migliorare la qualità dell'istruzione e della formazione professionale in tutta l'Unione, attraverso esperienze di mobilità e di conoscenza delle buone pratiche.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'inclusione dell'istruzione e della formazione professionale nel programma permetterà che esso raggiunga un'eterogeneità di cittadini e di giovani, favorendo le pari opportunità e l'inclusione sociale per tutti i giovani, compresi quelli con minori opportunità.</p>
      <p sl="en">In linea con il pilastro europeo dei diritti sociali, il nuovo programma Erasmus+ insiste anche positivamente sul ruolo fondamentale che l'istruzione svolge nella lotta contro la povertà, promuovendo un'istruzione inclusiva, equa e di qualità e ponendo l'accento chiaramente sull'obiettivo di potenziare la capacità di raggiungere anche le persone con minori opportunità, come quelle provenienti da gruppi socialmente svantaggiati.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo ritengo che il Fondo sociale europeo, da sempre il fondo di sostegno a favore delle persone svantaggiate, potrà fungere da complemento ai programmi di mobilità dell'Erasmus tramite la condivisione degli obiettivi comuni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059-0000" speaker_id="124867" name="Brando Benifei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Erasmus è certamente il programma europeo più conosciuto e di maggior successo, con migliaia di giovani che ogni anno decidono di partecipare, costruendo attivamente e progressivamente un pezzo importante dell'identità europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fondamentale è l'incremento di risorse che abbiamo stabilito. Ma in questi anni, nonostante tanta retorica sulla generazione Erasmus, troppi pochi ragazzi hanno avuto questa possibilità. Tra gli altri, i tanti giovani che non frequentano l'università.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo motivo sono particolarmente orgoglioso di aver contribuito in prima persona alla creazione di Erasmus Pro, nato come progetto pilota di noi europarlamentari, con l'obiettivo di estendere la logica di mobilità di Erasmus ai giovani in formazione professionale, creando 50 000 opportunità di mobilità per gli apprendisti, di una durata compresa tra i sei e i dodici mesi, per lo sviluppo delle loro competenze professionali trasversali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erasmus Pro permette a tante ragazze e tanti ragazzi, che si stanno inserendo nel mondo del lavoro, di vivere un'esperienza europea, di conoscere una nuova lingua e di arricchire il proprio bagaglio personale e professionale, facendo un'esperienza importante per completare la propria formazione in un altro paese.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un Erasmus più inclusivo significa un'Europa migliore per tutti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-061-0000" speaker_id="124893" name="Bogdan Andrzej Zdrojewski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Byłem posłem sprawozdawcą specjalnego aktu prawnego, który przyjęliśmy na poprzedniej sesji, tu, w Strasburgu. Chodziło o zabezpieczenie programu Erasmus+ na wypadek brexitu, brexitu w kształcie nieokreślonym, czyli z długim okresem przejściowym. Mówię o tym dlatego, że w czasie debaty, dyskusji pojawiły się też niepokoje dotyczące losów tego programu w przypadku brexitu bez umowy, jak również w przypadku brexitu z długim okresem przejściowym. Przypominam więc, że Parlament Europejski na poprzedniej sesji przyjął odpowiednie rozstrzygnięcie, rozstrzygnięcie prawne, zabezpieczające nas na te dwie ewentualności.</p>
      <p sl="en">Warto natomiast przy tej okazji powiedzieć – czy dopowiedzieć, że podobny krok musi uczynić oczywiście strona brytyjska. Natomiast dziś możemy powiedzieć, że Parlament Europejski jest lepiej przygotowany na scenariusze negatywne od londyńskiej Izby Gmin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-063-0000" speaker_id="124861" name="Caterina Chinnici" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il programma Erasmus rappresenta un importante strumento per lo sviluppo del senso comune di appartenenza europea attraverso l'educazione e la cultura e ha permesso a milioni di giovani cittadini di entrare in contatto con la società, la lingua e il sistema educativo di un altro Stato membro, favorendo l'acquisizione di competenze ma soprattutto offrendo occasioni di crescita personale e di apertura alla multiculturalità e all'integrazione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voglio pertanto esprimere il mio supporto al nuovo programma Erasmus+ che, nella proposta del Parlamento, risulta ancora più inclusivo ed accessibile ai giovani più svantaggiati. In tal senso considero positiva l'attenzione dedicata alle nuove tecnologie, ad esempio con l'introduzione della mobilità virtuale ai fini dell'apprendimento, quale strumento complementare ed integrativo della mobilità fisica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il mio auspicio è che il nuovo Erasmus+ venga adeguatamente supportato per consentire, a un numero sempre maggiore di giovani, nuove opportunità di crescita e per stimolare una loro crescente partecipazione nella società.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-064-0000" speaker_id="124794" name="Remo Sernagiotto" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, io vorrei ringraziare il relatore e tutti i colleghi che hanno lavorato a questo dossier. L'Erasmus è certamente il programma che ci inorgoglisce tutti a livello europeo, è il vero programma europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa è la grande sfida alla quale abbiamo lavorato insieme, su posizioni anche leggermente diverse, ma tutti con un unico obiettivo: l'Erasmus ci porta all'istruzione, alla formazione e allo sport.</p>
      <p sl="en">Anch'io credo che debba essere triplicato il budget, perché questo è lo strumento più importante che avremo nei prossimi anni. Lavoreremo su questo programma considerando l'obiettivo, non tanto l'investimento, in quanto quest’ultimo è secondario.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo noi riteniamo opportuno lavorare su questo programma come "programma Europa", il programma che ci dovrà riunire a prescindere dai conflitti che ci sono. Sarà questo il programma che ci aiuterà a riunire l'Europa che vogliamo e l'Europa che cercheremo anche per il futuro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-065-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Erasmus+ is well named because it’s a plus-plus or win-win for students and the European Union. In my home constituency, our great university, University College Cork, places students on Erasmus here in the University of Strasbourg every year, and every year over the last ten years, some of them come in to me on internships. They make a massive contribution. I have two at the minute – Nina and Alana. It’s wonderful for them, it’s wonderful for me and it’s wonderful for their education, especially learning language skills. I hope to continue doing that into the future if I’m re-elected.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s also very important that we look at expanding Erasmus, as has been said, and especially for those from disadvantaged backgrounds. That’s a real challenge for us, and it’s something we should really put every effort into. We should also be looking at a wider range of universities: technological universities, which are now coming onstream in my home country. They should definitely be more involved. Of course, as a sportsman myself, I think there are huge opportunities to expand it into sport, which would lead to best practice and indeed promote everything that’s good about European Union and sport.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-066-0000" speaker_id="183022" name="Lieve Wierinck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, Erasmus is een goed programma. Erasmus is eigenlijk Europa en wat Europa zou moeten uitdragen. Maar ik heb een vraag voor de commissaris en voor de Commissie: laten we in de toekomst Erasmus uitbreiden naar een Erasmus Med. De bedoeling is om artsen die al afgestudeerd zijn en in een specialisatiefase zitten aan een Erasmus-programma te laten deelnemen om dan stage te kunnen lopen in een gespecialiseerd centrum in een andere lidstaat om zo de gap die we nu hebben op volksgezondheid tussen de verschillende lidstaten te dichten door de best practices van andere lidstaten naar alle lidstaten over te dragen. We moeten daar ook de verpleegsters bij betrekken, verpleegsters die al werken, omdat niet alleen een operatie belangrijk is op dat ogenblik, maar ook de verzorging erna bepalend is voor de slaagkansen van de patiënt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-067-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the Erasmus programme is already responsible for millions of friendships, love affairs and even babies, as it has provided the means for young people to spread their wings and look beyond borders to learn more about themselves and others through immersion in formal and informal education with peers from across Europe. We all know about the Erasmus opportunities for students to study in universities outside their Member States, but few politicians seem to know about the extraordinary youth programmes that transform the lives of disadvantaged youth. For example, the people with learning difficulties from Headway Arts in Blyth, Northumberland, who’ve been exchanging ideas and best practices with European partners, growing in confidence as a result and achieving dignity when their own government threw them on the scrapheap. Another example are the autistic students from Inscape School in Stockport who returned from their Erasmus project to set up social enterprises, including a café. I met these young people and all are dismayed at the inward-looking direction of the UK Government who would deny them a European future. Young people will not forgive those who enable Brexit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-068-0000" speaker_id="124712" name="Andrea Bocskor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Úr! Először is gratulálni szeretnék Milan Zver kollégámnak a jelentéshez, nagyszerű munkát végzett. Az Erasmus Plus programot több millió fiatal európai ismeri és vett részt már benne, és a mostani, új program lehetőségeket nyújt, hogy több készséget és képességet, illetve nyelvtudást szerezzenek az új program révén. Az új Erasmus Plus program költségvetésének háromszoros növelése nagyon fontos számunkra azért, hogy minél többen vehessenek részt ebben a programban, a különböző mobilitásokban, és szintén fontos a program egyszerűbbé, hozzáférhetőbbé tétele, illetve a kisebb volumenű projektek támogatása, hatékonyabb támogatása is.</p>
      <p sl="en">Örülök annak, hogy az új program kiemelten foglalkozik a nyelvtanulással, a résztvevők online nyelvi támogatást kaphatnak, beleértve a nemzeti irányelveket is. A többnyelvűség támogatása nemcsak a nagy európai nyelvek tanulásának támogatását kell hogy célozza, hanem az őshonos kisebbségi nyelvek és a veszélyeztetett nyelvek többség általi megtanulását, illetve a szomszédos nyelvek megismerését is, ami jelentős impulzust adhat a határokon átnyúló kapcsolatok és projektek megerősítéséhez. Ösztönözném az ilyen jellegű pályázatokat, illetve felhívnám a figyelmet, hogy milyen fontos lenne a szakképzési programok megerősítése mellett a tehetséggondozásra is nagyobb figyelmet fordítani.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-069-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, doamnă comisar, stimați colegi, sigur, Erasmus este un program foarte cunoscut și foarte iubit în toate statele membre. Milioane de tineri au participat la acest program.</p>
      <p sl="en">Așa cum s-a spus aici, este nevoie și de o mărire a bugetului și, doamnă comisar, ne-ați dat vestea bună că se dublează. Dar ați văzut, aici a rezultat foarte clar din dezbateri, că nu este suficientă dublarea bugetului. Pentru că ar trebui acum să ne gândim cum putem să cuprindem cât mai multe categorii profesionale. S-a spus de medici și de asistenți medicali, dar cred că toate categoriile profesionale trebuie incluse. Pentru că avem o singură piață unică și avem această libertate de mișcare a lucrătorilor. Cred că trebuie să țintim zonele mai îndepărtate, zonele rurale și să găsim mijloace prin care să includem persoanele cu dizabilități. Nu este un procent corespunzător în programul Erasmus din punct de vedere al incluziunii și cred că aici trebuie să ne gândim pe viitor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu sper, doamnă comisar, că în noul cadru financiar veți lupta și dumneavoastră pentru un buget mai mare, pentru că, da, Erasmus trebuie să aducă efecte economice. Și aduce efecte economice dacă ne gândim la pregătirea profesională.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070-0000" speaker_id="119434" name="Dubravka Šuica" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, prije svega pozdravljam povjerenicu i drago mi je da i danas možemo ovdje potvrditi da je Erasmus+ jedan od najboljih i najuspješnijih programa Europske unije.</p>
      <p sl="en">Također se želim zahvaliti mome kolegi Zveru koji je napravio izvrsno izvješće, ali koji mi je ovog časa i rekao jedan podatak koji je vrlo interesantan, a to je da se je milijun novih beba rodilo temeljem projekta Erasmus+. Mislim da ne smijemo zaboraviti ni demografske razloge zašto podržavamo ovaj projekt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dakle, devet milijuna do sada je građana Europske unije, posebice mladih, sudjelovalo u ovom projektu, po novim pretpostavkama radi se o dvanaest milijuna građana koji bi mogli koristiti ovaj program. Naravno da vidim da želite udvostručiti sredstva. Ja mislim da ih treba utrostručiti i mislim da je dobro da se ova rasprava vodi prije nego što donesemo Višegodišnji financijski okvir.</p>
      <p sl="en">U svakom slučaju, ovaj projekt je uključiv, on potiče mobilnost, on potiče razmjenu, a prije svega je važno napomenuti pravičnost. Još jedanput, hvala gospodinu Zveru.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-071-0000" speaker_id="96812" name="Juan Fernando López Aguilar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, todos los intervinientes por unanimidad en este debate hemos exaltado las virtudes del programa Erasmus, uno de los activos, más preciados para la gente joven. Y creo que hemos hecho lo correcto al incrementar su potencia de fuego: 43 000 millones de euros en el escenario presupuestario 21-27 y ojalá pudiéramos hacerlo crecer más.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero ojalá fuésemos capaces también de comunicar a la gente joven que este Parlamento Europeo ha aprobado el cuerpo europeo del voluntariado y que la Unión Europea es un gigante mundial en ayuda humanitaria y en la causa de la paz; y que la Unión Europea es peso pesado en la cooperación al desarrollo y que, por tanto, hay un mensaje a la gente joven para movilizarse también en la defensa de los valores europeos, no solamente para el disfrute del programa Erasmus, sino para defender a Europa con el voto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hay unas elecciones europeas el próximo 26 de mayo. Ojalá fuésemos capaces de decirle a la gente joven que merece la pena movilizarse con todas sus fuerzas, tanto como lo hacen los eurófobos, para derrotar la eurofobia y el euroescepticismo en las urnas y defender en las urnas la causa de Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-073-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, your debate confirms the success of the Erasmus programme over the last 30 years. Erasmus has become indeed an iconic brand, symbolising the added value of the European integration project for our citizens. It contributes greatly to achieving the objectives of the first principle of the European Pillar, which is about access to education, training and lifelong learning. We agree with you that the programme can be and should be more accessible and inclusive, and this is why co-funding from other funds, such as ESF+, will be possible, also by doubling the budget we intend to triple the number of people participating in a learning experience abroad. Honourable Members of Parliament, this is not a trick. By boosting traditional mobility, by adding new and more flexible mobility formats, by optimising the grant levels, and by providing targeted financial incentives, we estimate that we can reach 12 million people from different backgrounds.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thank you for this rich discussion and for your support in achieving this goal, also in the name of my colleague, Tibor Navracsics. I’m certain that together we will make this programme bigger and even better than it is today, and that it has the budget to meet this ambition.</p>
      <p sl="en">To answer the question from Ms Wierinck, I can tell Ms Wierinck, and I will say it in Dutch.</p>
      <p sl="en">… dat het Erasmus-programma zeker toelaat voor artsen en verpleegkundigen als deel van hun opleiding om een deel van hun studie, maar ook hun stage in een andere lidstaat te doen bij een andere universiteit of opstellingsinstelling die deelneemt aan het Erasmus-programma.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-075-0000" speaker_id="96933" name="Milan Zver" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">poročevalec. – Spoštovani gospod predsedujoči.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dragi kolegi, hvala za to razpravo, v kateri ste mnogi poudarjali, da Erasmus+ vendarle gradi evropski identiteto. Nekateri so temu nasprotovali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ampak, vendarle bi rad poudaril, da Erasmus+ podpira tudi izoblikovanje osebne identitete, regionalne, tudi nacionalne in da se to z evropsko identiteto ne izključuje.</p>
      <p sl="en">V proračunu je Erasmus del poglavja z naslovom Vlaganje v ljudi. Verjamem, da je vlaganje v Erasmus vlaganje tudi v prihodnost Evrope, zato ob koncu ponovno pozivam Evropsko komisijo in države članice, da v trialogu podprejo trikratno povečanje proračuna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Države članice pogosto oklevajo, ko gre za višanje sredstev za evropske programe, še posebej, ko gre za tako imenovane mehke politike, kot so izobraževanje ali mladinske politike.</p>
      <p sl="en">A naj spomnim, da je Evropski svet lansko leto umestil program Erasmus+ med štiri glavne prioritete za obdobje po letu 2020, poleg varnosti, obrambe in migracij. Torej pozivam države članice, da ne pozabijo na to zavezo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zavedam se, da pogajanja s Komisijo in Svetom ne bodo lahka, gre za daleč največje povečanje sredstev za katerikoli program. Hvaležen pa sem vsem političnim skupinam, ki so podprle to naše skupno prizadevanje, zato verjamem, da bo pogajalec Evropskega parlamenta imel močan mandat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Idealno bi bilo, če bi trialog zaključili do konca leta 2019 ali vsaj v prvi polovici leta 2020, s čimer bi omogočili nemoten prehod s sedanjega na prihodnji dolgoročni proračun.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tako bi v letu 2021 omogočili odhod v tujino za skoraj milijon ljudi in nemoteno izvajanje 100.000 projektov.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-076-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się w czwartek 28 marca 2019 r.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-077-0000" speaker_id="96681" name="Vilija Blinkevičiūtė" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">raštu. – Europos Parlamentas palankiai vertina Komisijos pasiūlymą, ypač tai, kad buvo išlaikyta programos struktūra, kuri jau sėkmingai įsitvirtino ir gerai veikė dabartinėje programoje. Kai programos veikia gerai, pakeitimai turi būti orientuoti į tas sritis, kur jų išties reikia, to ir yra siekiama Komisijos pasiūlyme. Komisija ne tik išlaikė faktinę programos struktūrą, bet ir įtraukė kelias svarbiausias išvadas iš laikotarpio vidurio peržiūros bei 2017 m. vasario 2 d. Parlamento rezoliucijos. Iš pranešimų apie naują „Erasmus+“ pasiūlymą aiškiai matyti, kad naujoje programoje bus ypatingai pabrėžiama platesnė prieiga ir socialinės įtraukties stiprinimas. Pirma, reikalaujama, tik kad valstybės narės ir Komisija stiprintų pastangas, ir suteikiama galimybė koreguoti dotacijas. Todėl Parlamentas daugiau svarbos teikia įtraukties priemonėms, į teisinį tekstą įtraukdamas atskirą įtraukties skyrių ir reikalaudamas, kad valstybės narės parengtų įtraukties strategiją, grindžiamą tam tikrais galimais parametrais pagal Komisijos nustatytą sistemą. Jis taip pat aiškiai pateikia reikalavimą, kad Komisija ir valstybės narės teiktų finansinę paramą mažiau galimybių turintiems asmenims, kuriems dalyvauti Programoje trukdo jų nepalanki ekonominė padėtis arba tai, kad jų dalyvavimo išlaidos yra pernelyg didelės dėl jų konkrečios padėties.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078-0000" speaker_id="124887" name="Karol Karski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Program „Erasmus” zyskał wysokie uznanie i pozytywne opinie instytucji i organizacji oraz indywidualnych beneficjentów. Program ten sprawdził się i stał się jednym z flagowych programów UE, który współtworzy nowe pokolenie Europejczyków, wspomagając ich edukację i rozwój osobisty. Co roku tysiące studentów z całej Europy nabywa nowe kompetencje oraz poznaje kultury innych narodów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jednak nawet najlepszy program ma margines poprawy. Pojawiło się wiele wątpliwości w co do zarządzania programem, przejrzystości ogólnej struktury planu finansowego, gwarancji finansowych, uznawania kwalifikacji, przejrzystości oraz dostępności programu, jak również procedury naboru samych studentów. Troską nas wszystkich musi być wysoka jakość programu, jego efektywność i przejrzystość.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jeszcze długa droga przed nami, jednak cieszę się, że podczas negocjacji w dużej mierze udało się doprecyzować wiele niejasności oraz wprowadzić zmiany, które potencjalnie mogą program wzmocnić. Nowy program jest przede wszystkim ambitniejszy. Szczególnie cieszy mnie większy nakład budżetowy, objęcie zakresem programu osób o mniejszych szansach, ułatwienia administracyjne i uproszczenie kryteriów udzielania dofinansowania.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078-5000" speaker_id="96998" name="Evelyn Regner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – Erasmus+ ist eines der Erfolgsprogramme der EU, und das gilt es, auch anständig zu finanzieren. In den letzten Jahren konnten wir vier Millionen Menschen grenzenloses Lernen und Mobilität ermöglichen. Das müssen wir weiter ausbauen, und dafür fordern wir Sozialdemokraten und Sozialdemokratinnen eine Verdreifachung der Mittel. Erasmus+ darf aber kein Eliteprogramm sein. Studieren im Ausland muss unabhängig von der Geldbörse der Eltern möglich sein, Lehrlingsaustausche müssen weiter gefördert und ausgebaut werden, und der Zugang zu den Mitteln muss einfach und barrierefrei erfolgen. Zudem sollte das Informationsangebot insbesondere für Lehrlinge ausgebaut werden.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Establishment of a framework to facilitate sustainable investment (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-080-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dziennego jest sprawozdanie sporządzone przez Basa Eickhouta oraz Sirpę Pietikäinen w imieniu Komisji Gospodarczej i Monetarnej oraz Komisji Ochrony Środowiska Naturalnego, Zdrowia Publicznego i Bezpieczeństwa Żywności w sprawie wniosku dotyczącego rozporządzenia Parlamentu Europejskiego i Rady w sprawie ustanowienia ram ułatwiających zrównoważone inwestycje (COM(2018)0353 - C8-0207/2018 - 2018/0178(COD)) (A8-0175/2019).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-081-0000" speaker_id="96725" name="Bas Eickhout" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Mr President, my thanks to the Commission and to my colleagues for having worked on this file, for a while now, and for finally also having this moment of truth here in the plenary to get to a vote later on today. In principle, this file really is about putting the money where your mouth is. That’s basically what we’re doing with this file. I just want to remind all my colleagues who were always celebrating the Paris Agreement about how important it is that we – as Europe – are leading by example.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is also very important where we put our money. Where are the investments going? How do we ensure that our investments become Paris-proof? We are talking about shifting trillions of euros of investments here, and if we do that in the right way, we can help the financial sector and our industry to move to a green economy, which is the future. This is also being debated. We are debating at the Council level our zero—emission economy, a climate-neutral economy. If we want to get there, we need the right incentives; we need the right investments. We also need the right definitions, and that is exactly what is at stake here today.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, the taxonomy will describe and determine what a green investment is. Parliament is making some good proposals on really defining what a green investment is in order to prevent greenwashing. That is very important, because there are many green products on the market, but quite often we do not know exactly what their environmental impact is, what their green impact is. By adopting this taxonomy, we will put transparent standards on what green financing means, and that is very important to have.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, there are still some amendments on the table to make very clear what, in our mind, should not be considered a green investment. I will also ask my colleagues, are you really going to accept that later on an investment in coal can still be called green? While we are discussing the phasing out of coal in every country, any investment in coal cannot be seen as a green investment. This is just simple logic, and I hope that Parliament will follow that logic.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also have some other discussions to follow, because green investment is still a niche; it’s still a small part of the investments. The big part of the investments are not claiming to be green, but are still being done. Therefore, we deliberately opened up the discussion on defining when an activity is non—green.</p>
      <p sl="en">There has been a lot of lobbying out there really talking a lot of nonsense, as if we were forbidding activities; as if we were not giving a chance for industry to green. What we are doing is to show for every investment what the environmental impact is. If you have a downgrading of your impact, of course that should be highlighted, just like you highlight when you have a very positive green impact. It is not forbidding; it is not blacklisting; it is just providing transparency to the market. Hopefully, that will have an impact on the market, so that our finances will go from brown investments to more green investments. That is exactly what we need if we want to be Paris-proof.</p>
      <p sl="en">The last point that is on the table: if we talk about sustainable finance, it should not only be green, it should also be social. We are putting some proposals for minimum safeguards, but we know that it is very difficult for many people to accept. When we are talking about sustainable finance, you cannot avoid discussing what the social implications of sustainable finance are, and that too is on the table today. I am looking forward to a good discussion and, more importantly, a very good vote later today.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-082-0000" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Mr President, we have EUR 30 trillion in coal—risky and environmentally—risky stranded assets. EUR 30 trillion! That is millions of millions. That means that our pensions are threatened in the longer run if change is not made. It means that our economy is at risk and threat of a crises when change is going to come. And it means that our environment is under threat because we are investing in the wrong end of the economy.</p>
      <p sl="en">But then again, the good news is that EUR 30 trillion is a lot of money and as we have a clear indication what kind of investments are environmentally—friendly, sustainable and not causing significant harm in other fields, then we have plenty of money to turn the wheel and support environmentally—sustainable economies and investments. We need only EUR 180 billion every year to invest in combating climate change. So, we do have the money, but it is in the wrong place. The question is about transferring that money from economically and environmentally risky investments to more sustainable investments.</p>
      <p sl="en">There, we need a harmonised indicator so we really can compare industries to industries within a sector and between sectors. We need to define – and this is what this legislation is all about – the environmental requirements and, in the future, as a backstop, the social requirements that we consider to be sustainable. What that means is that in the case of palm oil, for example, you can’t focus on one issue like climate change and say this is a good investment if it causes significant harm in other fields of the environment like biodiversity in Indonesia and orang-utans. We know this to be the case with palm oil. And you couldn’t build a solar panel unit in a nature conservation area and claim it is green. And no, I don’t think that you could produce solar panels or any other green niceties with child labour. So the reference to significant environmental harm or other harm and the backstop makes consistent sense of how we understand and define sustainability.</p>
      <p sl="en">The financial sector is already much more advanced than setting green indicators and reporting mechanisms. For the majority of politicians in Member States – and let’s see what the figures are here, in the European Parliament – the issue is that now when we do not have a harmonised taxonomy they lose comparability, and the information they have does not have as big an impact as it should. But we, as politicians, shouldn’t perform worse than the markets are doing already. That brings us to some of the specific issues here in the file.</p>
      <p sl="en">First, coal. Frankly, with climate change, could you really call a coal investment a green investment? Put that question to yourselves. Second question, could you really call investments that follow only basic national legislation a green investment? My interpretation is that if you do not break the law you are not a criminal, but it does not mean that your activity would be green. So yes, there need to be some better standards that normal activity to be labelled green and sold as green investments.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is important that we get it right this time, because investors do need transparency, predictability and long-term guidance from this regulation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-083-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all, I would like to congratulate the rapporteurs, Mr Eickhout and Ms Pietikäinen, for taking on this file last year. I would like to thank you for your strong will and ambition, ensuring that the European Parliament could form its views quickly and effectively, which has led to this vote today.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you know, this file has raised some heated discussions between the committees, but this is why I welcome even more a strong commitment from the European Parliament to adopt this text. It will improve the ability of the financial sector to take part in the fight against climate change. It will deepen the single market for green financial services, and it will protect EU consumers from greenwashed financial products.</p>
      <p sl="en">You already know that in order to boost sustainable investment, we need a shared understanding of what sustainability entails. This is why creating an EU taxonomy is a cornerstone for our strategy. It fills an important gap because it establishes a common understanding of which economic activities can help reach climate and other environmental objectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">We heard time and again at the conference on a global approach to sustainable finance last Thursday, at which high-level representatives from many countries outside the EU, including China, Japan, India, Morocco and Hong Kong, were present, that in order to scale up sustainable investment, we need to start by having a common taxonomy. The high-level representatives are looking to the EU for that.</p>
      <p sl="en">Once complete, this taxonomy will help us develop labels for sustainable financial products or funds. It will support disclosure and reporting by financial institutions and companies on climate and environmental activities or risks and it will support standardisation, which is also necessary and called for by many jurisdictions.</p>
      <p sl="en">For example, if asset managers and institutional investors disclose how they have used the taxonomy in the design of their green products, this will help end investors compare products on how green they are. The taxonomy will also be one of the key elements in the upcoming EU green bond standard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, since financial markets are global, the EU will promote international convergence and alignment of those crucial tools to the extent possible. In practice, the taxonomy and its applications will have many advantages for companies and investors. Companies and project promoters will be better able to raise private capital to finance their sustainable activities. European companies will have a clear standard of what qualifies as sustainable for the purposes of raising finance. Polluting sectors will be encouraged to move onto more sustainable pathways by including activities that contribute to a reduction of emissions. The taxonomy will help them attract capital to finance this transition and financial companies looking to finance sustainable projects often say that there are too few investable projects and it’s too hard to search them out. The taxonomy will clarify this and help investors identify bankable and viable green projects, and it will also protect consumers from greenwashed products by providing clarity to end investors who are interested in sustainable investment, but currently have little information about what is sold to them.</p>
      <p sl="en">I believe that our European sustainable finance strategy can be a game changer, both for us and for other jurisdictions. By harmonising the way we classify sustainable investments, we can and will continue to be a front runner on sustainable finance globally.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will start with climate impact and then look at sustainability more broadly with a step-by-step approach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Honourable Members, right now we are at an historic juncture. We have one decade to mitigate the worst impact of climate change on our citizens, businesses and planet as a whole. Climate-focused policies are no longer optional but necessary, and we are refocusing our policies in this way across many sectors. So let us not miss this opportunity to ensure the financial sector is fully behind this shift and fully contributes towards a climate neutral economy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-084-0000" speaker_id="28257" name="Ivo Belet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de PPE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, duurzaam beleggen: inderdaad heel wat banken en financiële instellingen zijn er al mee bezig en de consumenten zijn altijd op zoek naar meer milieuvriendelijke financiële producten, maar vaak zien ze tussen de bomen het bos niet meer. Daarom is dit kader dat we hier vandaag gaan goedkeuren belangrijk. De wetgeving die we nu gaan goedkeuren, creëert een duidelijk kader voor welke investeringen als duurzaam, als milieuvriendelijk, klimaatvriendelijk kunnen worden bestempeld. En dat kan enkel als we duidelijk bijdragen aan milieu- en klimaatdoelstellingen zonder tegelijkertijd schade toe te brengen.</p>
      <p sl="en">We weten allemaal dat de komende jaren zeer grote investeringen zullen moeten worden gedaan om in een klimaatvriendelijke omgeving terecht te komen: in de staalsector, in de chemie, de cement, noem maar op. Ook in hernieuwbare energie, energie-efficiëntie. Met deze wetgeving krijgen investeringen in schone en duurzame technologie een heldere en een terechte steun in de rug. Dit is dus wel degelijk een belangrijke stap vooruit die een omwenteling in de financiële wereld op gang kan en zal brengen. U hebt, meneer de ondervoorzitter, terecht gesproken van een gamechanger. Ik denk dat dat duidelijk is. Niet alle ambities, meneer Eickhout, zitten in deze tekst, maar soms is het ook zo dat het goed is om de boot niet te vol te laden, want dat brengt soms ook ellende met zich mee. Dus een gamechanger en een belangrijke stap vooruit. Volgende stappen zullen ongetwijfeld volgen. Er is geen weg terug. Ook de financiële wereld is definitief de weg ingeslagen van een klimaatvriendelijke toekomst.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-085-0000" speaker_id="124814" name="Simona Bonafè" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo S&amp;D. – Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, parliamo sempre più spesso di lotta al cambiamento climatico, di transizione verso un'economia circolare e di nuovi modelli di sviluppo più sostenibili ambientalmente e più inclusivi socialmente. Parliamo, appunto, ma non basta parlare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per passare alle azioni, servono risorse, servono investimenti: investimenti per riconvertire le nostre industrie, per accompagnare i lavoratori verso nuove competenze, per realizzare infrastrutture, come quelle sulla mobilità e quelle digitali, innovative e sostenibili. Esiste un gap europeo di investimenti in tutti questi ambiti. 180 miliardi di euro l'anno per tenere fede ai soli accordi di Parigi e puntare su energie rinnovabili ed efficienza energetica, mentre sul fronte delle infrastrutture sociali si parla di 100-150 miliardi di euro l'anno necessari. Risorse che non possono essere soddisfatte dalle sole finanze pubbliche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Con questo regolamento possiamo orientare anche il mercato finanziario privato. Chi decide dove investire i propri soldi, che si parli del singolo cittadino o del grande investitore, deve avere informazioni attendibili e trasparenti sull'impatto ambientale e sul grado di sostenibilità delle attività economiche su cui vertono i prodotti finanziari. Cosa che oggi è quasi del tutto impossibile, a fronte della mancanza di un sistema di classificazione riconosciuto e riconoscibile in tutta Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oggi voteremo su un testo che è stato oggetto di mesi di appassionata e – devo dire anche – accesa discussione. Colleghi, io invito tutti a potenziarlo, sostenendo gli emendamenti presentati sull'ampliamento del campo di applicazione a tutti i prodotti finanziari, e non solo a quelli già green, e sulla necessità di declinare la sostenibilità in entrambe le dimensioni: quella sociale e quella ambientale. Non perdiamo l'occasione di dimostrare che questo Parlamento ha il coraggio di affrontare nuove sfide, non solo a parole, ma anche con i fatti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-086-0000" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Inicjatywa Komisji zmierzająca do ustalenia wspólnych zasad oceny zrównoważonych inwestycji jest oczywiście potrzebna. Konsumenci coraz chętniej sięgają po produkty o charakterze ekologicznym – żywność czy energię. Coraz bardziej interesuje ich wpływ produkcji dóbr, które kupują, na środowisko, na klimat czy też dobrostan zwierząt. Te ważne motywacje są nieraz wykorzystywane przez nieuczciwych producentów, dlatego zharmonizowane metody określania, jakie inwestycje są zrównoważone, mogą przynieść wymierne korzyści i ukrócić nieuczciwe praktyki.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uważam jednak, że do tematu trzeba podejść z pewną rozwagą, aby te ramy określania inwestycji zrównoważonych mogły funkcjonować w praktyce. Przede wszystkim nie ma sensu określanie, które inwestycje są złe dla środowiska. Mamy w Unii Europejskiej wiele regulacji prawnych ograniczających szkodliwość środowiskową działalności gospodarczej. Jeżeli ktoś nie łamie tych zasad, nie ma podstaw do karania go. Nagradzajmy raczej dobre praktyki.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poza tym na tym etapie nie ma sensu dodawanie oceny społecznej. Jestem jak najbardziej za sprawiedliwością społeczną i ochroną pracowników, ale na razie lepiej ograniczyć się do oceny środowiskowej, a dopiero po nabraniu doświadczenia zobaczyć, czy później będzie można ocenić wpływ na prawa pracowników. Wynik głosowania komisji ECON i ENVI stanowi wykonalne i zrównoważone rozwiązanie, unikające negatywnych elementów, które zagrażałyby pomyślnej realizacji zrównoważonych inwestycji. Zachęcam do rozwagi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-087-0000" speaker_id="183022" name="Lieve Wierinck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ALDE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, vandaag is een historische dag. Over enkele jaren kijken wij terug op deze stemming en zeggen we: dat was de dag waarop het Europees Parlement de basis voor een duurzame toekomst heeft gelegd. Dat was de dag waarop Europa het voortouw nam, en de standaard zette die de rest van de wereld vandaag nastreeft. Na meer dan een jaar onderhandelen ben ik ervan overtuigd dat er vandaag een meerderheid is voor een vooruitstrevende en evenwichtige tekst, een tekst die ons een vraag en antwoord op de vraag geeft: wat is duurzaamheid? Een antwoord dat de financiële wereld dringend nodig heeft om duurzame producten te maken. Financiële producten die binnenkort voor u, voor mij en voor elke andere Europeaan te koop zullen zijn. Natuurlijk kunnen we in de toekomst verder gaan. Ik nodig de Commissie uit om verder te onderzoeken hoe we kunnen bepalen wanneer een activiteit niet duurzaam is of concepten van sociale duurzaamheid te onderzoeken. Maar laten we beginnen met wat we vandaag hebben bereikt en dat is geen verhaal waarin we met de vinger wijzen, maar een positief verhaal, een inclusief verhaal waarin we niemand uitsluiten en elke industrie, elk bedrijf uitnodigen om de transitie te maken naar een duurzame toekomst. De toekomst van onze kinderen en kleinkinderen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-088-0000" speaker_id="124972" name="Ernest Urtasun" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo Verts/ALE. – Señor presidente, en primer lugar, quisiera felicitar a mi compañero Eickhout por su buen trabajo. Creo que en este Reglamento nos jugamos hacer realidad las declaraciones y las resoluciones que muchas veces votamos sobre el cambio climático. Sí, mover las inversiones hacia la transición ecológica y la sostenibilidad es fundamental; como decía Eickhout, mover los billones de euros que se mueven todos los días y que hacen avanzar y funcionar nuestra economía.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para ello, hay tres grandes objetivos: cambiar estas inversiones, moverlas hacia inversiones sostenibles; definir bien qué es y qué no es una inversión sostenible; y poner bajo estricto control climático al sector financiero.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y para ello hay algunas cosas que debemos hacer y que son muy importantes. En primer lugar, no solo regular las inversiones que ya son sostenibles, sino abarcar al conjunto del sector financiero, que yo creo que ha sido el esfuerzo que se ha hecho con este Reglamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">En segundo lugar, definir una lista de lo que no son inversiones sostenibles. Y coincido plenamente: no podemos incluir cuestiones como el carbón, como el gas de esquisto, como la cría intensiva de animales como inversiones sostenibles. Esto está fuera de cualquier lógica.</p>
      <p sl="en">En tercer lugar, también, tener una definición estricta de lo que es una inversión sostenible y no permitir un cierto greenwashing o que alguien pueda ponerle el sello de inversión sostenible a algo que no lo es.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y finalmente, cuando hablamos de inversiones sostenibles, no podemos olvidar la dimensión social, que es fundamental. Por ello, yo espero que, en la votación de hoy, también con las enmiendas presentadas, podamos tener un Reglamento ambicioso que haga realidad las promesas de lucha contra el cambio climático del Acuerdo de París, que muchas veces se expresan verbalmente en esta Cámara.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-089-0000" speaker_id="124863" name="Stefan Eck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Zunächst möchte ich mich bei den beiden Berichterstattern für die außergewöhnlich gute Arbeit bedanken. Liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, gegenwärtig gibt es viel zu wenig Möglichkeiten, unsoziale und insbesondere umweltschädliche Investitionen zu verhindern, und das in einer Zeit, in der es wirklich schlecht um die Umwelt bestellt ist. Es ist daher höchste Zeit gewesen sicherzustellen, dass der Finanzsektor in die Pflicht genommen wird, mehr auf Nachhaltigkeit zu achten. Und dabei dürfen wir nicht nur auf Freiwilligkeit setzen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Verbindliche EU-Rechtsvorschriften mit strengen und klaren Normen sind notwendig. Es ist daher dringend geboten, dass der Finanzsektor nur in Projekte und Geschäfte investiert, die eben zu keinen Schäden für die Umwelt oder für die Gesellschaft führen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unterstützen Sie bitte die Übernahme der EU-Indikatoren für soziale und umweltbezogene Faktoren in die bestehenden Finanzvorschriften! Das ist ein wichtiger Schritt, um zu gewährleisten, dass im Finanzsektor der Begriff Nachhaltigkeit nicht eine lapidare Floskel bleibt, sondern zukünftig ernster genommen wird.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-090-0000" speaker_id="103246" name="Auke Zijlstra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ENF-Fractie. – Voorzitter, vandaag bespreken we een verslag over duurzame beleggingen en een van de doelstellingen uit dat actieplan is, en ik citeer, "het heroriënteren van kapitaalstromen in de richting van duurzame beleggingen om zo duurzame en inclusieve groei te bewerkstelligen", einde citaat. Een hele mondvol om te zeggen dat de rapporteurs een tekort zien aan kapitaal voor duurzame investeringen. Dat is vreemd omdat de Europese Centrale Bank al jaren aan geldverruiming doet en de rente voor investeringen momenteel op een recordlaag niveau staat. Alles is al gedaan om de prikkel om te lenen voor investeringen te vergroten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dus waarom willen die investeringen dan niet ontstaan? Als we kijken naar de doelstellingen van dit beleid, van dit plan, is dat niet vreemd. Ik noem er drie: koolstofvoetafdruk, doelgroepenbeleid, sociale doelstellingen. Dat is geen investeringsprogramma. Dat is het partijprogramma van links. Waar is het rendement op investeringen? Dat is er niet. Dat worden dus fiscale maatregelen en dat worden dus subsidies. Schaarste drijft de markt. Een productieproces dat minder grondstoffen en minder energie gebruikt wint. Behalve als de overheid erin gaat zitten rommelen – jammer dat de rapporteurs dat niet geloven. Monetaire politiek heeft al tot brokken geleid, dit maakt het nog erger. Van dit programma worden we allemaal slechter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091-0000" speaker_id="1927" name="Peter Liese" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Die Finanzmärkte müssen einen Beitrag leisten, damit wir die Klimaziele erreichen. Dieser Beitrag muss auch darüber hinausgehen, dass man sich einfach nur an die bestehenden Gesetze hält. Es muss Anreize geben für Investoren, wenn Unternehmen über die bestehende Gesetzgebung hinausgehen. Und selbstverständlich müssen wir dafür sorgen, dass es kein Greenwashing gibt, dass man also nicht etwas als nachhaltig labelt, das es ist nicht wirklich ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber wir als EVP waren auch ein bischen vorsichtig jetzt zu viele Details zu regeln, denn wir möchten, dass sich dieser Markt entwickelt. Viele Finanzinvestoren achten sehr auf Nachhaltigkeit, und wenn wir es zu kompliziert machen, könnte das kontraproduktive Effekte haben, insbesondere weil ja auch sehr viele kleine Kreditinstitute dann mit dieser Gesetzgebung umgehen müssen. Deswegen haben wir uns für einen praktikablen Kompromiss eingesetzt. Ich bin sehr dankbar, dass der gemeinsame Ausschuss von ECON und ENVI ein aus unserer Sicht sehr gutes Ergebnis erzielt hat. Es würde mich freuen, wenn wir das gleich mit großer Mehrheit im Plenum beschließen. Dann haben wir einen praktikablen Weg, der die Richtung vorgibt, der aber wichtige, gute Ideen nicht im Keim erstickt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092-0000" speaker_id="124847" name="Elena Gentile" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ritengo questa premessa politica utile alla comprensione e dunque alla condivisione, non solo dei passaggi squisitamente regolamentari, dell'argomento che oggi ci appassiona e del quale discutiamo. Una visione politica d'insieme che il regolamento, con le puntualizzazioni contenute, potrà offrire ai cittadini europei, al sistema di impresa, a quella larga parte dell'opinione pubblica che percepiamo vicina all'idea che la bussola dello sviluppo debba essere sostenibile e, quindi, anche inclusiva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sullo sfondo, la lettura di quello che è stato il lavoro di questi anni. La parola d'ordine: rigenerare i luoghi della vita in uso al capitale umano, dentro la rinnovata attenzione alla sostenibilità, per contrastare ogni forma di insulto all'ecosistema e alla salute delle persone, per affermare l'idea che la povertà va contrastata, appunto, con scelte di visione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ci sembra dunque necessario connettere tra di loro le più importanti scelte politiche di questi anni: la visione di un'Europa più giusta, più equa, che contrasti le diseguaglianze, più attenta alla salute dei cittadini e dei lavoratori, che cresce rispettosa dell'ambiente e dei diritti sociali. Appunto, l'Europa dei diritti e delle pari opportunità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ecco perché per noi è importante cominciare sin da ora a piantare saldamente le radici per una tassonomia sociale. Penso che tra gli indicatori maggiormente rilevanti debba esserci l'esclusione dall'ambito degli investimenti delle attività incentrate sulla generazione di energia da combustibili fossili.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dunque, c'è una nuova consapevolezza in campo tra i cittadini, nel sistema d'impresa e tra i lavoratori. Questo è il tempo di una nuova responsabilità sociale della filiera della produzione e della finanza, altrettanto eticamente responsabile. C'è un cambiamento culturale in atto: va incoraggiato e sostenuto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-093-0000" speaker_id="195454" name="Ralph Packet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, de Groenen en de socialisten willen dat we hopen geld in Europa pompen om het te redden van de klimaatondergang en ze weten al heel goed waar ze dat geld gaan halen: bij de belastingbetaler, uit jullie zakken. Nog meer overheidsuitgaven, nog meer belastingen, voor ons is dat geen optie. We willen wel keihard inzetten op duurzame energie, we willen keihard inzetten op natuur, op de strijd tegen vervuiling, maar wij gaan dat doen op een veel efficiëntere manier. De energietransitie en de ecologische transitie zullen voor het grootste deel privaat gefinancierd moeten worden en daarom beginnen wij hier, bij de privésector, door aan beleggers en investeerders duidelijk te maken, door duidelijk te definiëren wat ecologisch duurzaam echt betekent, zodat ze daar bewust voor kunnen kiezen. Zo begeleiden we miljarden naar een groene economie. Want wat een groen label krijgt, moet ook echt groen zijn. Geen green washing, daar zorgen we hier voor. Het is een goede eerste stap in de groene richting, voor een bewuste en duurzame belegger en investeerder.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094-0000" speaker_id="96940" name="Gerben-Jan Gerbrandy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, in de zo belangrijke transitie naar een duurzame economie heeft natuurlijk de financiële sector de sleutel in handen. Want elke investering, hoe groot en klein ook, beïnvloedt de snelheid van die transitie positief en ook negatief. Om die reden is deze taxonomie zo belangrijk, want het bepaalt wanneer financiële producten ook echt duurzaam genoemd mogen worden. Maar we moeten natuurlijk verder gaan. Die ambities moeten echt omhoog. Wij mogen niet zwelgen in tevredenheid als 5, 10 of 15 % van de investeringen duurzaam is. Want als dat het geval is, hebben we nog altijd 95, 90, 85 % van de investeringen die niet duurzaam zijn. Dat is in mijn ogen dweilen met de kraan open.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarom vind ik ook dat de Europese Commissie naast de groene taxonomie ook werk moet maken van die bruine taxonomie. De Commissie, de Raad en zeker ook het conservatieve deel van dit Parlement moeten zich realiseren dat wij alleen Parijs kunnen halen, dat wij de doelen van een circulaire economie en al die andere duurzame doelstellingen die we onszelf zetten, alleen maar kunnen bereiken als wij de financiële sector weten te verduurzamen. Dat is het doel en daarom verwacht ik van de Europese Commissie in de toekomst ook echt veel meer ambitie op dit terrein.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095-0000" speaker_id="124986" name="Matt Carthy" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this report gives us an opportunity to define what is sustainable economic activity and what is not, and to consider the interaction between environmental goals and social protections. The attempts that we’ve heard here today by the right-wing groups in this House to limit the scope of this proposal and to limit its effect in shifting finance away from fossil fuels is shameful.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s report of last October was the starkest message yet of the impending climate catastrophe. The scientific consensus is that we have until 2030 to act to make rapid and far—reaching transitions in all areas of our economies if we are to limit global warming to 1.5° – that’s just 11 years away. Changing finance is one of the fastest and most effective ways to achieve this.</p>
      <p sl="en">The opposition that we’ve heard in this House to climate action is actually about protecting the profits of corporations and financial institutions above our future, and everyone knows it. The millions of schoolchildren who have been striking from school to march on the streets across Europe and around the world know it. They demand real action – not tokenism, not carbon taxes – real action, such as a 100% renewable energy by 2030. You call them idealistic, but actually they are the ones who are being realistic. We can’t compromise or negotiate with the laws of physics or chemistry. We can’t buy time, and there’ll be no profits for your corporate friends on a dead planet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-096-0000" speaker_id="2025" name="Françoise Grossetête" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Vice- président de la Commission, chers collègues, face à l’urgence climatique et afin de mettre en œuvre les accords de Paris, il est indispensable d’encourager le développement de la finance verte. Les besoins dans ce domaine sont exponentiels.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons un rapport d’Oxfam qui dit que les grandes banques françaises n’ont pas tenu leurs engagements pris dans le cadre de la COP 21. Il est temps de mettre la finance au service de la transition énergétique car elle constitue l’avenir de notre industrie. Cependant, il faut rester pragmatique et c’est pour cela que je ne souhaite pas que nous ayons une liste négative d’activités, qui serait par principe exclue du champ des investissements durables, parce qu’on peut prévoir aussi des investissements pour des améliorations de technologies existantes. De la même façon, orienter ces investissements uniquement vers les énergies renouvelables au détriment d’autres sources d’énergie à basses émissions de carbone serait une erreur. Revenir sur la neutralité technologique de notre texte reviendrait à hypothéquer l’avenir.</p>
      <p sl="en">Souvenons-nous que le mieux est souvent l’ennemi du bien. Je défends une vision plus ouverte de ce que pourrait être un investissement durable car une vision trop restrictive, trop idéaliste conduirait en réalité à limiter fortement la labellisation de ces investissements.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-097-0000" speaker_id="1985" name="Pervenche Berès" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, si nous voulons être cohérents dans la transition écologique, ce dossier est absolument essentiel, car la meilleure manière d’aller vers la transition écologique, c’est d’orienter les investissements. C’est l’outil le plus efficace pour garantir cette transition écologique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Or, ce que je constate, c’est qu’au pied du mur, trop souvent, ici et ailleurs, certains conservateurs et certains lobbies font de grandes déclarations en faveur de cette transition écologique et, lorsqu’il faut vraiment mettre en œuvre des outils concrets, ils reculent devant l’obstacle.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est pour cette raison que nous sommes déçus du résultat obtenu à l’issue des travaux de la commission de l’environnement et de la commission des affaires économiques et monétaires. Aussi, nous vous demandons de vous mobiliser pour corriger le tir et pour que, à travers le vote de cette plénière, nous puissions rétablir l’idée de catégories d’activités ayant une incidence négative importante pour l’environnement et rétablir l’idée que des aides aux combustibles fossiles solides ne sont pas possibles. Il n’y aura pas de transition écologique sans dimension sociale! Dans le cas contraire, la rue se retournera contre son bien commun. Cela ne peut pas être le message de cette assemblée.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-098-0000" speaker_id="125047" name="Paloma López Bermejo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, no habrá finanzas sostenibles sin compromiso con la justicia social y sin el control democrático de las inversiones.</p>
      <p sl="en">El informe del grupo de expertos aconsejó un enfoque global sobre las finanzas sostenibles que hacía referencia a la necesidad de criterios medioambientales, sociales y de gobernanza. La lucha contra la exclusión y la mejora de la calidad democrática en todos los ámbitos son una exigencia en la batalla del siglo: hacer que nuestro planeta siga siendo sostenible.</p>
      <p sl="en">En España el 70 % de la población se ve afectada por el cambio climático y el avance de la desertificación es el mayor desafío al que nos enfrentamos. La palabra que describe la situación en todo el planeta es emergencia. Tenemos apenas unos años para revertir esta tendencia suicida. Por eso las finanzas deben dejar de ser un estímulo para la destrucción del planeta. Si falta la ambición solo tendremos palabras que ofrecer. Y nuestros jóvenes, la sociedad, nos exigen hechos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-099-0000" speaker_id="28394" name="Dariusz Rosati" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Omawiamy dziś ważne sprawozdanie w sprawie ustanowienia ram ułatwiających finansowanie zrównoważonych inwestycji gospodarczych w Unii Europejskiej. Komisja Europejska przygotowała kryteria pozwalające ustalić, czy dana inwestycja przyczynia się do transformacji gospodarki europejskiej na rzecz realizacji celów środowiskowych i klimatycznych. Naszym zadaniem jest ambitna walka ze zmianą klimatu, dlatego popieram propozycję Komisji Europejskiej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jednocześnie jednak uważam, że podejście do zrównoważonego finansowania musi być realistyczne i opierać się na neutralności technologicznej. Zmniejszanie emisji gazów cieplarnianych powinno iść w parze z zachowaniem konkurencyjności europejskiego przemysłu. Powinniśmy brać pod uwagę jak najszerszy wachlarz technologii, które wspierają walkę z ociepleniem klimatycznym.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niestety, propozycja przedłożona przez sprawozdawców grozi wyeliminowaniem całego szeregu inwestycji, których celem jest zmniejszenie emisji CO2. Arbitralne wykluczenie niektórych technologii doprowadzi do sytuacji, w której zrównoważone finansowanie będzie dotyczyło bardzo wąskiej grupy inwestycji i nie wywoła efektu skali. Nie możemy poprzeć rozwiązań, które a priori i w sposób administracyjny wyłączają całe sektory przemysłu z dostępu do zrównoważonego finansowania.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uważam, że naszym zadaniem jest stworzyć zachęty i mobilizować przemysł do niskoemisyjnej działalności, a nie go karać. Stygmatyzowanie i karanie całych sektorów nie jest potrzebne. Kryteria wyboru zrównoważonych inwestycji muszą być obiektywne, proporcjonalne i oparte na badaniach naukowych, w tym rynkowych. Dlatego apeluję do wszystkich kolegów o przyjęcie sprawozdania w takim kształcie, w jakim zostało przegłosowane podczas posiedzenia połączonych komisji ECON i ENVI.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-100-0000" speaker_id="125020" name="Paul Tang" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this should be an important file, if the criteria set out in an initiative report on sustainable finance by this Parliament are met. Firstly, it needs to be broad in scope. It should apply to all financial products, not just to a small niche of green products. We need mainstreaming. If Europe cannot bring the financial sector in line with the Paris Agreement, who can?</p>
      <p sl="en">Second, we need a broad view. Sustainability is not about being green: it should also include tax compliance, human rights, and – speaking as a Social Democrat – a social dimension, so that the financial sector serves us and not the other way around. A law that lays down green standards for green products is, in a sense, not effective and is no progress. Amendment 87 on the scope, and Amendment 91 on the social dimension, are therefore key.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-101-0000" speaker_id="1917" name="Markus Ferber" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und liebe Kollegen! Die Taxonomie hätte eigentlich als erstes Dossier das Sustainable-Finance-Pakets sein müssen. Schließlich müssen wir erst mal wissen, worüber wir reden, bevor wir uns dann über weitere Details unterhalten. Aber wir haben mittlerweile ja schon Offenlegungspflichten und nachhaltige Benchmarks verabschiedet. Wir zäumen also das Pferd ein bisschen von hinten auf.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dass wir die Taxonomie erst als Letztes dieser drei Dossiers behandeln, ist mehr als unglücklich. Umso wichtiger ist es aber, dass das Taxonomie-Dossier gut wird und dass es gelingt. Wir haben im Ausschuss mit knapper Mehrheit eine Position gefunden, die angemessen und vernünftig ist. Andernfalls wird der Wandel zu mehr Nachhaltigkeit im Finanzwesen nicht gelingen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Am Markt gibt es natürlich Appetit für klare europäische Vorgaben und für Produkte. Aber es kann nicht unsere Aufgabe sein, nur Labeling zu machen, sondern es muss sich wirklich um nachhaltige Finanzprodukte handeln.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es kann aber auch nicht dazu führen, dass wir zum kompletten Umbau unseres Wirtschafts- und Gesellschaftssystems kommen. Finanzinstrumente sind nicht dazu da, die Gesellschaft umzubauen, sondern die Gesellschaft hat sich um die Finanzinstrumente zu kümmern, dann wird das Ganze richtig. Wenn wir das nach dem Motto machen: „Unsere Ziele können wir nirgends durchsetzen, dann machen wir es halt beim Finanzsystem“, wird das nicht erfolgreich sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deswegen bin ich für eine klare Taxonomie, einen klaren Fokus auf Nachhaltigkeit, keine Wirtschaftsbereiche grundsätzlich ausschließen und Freiwilligkeit. Dann wird es auch vom Markt und auch von den Kunden akzeptiert.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-103-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, congratulo a Sirpa e o Bas pelo excelente trabalho desenvolvido neste dossier. Harmonizar o investimento sustentável é trazer mais transparência e maior competitividade ao investimento dentro da União e não ficar sujeito a vinte e oito sistemas diferentes que só contribuem para fragmentar o mercado e para as assimetrias na Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Combater as alterações climáticas vai-nos custar dinheiro. Conseguir fazer com que a nuvem económica se desloque para poder regar as zonas verdes implica que assumamos na plenitude as diretrizes ecológicas em que a Europa está a apostar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se estamos orientados para descarbonizar a economia só podemos considerar atividades económicas sustentáveis aquelas que não contribuem para efeitos de dependência do carbono, nem produzem resíduos não renováveis ou prejudiciais ao ambiente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Queremos criar um ambiente favorável ao investimento verde e, por isso, a informação aos investidores tem que ser transparente em todos os negócios para que lhes seja possível exercer as suas preferências com toda a consciência e comprometimento que isso acarreta e é importante que se saiba quando estão a investir em negócios castanhos para que se lhes possa exigir as devidas responsabilidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">Caros Colegas, temos que ter a coragem de saber divergir quando a nossa consciência assim o dita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-104-0000" speaker_id="124963" name="Julie Ward" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is long overdue that environmental concerns take precedence over purely business—driven interests. Governments can no longer gamble with the future generation’s survival. Prosperity in the 21st century must go hand in hand with sustainability.</p>
      <p sl="en">I therefore urge this Parliament to take an ambitious stance for a genuine alignment between investment, sustainability and social impact. We must collectively operate structural changes regarding the legal standards that our businesses must uphold. We cannot satisfy ourselves with merely cosmetic measures. We must, first and foremost, provide support to the many initiatives aimed at alternative and sustainable business models, such as cooperatives. We must support, politically and financially, initiatives aimed at linking economy with human rights, workers’ rights, social justice, equity and sustainability, because that provides the way forward to achieving the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs). In that respect, I want to applaud the work of the civil society network, SDG Watch, who are scrutinising our work and will call out any backpedalling.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-105-0000" speaker_id="2278" name="Paul Rübig" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich glaube, dass dieses Dossier gerade für die nächsten Jahre von besonderer Bedeutung ist, wenn wir nehmen, dass die Ziele für nachhaltige Entwicklung ja auch eine globale Ausrichtung haben. So ist es ganz zentral, dass wir die Ziele Nr. 2, 6 und 7, nämlich nachhaltige Ernährung, Sanitärmaßnahmen, Wasser, Abwasser, aber auch erneuerbare Energien, in den Mittelpunkt stellen, dass wir schauen, dass vor allem die kleinen und mittleren Betriebe in dieser nachhaltigen Investitionskultur Anreize vorfinden, dass sie auch dementsprechend investieren, und dass wir natürlich auch gerade für die kleinen und mittleren Betriebe neue Jobs in diesen Bereichen schaffen, dass wir die Arbeit wieder nach Europa zurückholen. Für gut bezahlte, neue Aktivitäten ist es sinnvoll diesen Ansatz zu unterstützen. Und ich freue mich, dass das damit möglich wird.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-106-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule comisar, este un regulament extrem de important, dar, datorită faptului că este foarte important, Comisia are o sarcină foarte grea. În primul rând, trebuie să stabiliți acele criterii și trebuie să fim atenți cum stabilim. Foarte multă transparență și extrem de bine definit. Ce înseamnă durabilitate? Evident că investiții durabile trebuie să țină cont de cerințele de mediu, de cerințele sociale, de protejarea resurselor.</p>
      <p sl="en">În același timp, nu trebuie să blocheze - așa cum mai spuneau aici colegii - dezvoltarea IMM-urilor. Trebuie să vedem în ce context național, cum putem în anumite zone îndepărtate să nu avem același efect ca la Fondul european pentru investiții strategice, care s-a definit ca fiind un fond care vrea să dezvolte coeziune și să dezvolte zonele mai sărace și acum constatăm că s-au concentrat fondurile în cinci state membre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deci este extrem de important Comisia ce face cu aceste criterii. Evident că trebuie urmărite și - așa cum prevede și regulamentul - să faceți un raport prin care să arătați efectele acestui regulament, însă sunt îngrijorată, pentru că sunt anumite puncte în acest regulament care duc la blocarea investițiilor în anumite sectoare.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-108-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Valdis Dombrovskis" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to congratulate once again the co-rapporteurs for their work and dedication, and the shadow rapporteurs for their support in the negotiating of this file. I do hope that this Assembly will adopt this ambitious and balanced report, which will provide an excellent basis for further work among the co-legislators. I truly believe that this will be a key step towards making the financial sector work for the planet and for European citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-109-0000" speaker_id="96725" name="Bas Eickhout" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Mr President, I would like to thank all my colleagues for this good debate. Maybe the only point to make is that some colleagues said ‘well, it’s good what you’re doing, but don’t go too fast’. This is a very peculiar reasoning, because we signed the Paris Agreement and we need to be climate-neutral before 2050.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need investments in achieving that, and those investments are being made today. If we do not get our taxonomy right, we do not give the right signals to the market to shift the trillions from non-sustainable investments to sustainable investments. That needs to be done today. That is what we are talking about, and that is what is so crucial about the votes we are going to have. This is not about rocking a boat; this is about our future economy. Do we want the green jobs in our economy or not?</p>
      <p sl="en">Other regions are moving; we should do the same. As the Commissioner said, the taxonomy that we are putting in place here today will be a global standard. The rest of the world is watching us, so we need to get this right and we need to get this right today. That is why I plead once more with my Conservative colleagues to really look at a couple of these amendments, where we are making it very clear that when you look at investments, you should not only look at the green niche of the investment. You should look at the broader spectrum of the investments, and they all should go towards greening of our economy.</p>
      <p sl="en">As soon as an investment delivers on its sustainability performance, it will get a positive signal, and that is what this is about. This is not about forbidding activities; this is about steering the activities towards a green economy so that we can achieve the zero-emission, climate-neutral economy, which will provide the additional amount of jobs that the Commission showed in its analysis. That is what is at stake today. That is worth rocking a boat, ladies and gentlemen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-110-0000" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Mr President, the financial sector and investors are all on board already. They are willing to move, and they are willing to change the investment structure transparently so that it is more sustainable. Let us give them the right tools.</p>
      <p sl="en">You all know that the time span of the investment from the decision to invest on something, up to the building construction and up to the use, is tens of years. The worst thing we can do is give the wrong signal to investors – for example, ‘please let’s invest in coal and old—fashioned technologies, and label it as green’. We cannot go back to them after five to ten years, like it is with the 2030 targets on climate reduction, and say ‘look, we got it wrong, now we are changing the rules of the game once again’, and after five or ten years go back and say ‘look, actually, palm oil was a huge mistake, you shouldn’t invest in it’ – because the money and investment is already there.</p>
      <p sl="en">This means that we have to bear our responsibility. We have to set that kind of a taxonomy that takes other aspects other than just climate on board, that gives the right incentives and guidance for investors and that is reliable from the investment perspective for the upcoming 30 years. We owe this to investors, to our pensioners, and to future generations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-111-0000" speaker_id="23768" name="Przewodniczący" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Debata została zamknięta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie: pkt 8.7 protokołu z dnia 28.3.2019.</p>
      <a text="(Posiedzenie zostało zawieszone o godz. 11.41 w oczekiwaniu na głosowanie.)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Voting time">
    <intervention id="4-116-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The next item is the vote.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">(For the results and other details of the vote: see Minutes).</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Colleagues, it is 12.00. We are starting our voting session on time, as I said. I am not Italian, but I will try and be as fast as Mr Castaldo yesterday.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="8.1. Listing the third countries whose nationals must be in possession of visas when crossing the external borders and those whose nationals are exempt from that requirement (Kosovo) (A8-0261/2016 - Tanja Fajon)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="8.2. Quality of water intended for human consumption (A8-0288/2018 - Michel Dantin)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="8.3. Increasing the efficiency of restructuring, insolvency and discharge procedures (A8-0269/2018 - Angelika Niebler)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="8.4. Exercise of copyright and related rights applicable to certain online transmissions and retransmissions of television and radio programmes (A8-0378/2017 - Pavel Svoboda)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="8.5. Establishing the Creative Europe programme (2021 to 2027) (A8-0156/2019 - Silvia Costa)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="8.6. 'Erasmus': the Union programme for education, training, youth and sport (A8-0111/2019 - Milan Zver)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="8.7. Establishment of a framework to facilitate sustainable investment (A8-0175/2019 - Bas Eickhout, Sirpa Pietikäinen)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="8.8. Estimates of revenue and expenditure for the financial year 2020 – Section I – European Parliament (A8-0182/2019 - Vladimír Maňka)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="8.9. Emergency situation in Venezuela (RC-B8-0225/2019, B8-0225/2019, B8-0226/2019, B8-0227/2019, B8-0228/2019, B8-0229/2019)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="8.10. Situation of rule of law and fight against corruption in the EU, specifically in Malta and Slovakia (B8-0230/2019)  (vote)"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="8.11. Recent developments on the Dieselgate scandal (B8-0222/2019, RC-B8-0223/2019, B8-0223/2019, B8-0224/2019)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-129-0000" speaker_id="124779" name="Eleonora Evi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, volevo fare un richiamo al regolamento per verificare la votazione sull'emendamento 9, perché non mi è chiaro se lo abbiamo votato oppure no.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">We did vote on Amendment 9 and it was rejected.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="8.12. Decision establishing a European Peace Facility (A8-0157/2019 - Hilde Vautmans)  (vote)">
    <intervention id="4-132-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the vote.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133-0000" speaker_id="96674" name="Anna Maria Corazza Bildt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to ask you, and to ask colleagues, to condemn in the strongest way possible the attack by air strikes yesterday in Sana’a, Yemen, against a hospital where children, aid workers and civilians died. It was a hospital supported by Save the Children. It is in total breach of humanitarian law, international law and human rights. I will ask you, Madam President, to condemn the attack and to ask the coalition partners led by Saudi Arabia to respect international law. We cannot continue to turn our back on the plight of the people of Yemen, which is undergoing the worst humanitarian crisis in the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Thank you, Ms Corazza Bildt. The House appreciates your words and I will convey your message to the President.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="9. Explanations of vote">
    <intervention id="4-136-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">We will begin the explanations of votes in one minute.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">Voting time on Wednesday 27 March 2019</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="9.1. European Regional Development Fund and Cohesion Fund (A8-0094/2019 - Andrea Cozzolino)">
    <intervention id="4-139-0000" speaker_id="124835" name="Rosa D'Amato" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, esprimo la mia soddisfazione nell'aver approvato il regolamento sul Fondo europeo di sviluppo regionale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Siamo riusciti ad approvare un regolamento che è ambientalmente equo, che permette una concentrazione tematica a livello regionale e non a livello nazionale. Certo, non siamo stati così coraggiosi da riuscire a scorporare dal calcolo del deficit il cofinanziamento nazionale computato al Patto di stabilità. Sicuramente nel prossimo Parlamento europeo e nella prossima legislatura questa battaglia sarà riaperta.</p>
      <p sl="en">La soddisfazione maggiore è quella relativa all'articolo 6, poiché abbiamo finalmente impedito che ci siano investimenti con denaro pubblico nelle fonti fossili: abbiamo scongiurato di finanziare centrali termoelettriche, a gas metano e carbone e, quindi, anche di finanziare indirettamente il business dello smaltimento in discarica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ringrazio quindi i colleghi che hanno ascoltato i cittadini, che sono stati da noi allertati tramite una vera e propria petizione popolare. Finalmente il Fondo europeo di sviluppo regionale sarà utilizzato per uno sviluppo e per l'occupazione ecosostenibile.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-140-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">г-н Председател, през следващия програмен период Европейският фонд за регионално развитие и Кохезионният фонд трябва да се справят с редица предизвикателства, сред които изоставането на отдалечените и по-бедни региони на Съюза.</p>
      <p sl="en">В тази връзка социалната и икономическата криза през последните години, за съжаление, задълбочи още повече неравенствата между регионите. В тази връзка бих искал да акцентирам върху две важни направления. На първо място липсата на позоваване на култура или недостатъчно такова в законодателните текстове създава допълнителни пречки пред сектора за кандидатстване за европейски средства. Това от своя страна е проблематично, защото когато говорим за бедни, изоставащи региони в Съюза, трябва да имаме предвид, че една голяма част от тях разчитат основно на европейско финансиране.</p>
      <p sl="en">На второ място смятам, че бъдещата кохезионна политика трябва да създаде приоритет на справянето на демографската криза. Най-малко 5% от ресурса по линия на Фонда за регионално развитие трябва да бъде заделен за регионите, които са най-силно засегнати от процесите на обезлюдяване и застаряване на населението.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-141-0000" speaker_id="4555" name="Daniel Hannan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would like to use what may be my last ever intervention to thank you for the way in which you have briskly and efficiently chaired these votes over the years. It seems apt that my last intervention, like so many of the others, is about a plan to shovel around more taxpayers’ money in Europe. Almost nobody ever stands back and asks whether these cohesion and regional grants have any impact. If they did, then the major recipient regions would now be very wealthy, and we would have seen the spectacle of Greek taxpayers being asked to bail out Germany.</p>
      <p sl="en">The reason that they do not work is, first of all, because the money goes primarily to buy the loyalty of NGOs, local government associations and the like, in order to bind them into the European project. Secondly, because it creates perverse incentives – people find it easier to arrange their affairs to qualify for a pot of money, than to make things, sell things or create wealth. I’m not going to be here for much longer, so you do not need to listen to my advice for much longer, but if the EU carries on in this racket of just shuffling around taxpayers’ money, it will continue to dwindle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in order to improve the daily life of EU citizens we need a strong commitment in terms of cohesion policy. In Latvia we still have regions that experience a persistent lack of growth and massive emigration of young people. This is also valid for some urban areas. Unfortunately, world globalisation means that regions that are lagging stay even more behind the times. Therefore, in the EU, we need regional policies to support economic growth and employment. Like Latvia, many EU Member States would not be able to introduce modernisation results without these two EU funds that will make up 25% of the next MFF budget. I am proud that with this legislature, we managed to guarantee support for concrete sectors, such as the creation of new jobs in small and medium enterprises, digital connectivity, natural heritage, zero emission urban mobility, sustainable tourism and others. Of course I voted in favour, as I’m convinced that with this regulation we can bring Europe closer to the citizens.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="9.2. Reduction of the impact of certain plastic products on the environment (A8-0317/2018 - Frédérique Ries)">
    <intervention id="4-145-0000" speaker_id="24942" name="Ana Miranda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, avançar em restringir os produtos de plástico descartáveis conta com o meu voto a favor, porque as novas regras aprovadas no Parlamento Europeu proíbem certos produtos de plástico de utilização única para as quais existem alternativas, como pratos, talheres, cotonetes, palhinhas, agitadores de bebidas, barras para balões, recipientes para alimentos e bebidas, como esta garrafa de plástico, porque para estas garrafas de plástico há que assegurar a recolha seletiva de pelo menos 90% delas até 2029.</p>
      <p sl="en">Além disso, mais de 80% do lixo marinho da UE é constituído por plástico, sabemo-lo muito bem na Galiza. E os produtos de plástico descartáveis e as artes de pesca abrangidas por esta diretiva representam também 70% do lixo marinho, por isso há que ajudar também o setor pesqueiro para que faça essa recolha seletiva.</p>
      <p sl="en">Os resíduos que são encontradas em muitas espécies marinhas podem entrar na cadeia alimentar.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem24" title="9.3. Post-Arab Spring: way forward for the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) region (A8-0077/2019 - Brando Benifei)">
    <intervention id="4-148-0000" speaker_id="124927" name="Branislav Škripek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I was happy to support this motion designed to reduce racism. I think it should in no way be outdated in our European societies. Many of our African brothers and sisters were brought to Europe under awful situations. We cannot be proud of these thefts and dehumanising acts. For true reconciliation to take place, we must acknowledge these facts, apologise and if possible make restitution, then forgiveness between nations can bring these issues to an end. It is essential that this generation be colour blind. There is no one who shouldn’t be promoted or marginalised based on their skin colour. We are all fearfully and wonderfully made in the image of our greater God.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-149-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! W rezultacie arabskiej wiosny tak naprawdę to rząd musi bronić w Egipcie Koptów przed stałym zagrożeniem terrorystycznym. Tunezja, która jest wzorcowym sukcesem arabskiej wiosny, jest krajem, w którym też w międzynarodowych rankingach tolerancji religijnej widzimy ciągle problemy. Ale tych problemów nie ma w istocie rzeczy w naszym sprawozdaniu. Chrześcijanie nie zasługują na osobne wymienienie. Co więcej tak naprawdę biseksualiści są kimś bardziej zauważalnym dla Parlamentu Europejskiego niż Koptowie żyjący w stałym zagrożeniu terroryzmem, Koptowie, których kościoły płoną, jeżeli nie broni ich wojsko. To wszystko pokazuje, jak fikcyjne znaczenie ma zapis we wstępie do Traktatu o Unii Europejskiej o dziedzictwie religijnym Europy jako sile inspirującej naszą politykę.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-150-0000" speaker_id="23894" name="Anna Záborská" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca. Nemohla som včera hlasovať za uznesenie o situácii po Arabskej jari. Európska únia ani tento Parlament ako jej inštitúcia nemá právo vyzývať iné krajiny na liberalizáciu umelých potratov. Takéto odporúčania sú v prvom rade prejavom pokrytectva, pretože Únia nemá v tejto otázke žiadnu kompetenciu. Prístup jednotlivých členských štátov k tejto otázke sa výrazne líši. Požiadavka formulovaná v tomto uznesení nereprezentuje politiku Únie, pretože takáto politika jednoducho podľa zmlúv nemá existovať. Zároveň je nerozumné a krátkozraké žiadať zavádzanie umelých potratov v arabských krajinách. V tých drvivá väčšina občanov zásadne odmieta z hlboko zakorenených kultúrnych dôvodov. Európska únia tým oslabuje vlastnú pozíciu a uvoľňuje priestor iným svetovým hráčom, predovšetkým Číne.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem25" title="9.4. Listing the third countries whose nationals must be in possession of visas when crossing the external borders and those whose nationals are exempt from that requirement (Kosovo) (A8-0261/2016 - Tanja Fajon)">
    <intervention id="4-153-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">г-жо Председател, гласувах в подкрепа на идеята да отпаднат визите за Косово, защото съм убеден, вярвам, познавайки ситуацията там, че това ще спомогне първо за развитието на държавата Косово. Ще помогне на нейните граждани да имат по-тесни връзки с останалите държави от Европейския съюз, ще помогне за повишаване на тяхното качество на живот, на образование, търговски връзки, изобщо полезни неща, които биха направили по-стабилна тази част от региона на Западните Балкани.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem26" title="9.5. Quality of water intended for human consumption (A8-0288/2018 - Michel Dantin)">
    <intervention id="4-163-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in the United Kingdom, 2.4 billion litres of water every single day go to waste through leaks from the network – 432 million litres in my own region of the East Midlands. I am sure we would all agree that that is an unacceptable waste, bad for the environment and bad for people who are paying their water bills and paying for that wastage and leakage in ever—higher water bills.</p>
      <p sl="en">When this report is considered in interinstitutional negotiations in the next mandate, I call on the Commission, the Council and Parliament to ensure that the mandatory targets for the reduction of leakage remain part of this report. It is what we agreed in the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and food Safety (ENVI); it is what we agreed in this Parliament in October. We need the water industry to do far more to reduce that leakage so consumers get a fairer deal, and so that we reduce water wastage, which is bad for the environment, as well.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-164-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem nakonec podpořila zprávu pana poslance Dantina, která po dvaceti letech přináší revizi směrnice. Myslím, že tato revize je namístě. Přesto, že některé členské státy včetně České republiky měly na počátku jisté výhrady a požadovaly větší subsidiaritu, větší pravomoc členských států, výsledná podoba je přijatelná.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ve chvílích, kdy se i důsledkem změny klimatu stává pitná voda nedostatkem i na území Evropské unie, musíme si uvědomit její velkou hodnotu, tuto vodu ošetřovat, chránit a také zajistit dostupnost všem občanům.</p>
      <p sl="en">Souhlasím s panem zpravodajem s důrazem na subsidiaritu a rozhodování v členských státech v zásadních otázkách a oceňuji transparentnost, kterou tato zpráva, tedy přístup Evropského parlamentu, zdůrazňuje.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-165-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já velmi vítám tuto zprávu, protože téma pitné vody souvisí s klíčovými ekologickými tématy, které nemohou řešit jednotlivé členské státy, ale je třeba je řešit koncepčně na celém kontinentu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ta filozofická myšlenka této zprávy, když zvýšíme důvěryhodnost pitné vody, přimějeme, podpoříme, aby spotřebitel více využíval pitné vody z kohoutku, nikoliv pitné vody v balených plastových lahvích, tak ta myšlenka je podle mě velmi správná a může vést k tomu, že budeme tímto nepřímo regulovat množství plastového odpadu, který po vypití vody z plastu zkrátka objektivně zůstává.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takže zvýšení informovanosti o tom, jakou kvalitu má voda v kohoutcích, zvýšení tvrdosti podmínek pro to, aby pitná voda v kohoutcích opravdu byla kvalitní, to jsou myslím významná pozitivní proekologická opatření, která je nutno podpořit a která mohou vést v konečném důsledku k tomu, že budeme mít méně plastového odpadu u vody, kterou jinak občané nakupují v takto balené podobě. Takže zpráva jde dobrým směrem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-166-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca. Kvalita vody určená na ľudskú spotrebu je veľmi dôležitá téma a dotýka sa každodenného života všetkých obyvateľov. Prístup k pitnej vode vo svete je veľkým problémom. Na druhej strane my, ktorí máme kvalitnej vody dostatok, ju mnohokrát využívame neracionálne, plytváme ňou a znehodnocujeme ju. Štatistiky o znečisťovaní prírodných vodných zdrojov sú alarmujúce. Podporujem uznesenie a súhlasím, aby sa na úrovni Európskej únie určili minimálne požiadavky na kvalitu pitnej vody. Členské štáty a príslušné kontrolné orgány musia garantovať, že voda určená na ľudskú spotrebu neobsahuje žiadne mikroorganizmy, parazity ani iné látky, ktoré predstavujú vážnu hrozbu pre ľudské zdravie. Som veľmi rada, že v mojej krajine, na Slovensku, ideme vzorom a ochranu vody a pôdy sme legislatívne upravili ústavným zákonom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-167-0000" speaker_id="28116" name="Marian Harkin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, today we voted on our obligation to provide our citizens with water that’s fit to drink. But unfortunately, because of consistent failures by successive Irish governments to protect habitats in Special Areas of Conservation (SAC) that they themselves designated, we have a situation whereby 12 000 people on the Lough Talt scheme have a boil water notice in place for 12 months and are likely to have it in place for the next 12 to 18 months because of the presence of cryptosporidium and unacceptable levels of THM in their drinking water. This is a disgrace. It’s totally unacceptable that 13 000 people are paying the price for foot-dragging by successive governments. If proper safeguards had been put in place 15 years ago, there would be no need for further boil water notices.</p>
      <p sl="en">The pattern in Ireland is, if you’re an individual wanting to build a house, dig a drain or erect a fence in an SAC they come down on you like a ton of bricks. If you’re a state agency, the rules are ignored.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-168-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Thank you Marian, and indeed I applaud your words on that particular issue.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem27" title="9.6. Establishing the Creative Europe programme (2021 to 2027) (A8-0156/2019 - Silvia Costa)">
    <intervention id="4-189-0000" speaker_id="125013" name="Момчил Неков" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">г-жо Председател, „Творческа Европа“ е единствената по рода си програма в областта на културата и творческите индустрии в европейски план.</p>
      <p sl="en">За съжаление трябва да отбележим ниския процент на успеваемост на проектите, което се дължи на една причина - сериозен недостиг на финансиране по програмата. Липсата на адекватен бюджет и подкрепа за хората на културата създава усещане на разочарование сред тях и ги демотивира да кандидатстват повторно.</p>
      <p sl="en">Смятам, че в следващия програмен период трябва да се постараем да подобрим тази лоша репутация, с която се слави програмата сред културните среди. Трябва да покажем на творците в Европейския съюз, че техният труд си заслужава, като им осигурим необходимата финансова подкрепа и значително намалим бюрокрацията чрез опростяване на процедурите за кандидатстване по програмата.</p>
      <p sl="en">В това отношение напълно заставам зад това, че бюджета на „Творческа Европа“ трябва да бъде удвоен за следващата Многогодишна финансова рамка. За културата не бива да се говори само предизборно.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-190-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já považuji za úspěch to, že Evropský parlament přijal ještě v tomto mandátu svoji pozici k programu Kreativní Evropa. Kultura je naše společné bohatství, všichni to tak vnímáme a víme, že Evropská unie podporuje tvůrčí umění v členských státech.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já jsem také ráda, že zpráva Evropského parlamentu obsahuje některé pozměňovací návrhy, jako například podporu filmové výchovy, kterou jsem prosazovala. Nadále bude podpořena evropská cena LUX, tedy to je podpora evropských filmů, která zviditelňuje Evropskou unii, ale především zviditelňuje kvalitní filmy a hovoří o hodnotách Evropské unie, dostává je do regionů a mezi lidi. Myslím si, že to je ten správný cíl, správný program pro členské státy, pro umělce a je dobře, že jsme stihli odhlasovat navýšení tohoto programu.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem28" title="9.7. 'Erasmus': the Union programme for education, training, youth and sport (A8-0111/2019 - Milan Zver)">
    <intervention id="4-201-0000" speaker_id="190099" name="Rory Palmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I didn’t do Erasmus when I was at university, and I wish I had. I really, really want Erasmus opportunities to be available to young people from all backgrounds in the UK into the future. And how appalling is it: here we are, almost three years on from the referendum, and the UK Government has failed – failed to negotiate, failed to give any clarity or certainty that the UK will continue to be part of the Erasmus programme in the future. Young people that I listen to across the East Midlands region are furious about how their futures are being compromised, how their rights and opportunities are being short-changed by this government’s failure of these past two years or so. If we get to the point of the question of Brexit being put back to the people, it is therefore fair and appropriate and right that those young people, including 16 and 17 year olds, get to have their say.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-202-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, program Erasmus je snad nejviditelnějším, nejúspěšnějším programem, finančním nástrojem, kterým Evropská unie podporuje své cíle zaměstnanosti, v tomto případě vzdělání, které k té zaměstnanosti velmi přispívá.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jsme ráda, že Evropský parlament se zasadil a navrhuje dokonce ztrojnásobení rozpočtu, tedy i ztrojnásobení účastníků, jak už tady bylo zmíněno na 12 milionů EUR v tom příštím finančním období.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chtěla bych v této chvíli zdůraznit, že ten program není jenom pro žáky, učitele na území Evropské unie, ale také pro země, které přistupují, a také pro země, které my považujeme za naše země partnerské, a já jsem právě dnes obdržela důležitou informaci od Evropské komise, že také Turecko nadále má velký zájem spolupracovat a zúčastnit se v těchto programech. Pro budování demokracie, občanské společnosti v Turecku to považuji za velmi důležitou informaci a je dobře, že se budou moci i nadále zúčastnit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-203-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Erasmus + is a life-changing initiative and it can certainly be called an EU success. But this is a success only for 3.7% of young Europeans who benefit from Erasmus. I ask myself, what is your proposal for the remaining 96.3%? Erasmus was never thought to be an elitist project, but it turned out that people from lower socio-economic backgrounds are often left outside. This has also been the case of Latvia, so I wish that Erasmus + becomes more democratic and easily accessible. We need to diversify the profiles of applicants, we need to reduce the bureaucracy and we need to carefully observe how professional excellence is generated. I support the rapporteur Zver in his call to triple Erasmus funding, compared with the Commission proposal to double it. I’m following the process closely and I hope the delay in negotiations will not jeopardise the result.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-204-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca. Program Erasmus+ považujem za jeden z najvýznamnejších a najlepších programov, ktoré EÚ má. Aj preto je aj môj podpis pod pozmeňujúcim návrhom, aby sa rozpočet pre Erasmus+ výrazne navýšil. Za tridsať rokov svojej existencie pozitívne ovplyvnil viac ako 9 miliónov občanov EÚ, predovšetkým mladých ľudí. Je to skoro dvojnásobok, ako má Slovensko, moja krajina, obyvateľov. Erasmus dáva každoročne možnosť mladým ľudom kontaktovať sa s rovesníkmi z iných členských štátov a okrem získania jazykových zručností a odborných vedomostí, spoznávania iných kultúr je aj skutočným mostom do Európy. Dôležité je, aby sme o jeho úspechoch viac hovorili. Aby sme ho mladým ľuďom, pedagógom ešte viac priblížili, lebo je to program, ktorý podporuje idey spoločnej Európy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-205-0000" speaker_id="96824" name="Monica Macovei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, cercetarea, inovația sunt singurele care aduc progresul pentru fiecare țară în parte și pentru Uniune și pentru fiecare individ și comunitate. Inteligența, creativitatea, toate puse la muncă, toate împreună, uneori național, uneori transfrontalier, sunt cele care ne duc înainte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Asta se vede și la vot. Oamenii needucați, oamenii care nu circulă, care nu studiază, care nu au contact cu alții din alte țări nu vor vota un partid democratic și nu vor înțelege ce e democrația și nu vor reacționa la măsuri antidemocratice.</p>
      <p sl="en">De aceea, programul Erasmus+ este unul fantastic. El a învățat până acum peste nouă milioane de tineri, care au învățat în străinătate, au învățat fie la școală, fie au învățat să practice o meserie, iar în România în 2007, până în primii ani după 2007 au fost 35 000 de beneficiari. Acum avem peste 250 000 de beneficiari. Aceasta este … (Președinta a retras cuvântul vorbitoarei)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-206-0000" speaker_id="192298" name="Dobromir Sośnierz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Gdy mowa o potrzebie podnoszenia podatków, zawsze pojawiają się te same argumenty: że potrzeba na drogi, szpitale, szkoły … Nawet podczas tej sesji gdy debatowaliśmy nad potrzebą harmonizacji podatków i metodami wyciśnięcia z gospodarki jeszcze większej ilości pieniędzy i wytrząśnięcia kieszeni chciwym kapitalistom, słyszałem znowu te same łzawe argumenty: że potrzebujemy na drogi, na biedne dzieci itd., itd. Ale jakoś nigdy nie mówicie, że mogłoby zabraknąć pieniędzy na studentów, którzy mają kaprys jeździć sobie studiować do innego kraju, albo na organizacje pozarządowe w krajach trzecich, które chcemy utrzymywać, na rozrzucanie pieniędzy po świecie, na spłacanie długów nieostrożnych przedsiębiorców (żeby wymienić tylko dorobek tej sesji). Zawsze jeśli brakuje pieniędzy na drogi, na bezpieczeństwo, na szpitale, to dlatego że trwonimy je właśnie na takie głupie programy jak „Erasmus” i że pozwalamy dla kaprysu jeździć studentom z jednego kraju studiować w innym kraju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-207-0000" speaker_id="28228" name="Albert Deß" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! In meiner Jugendzeit gab es kein Erasmus-Programm, aber ich durfte bereits 1963 an einem einwöchigen Schülertreffen hier in Straßburg teilnehmen. Das hat mich politisch geprägt. Und ich habe damals festgestellt: Bei der Jugend hat die deutsch-französische Aussöhnung begonnen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wenn jetzt gefordert wird, dass wir dieses Programm auf das Dreifache aufstocken, dann unterstütze ich das gerne – auch wenn es uns Agrarpolitiker vielleicht ein paar Millionen kostet. Aber ich bin der Meinung, das Geld ist gut angelegt. Wir sollten aber darauf achten, dass nicht nur die akademische Jugend an dem Programm teilnimmt, sondern auch die jungen Handwerker, die jungen Landwirte, da es hier auch wichtig ist, andere Länder kennenzulernen. Und ich finde, dass dieses Programm eines der besten Programme für die europäische Jugend ist. Deshalb unterstütze ich es gerne.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem29" title="9.8. Emergency situation in Venezuela (RC-B8-0225/2019, B8-0225/2019, B8-0226/2019, B8-0227/2019, B8-0228/2019, B8-0229/2019)">
    <intervention id="4-229-0000" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław Piotrowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! We wspólnej rezolucji Parlament nasz stwierdza, że Wenezuela znajduje się w głębokim i bezprecedensowym kryzysie politycznym, gospodarczym, instytucjonalnym, społecznym i humanitarnym. W kraju tym brakuje lekarstw i żywności, prawa człowieka są łamane na masową skalę. 78 % dzieci w Wenezueli grozi niedożywienie, a na tysiąc dzieci 31 nie dożywa wieku pięciu lat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sytuacja jest tragiczna, wzywamy więc państwa członkowskie, wiceprzewodniczącą Komisji / wysoką przedstawiciel Unii do spraw zagranicznych i polityki bezpieczeństwa oraz kraje regionu do zbadania możliwości ustanowienia międzynarodowej konferencji darczyńców w celu zapewnienia szerokiego wsparcia finansowego na rzecz odbudowy i przemian demokratycznych w tym kraju. Dlatego też głosowałem za przyjęciem tej rezolucji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-230-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, já jsem podpořil tuto rezoluci, ale nepodpořil jsem pozměňovací návrhy, zvláště navržené levicí, sociálními demokraty, které mají hodně obecný charakter a které hovoří pouze o mírovém řešení situace ve Venezuele. Aktuálně nyní v tuto chvíli Rusko posílilo svoji vojenskou přítomnost v regionu. Sto ruských námořníků je ve Venezuele a je zjevné, že pouze mírovými proklamacemi tu tragickou situaci, která se táhne měsíce, dnes zkrátka nevyřešíme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takže já prosím Komisi, aby na základě tohoto usnesení Parlamentu vyhodnotila aktuální situaci ve Venezuele, aby reagovala na to, že Rusko poslalo své vojáky, námořníky do této země, abychom byli schopni reagovat aktivněji a tvrději, než pouze proklamacemi, které sice mají významný morální charakter, ale jak se ukázalo v minulosti, jedná se o opakované proklamace a usnesení Evropského parlamentu, které bohužel k ničemu nepřispěly a se samotným Madurem nic neudělaly. Maduro diktátor, nedemokratický socialista, který ničí tuto zemi, asi pouze usneseními nebude svržen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-231-0000" speaker_id="125101" name="José Inácio Faria" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, votei favoravelmente esta resolução sobre a Venezuela porque, quase sessenta dias depois de termos aprovado nesta casa uma outra sobre este martirizado país, da qual também fui um dos subscritores, a repressão intensificou-se. Os coletivos armados continuam a atacar com absoluta impunidade a população civil, deputados e o próprio Presidente Guaidó, sequestrando, inclusive, o seu chefe de gabinete, Roberto Marrero.</p>
      <p sl="en">A ajuda humanitária continua bloqueada nas fronteiras e milhares de venezuelanos voltam a despertar desde há três dias sem eletricidade, escurecendo ainda mais o seu sombrio quotidiano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Depois de ontem a Comissão ter anunciado o reforço da ajuda humanitária em 50 milhões de euros, esta casa, o que devemos fazer, dizer ao Sr. Maduro, é o que certamente milhares de venezuelanos repetirão depois de amanhã na nova toma de Caracas. O seu regime, de facto, está encurralado e não há amigos castristas, especialistas militares ou baterias antiaéreas russas que impeçam o seu crescente isolamento internacional.</p>
      <p sl="en">A sua permanência ilegítima no Palácio de Miraflores apenas significa mais mortos, mais presos, mais perseguição e mais compatriotas seus forçados a emigrar para fugir da fome e da miséria.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem30" title="9.9. Recent developments on the Dieselgate scandal (B8-0222/2019, RC-B8-0223/2019, B8-0223/2019, B8-0224/2019)">
    <intervention id="4-245-0000" speaker_id="28341" name="Mirosław Piotrowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Głosowałem przeciwko rezolucji autorstwa socjalistów, liberałów, Nordyckiej Zielonej Lewicy i innych, ponieważ po jej odrzuceniu mieliśmy głosować nad naszą rezolucją, grupy ECR, a także PPE. W naszej rezolucji znalazły się istotne stwierdzenia, których brak w tej pierwszej. Już w punkcie pierwszym podkreśliliśmy, że od wybuchu „Dieselgate” poczyniono znaczne postępy w unijnych programach prawodawczych. Kluczowym jednak dla wielu użytkowników Diesla w Europie był punkt dziewiąty, w którym zauważamy z niepokojem, że niektóre państwa członkowskie lub ich władze lokalne wprowadziły niewspółmierne środki, takie jak ograniczenia dotyczące starszych pojazdów z silnikiem Diesla, co utrudnia życie codzienne właścicieli takich pojazdów, obniża wartość tych pojazdów, a w państwach o niższych dochodach zwiększa popyt na pojazdy starsze i silnie zanieczyszczające. Szkoda, że nie głosowaliśmy właśnie nad tym sprawozdaniem.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem31" title="10. Corrections to votes and voting intentions : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem32" title="11. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem33" title="12. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem34" title="13. Major interpellations (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-263-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die große Anfrage zur schriftlichen Beantwortung mit Aussprache von Daniel Buda, Theodor Dumitru Stolojan, Marian-Jean Marinescu, Adina-Ioana Vălean, Cristian-Silviu Buşoi, Mihai Ţurcanu, Csaba Sógor, Siegfried Mureşan, Emil Radev, Milan Zver, Romana Tomc, Ivana Maletić, Michaela Šojdrová, Marijana Petir, Dubravka Šuica, Danuta Jazłowiecka, Krzysztof Hetman, Franc Bogovič, Anna Záborská, Željana Zovko, Marek Plura, Dariusz Rosati, Tamás Deutsch, Kinga Gál, Norbert Erdős, László Tőkés, Andrea Bocskor, András Gyürk, György Schöpflin, Andor Deli, Pál Csáky, Vladimir Urutchev, Michał Boni, Lívia Járóka, Andrey Kovatchev, Asim Ademov, Stanislav Polčák, Eva Maydell, Ivica Tolić, Alojz Peterle an die Kommission: Verstöße gegen die Rechte von Kindern, deren Eltern in Österreich beschäftigt sind (G-000001/2019 - B8-0018/2019).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-264-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Domnule președinte, mulțumesc, doamnă comisar, pentru prezența dumneavoastră astăzi aici în vederea dezbaterii unui subiect extrem de important pentru întreaga Uniune Europeană. Parlamentul de la Viena a adoptat anul trecut o lege prin care alocațiile copiilor lucrătorilor străini, care nu trăiesc împreună cu părinții lor în Austria, au fost ajustate în funcție de costul vieții din țările în care își au rezidența. Această măsură implică o diminuare substanțială pentru alocațiile copiilor din estul Europei începând cu 1 ianuarie 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">Legislația adoptată încalcă însă regulamentele Uniunii Europene privind coordonarea sistemelor de securitate socială. Acestea prevăd norme comune ale plății prestațiilor familiale pentru lucrătorii încadrați în muncă în alt stat membru. Lucrătorii mobili - și aici subliniez - lucrătorii mobili au dreptul la aceleași alocații pentru copii, la fel ca lucrătorii locali, indiferent de locul de reședință al copiilor lor. Tratatul interzice orice formă de discriminare, directă sau indirectă, a lucrătorilor, pe motiv de cetățenie. Muncitorii europeni trebuie să beneficieze de aceleași drepturi, iar Comisia Europeană nu poate tolera acțiuni discriminatorii, care afectează ideea de unitate, solidaritate la nivel european, acțiuni care contribuie din plin la agravarea sentimentului că în Uniunea Europeană ar putea exista cetățeni de rangul I și de rangul II.</p>
      <p sl="en">Subliniem faptul că discutăm de copiii celor care au contracte de muncă legal încheiate și plătesc taxe și impozite statului austriac, copii care stau departe de părinții lor, pe care îi văd doar de Paști sau de Crăciun, care nu au parte de sărutul părintesc de noapte bună și care nu au parte de acea creștere și educare părintească atât de necesară. Este cinic cum unele guverne aleg să lovească în interesele celor mai slabi și fără apărare, respectiv în copii.</p>
      <p sl="en">În acest context, doamnă comisar, care sunt măsurile pe care Comisia Europeană le va lua în acest caz? Și cum va proceda pentru gestionarea în timp util a acestei probleme?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-265-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank Parliament for this opportunity to clarify the Commission’s position on the legislation adopted in Austria that provides for indexation of family benefits and family tax reductions when the children concerned reside abroad. For me, the discussion is about fairness and equal treatment. You have heard me say before that there are no second-class workers in the Union and I’ve always insisted on equal pay for equal work at the same place. We ensured this key principle when we revised the rules for posted workers. Equal treatment also means equal benefits.</p>
      <p sl="en">When mobile workers contribute to a social security and tax system in the same way as local workers do, they should receive the same benefits, regardless of where the children live abroad. There should be no second class workers, but also no second class children. Under the European Social Security Regulation, European citizens that work in another Member State and contribute just like local workers are entitled to the same social security benefits and tax advantages. The Commission considers that any adjustment mechanism for family benefits and family tax credits for children of migrant workers who are residing in another Member State are not compatible with our acquis. Such indexation mechanisms go against the principle of equal treatment set out in Regulation 883 on social security coordination. It also goes against Article 7 of that Regulation, which expressly states that cash benefits cannot be reduced or modified merely because family members reside in other Member States. It also breaches the principle of equal treatment as regards social and fiscal advantages laid down in the Free Movement Regulation – the principle of equal treatment that is also at the heart of the single market.</p>
      <p sl="en">You know that some Member States asked to introduce indexation of child benefits when we launched a revision of the European Union social security regulations. But we refused to propose such indexation, based on our strong belief that mobility needs to be based on fair rules. That has remained the Commission’s position throughout the negotiations on the proposed modernisation of social security rules on which we reached a political agreement last week – an agreement that, I can assure you, is a balanced agreement, built on the shared understanding that European rules should safeguard free movement and protect citizens’ rights by strengthening the tools to address possible fraud or abuse. An agreement that still has to be confirmed by Coreper next Friday, so tomorrow, and also of course by Parliament in the coming weeks.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards the legislation introduced in Austria since 1 January, you know that the Commission has already launched an infringement procedure. We sent a letter of formal notice to the Austrian Government on 25 January. This Monday we received a reply from the Austrian Government and we are now in the process of analysing this reply before we can decide on the appropriate next step.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can assure you that we take this situation seriously, as indeed many families are directly affected by this Austrian law and have seen their benefits reduced. I have to add, however, that in order to preserve their rights, the citizens concerned should be prepared to claim their rights before the Austrian administration and, if necessary, start court proceedings. National courts are bound to apply European law and they are the only ones that can offer citizens direct redress when their rights are not respected. As in other infringement cases, I am confident that the Commission’s actions will result in the correct and effective application of European law in all Member States. That is indeed what citizens and businesses and also Member States expect from us in a single market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-266-0000" speaker_id="125706" name="Jiří Pospíšil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Pane předsedající, paní komisařko, vyzývám Komisi, abyste v této věci byli naprosto nekompromisní. Není možné zavírat oči nad tím, když některý z členských států porušuje základní principy evropského práva, principy volného pohybu osob a principy rovného zacházení. Tady nejde pouze o to, že jsou takto diskriminováni Evropané, občané jiných států Evropské unie, kteří v Rakousku pracují a kteří tedy platí daně v Rakousku a mají tedy logické i morální práva na stejné sociální výhody. Ale je to velmi nebezpečný precedent, který kdybychom nechali být, začneme rozbíjet vnitřní trh Evropské unie a zničíme myšlenky, na kterých stojí evropská integrace. A to je mimořádně nebezpečné.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takže velmi děkuji za to, že vnímáte tento rakouský populistický návrh jako nepřijatelný, a moc prosím o to, aby Evropská komise zde učinila vše pro to, aby Rakousko sjednalo nápravu. Bylo to jasně řečeno, občané Evropské unie, kteří pracují v Rakousku a odvádějí daně a sociální odvody v Rakousku jako Rakušané, mají logicky stejné právo na sociální výhody jako Rakušané. Je to princip evropské integrace a my nemůžeme posuzovat ekonomické rozdíly jednotlivých členských států, bourat princip evropské solidarity a tvrdit, že když někdo má své děti v zemi, kde jsou sociální příspěvky nižší, tak má dostávat nižší příspěvky, když platí poplatky stejné v Rakousku jako Rakušané.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takže myslím si, že to je jasné z hlediska principiálního, je to jasné z hlediska morálního a já moc prosím, vyvarujme se toho. Podobnou debatu jsme vedli před rokem ve vztahu k Velké Británii, která uvažovala o podobné právní úpravě, tady bohužel brexit otázku Velké Británie vyřešil, ale pokud bychom zde zavírali oči a jiné země přistupovaly k takovým populistickým opatřením, jak jsem naznačil, můžeme tím evropskou integraci mimořádně ohrozit. A škoda nebude jen u těch občanů, ale v celé Evropské unii.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-267-0000" speaker_id="190799" name="Michael Detjen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Die österreichische Regierung handelt grundfalsch, wenn sie EU-Bürgerinnen und Bürgern in Österreich das Kindergeld kürzt. Die Regierung bricht damit auch EU-Recht: das Recht der Gleichbehandlung: Alle Beschäftigten, egal welcher Herkunft, haben, wenn sie in die Sozial- und Steuersysteme einzahlen, auch die gleichen Rechte und die gleichen Rechte auf Leistungen. Die Anpassung des Kindergelds an die Kosten im Wohnortstaat ist zutiefst ungerecht. Es ist schon bizarr, dass im selben Augenblick die österreichische Regierung Diplomaten Ausnahmeregelungen zuteil werden lässt, während der normale Österreicher, der Kinder im Ausland hat, andere Regelungen hinnehmen muss.</p>
      <p sl="en">Als Sozialdemokraten stehen wir fest zum Grundsatz der Gleichbehandlung. Gleichbehandlung und das Verbot von Diskriminierung – das ist das starke Fundament Europas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich kenne die Debatte aus Deutschland. Dabei ist unser Standpunkt klar: Nicht die Freizügigkeit ist das Problem, sondern Missbrauch in Einzelfällen. Es gibt tatsächlich auch bandenmäßig organisierten Missbrauch. Hier muss der Staat aktiv werden – das ist er in Deutschland auch geworden. In Deutschland haben Familienkassen, Jobcenter in Verbund mit Ausländerbehörde und Zoll angefangen, stärker zu kontrollieren. Das ist auch der richtige Weg, dem Missbrauch Einhalt zu gebieten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gegen Beschäftigungsverhältnisse, die zum Schein bestehen, damit Kindergelder bei der Familienkasse beantragt werden, wird aktiv hervorgegangen. Leistungsansprüche aber, die EU-Bürger an ihre wirtschaftlichen Aktivitäten knüpfen, können nicht gekürzt oder gar gestrichen werden. Wir brauchen keine solchen Maßnahmen, wir brauchen ein Europa, das sozial absichert. Mein Appell an die Kommission: Prüfen Sie ganz genau, ob die von der österreichischen Regierung eingeführte Indexierung des Kindergeldes dem Gleichbehandlungsprinzip entspricht.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-268-0000" speaker_id="124892" name="Marek Jurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Działania podjęte przez Austrię przeciwko uprawnieniom rodzinnym zagranicznych pracowników oczywiście naruszają powszechnie obowiązujące zasady i dobrze, że w tej kwestii wszyscy się zgadzamy. Ale są również wyrazem filozofii, z którą bardzo często się spotykamy, a która przejawiła się na przykład w tej skandalicznej antywęgierskiej akcji przewodniczącego Verhofstadta. To jest traktowanie Europy jako grupy państw, z których jedne robią łaskę innym i gwarantują im jakieś specjalne prawa. A przecież Europa jest organizmem, który musi być świadomy swoich wzajemnych powiązań.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dzięki temu, że Polska i inne kraje Europy Środkowej walczyły o wolność w czasach dominacji sowieckiej w środkowej Europie, dzisiaj kraje Europy Zachodniej korzystają z bezpieczeństwa i mogą znacznie mniej wydawać na obronę, a pieniądze przeznaczyć na inwestycje, politykę społeczną i inne budżetowe potrzeby. Co więcej, wszystkie dane pokazują, że nasi zachodnioeuropejscy sąsiedzi skorzystali na wspólnym rynku. Rynek jest otwarty. Znosiliśmy już bardzo ciężkie rygory systemu stowarzyszeniowego i warto wreszcie uświadomić sobie, że owszem w budżecie są ci, którzy być może są beneficjentami netto, ale korzyści z otwartego rynku są obopólne, więc nie traktujmy części Europejczyków jako tych, którzy mają być … (Przewodniczący odebrał mówcy głos)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-269-0000" speaker_id="124754" name="Ivan Jakovčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">u ime kluba ALDE. – Poštovani predsjedavajući, moram reći da sam vrlo zadovoljan stavom koji je iznijela povjerenica. Vaš optimizam i vaše namjere ulijevaju povjerenje i vjerujem da Komisija i vi zaista želite učiniti ono što je jedino ispravno i jedino pravedno, a to je da imamo zajedničku koordiniranu socijalnu politiku, da imamo solidarnost u Europskoj uniji i da, naravno, oni koji plaćaju poreze, radnici koji plaćaju poreze u pojedinim državama imaju ista prava. To je postulat i našega, na kraju krajeva, jedinstvenoga tržišta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato vjerujem da je ova inicijativa koja je došla iz EPP-a, da budemo jasni, a istovremeno EPP ima vlast u Austriji, ali znamo s kime još, s koalicijskim partnerom s kojim će upravo sada poslije mene govoriti. Malo mi je žao da ne govorim ja poslije njega, ali želim vrlo jasno reći: i moj tata je radio u Austriji, i moj tata je sudjelovao i pomogao rast u Austriji kao vinski inženjer u Kremsu i znam što to znači kada je netko gastarbajter u Austriji. Moja mama je Austrijanka i zato me čudi ovakvo ponašanje Austrije, jer znam koliko solidarnosti i poštenja u toj Austriji ima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vjerujem da će na kraju ipak pobijediti oni koji žele bolju i sigurniju Europu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-270-0000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz Obermayr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ENF-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Es geht in der Tat um Indexierung der Familienbeihilfe, wie sie jetzt in Österreich andiskutiert worden ist und offensichtlich zu einem Mahnschreiben der Kommission geführt hat. Es ist im Kern ja richtig, das Prinzip der Gleichbehandlung einzuhalten oder ins Auge zu fassen. Doch offensichtlich lässt dabei die Kommission das Prinzip, dass Ungleiches eben nicht gleich behandelt werden darf, völlig außer Acht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und das passiert und ich möchte das anhand eines Beispiels festhalten: Wenn zum Beispiel einem rumänischen Arbeitnehmer für ein Kind, das in Rumänien zu Hause ist und lebt und für das damit wesentlich niedrigere Lebenshaltungskosten anfallen, der gleiche Betrag ausgezahlt wird, als würde ein Kind in Österreich mit wesentlich höheren Lebenshaltungskosten leben. Das stark unterschiedliche Niveau, das Preisniveau, diese Lebenshaltungskosten rechtfertigen durchaus eine an das jeweilige Land des Wohnorts angepasste Indexierung. Somit handelt es sich bei dieser Indexierung nicht um Einsparungen, nicht um Kürzungen oder Entzug, sondern um Anpassung an die jeweiligen Lebenshaltungskosten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich kann ja gerne Beispiele geben: Allein in den letzten fünfzehn Jahren sind diese Ansprüche für Kinder, die im EU-Ausland leben, von 1500 auf 130 000 angestiegen, also hat sich diese Summe der beziehenden Personen verhundertfacht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich darf Ihnen auch ein Beispiel Rumänien-Österreich geben: Rumänien: ein Weißbrot, ein halbes Kilo 50 Cent – Österreich 1,83 Euro; lokaler Käse 0,47 Cent gegenüber 1,08 Euro in Österreich; Rindfleisch 6,11 Eurogegenüber circa 19,96 Euro. Das geht so weit, dass man festhalten kann, dass ein durchschnittliches Kindergeld in Österreich, ausbezahlt mit 135 Euro, ein Viertel eines Durchschnittseinkommens in Rumänien ausmacht. Also diese unterschiedliche Situation ist bitte mit vollen Respekt zu beachten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und abschließend noch ein Wort zum Thema Gleichbehandlung. Wenn 2019 der Herr Tusk dem Herrn Cameron eine Notbremse dahingehend versprochen hat, die Sozialleistungen der Union für kurze Zeit auszusetzen, wo zu auch das Kindergeld und viele andere Leistungen gehört hätten, dann frage ich mich, warum, wenn das die Kommission selber Herrn Cameron angeboten hätte, um einen Brexit zu verhindern, selbiges offensichtlich für Österreich nicht gilt? Das ist Ungleichbehandlung.</p>
      <a text="(Der Redner ist damit einverstanden, eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ gemäß Artikel 162 Absatz 8 der Geschäftsordnung zu beantworten.)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-271-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Întrebare adresată conform procedurii „cartonașului albastru”. – Domnule președinte, stimate coleg, v-aș întreba un lucru foarte clar. Sunteți conștient de faptul că legislația adoptată în Austria încalcă regulamentele europene? Sau să înțeleg că ați ieșit afară din Uniunea Europeană? Înțelegeți că acei copii care trăiesc în România au nevoie de o compensație financiară ca urmare a lipsei îngrijirii părintelui în mod direct, sau nu?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-272-0000" speaker_id="96981" name="Franz Obermayr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Antwort auf eine Frage nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“. – Ich bin über diese sogenannte Frage – eher eine Feststellung – sehr froh, denn dann kann ich auch dementsprechend antworten. Was Sie offensichtlich nicht wissen, ist, dass bei uns die Arbeitgeber auch zu einem Topf, dem sogenannten Familienlastenausgleichsfonds, beitragen und in ihn einzahlen. Und das ist dieser Topf, aus dem auch diese Kinderbeihilfe bezahlt wird. Es ist also nicht wie in anderen Ländern eine Sozialversicherungsleistung, sondern einfach eine Familienleistung, aus einem anderen Topf gespeist. Und das muss man auch einmal wissen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-273-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pane předsedající, já jsem velmi ráda, že kolega Buda inicioval tuto ústní otázku, protože on zde nehovoří jenom za rumunské rodiče, rumunské děti. Já myslím, že tady jde o princip, a ten musíme hájit, ať se jedná o Rakousko, Českou republiku nebo kteroukoliv jinou zemi Evropské unie, protože pokud bychom se tvářili, že se nic neděje, že kterákoliv země může přijmout zákon, který je v rozporu s legislativou Evropské unie, ba přímo s principy a zásadami, tak to by byla opravdu cesta k rozpadu Evropské unie a to tady nikdo nechce.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já moc děkuji za odpověď paní komisařce, je zřejmé, že Komise si je vědoma tohoto problému, víme také, že Rakousko, rakouští poslanci prosazovali indexaci právě při změně legislativy ohledně koordinace sociálních systémů, zdá se, že tato změna nebude přijata, a tudíž Rakousko bude muset respektovat tu společnou zásadu a společnou legislativu. Rakousko je země bohatá, s poměrně štědrým sociálním systémem, ale já bych chtěla reagovat na to, že každý pracovník nejenom, že má děti, které potřebují určitou péči, ale mohou za ním jezdit do Rakouska, čili jim se zvyšují náklady. Mohou s rodiči bydlet v Rakousku, a to vůbec není v tom návrhu zohledněno. Navíc jde o to, že odvádí naprosto stejné daně, naprosto stejné odvody, takže pokud by mělo dojít k indexaci těch výdajů na děti, pak by muselo zřejmě dojít i k indexaci odvodů, to znamená daní a k tomu Rakousko nepřikročilo. Myslím si, že Rakousko bude muset respektovat, tak jako by každá jiná země musela respektovat, pravidla Evropské unie. A děkuji tedy paní komisařce za to, že prosazuje tento přístup.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-274-0000" speaker_id="124746" name="Andrejs Mamikins" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I’m surprised that some tried to justify the practice of child benefits indexation, which constitutes a breach of the treaties. To understand how absurd it seems to the majority of this House, it’s enough to say that more than 40 amendments on indexation were tabled to the new regulation on the coordination of social security systems and, even with the support of three shadow rapporteurs – Sven Schulze, Helga Stevens and Marian Harkin – none of them got through. Mobile workers are entitled to the same child allowances as local workers. The principle of free movement implies that paying social contributions gives the right to equal benefits, whatever the nationality of the worker. This has just been stated by the honourable Commissioner and this has been confirmed by the EU Court of Justice. But since we still need further arguments, let me give you some. The disrespect for equality in cross-border transfer of child allowances is one of the reasons that brought about Brexit. How can we afford to let the Austrian welfare system get out of the equality balance with other Member States? Moreover, child benefits is only one element of social allowances, together with unemployment, sickness benefits, family benefits – indexation means violation of reciprocity among Member States in all these aspects. I urge the Member States to approve tomorrow in the Council the deal they reached last week.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-275-0000" speaker_id="112753" name="Jozo Radoš" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, gospođo povjerenice, kolegice i kolege, najprije bih zahvalio gospodinu Budi na pokretanju ove inicijative, kao i ostalim kolegama. Radi se o temeljnom načelu, a to je da radnici u Europskoj uniji trebaju imati jednake obaveze i jednaka prava. Dakle, ovdje se ne radi o tome da to nije odluka koja počiva na solidarnosti, nego ta odluka krši načelo jednakosti građana Europske unije pred institucijama država članica, krši načela zajedničkog tržišta i, ako hoćete, krši i načelo slobodnog izbora mjesta i načina života.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pozdravljam vrlo jasan stav Komisije u tom pogledu. Povjerenica je najavila i mogućnost da građani podnose tužbe pred austrijskim sudovima, ali puno bi bilo efikasnije da se Komisija snažno angažira, i za građane, ali i za austrijsko pravosuđe, da Komisija ima snažni angažman u ovom postupku koji je otvorila jer vrlo jasno je rečeno: ne radi se samo o povredi načela, radi se i o povredi europskog prava, Uredbe o koordinaciji sustava socijalne sigurnosti i, jednako tako, pravila o upućenim radnicima.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dakle, mimo solidarnosti, mimo načela, ovdje se radi o kršenju europskih zakona i zato očekujem snažan angažman Komisije protiv Republike Austrije zbog kršenja europskog zakona.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-276-0000" speaker_id="96655" name="Monika Smolková" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážený pán predsedajúci. Aj ja chcem poďakovať pani komisárke za jej úvodné slová. Už tri mesiace trvá v Európskej únii stav, keď sa v jednom členskom štáte nedodržiavajú spoločné pravidlá voľného pohybu osôb. Od januára tohto roku sa Rakúsko rozhodlo rozdeliť občanov EÚ, pracujúcich na jeho území, do dvoch kategórií. Na tých, ktorí majú právo na plný podiel zo sociálneho zabezpečenia, a na tých, ktorým je toto právo obmedzované. Napriek tomu, že Európska únia formálne nepozná druhotriednych pracovníkov, ako uviedla aj pani komisárka, jednej členskej krajine sa takýto stav zatiaľ toleruje. Ak pracovníci odvádzajú do sociálneho systému rovnaké odvody ako ich susedia, ale dostávajú z neho pomerne nižší podiel, môžeme tu hovoriť o spravodlivom jednotnom trhu? Domnievam sa, že nemôžeme. Preto vítam, že Komisia začala konanie pre nesplnenie povinnosti voči Rakúsku a rovnako považujem za nesmierne dôležité, aby sme sa k tejto veci pravidelne vracali aj na pôde Európskeho parlamentu. Pretože v prípade, ak by komisia nebola schopná proti tomuto stavu zasiahnuť, riskujeme dôveryhodnosť európskeho projektu a jeho zakladajúcich princípov. Obávam sa totiž, že tento prípad by mohol pre ďalšie krajiny slúžiť ako neprijateľná inšpirácia. Pani komisárka, verím, že spôsob indexácie rodinných dávok v Rakúsku sa nestane precedensom. Súhlasím s Vami, že náš jednotný trh má byť založený na spravodlivom a rovnakom zaobchádzaní. Bude však dôležité, aby sa tento prístup odrazil aj pri vytváraní európskej legislatívy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-278-0000" speaker_id="28292" name="Inés Ayala Sender" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, muchas gracias por darme la oportunidad de intervenir. Solamente quería plantearle al señor Obermayr — puesto que no iba a pedir una segunda tarjeta azul— si estaría de acuerdo en que los jubilados austriacos que viven, por ejemplo, en el sur de Europa, en España, también percibieran pensiones de acuerdo con las pensiones que percibimos en España y, por lo tanto —mira qué bien—, el Gobierno austriaco se ahorraría todas las pensiones de los jubilados austriacos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo creo que, si ese principio, seguramente, le parece a usted completamente fuera de lugar, de la misma manera, lo que está haciendo su Gobierno con los niños que tienen derecho a asignación por el trabajo de sus padres y por las cotizaciones debería quedarle claro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y a la señora Thyssen, quisiera solamente preguntarle por qué la Comisión no puede abrir directamente procedimientos de infracción ante esta situación. Yo creo que es de las cosas más duras que hacen perder la confianza en la Unión Europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-280-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Marianne Thyssen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, this debate has touched upon the essentials of the single market and EU citizenship. As regards the Austrian legislation, the Commission now needs to analyse the reply of the Austrian Government that we received this Monday, and we can only decide upon any further steps after having carefully assessed the arguments put forward, as we always do. But let me recap. First of all, for me, this is a question of fairness and equal treatment. The issue that we have in front of us is not one of social dumping, it is not a situation prone to abuse or fraud: we are indeed talking of European citizens who took up a job abroad and provide their skills in a host country where they are contributing to the social security system and to the tax system. Equal treatment and fairness demand that these workers receive the same benefits as local workers regardless of where their children are living. The fact that their children are living in a Member State with a lower cost of living than the Member State of work should not be relevant for the benefit that is paid out as a lump sum and that is not linked to the actual expense of maintaining a child. I am well aware of the peculiarities of certain national systems whereby employers finance a large part of the benefits. Let me just recall that in such systems, employers pay the same amount of contributions for their employees, regardless of the nationality or place of residence of the children in question. I’m also aware of the content of what we called a couple of years ago the UK settlement agreement, but, as you all know, this ceased to exist. It was foreseen in the agreement that if the outcome of the referendum were to leave the European Union, then this agreement would be null and void.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allow me also to ask the question: if you open the door to indexation for child benefits, then what would be the next candidate for adjustment of benefits on the basis of living costs? Allow Member States to reduce pension rights when workers retire to States where it is cheaper to live, as Ms Ayala Sender said? Some people say we have concerns about fraud and abuse and I share all those concerns, but then I have to say that indexation is not the answer. On the contrary, you are hitting those people who get up in the morning, work hard and make a real contribution to the Member State of work. In order to fight abuses and fraud, we need to strengthen the tools for national authorities to control and obtain information from their counterparts abroad, and that this why we have created the European Labour Authority. That is also why we strengthened the cooperation requirements for Member States when revising the European social security rules, strengthening cooperation between Member States while also avoiding excessive control measures based on distrust.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, mobility needs to be based on clear, fair and enforceable rules. These rules benefit Austrians, Slovaks, Germans, Belgians and all the other European citizens alike by protecting their social rights when they are on the move. I thank you for the support of the action that I have been taking in this area and on which we have been able to reach an important political agreement that will improve the situation for our citizens’ families and businesses. Together with some members who mentioned this agreement on which Coreper has to decide tomorrow, I hope together with you that this deal will be accepted by the Member States, and of course after that also by the European Parliament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-281-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 162)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-281-5000" speaker_id="96781" name="Danuta Jazłowiecka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Przez ostatnie lata na sali plenarnej prowadziliśmy dyskusje na temat konieczności zbudowania Europy sprawiedliwej społecznie. Wielu kolegów podkreślało, jak ważna jest ochrona praw pracowników i poprawa warunków pracy. Spieraliśmy się na temat wprowadzenia zasady „tej samej płacy za tę samą pracę w tym samym miejscu”, za którą opowiadało się wielu eurodeputowanych.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlatego tak bardzo dziwi fakt, że w krajach, które niosą na swych sztandarach hasła ochrony praw pracowników mobilnych, pojawiają się pomysły wprowadzenia indeksacji świadczeń na dzieci. Jest to niezgodne z prawem unijnym oraz z wartościami głoszonymi przez te kraje. Austria poszła o krok dalej i, nie bacząc na przepisy europejskie, wprowadziła indeksację z dniem 1 stycznia 2019 roku. Tym samym Austria podzieliła pracowników i ich dzieci na dwie kategorie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Takie działanie jest niedopuszczalne i chciałabym dzisiaj głośno przeciwko takiej polityce zaprotestować. Protestuję w imieniu tych osób, które skorzystały z mobilności, pracują za granicą, budują PKB i płacą takie same podatki i składki jak ich koledzy. Protestuję w imieniu tych osób, które wyjechały do pracy, zostawiając w kraju swoje rodziny i dzieci, i które dzięki zarobionym pieniądzom i świadczeniom mogą im zaoferować lepszą przyszłość. Protestuję w imieniu tych, którym bliskie są europejskie wartości oparte na równym traktowaniu i solidarności.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem35" title="14. Delegated acts (Rule 105(6)): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem36" title="15. Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem37" title="16. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem38" title="17. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem39" title="18. Approval of the minutes of the sitting and forwarding of texts adopted: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem40" title="19. Dates of forthcoming sittings : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem41" title="20. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem42" title="21. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="4-291-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die Sitzungsperiode des Europäischen Parlaments für unterbrochen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
