<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20190715.EN" lang="en" date="2019-07-15" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro ripresa la sessione del Parlamento europeo interrotta giovedì 4 luglio 2019.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Composition of committees and delegations">
    <intervention id="1-010-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ho ricevuto dai gruppi PPE e ECR alcune richieste di modifica nella composizione delle commissioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tali nomine figureranno nel processo verbale della presente seduta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se non saranno state presentate osservazioni fino all'adozione del processo verbale, tali nomine saranno considerate approvate.</p>
      <p sl="en">*</p>
      <p sl="en">**</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-011-0000" speaker_id="2309" name="Richard Corbett" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, you announced the names of a number of Members who have already left this Parliament. Are you sure that shouldn’t have included the entire EPP Group, who seem to be absent?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-012-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Colgo il suo sottile umorismo.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Action taken on Parliament’s positions and resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-016-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il progetto definitivo di ordine del giorno, approvato dalla Conferenza dei presidenti, ai sensi dell’articolo 157 del regolamento, nella riunione di giovedì 11 luglio 2019, è stato distribuito. Sono state presentate le seguenti proposte di modifica:</p>
      <p sl="en">Lunedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Non sono proposte modifiche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Martedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Il gruppo GUE/NGL ha chiesto che la dichiarazione del Vicepresidente della Commissione/Alto rappresentante dell’Unione per gli affari esteri e la politica di sicurezza sulla situazione in Venezuela non si concluda con una risoluzione.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-017-0000" speaker_id="197827" name="Idoia Villanueva Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor presidente, eurodiputadas, eurodiputados, en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL, solicitamos que se retire del orden del día la Resolución sobre Venezuela. Mantengamos el debate si así lo creemos necesario, pero en un momento como el que estamos viviendo ahora mismo, con un nuevo proceso de diálogo impulsado por Noruega, donde todos los actores están implicados, donde las negociaciones avanzan —incluso el papa las ha apoyado—, este Parlamento tiene la oportunidad de dejar de hacer resoluciones, de no intentar injerir en la política de Venezuela y de mostrarse como un actor fundamental en la defensa del diálogo, en la defensa de la paz, y así poder ayudar, sin ninguna duda, por la única vía por la que conseguiremos una situación estable y beneficiosa para el pueblo de Venezuela.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-018-0000" speaker_id="2341" name="Michael Gahler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, on behalf of the EPP Group, I would like to reject this suggestion. We can, indeed, in our resolution, take up ongoing discussions and initiatives and welcome them, but we think that the situation is sufficiently dramatic and clear in this regard to enable us to make up our mind at this stage with the resolution we saw earlier. We are aware of the dramatic situation with millions of refugees that have left the country and also destabilising the neighbourhood. I think we can, and must, take a clear position on the situation there.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <a text="(Il Parlamento respinge la richiesta)"/>
      <p sl="en">Mercoledì</p>
      <p sl="en">Presidente. – Ho ricevuto dal gruppo GUE/NGL la richiesta che le dichiarazioni del Consiglio e della Commissione sulle relazioni Unione europea-Mercosur siano aggiunte come terzo punto all’ordine del giorno di mercoledì pomeriggio, dopo le dichiarazioni del Consiglio e della Commissione sulla zona di aria pulita nelle città dell’Unione europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-020-0000" speaker_id="197827" name="Idoia Villanueva Ruiz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señor presidente, de nuevo consideramos importante incluir, como punto en el orden del día del miércoles, el tratado del Mercosur, un tratado que ha estado negociándose desde hace más de veinte años de una manera opaca; un tratado que va a tener, sin ninguna duda, impacto en muchas organizaciones, en muchos países, en muchos agricultores —más de 33 000 agricultores sufrirán nuevas y duras consecuencias a raíz de este tratado—, y creemos que es muy importante que se dé ese debate el miércoles en este Parlamento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-021-0000" speaker_id="193419" name="Christophe Hansen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, in the name of the European People’s Party (EPP), I would oppose adding this point to the agenda. The documents are just being published so we want to analyse them carefully. Commissioner Malmström announced her presence for next week at the Committee on International Trade (INTA) so we would like to reject this addition to the agenda.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-0000" speaker_id="4554" name="Chris Davies (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Chair, European Parliament Committee on Fisheries. – Mr President, pursuant to Rule 184a, as Chair of the Committee on Fisheries, I want to point out that a British Member of this House, Robert Rowland, last week published the comment that, in the event of Brexit, any foreign fishing vessel in British waters should be given the same treatment as the Belgrano.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mr President, you will know that the ‘General Belgrano’ Argentinian cruiser was sunk with the loss of more than 300 lives during armed conflict in 1982. I want to point out that, in the UK the National Federation of Fishermen’s Organisations, has strongly denounced these words. Sickening though they are, it may be that this comparison and the suggestion that European fishermen could be killed for fishing in waters that they have used for generations will be dismissed as just words and hyperbole, and that free speech matters – and indeed it does. But the history of Europe shows that words matter. Words can promote friendship and they can foster hatred and division.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I hope you will join me in regretting that someone from my country should have chosen to use these words for the latter purpose.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Grazie onorevole Davies, prendiamo atto delle sue considerazioni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-025-0000" speaker_id="197733" name="Robert Rowland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, thank you for allowing me to speak. First of all, in response to the other MEP, I’d like to make the following comment: I was responding to the verbal assault which you administered to one of my colleagues, June Mummery, after she confronted you outside the Committee on Fisheries, of which you are Chair. You verbally assaulted her, and we are issuing a disciplinary committee warning against you because of that. In regard to my response, it was based on the defence of the British fishing industry, which has been systematically destroyed by the European Union’s policy of pulse fishing, and I will do my utmost to defend British fishermen.</p>
      <p sl="en">In terms of the language, it was a tongue-in-cheek comment based on the fact that our industry has been decimated. You should not have taken it literally. Of course I’m not implying any form of violence on the high seas, even though we have seen it in 2018 when French and British fishermen did end up with a confrontation on the seas. But I am not suggesting for one minute that British fishermen should engage in any kind of military assault on overseas fishermen. I stand resolutely behind British fishermen and our fishing industry. I will never back down in that quest to defend them.</p>
      <a text="(Applause from a section of the House)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-026-0000" speaker_id="197708" name="Claire Fox" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, one thing that you can say about the British delegation in this part of the House is that we have a sense of humour and know that free speech matters. It’s outrageous, when there are more important things to do, that this House has been used by one of our so-called colleagues from the UK to make cheap points. There are far more important and serious matters that we need to take up.</p>
      <p sl="en">I defend the right of anyone to say anything, including his right, in fact, to be abusive. Free speech matters and liberty matters. You would do well to take notice of us in the Brexit Party when we say that we’ll defend you. You should stop nit-picking and having a go at us.</p>
      <p sl="en">This house, as much as it is not democratic, has really got better things to do than the internal rows led by the Liberal Democrats having a go at their colleagues from the UK.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. One-minute speeches on matters of political importance">
    <intervention id="1-029-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">On the matter of free speech, the next item is the one-minute speeches on matters of political importance (Rule 172).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="98582" name="Loránt Vincze" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Úr, Képviselőtársak! Az Európai Unió tagállamaiban nagyon eltérő az őshonos kisebbségi közösségekre vonatkozó jogi keret. Míg több országban erős jogosítványokat tartalmazó törvények vannak, másutt a meglévő jogok csak részleges megoldást jelentenek, néhány országban pedig el sem ismerik a kisebbségeket. Az egyenlőtlenséggel az emberi jogok sérülnek.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az én országomban, Romániában, a közigazgatási törvény nemrégiben történt módosítása meglévő jogok szűkítését is célozta. A magyar nyelvre vonatkozó előírásokat nagyon sok esetben nem alkalmazzák, az állam tiltja a magyar közösség szimbólumainak használatát.</p>
      <p sl="en">Különösen aggasztónak tartom, hogy jelenleg nincs érdemi párbeszéd a román többség és a romániai magyar közösség között.</p>
      <p sl="en">Itt, a Parlamentben szorgalmaznunk kell az együttműködést a kisebbségi kérdésben, a jó gyakorlatok megosztását, legyen jogállamisági elv a kisebbségvédelmi jogszabályok betartása.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ötvenmillió kisebbségi uniós polgár abban bízik, hogy az új mandátumban az Európai Unió kisebbségvédelmi standardokat teremt. Tegyünk róla!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="188636" name="John Howarth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the right to vote is a fundamental right. Our job as politicians is to make it easier for people to exercise that right. Six weeks ago in the United Kingdom and elsewhere, the opposite happened. Turnout in the European Parliament elections across Europe increased to 51%, yet many citizens resident in Member States other than their own were turned away at polling stations, particularly, but not solely, in the United Kingdom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Unfortunately, the UK Government’s response to criticism on this matter has been characteristically negative. Therefore, changes are required at EU level to simplify the process and to make it easier for every EU citizen to vote, wherever they live, simply by signing a declaration at the polling station.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have written to the President and the Chair of the Committee on Constitutional Rights (AFCO), asking that this matter be re-examined now to ensure well in advance of the next European elections, so that every EU citizen has the right to vote and it’s upheld.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="197447" name="Irena Joveva (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spoštovana predsedujoča, drage kolegice, dragi kolegi, veseli me, da vas imam prvič možnost nagovoriti, in to priložnost bi želela izkoristiti za temo, o kateri se pogovarjamo po eni strani veliko, ampak po drugi očitno premalo. Odvisno od primera oziroma od države oziroma od takšnih ali drugačnih političnih igric.</p>
      <p sl="en">Govorim o vladavini prava in ob tem me veseli, da je potencialna bodoča predsednica Komisije izpostavila, da bo vztrajala na vzpostavitvi evropskega mehanizma, ki bo zagotovil spoštovanje te temeljne vrednote v vseh državah članicah.</p>
      <p sl="en">In čeprav zadnjič ni želela konkretno govoriti o primeru, bi vseeno na tem mestu še enkrat izpostavila hrvaško nespoštovanje arbitražne razsodbe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Verjamem, da bo to gospa von de Leyen enkrat tudi jasno povedala za razliko od njenega predhodnika, ob tem pa želim izpostaviti, da bom od vodstva Komisije zahtevala objavo pravnega mnenja glede arbitražne razsodbe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Želim, da se spoštuje vladavina prava, in verjamem, da nisem edina.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-0000" speaker_id="197644" name="Christian Allard" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, merci de m’aider pour le premier discours que je fais devant ce parlement et merci de donner la parole à un nouvel élu pas comme les autres. Je suis le citoyen français qui représente l’Écosse en Europe. Après avoir été député au parlement écossais, je suis ici à cause du Brexit et pour vous démontrer notre attachement à l’Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a 20 ans, 20 ans déjà, j’ai voté pour que le parlement écossais se réunisse à nouveau après une interruption de plus de 300 ans; un parlement qui n’aurait jamais siégé sans l’aide de l’Union européenne. C’est l’Union européenne qui nous a permis d’avoir ce parlement écossais. Vous nous avez aidés et nous ne vous avons pas oubliés. En 2016, 62 % de l’électorat écossais a voté pour rester en Europe, ce qui fait de nous l’un des pays les plus européens d’Europe. Cela s’explique par le fait qu’en Écosse, nous sommes habitués à l’idée d’avoir plusieurs identités: je suis 100 % Écossais, je suis 100 % Français et 100 % Européen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Notre idée de l’Europe est la vôtre: la libre circulation des personnes, le libre-échange, nos valeurs communes. Nous sommes prêts à défendre notre identité européenne. Aidez-nous à rester au cœur de l’Europe, aidez-nous à mieux vous aider.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-034-0000" speaker_id="119431" name="Ruža Tomašić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, Međunarodni kazneni sud za bivšu Jugoslaviju objavio je u prosincu 2015. uhidbene naloge za odvjetnike Vojislava Šešelja, Petra Jojića i Vjericu Radetu, koji su optuženi za nepoštivanje Suda pod sumnjom da su prijetili, zastrašivali i pokušali podmititi svjedoke. Uhidbeni nalozi tajno su predani u siječnju 2019., ali srbijanske vlasti nisu po njima postupile pa ih je Sud javno objavio. Službeni Beograd i dalje ih odbija izvršiti uz obrazloženje da im to priječi Zakon o suradnji s Haškim tribunalom koji predviđa obvezu izručenja optuženika za ratne zločine, ali ne i osoba optuženih za nepoštivanje suda. Sličnu je argumentaciju prethodno upotrijebila i Francuska u slučaju Florence Hartmann.</p>
      <p sl="en">O žalbi Srbije protiv naloga za uhićenje trebalo bi odlučivati posebno žalbeno vijeće. Postavlja se pitanje zašto Srbija uopće ima pravo podnijeti tužbu protiv tog naloga. Je li tajnost tog službenog postupka znak da se Srbiji ponovno gleda kroz prste?</p>
      <p sl="en">Sramotno je da država koja otvoreno odbija punu suradnju s Haškim sudom i štiti ratne zločince u predmetu „Ovčara” nastavlja pregovore o poglavlju 23. To puno govori o Europskoj uniji i njezinom licemjerju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="197416" name="Giorgos Georgiou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, έρχομαι από την Κύπρο. Αυτές τις μέρες συμπληρώνονται 45 χρόνια από την πιο μαύρη σελίδα στην ιστορία του νησιού, όταν η χούντα μέσα από τους σχεδιασμούς του ΝΑΤΟ και έχοντας τη στήριξη της ντόπιας φασιστικής οργάνωσης ΕΟΚΑ Β διέπραξε πραξικόπημα αποβλέποντας στη θανάτωση του νόμιμου προέδρου Αρχιεπισκόπου Μακαρίου. Οι συνέπειες υπήρξαν και συνεχίζουν να είναι τραγικές για τον τόπο και τον λαό μας, με χιλιάδες νεκρούς, πολλούς μέχρι και σήμερα αγνοούμενους, με μια βίαιη κατοχή του 37% του κυπριακού εδάφους, με έναν εποικισμό και μια προσπάθεια αλλαγής του δημογραφικού χαρακτήρα του τόπου μας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Χρειαζόμαστε και ζητούμε την έμπρακτη στήριξη της Ευρώπης μακριά από μέτρα τα οποία επαναλαμβάνονται ή αναμασιούνται και είναι κατώτερα των περιστάσεων, μια Τουρκία η οποία φαίνεται να είναι πολύτιμη για κάποια συμφέροντα της Ευρώπης, όμως πολυτιμότερη είναι η υπεράσπιση του Διεθνούς Δικαίου με σκοπό να επαναρχίσουν οι συνομιλίες από το σημείο όπου διακόπηκαν στο Κραν Μοντανά, για να υπάρξει μια λύση η οποία θα βοηθά τον κυπριακό λαό και τους λαούς της περιοχής, θα συμβάλει όμως και σε μια ασφαλέστερη Ευρώπη.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-036-0000" speaker_id="197620" name="Matthew Patten" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, 400 000 people from the East Midlands elected me to come here and speak for them. Two hundred million people across Europe voted for us all to be here. The democratic foundation of the EU is based on us – 751 directly elected MEPs who represent our voters in this Hemicycle, the debating Chamber and its replica in Brussels. So why are the Parliament Chambers open less than 60 days a year? Last week in Brussels our Chamber was locked all week. Tonight is the only time that MEPs are allowed to speak freely for the whole of July, and then only some of us have been chosen and we’re only allowed 60 seconds each. No wonder there are so few MEPs here now. Is it the case that there is nothing to speak about? Is it the case that our voters don’t want their voices heard? Or is the real answer that the people in the Commission, in the Council, behind the closed doors don’t want to hear what we have to say? Sixty days is not enough to hear our voice. Sixty seconds is not enough. Our voices must be heard. Please, Madam President, please can we have more parliament?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">The trouble is that if everyone exceeds a minute then fewer get to speak – which isn’t an issue this evening but it will be in future parliaments. So we try and stick to the rules, and you did take extra time.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="124712" name="Andrea Bocskor" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony, tisztelt Képviselőtársaim! Július 21-én Ukrajnában előre hozott parlamenti választások lesznek, amire az Európai Uniónak és a Parlamentnek is fokozottan oda kell figyelnie. A tavaszi elnökválasztás után bíztunk benne, hogy gyors változások következnek, azonban a Központi Választási Bizottság ismét megtagadta, hogy létrehozzon egy magyar többségű választókerületet, és további aggodalomra ad okot, hogy számtalan visszaélés tapasztalható mostanában a választási kampány során. Elsősorban ezek a visszaélések szavazatvásárlásokban nyilvánulnak meg, vagy hasonló nevű, politikai tapasztalattal nem rendelkező klónok indítása a választópolgárok megtévesztése, illetve a szavazat elvonások érdekében, és ami még durvább: a titkosszolgálatok is vegzálják azokat, akik részt vesznek egy bizonyos képviselő kampányában.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sajnos a magyar közösség vezetői, az újságírók, tanárok még mindig vegzálásoknak vannak kitéve, ezért én nagyon kérem Önöket, hogy vegyék figyelembe, hogy mi történik jelenleg Ukrajnában. Fordítsunk figyelmet arra, hogy Ukrajna ne csak hangoztassa az európai integrációs törekvéseit, hanem valóban be is tartsa azokat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="33997" name="Corina Crețu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, doamnă comisar Vestager, îmi face mare plăcere să vorbesc din nou din Parlamentul European. Aș vrea să vorbesc despre cadrul financiar multianual, care reprezintă garanția unei Europe stabile și predictibile din punct de vedere economic, și cred că următorul buget pentru perioada 2021-2027 nu mai reprezintă doar o prioritate, ci o urgență. Vreau să vă spun că, deși Comisia Europeană a depus propunerea de buget încă din 2 mai 2018, n-au avut loc decât trei triloguri pe această temă, și atunci cred că nu ar trebui să ne mirăm că populismul crește în Europa. Este vorba de un nou început pentru Europa. În propunerea Comisiei s-au dublat sumele -dacă vor fi aprobate de către dumneavoastră ca și colegislatori și de către Consiliu - atât pentru cercetare, pentru inovare, pentru tineret, pentru programele Erasmus, ca să nu mai vorbesc de politica de coeziune care contribuie la reducerea decalajelor dintre regiuni și, pe de altă parte, despre agricultură, subvențiile pe agricultură. Deci apelul meu este de a relua cât mai curând trilogul între Comisie, Consiliu și Parlament pe tema bugetului 2021-2027. Scuze, dar nu mai sunt obișnuită să vorbesc un minut, trebuie să mă reobișnuiesc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">I know that when you are in the Commissioner’s seat you get more time, but I’m afraid in Parliament … But our British colleagues should know that brevity is the soul of wit. There you are. Thank you for the recognition.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="96922" name="Izaskun Bilbao Barandica (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, abante. «Abante» es la expresión que utilizamos en mi pueblo marinero para referirnos a la determinación que se necesita para salir adelante de las peores situaciones. Fuerza, ánimo, solidaridad. Son sentimientos que envío desde aquí a los familiares del joven de Villava que falleció la semana pasada en unas terribles inundaciones; a los vecinos del centro y este de Navarra, de Tafalla, Olite, Pueyo, Pitillas, Beire, y a sus instituciones, afectadas por una tormenta sin precedentes que descargó en tres horas el triple de lluvia de la que cae en la zona en todo el mes de julio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trece municipios son ya zona catastrófica y nos hacen reflexionar sobre la proliferación de fenómenos atmosféricos extremos que están ligados al cambio climático. Por eso esta expresión de solidaridad es también un llamamiento para que la emergencia climática sea una prioridad en esta legislatura. Necesitamos una estrategia global, sin duda, pero la queremos construida desde abajo. Porque muchas de las batallas decisivas se ganan desde el nivel local y el nivel regional.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="197786" name="Susanna Ceccardi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, l'avvio di questa legislatura ha reso evidente che esistono due concezioni di Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La prima, quella dei burocrati, che ha le sue fondamenta nell'euro, la sua ragion d'essere nella tutela delle élite e il suo fine ultimo nella realizzazione di un'Europa senza confini, senza identità, fatta di lavoratori sottopagati, sfruttati, mansueti, di accaniti consumatori, sudditi del mercato finanziario e delle sue logiche malate.</p>
      <p sl="en">La seconda, la nostra, invece, basa le sue fondamenta nella storia gloriosa di questo continente, che trova la sua ragion d'essere nella tutela dei nostri popoli e ha come fine ultimo la costruzione di un'Europa che tuteli le identità e la democrazia. Lo stesso Presidente Sassoli è espressione che siede su quella poltrona di presidenza, è espressione di queste alchimie parlamentari tra democristiani e socialisti, quelli che hanno penalizzato l'Italia per tanti anni, quelle logiche che hanno penalizzato il nostro paese per tanti anni e hanno penalizzato i nostri artigiani, i nostri agricoltori e le nostre famiglie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lo dico all'Aula, ma soprattutto a quelli che ci ascoltano fuori da questo palazzo. Non fermerete la nostra rivoluzione con gli accordi di palazzo. Noi, questa Europa la cambieremo e il riscatto dei popoli arriverà.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-0000" speaker_id="187917" name="Marc Botenga" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, aujourd’hui, 113 millions d’Européens risquent la pauvreté, 113 millions risquent l’exclusion sociale. C’est dix fois la population de mon pays, la Belgique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons aujourd’hui une urgence sociale dans l’Union européenne. Ce n’est pas une coïncidence mais la conséquence de politiques qui ont été votées et approuvées ici par les partis traditionnels qui nous entourent, ces partis traditionnels qui ont voté libéralisation après libéralisation et coupes budgétaires après coupes budgétaires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aujourd’hui, cette logique des traités européens qui, face aux besoins du peuple, face aux besoins des gens, préfère donner la priorité aux marchés, est inacceptable. Nous avons le choix: soit nous continuons à accompagner cette spirale vers le bas, soit nous renforçons la résistance sociale pour créer une Europe non pas de l’austérité, mais de la prospérité et une Europe non pas du dumping social, mais du progrès social.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="125093" name="Κωνσταντίνος Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, καταδικάζουμε τη χρησιμοποίηση δύο πλοίων με γεωτρύπανα στην κυπριακή ΑΟΖ όπως και τις διαρκείς παραβιάσεις στο Αιγαίο απ’ την αστική τάξη της Τουρκίας, χώρας μέλους του ΝΑΤΟ και στρατηγικού εταίρου της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης που διατηρεί 45 χρόνια τώρα την κατοχή στο 37% της Κύπρου.</p>
      <p sl="en">Οι τεράστιες ευθύνες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης δεν ξεπλένονται με φραστικές ανησυχίες και με μέτρα που αποτελούν μέρος του γνωστού παζαριού με την αστική τάξη της Τουρκίας. Οι ίσες αποστάσεις και τα περί αυτοσυγκράτησης από ΗΠΑ, Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και ΝΑΤΟ νομιμοποιούν την επιθετικότητα της Τουρκίας και διαμορφώνουν έδαφος για την επικίνδυνη συνδιαχείριση του Αιγαίου και των κυπριακών θαλάσσιων ζωνών.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η νέα κυβέρνηση της Νέας Δημοκρατίας στην Ελλάδα, στο έδαφος που έστρωσε ο ΣΥΡΙΖΑ, επιταχύνει τη βαθύτερη εμπλοκή στους ιμπεριαλιστικούς σχεδιασμούς των οποίων τα μονοπώλια λυμαίνονται τις ενεργειακές πηγές. Κόντρα στον εφησυχασμό αλλά και τους εθνικιστικούς λεονταρισμούς οι λαοί να δυναμώσουν την επαγρύπνησή τους για την απεμπλοκή από τα ιμπεριαλιστικά σχέδια, για να γίνουν κύριοι του ενεργειακού πλούτου με σχέσεις φιλίας, αλληλεγγύης και κοινής πάλης.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="124710" name="Michaela Šojdrová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Paní předsedající, tento měsíc si připomínáme 70 let od konce první izraelsko-arabské války. V té době také země evropské, včetně Francie nebo Československa, pomohly Izraeli bránit svoji svébytnost a mladý stát.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bylo to jistě i proto, že s Izraelem země EU sdílí hodnoty, sdílí úctu k lidským právům a úctu k demokracii. Je to jedna z mála zemí, kde skutečně existuje demokracie, a proto by EU měla s Izraelem mít ty nejlepší vztahy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Já dnes vystupuji proto, že mi velmi vadí a leží mi na srdci to, aby EU s Izraelem vedla dialog i na základě asociační dohody. Tak jako ho vede i s dalšími sousedními zeměmi, které mají podobnou dohodu. Jak je možné, že od roku 2012 se nesešla asociační rada? Proto také zítra s paní Mogheriniovou o tom budu hovořit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="197718" name="Nicolás Gonzalez Casares" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, la sanidad pública constituye el corazón del estado de bienestar y de una sociedad justa. Para una atención sanitaria de calidad el capital humano es fundamental. Lamentablemente, en muchos puntos de Europa y, singularmente, en algunas regiones de España, la enfermería está sometida a una temporalidad salvaje.</p>
      <p sl="en">En Galicia, mi tierra, las enfermeras, pero también otros colectivos sanitarios, son víctimas de abusos en la contratación por parte del Gobierno regional, la Xunta de Galicia. Esta situación ha llevado a colectivos como Enfermeiras Eventuais en Loita a organizarse para denunciar abusos, como que una enfermera se vea obligada a firmar más de quinientos contratos en diez años, muchos de ellos por horas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es una situación inaceptable que maltrata a una profesión esencial para proveer de cuidados a nuestras familias. Por eso, en mi estreno en este Pleno, quiero reivindicar el papel de la enfermería en Europa, de millones, de cientos de miles de profesionales, y exigir respeto y condiciones laborales dignas y justas para estas profesionales.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="197419" name="Valter Flego (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, Europa je za mene oduvijek imala i siguran sam da mora imati i nadalje snažan duh, snažnu ideju otvorenosti, progresivnosti i tolerantnosti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nažalost, danas, sada, u 2019. godini, prepunoj tehnoloških inovacija i dostignuća, pa i za kontrolu granica, hrvatski susjedi, naše prijateljske države Slovenija i Italija najavljuju dizanje novih kilometara žičanih ograda na našim granicama.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mi smo odlučno protiv toga jer izgradnjom novih žičanih ograda ne rješava se problem ilegalnih migracija. Zidovi potiču zidove, a ograde potiču na jednoj strani ograde na drugoj strani. To je potpuno pogrešno. Naravno da treba voditi računa o sigurnosti ljudi, treba voditi računa itekako o migrantima kao ljudima i humano se prema njima ponašati, ali žica ne rješava problem. Ono što treba učiniti Europska komisija je zajednička borba, protiv krijumčara i riješiti problem na samome izvoru.</p>
      <p sl="en">To očekujem da se riješi vrlo hitno i skoro.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="197480" name="Nicolaus Fest" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Schönen guten Abend. Hier geht es meist um die große Politik. Ich bin eher besorgt über die Verfasstheit dieses Hauses. Grundsätzlich ist es Aufgabe der Abgeordneten, die politische Agenda selbst zu bestimmen. Deshalb entscheiden sie selbst, mit welchen politischen Anliegen, mit welchen Initiativen sie sich beschäftigen wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diese Regel wird im Augenblick leider durchbrochen. Mir ist heute ein Papier zugespielt worden – verantwortlich ist hier wahrscheinlich Herr Klaus Welle, das ist die Verwaltung für den LIBE-Ausschuss. Dieses Papier hat die Überschrift „Mögliche erste parlamentarische Initiativen“ und behandelt all das, weshalb wir von den Wählern ins Parlament gewählt wurden, damit wir das verhindern, nämlich beispielsweise humanitäre Visa, Wiederaufnahme von Rescue-Operationen, Resettlement und so weiter. Die Verwaltung glaubt also offensichtlich, dass nicht die Abgeordneten die politische Agenda setzen sollten, sondern dass sie es selber tut. Dies ist eine unerhörte Respektlosigkeit, und ich fordere Sie auf, dagegen vorzugehen und zu klären, wieviel Geld hierfür ausgegeben wurde und wie man solche Dinge in Zukunft verhindert.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="28389" name="Zbigniew Kuźmiuk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Jako członek Komisji Rolnictwa i Rozwoju Wsi parlamentu z Polski chciałbym wyrazić najwyższe zaniepokojenie zawarciem w dniu 28 czerwca porozumienia dwustronnego o wolnym handlu pomiędzy Unią a krajami Mercosuru. Negocjacje w tej sprawie były prowadzone od 2000 r. i nie było powodów, aby gwałtownie je przyspieszać i zawierać porozumienie wtedy, kiedy nie pracował już Parlament Europejski.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wiem, że protestowały w tej sprawie rządy Francji, Polski, Belgii i Irlandii, wskazując, że dodatkowy import na rynek Unii, w szczególności wołowiny, drobiu, wieprzowiny, cukru i etanolu, może zdestabilizować te rynki, tym bardziej w przypadku bezumownego brexitu. W sytuacji kiedy produkcja rolna w krajach Mercosuru nie jest objęta koniecznością spełniania wysokich norm sanitarnych, fitosanitarnych, dobrostanu zwierząt i ochrony środowiska, trudno będzie z nią konkurować europejskim rolnikom. Mam nadzieję, że nie dojdzie do tymczasowego wdrażania tej umowy bez zgody nowego Parlamentu i nowej Komisji Europejskiej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, poucos dias depois das eleições para o Parlamento Europeu – como convém –, a Comissão Europeia emitiu as suas recomendações por país, aquelas que se não forem cumpridas podem dar lugar a sanções aos Estados—Membros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não há grande novidade, mas há algumas que vale a pena sublinhar, por exemplo para Portugal. Recomenda a Comissão um ainda maior aperto orçamental, ou seja, menos recursos para os serviços públicos, para a saúde, para a educação, para os transportes, para a habitação, para a cultura, desviando recursos – o fruto do suor dos trabalhadores portugueses – para alimentar os lucros daqueles que especularam com a nossa dívida soberana, ou seja, mais dinheiro para os credores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Outra recomendação: mais precariedade laboral. É isso que querem dizer com a redução da segmentação do mercado de trabalho, ou seja, nivelar por baixo as condições de trabalho.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tem-se discutido muito nestes últimos dias quem vai ocupar os lugares de topo nas instituições da União Europeia, mas a verdadeira questão com que os povos estão confrontados é a necessidade de uma mudança de política. Não interessa quem vai brandir o chicote, o que é inaceitável é continuarmos a fustigar os povos com este tipo de políticas.</p>
      <p sl="en">São estas políticas que é necessário mudar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="125065" name="Ελισσάβετ Βόζεμπεργκ-Βρυωνίδη" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, στην περασμένη θητεία του το Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο ασχολήθηκε με το πολύ σημαντικό θέμα της μετανάστευσης. Είμαι απ’ την Ελλάδα και ξέρετε ότι η χώρα μου αντιμετωπίζει μείζον πρόβλημα. Η νέα κυβέρνηση της Ελλάδας εγγυάται την αποτελεσματική φύλαξη των εξωτερικών συνόρων και έχει ολοκληρωμένο σχέδιο για μια υπεύθυνη μεταναστευτική πολιτική.</p>
      <p sl="en">Όμως έχουμε μπροστά μας δύο προβλήματα: Το ένα αφορά στη μη αναθεώρηση του κανονισμού του Δουβλίνου, που έχει μείνει στο Συμβούλιο, και το δεύτερο πολύ σοβαρό πρόβλημα αφορά σε εκείνα τα κράτη μέλη που έχουν κλείσει τις πόρτες τους και δεν δέχονται να εφαρμόσουν τις κοινές μας αποφάσεις, δεν δέχονται την ανάληψη κοινών ευθυνών, δεν βοηθούν ούτως ώστε να μπορούμε να έχουμε ένα ευρωπαϊκό κοινό πρόγραμμα αντιμετώπισης του ασύλου, έτσι ώστε να μην κλονίζεται η αξιοπιστία των Ευρωπαίων πολιτών και να μη ρίχνουμε νερό στον μύλο του λαϊκισμού.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="5392" name="Lara Wolters" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, ik heb de afgelopen maand genoten van de Oranjeleeuwinnen. Nog niet zo lang geleden was het WK vrouwenvoetbal onbekend en onbemind. En nu, nu keken Europeanen massaal naar de finale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Onbekend en onbemind waren lange tijd ook de Europese verkiezingen, maar de klimaatcrisis, de opkomst van rechts-extremisme en de brexit hebben mensen wakker geschud. Het gevolg is de hoogste opkomst in decennia, en dat kwam met name door jongeren. Hun stem ging niet naar Ursula von der Leyen. Hun stem ging naar kandidaten die vóór de verkiezingen duidelijk maakten waar ze voor stonden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stel je eens voor dat die WK-finale tussen Nederland en de VS na een geheime wedstrijd opeens door Frankrijk zou worden gewonnen. Zou iemand dat accepteren? Nee. Ik zal morgen dus niet voor mevrouw von der Leyen stemmen. Ik wil strijden voor een democratischer Europa, en een achterkamertjeskandidaat als Commissievoorzitter hoort daar niet bij.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="197570" name="Peter Kofod" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Jeg har valgt at tage ordet her i dag, fordi Danmark tabte en principiel sag i sidste uge ved EU-Domstolen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det, EU-Domstolen nåede frem til, var som at rette en torpedo direkte mod den stramme danske udlændingepolitik. Og det er i sig selv grotesk. For sagen er, at danskerne aldrig har accepteret, at EU skal blande sig i vores udlændingepolitik. Derimod har danskerne i årevis arbejdet på at vælge politikere, og det har jo så ført til, at der i dag er et meget stort flertal i det danske Folketing, der kæmper for en stram udlændingepolitik. Det er, fordi vi anerkender, at Danmark er danskernes land. Det er ikke alle, der kan komme ind i vores land. Man skal leve op til en lang række kriterier, fordi vi vil passe på vores eget land.</p>
      <p sl="en">Derfor er det grotesk, at man ser, at EU i stadig større grad blander sig og underminerer vores ret til at passe på os selv, vores ret til selv at bestemme, hvem vi vil lukke ind i Danmark.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="125012" name="Daniel Buda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamna președintă, fermierii europeni au nevoie de un răspuns ferm și rapid cu privire la noua politică agricolă comună.</p>
      <p sl="en">Acum, când se negociază componența noii Comisii Europene, solicit public tuturor forțelor politice să nu folosească Regulamentul privind politica agricolă comună ca monedă de schimb în vederea atingerii altor obiective politice. Le atrag atenția tuturor responsabililor politici să nu se joace cu soarta fermierilor europeni care au nevoie de stabilitate.</p>
      <p sl="en">Acest regulament, votat la Comisia AGRI în mandatul anterior, corespunde unor exigențe majore privind interesele fermierilor mari sau mici. În același timp, reprezintă o garanție pentru consumatori, care vor avea posibilitatea să aibă acces la o hrană de calitate și la prețuri rezonabile, dar, în același timp, și garanția unui mediu curat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Astfel, apreciez că singura soluție viabilă este trimiterea acestui raport în plenul Parlamentului European, urmând ca ulterior, conform procedurilor existente, să urmeze calea trialogului și livrarea acestui document către fermierii europeni. Statele membre trebuie să aibă timp suficient în vederea adoptării planurilor naționale.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="124953" name="Jude Kirton-Darling" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, as divided as we are on the EU, our cooperation is vital in the fight against modern day slavery. Worldwide, the trafficking of human beings for forced labour, criminality or sexual exploitation affects around 24 million people. The UK tops the EU poll with the highest number of registered victims, and the North East has the biggest regional problem outside London. But, equally, we are a world leader in modern slavery legislation and in action.</p>
      <p sl="en">That’s why it matters that the next Northumbria Police and Crime Commissioner has a proven track record working in and for our communities, as Kim McGuinness does. Working together regionally, and as part of the EU, is the only way to eradicate this criminal exploitation that doesn’t belong in the modern world and should be a thing of our past. We mustn’t let Brexit pull us back to that past.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="125004" name="Franc Bogovič" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Spoštovana predsedujoča, v Sloveniji imamo v zadnjih mesecih velike probleme s porastom napadov medvedov in volkov na živali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gre za ovce, govedo, tudi konje. Preko sto ovac je že bilo poklanih, več kot dvajset govedi, konjev. V zadnjem času se je žal zgodil tudi napad na starejšo gospo.</p>
      <p sl="en">To je posledica velikega porasta števila divjadi, kajti v zadnjih letih je večji naravni prirast, kot je odstrel teh zveri. Zato imamo velik problem in kmetje počasi obupujejo, predvsem živinorejci, in najavljajo opuščanje reje govedi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato je nujno, da se o tej temi spregovori tako v Sloveniji, ministrica za kmetijstvo je predlagala zakon o izrednem ulovu volkov, medvedov, prav tako pa mislim, da bi bilo potrebno, da v Evropskem parlamentu spregovorimo o tem problemu, kajti to ni problem samo Slovenije, problem je tudi v drugih evropskih državah, in to se zgodi, če se v naravi poruši ravnovesje.</p>
      <p sl="en">V Sloveniji je to ravnovesje porušeno, zato mislim, da bi bilo prav, da naredimo svojo obveznost doma, se pravi z izrednim odstrelom medvedov in volkov, prav tako pa ne smemo dopustiti, da se ta problem razširi po Evropi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="28115" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Colleagues, we had a number of other Members who wished to speak but they have not arrived in the Chamber.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">That concludes the item.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Agenda for next sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
