<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20190704.EN" lang="en" date="2019-07-04" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Composition of committees: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Election of the Quaestors of Parliament">
    <intervention id="3-007-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca l'elezione dei Questori del Parlamento europeo. Comunico di aver ricevuto le seguenti candidature:</p>
      <p sl="en">On. Monika Beňová</p>
      <p sl="en">On. Gilles Boyer</p>
      <p sl="en">On. David Casa</p>
      <p sl="en">On. Karol Karski e</p>
      <p sl="en">On. Anne Sander.</p>
      <p sl="en">I candidati mi hanno confermato di accettare le rispettive candidature.</p>
      <p sl="en">Poiché il numero dei candidati non supera il numero dei seggi da assegnare, propongo di eleggerli per acclamazione a norma dell'articolo 15, paragrafo 1, del regolamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi sono richieste di scrutinio segreto?</p>
      <p sl="en">Non ce ne sono. Pertanto i candidati in questione sono eletti alla carica di Questori del Parlamento europeo. Naturalmente, mi congratulo con i colleghi per la loro elezione.</p>
      <p sl="en">È però richiesta una votazione, come sapete, per stabilire l'ordine di precedenza, ossia l'ordine in cui vengono assegnati i voti ai cinque Questori.</p>
      <a text="(Il Parlamento procede ad un test per verificare il corretto funzionamento dei dispositivi di voto)"/>
      <p sl="en">La prova ha funzionato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Passiamo quindi alla votazione sui Questori del Parlamento per stabilire l'ordine di precedenza. Anche in questo caso i seggi da assegnare sono 5, per cui dovete votare almeno 3 candidati, altrimenti il voto sarà considerato nullo.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione è aperta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hanno votato tutti?</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comunico i risultati:</p>
      <p sl="en">numero di votanti: 574</p>
      <p sl="en">voti bianchi o nulli: 71</p>
      <p sl="en">voti espressi: 503</p>
      <p sl="en">I candidati hanno ottenuto i seguenti risultati:</p>
      <p sl="en">On. Sander: 407 voti</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">On. Beňová: 391 voti</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">On. Casa: 391 voti</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">On. Boyer: 317 voti</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">On. Karski 261 voti</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">Auguri e complimenti agli eletti. A norma dell'articolo 18 del regolamento l'ordine di precedenza è quello che ha stabilito il voto di poco fa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La composizione del nuovo Ufficio di presidenza sarà notificata ai presidenti delle istituzioni dell'Unione europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">A norma dell'articolo 18 del regolamento l'ordine di precedenza è determinato dall'ordine secondo il quale si sono stati eletti e, in caso di parità di voti dall'età.</p>
      <a text="(La seduta è tolta alle 9.19)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Conclusions of the European Council meeting of 20 and 21 June 2019 (debate)">
    <intervention id="3-011-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca le dichiarazioni del Consiglio europeo e della Commissione sulle conclusioni della riunione del Consiglio europeo del 20 e 21giugno 2019 (2019/2686(RSP)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-012-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Donald Tusk" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President of the European Council">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Members of the European Parliament, first of all I want to congratulate the Members of this House on their election and to congratulate the new President. I offer you my best wishes and I hope for good cooperation between our institutions.</p>
      <p sl="en">To some, it is Parliament that represents genuine European democracy because of its directly elected Members, while to others it is rather the European Council because of the strong democratic legitimacy of the leaders. In fact, such disputes make little sense, as both institutions are democratic. In the end, we must respect each other and cooperate with each other, because only then can we build trust and change Europe for the better.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why, honourable Members, before the European Council proposed the new leadership of the Union, I met with your representatives many times. I did so not only out of respect for you but also, above all, to make sure that the decisions are truly common. We managed to make these decisions on time, and actually much more quickly than five years ago. I believe they are good choices. For the first time in our history, the European Council proposed two women and two men to lead the key EU institutions. I feel happy and proud that we have achieved perfect gender balance in the top positions. This is a very positive change. Europe is not only talking about women, it is choosing women. I hope that this choice will inspire many girls and women to fight for their beliefs and passions. I also hope that it will inspire the European Parliament in its decisions.</p>
      <p sl="en">During the process of nominations, I was in close contact with the leadership of the Greens, especially with Ska Keller and Philippe Lamberts. I am fully confident that cooperation with the Greens and their presence in the EU decision-making bodies will benefit not only the governing coalition, but also Europe as a whole. Therefore, I will appeal to all my partners to involve the Greens in the nominations, even though there is still no European Council leader from this party. I hope that the newly nominated Ursula von der Leyen will also listen to my appeal and, in fact, I will pass this message to her directly later today. As you know, in many countries green symbolises hope and freedom. I have much faith in this symbol.</p>
      <p sl="en">Speaking about different sensitivities in Europe, I would also like to mention unity and geographical balance on the continent. As you know, I have personally struggled to maintain European unity in recent years, whether on solidarity with Ukraine, assistance to Greece, the migration crisis or the Brexit talks. Sometimes we were more and sometimes less successful, but eventually we always managed to stay together. This is because the leaders truly understand the power of unity. It is clear that only when we are united can we counterbalance the most powerful global players.</p>
      <p sl="en">At our last summit, we were also able to build consensus. It took us three days because I wanted to be sure that every Member State, big or small, from every corner of Europe, was on board when it came to the future leadership of the Union. Of course, there is still room for improvement, as regards representatives from the East, in the overall architecture of European positions. In particular, some Prime Ministers from the Socialist family were making commitments as regards geographical balance in this House.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Council also covered a number of other topics but, since you know our conclusions, I will not take up any more of your time. Thank you and good luck again.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-013-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Maroš Šefčovič" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I have the pleasure and the honour to address this House, on behalf of President Juncker, in its first plenary session of the new legislature. We have talked about jobs and names over the past few days and the past few nights. It can often take time to find the right balance and the right compromise and it is worth taking the time to get the right people for the right jobs when the future of our Union for the next five years is at stake.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why I am delighted that this House has chosen President Sassoli for what might be the most difficult job of all. So, caro Presidente, congratulazioni, and congratulations of course to all Members of the European Parliament on their successful election. I would like to congratulate you not only on my behalf but also on behalf of the President of the European Commission and my colleagues in the College, and I would like to underline that we are all looking forward to working very closely with all of you. The same applies to all the candidates nominated by the European Council, including the candidate for President of the European Commission, Ms Ursula von der Leyen, who has all the credentials to lead our institutions. This House will of course have the final say and we will have the opportunity to debate this in the weeks ahead.</p>
      <p sl="en">But the June European Council was not just about people and personalities. It was about our strategic priorities for the next five years and I am pleased to say that there is a lot of common ground between our two institutions. I would like to emphasise just two points. First, the social dimension. Now, more than ever, we must ensure equal opportunities for all at a time when Europeans are confronted with, and have to go through, multiple transitions – economic, ecological, digital – which all have profound repercussions on our daily lives.</p>
      <p sl="en">My second point, which I believe is equally vital, is the question of climate change. My proudest moment, serving as a Commissioner, was when I was honoured to be able to sign, on behalf of the European Union, probably the most important agreement in recent history, the Paris Agreement, in New York. This House knows very well that this was one of the key priorities for the Commission and how hard we’ve all been working, together with you, over the last five years to deliver on our pledges and commitments. Today we can say that ours is the first big economy in the world to have committed itself under the Paris Agreement to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by at least 40% by 2030 compared with 1990. You know very well that, with all your hard work, we set the framework, making sure that we would overachieve this target by 2030. We have to say that this is the most ambitious contribution of any major economy and that we have now established the legislative framework to deliver on all of our commitments. For the European Union to continue to lead, all Member States must now match their deeds to their words when it comes to achieving our commonly agreed 2030 targets.</p>
      <p sl="en">But climate change will not stop in 2030, whether we meet our targets or not. Therefore Europe must very clearly commit to a path of climate neutrality by 2050, as proposed by the Commission last year and supported by the Parliament and recognised by a vast majority of the European Council. A clean planet for all is in all our interests, not least in our economic interests, including the interests of the very small minority of Member States that may still need to be brought fully into our common ambition. This is why we have committed to investing at least 25% of the next long-term budget in climate action. For this reason we have launched a sustainable finance strategy as a part of the capital markets union in order to channel the flows of private capital more effectively into more sustainable investment.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, none of these objectives can be achieved by the European Union unless we have the right money to hand at the right time. That is why I insist that we must still reach an agreement on the future Multiannual Financial Framework this autumn and I trust that you, honourable Members, will also make it your priority to finalise the negotiations jointly with the Finnish Council Presidency. Voters in the European elections called for an effective Europe, a Europe that can act effectively, and we know that this can happen only if a budget is concluded on time. This requires willingness to compromise on all sides. When I think of Europe’s tens of thousands of researchers, 100 000 cohesion projects and one million Erasmus students, every single day counts if programmes are to begin promptly on 1 January 2021. In this case, the phrase ‘time is money’ really applies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Since we are talking about money, at the European Council we could see how our hard work in recent years on deepening the economic and monetary union has paid off. Today we have a stable currency with an average inflation rate of 1.8% in the euro area. European banks are now much more secure than before the financial crisis. The equity buffer is now close to 20% of total expenditure, compared with only 10% before the financial crisis and, as a result of the banking union, the share of non-performing loans has also been more than halved since 2014 and is approaching pre-crisis levels.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we must not rest on our laurels. There is still work to be done in order to complete the economic and monetary union. The budgetary instrument for convergence and competitiveness is an important step towards a budget line for the euro. We need to secure its financing and governance. Further efforts are also needed on the Treaty on the European Stability Mechanism to make it effective and credible and it needs to be integrated into Union law over time. We also need a common deposit guarantee to complete our banking union. We cannot afford to wait until the next crisis before we finally make headway on these crucial issues. There is still much to do and I am therefore happy that, with this plenary session, your work is only just the beginning.</p>
      <p sl="en">Honourable Members, allow me to finish with a few words on some of the other issues we discussed during the last European Council. Firstly, I want to reaffirm our full support for Cyprus in light of Turkey’s continued illegal drilling activities. President Juncker was the first to say, back in Sibiu, that on this issue he is a Cypriot. I was delighted that at the European Council every Member State spoke in unison and said ‘we are all Cypriots’. The Commission is now backing up that spirit of solidarity. We are working on concrete actions we can take and I can assure the people of Cyprus that we will do what we have to do. Europe will stand in full solidarity with Cyprus. I cannot mention Cyprus without once again offering my sincere condolences to the family of former President Dimitris Christofias, a man who shared his love for Europe and Cyprus in the same way as we do.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the Western Balkans, I want to repeat the Commission’s commitment to a firm and credible EU perspective for the region. I believe it is the best way to bring stability to the region. It the best way to overcome bilateral issues and keep up the reform momentum that is serving the people of the region so well. The Member States put back a decision on accession negotiations for North Macedonia and Albania until October. The Commission is ready to keep explaining its recommendation to open talks on the basis of our objective assessment of the progress achieved. In the meantime, it is essential that the two countries and the region as a whole keep up the momentum. These reforms and efforts are, first and foremost, for the citizens of the region. They are about building a society based on fairness and respect of the rule of law. The European Union will support all efforts to achieve this.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, let me reiterate our full and unequivocal support for Ukraine. We are following the issues in the east of the country very closely and we will continue to make the full implementation of the Minsk Agreements the number one priority. The Commission will repeat this message loud and clear in Kiev next week at the next EU-Ukraine summit and I will personally do my utmost to make sure that there will be a continuation of the long-term gas transit through Ukraine for the next long-term period. Lastly, I would like to inform you that the next trilateral talks between Ukraine, Russia and the Commission under my chairmanship will resume in September.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-014-0000" speaker_id="125027" name="Esteban González Pons" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo PPE. – Señor presidente, en nombre de la fuerza mayoritaria del Parlamento quiero felicitarle, presidente Sassoli, y desearle la mejor de las suertes. Ha contado usted con nuestros votos; solo le pido que ni ahora ni en dos años y medio lo olvide. También quiero felicitar y dar las gracias al presidente Tajani, que ha defendido siempre el honor y la dignidad de este Parlamento y de todos sus miembros. Además, debo felicitar a los colegas nuevos y a los veteranos. Sobre nuestros hombros recae la responsabilidad de representar al pueblo europeo. Somos la única institución elegida por el pueblo europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">A quien no voy a felicitar es al Consejo. Con todo respeto, presidente Tusk, no pueden ustedes presumir de cómo han hecho las cosas, ni por las formas, ni por los vetos, ni por su falta de respeto al resto de las instituciones.</p>
      <p sl="en">A los extremistas ―no sé si hoy están aquí― que el pasado martes dieron la espalda al himno de Europa también quiero decirles que nosotros jamás daremos la espalda al himno del Reino Unido. Esa es la diferencia entre tener principios y no tenerlos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hoy hablo aquí en nombre de un Grupo político profundamente europeísta, que ha ayudado a construir Europa desde sus cimientos; el Grupo de un partido fundador de la Unión Europea; un Grupo que, a diferencia de otros, siempre estará dispuesto a hacer renuncias y sacrificios para llegar a acuerdos; un Grupo orgulloso de su presidente y candidato vencedor de las últimas elecciones europeas, Manfred Weber. ¡Manfred, cuenta con nuestro apoyo! Sin haberlo pretendido, hoy representa el espíritu de la democracia europea frente al Consejo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Europa, además de parecer democrática, debe serlo. Por eso esta Cámara ha defendido desde hace años el proceso del Spitzenkandidat; porque creemos que los europeos tienen derecho no solo a votar cómo se les gobierna, sino también quién les gobierna. Y les digo una cosa: creíamos ayer en el Spitzenkandidat, creemos hoy y les aseguro que dentro de cinco años seguiremos creyendo, porque preferimos las urnas a los cuartos cerrados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Los intereses legítimos de los gobiernos representados en el Consejo no deberían imponerse por la fuerza de los Estados a la voluntad de los ciudadanos representados en este Parlamento. Llegados a este punto, sí les diré que el Partido Popular Europeo va a respaldar a la candidata propuesta por el Consejo, por responsabilidad, porque pertenece al partido político que ha ganado las elecciones y porque al frente de la Comisión habrá una persona capacitada y preparada para dar la batalla en defensa de los intereses de Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Como Grupo político, además, estamos orgullosos de que Ursula von der Leyen vaya a ser la primera mujer al frente de la Unión Europea y de que, precisamente, sea una mujer de centroderecha. Sin embargo, el Consejo y su candidata deberán negociar un programa con esta Cámara. A los miembros del Consejo les invitamos a compartir una reflexión. El futuro de Europa debe dejar de decidirse a puerta cerrada y en conspiraciones secretas. El proceso del Spitzenkandidat no es sobre un hombre o sobre una mujer. Se trata de que los ciudadanos puedan elegir a la persona que les gobierna en Europa; una idea verdaderamente revolucionaria: se llama democracia.</p>
      <p sl="en">El Consejo tiene derecho a proponer al Parlamento un candidato a presidente de la Comisión. Eso es verdad. Pero el Consejo no tiene derecho a ignorar a todos los candidatos que han sido votados por los ciudadanos europeos. Ustedes, señor Tusk, han formado una cúpula de la Unión Europea que prescinde de Europa del Este. Nadie de Europa del Este está en su paquete de nombres. Ustedes, señor Tusk, han vetado ―sí, vetado― al candidato al que votaron más de cuarenta millones de europeos, la misma población que tiene su país o que tiene el mío. Lo han vetado.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ustedes le han impuesto a la candidata a presidenta de la Comisión la estructura de la Comisión. No solo la estructura ―incluso cuántas vicepresidencias va a tener―, sin haberlo consultado con ella y antes de que la vote el Parlamento, lo que va claramente contra los Tratados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ustedes han pretendido decirle al Parlamento a quien tenían que nombrar presidente de la Cámara, incluso por cuanto tiempo los Grupos teníamos que repartirnos la Presidencia. Ustedes han llegado al punto de decidir quién va a ser el presidente del Banco Central Europeo como si fuera un puesto político más. Eso se llama mala educación democrática. Ustedes les han dado la razón a los euroescépticos. Gobernar desde las capitales también es nacionalismo. Ninguno de los presidentes que forman parte del Consejo se atrevería a hacer en sus respectivos países lo que han hecho en el Consejo, porque se lo impediría el Tribunal Constitucional.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si me permite la broma, tienen ustedes suerte de que el artículo 7 del Tratado no se le pueda aplicar al Consejo porque si no, hoy, la Comisión tendría un verdadero problema. Han abierto ustedes un conflicto político muy grave entre el Consejo y el Parlamento sobre quién decide en Europa. Y le voy a decir una cosa: mi Grupo parlamentario es de los que piensa que en Europa decide el pueblo. Que eso se llama democracia.</p>
      <a text="(Aplausos)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-015-0000" speaker_id="28298" name="Iratxe García Pérez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señor presidente, señorías, en las elecciones de mayo la ciudadanía europea nos dejó un mensaje claro: confían en Europa, pero quieren cambios, y les puedo asegurar que mi Grupo político tiene el compromiso y la responsabilidad de impulsarlos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quien mejor habría liderado ese cambio en la Comisión sería, sin ninguna duda, Frans Timmermans. Primero, por la figura de Spitzenkandidat que puede obtener una mayoría de votos en este Parlamento Europeo y por respeto a las normas democráticas que nos establecemos. Y segundo, y tanto o igual de importante, porque nuestro candidato ha sido descartado por defender los valores de la Unión y el Estado de Derecho. Pues tengan bien claro que nosotros trabajaremos con más energía para hacer que esos valores se respeten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero hay una cuestión importante en política que también es fundamental y es la coherencia. Y no es coherente venir aquí a tirar por el suelo la decisión del Consejo y luego decir que se va a votar a favor de la misma. La verdad es que muy coherente esa posición no es.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero tengamos claro una cuestión: el principio fundamental que sustenta la Unión Europea es la dignidad humana. Y si fuéramos coherentes con esos valores hace tiempo que habríamos actuado de manera contundente y coordinada para hablar de política en Europa; para hablar de cómo somos capaces de respetar los derechos humanos; para ver cómo somos capaces de hacer que los valores fundamentales de la Unión sean respetados. Debemos ir más allá.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero hablar de política y quiero hablar de cómo este Grupo va a liderar los cambios en Europa. Me alegro de que los tribunales italianos hayan liberado a la capitana Carola Rackete. Esto sucede cuando, efectivamente, hay separación de poderes, y por eso es fundamental preservar la separación de poderes frente a democracias y liberales. Pero debemos ir más allá y evitar que se produzcan estas situaciones dramáticas por la falta de solidaridad en la Unión Europea. Es indecente criminalizar a quienes salvan vidas y es indecente tratar de sacar rédito político de la desgracia de estas personas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablando de política, y hablando de contenido, tampoco apoyaremos a ninguna candidata y a ningún candidato que pretenda quedarse en el inmovilismo frente a la necesidad de reformas con la gobernanza económica, de fortalecimiento de las políticas sociales y de transformación ecológica. El reloj no espera. Nos lo dicen cada viernes los adolescentes europeos. Actuemos ante la emergencia climática global; no les defraudemos. Por eso seremos muy exigentes con la agenda de la próxima Comisión.</p>
      <p sl="en">El cambio climático exige una transformación que debe tener dos ejes: la inclusión, para que sea una transición justa, y la sostenibilidad. Nos decepcionó ver la falta de unanimidad para cumplir los nuestros compromisos adoptados en París. Este Parlamento siempre ha ido por delante, y nuestro Grupo seguirá construyendo mayorías para instar a la Comisión y al Consejo a ser más ambiciosos. Y en este sentido debo felicitar a la Presidencia finlandesa del Consejo por sus propuestas para un futuro sostenible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Seguimos hablando de política. Necesitamos un marco financiero plurianual ambicioso para realizar el cambio necesario; no podemos hacer más con menos. Y este Parlamento dará la batalla para tener los fondos que exigen las políticas que vamos a adoptar. ¿Se acuerdan de la Europa 2020? Pues quedan seis meses y no hemos sido capaces de cumplir los objetivos, de reducir el número de personas en riesgo de pobreza y de exclusión. De veinte millones solo hemos conseguido cinco. Porque mientras algunos se benefician de la crisis, otros siguen pagando sus consecuencias, y a nosotros no nos bastan las grandes cifras. Nos interesan las personas y queremos que el crecimiento económico se traduzca en que las personas, los hombres y mujeres de Europa, puedan vivir mejor con más justicia social.</p>
      <p sl="en">Debemos cambiar la gobernanza económica. Queremos una economía social y solidaria, y para eso es preciso reforzar el Semestre Europeo, de manera que incluya los Objetivos de Desarrollo Sostenible de las Naciones Unidas y el pilar de los derechos sociales. Y también necesitamos reformar la unión monetaria. No podemos esperar a otra crisis para reformar la zona del euro, para dotarla de capacidad fiscal y una garantía de depósitos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero no seremos capaces de alcanzar estos objetivos si no trabajamos al mismo tiempo en una agenda global. Queremos una Europa fuerte, promover estándares de derechos humanos, laborales y medioambientales en los acuerdos multilaterales. La ciudadanía espera más de nosotros: espera que defendamos las conquistas sociales, como los derechos sexuales y reproductivos o los derechos de la comunidad LGTBI; que sigamos avanzando para que situaciones injustas como la brecha salarial entre hombres y mujeres se acabe de una vez por todas. Y, por supuesto, en nuestras manos está acabar con la mayor lacra social que vive en estos momentos Europa, que es la violencia de género, las mujeres que siguen siendo asesinadas por el mero hecho de ser mujeres Y, por supuesto, porque estamos para dar respuestas ya, no podemos esperar más tiempo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Estamos aquí para construir una Europa fuerte sobre los valores de la igualdad, de la solidaridad, de la sostenibilidad y de la justicia, y trabajaremos codo con codo con quien defienda estos objetivos. No defraudemos la confianza de quienes la han puesto en nosotros.</p>
      <a text="(Aplausos)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-016-0000" speaker_id="197631" name="Dacian Cioloș" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului „Renew”. – Domnule președinte, doresc să vă felicit și pe dumneavoastră și pe toți ceilalți colegi care au fost aleși în conducerea Parlamentului în aceste zile. Nu pot decât să-mi exprim speranța că, împreună și împreună cu noul grup „Renew Europe”, vom face ca vocea acestui Parlament să fie mai mult auzită. Pentru ca această voce să fie mai mult auzită, avem nevoie în primul rând de o democratizare a procesului de numiri în funcțiile de conducere în Uniunea Europeană. De aici trebuie să plece aceste propuneri, pentru că altfel putem discuta de nume, putem discuta de echilibru de gen, putem discuta de echilibru geografic, atât timp cât nu vom avea un proces democratic și transparent de alegere a celor care trebuie să conducă Europa, nu avem cum să fim mulțumiți. (aplauze)</p>
      <p sl="en">Da, avem de data aceasta niște propuneri. Colegii care m-au precedat în intervenție și-au spus opiniile legate de modul în care aceste persoane au fost selectate. Nu avem un echilibru, domnule Președinte, nu avem un echilibru geografic în niciun caz. Europa de Est, din păcate, nu mai este reprezentată așa cum a fost în momentul în care dumneavoastră ați fost numit în funcția pe care o reprezentați în momentul de față. Deci, avem nevoie de o modalitate în care să ținem cont de tot ceea ce prevede Tratatul Uniunii Europene și lucrurile acestea trebuie traduse într-un proces democratic. Dragi colegi populari și socialiști, dacă vrem cu adevărat un spirit democratic și dacă vrem ca acești conducători de liste să fie într-adevăr reprezentativi, haideți să ne gândim cum putem pune la punct un sistem de liste de alegeri transnaționale sau de liste prin care acești candidați să poată să fie accesibili tuturor cetățenilor europeni, nu doar cetățenilor germani, nu doar cetățenilor francezi sau spanioli sau olandezi și așa mai departe. (aplauze)</p>
      <p sl="en">Acești „Spitzenkandidaten” vor fi legitimi în momentul în care fiecare cetățean european va avea acces la ei și va putea să îi voteze. Vă propunem să facem acest lucru și să începem aici în Parlament acest lucru, pentru că nu putem aștepta nici de la Comisie, nici de la Consiliu să facă un lucru, care este în responsabilitatea noastră.</p>
      <p sl="en">Grupul „Renew Europe” vă propune și va propune și Consiliului și Parlamentului să organizăm o conferință europeană, o conferință pentru reînnoirea Europei, pentru democratizarea procesului electoral, o conferință cu o durată suficient de lungă, de doi ani, doi ani și jumătate, care să facă propuneri împreună cu Comisia, cu Consiliul, cu cetățenii, cu organizații neguvernamentale, să venim cu propuneri despre cum putem îmbunătăți procesul pe care îl avem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sunt întru totul de acord cu domnul González Pons, sunt întru totul de acord cu Iratxe García Pérez că avem nevoie de oameni care să reprezinte, într-adevăr, europenii și de acolo Consiliul să poată să aleagă. Dar haideți să formalizăm acest proces, ca să nu mai stăm să ne certăm în schimburi de idei și de păreri când deja este prea târziu, când Consiliul trebuie să aleagă și când noi trebuie să putem să decidem! Haideți să folosim acest mandat pentru ca până la alegerile următoare să avem un astfel de dispozitiv care să fie deja agreat cu Parlamentul, cu Consiliul și cu statele membre și să nu mai pierdem vremea aruncându-ne invective și să arătăm cetățenilor europeni că suntem capabili să luăm decizii și suntem capabili să îi reprezentăm!</p>
      <p sl="en">Asta vă propunem, sper să avem susținerea dumneavoastră, pentru că avem timp, de acum până la alegerile viitoare, să parcurgem acest proces.</p>
      <p sl="en">În al doilea rând, valorile europene și statul de drept, respectul pentru drepturile omului, din punctul nostru de vedere și pentru noi, nu sunt negociabile și încălcarea acestora înseamnă subminarea democrației. De aceea, pentru noi este foarte important ca în această legislatură să putem discuta un set de propuneri legislative pentru protejarea statului de drept și pentru drepturile fundamentale și un mecanism eficient care să prevadă inclusiv sancțiuni pentru toate statele membre, să avem acest mecanism foarte clar care să joace în primul rând un rol de prevenție, dar să știm exact ce așteaptă fiecare stat membru care încalcă statul de drept și care nu respectă justiția.</p>
      <p sl="en">De asemenea, trebuie să încheiem cât mai rapid procesul de desemnare a procurorului european. Am așteptat prea mult pentru asta. Această instituție trebuie să fie funcțională cât mai repede pentru a proteja interesele financiare ale Uniunii Europene de corupție, de fraudă, dar, mai ales, pentru a da un semnal foarte clar că Uniunea Europeană știe nu doar să pedepsească, ci știe și să prevină și că instituțiile europene au instrumentele să facă acest lucru.</p>
      <p sl="en">În al treilea rând, avem nevoie de o nouă viziune și de politici care să pună de acord imperativele ecologice cu cele economice și sociale. Avem o agendă privind schimbările climatice care este foarte clară. Trebuie să putem să o aliniem cu obiectivele noastre de dezvoltare economică, cu cele de dezvoltare socială. Mesajul trebuie să fie foarte clar pentru viitoarea Comisie Europeană legat de aceste obiective pe care le avem și în Parlament. În acest context adoptarea noii Agende strategice 2019-2024 pe care Consiliul a adoptat-o este un pas important, dar asta nu este suficient. Din punctul nostru de vedere, trebuie să avem o astfel de agendă politică stabilită aici în Parlamentul European. Sper să putem continua și să ducem până la capăt procesul pe care l-am început cu grupurile politice pro-europene din Parlament prin care să stabilim aceste priorități și să le putem pune pe masa viitoarei conduceri a Comisiei Europene cât mai repede. Parlamentul trebuie să joace un rol cheie în stabilirea acestor priorități și lucrul acesta trebuie să-l facem acum, înainte de numirea viitoarei președinte sau a viitorului președinte al Comisiei Europene. Altfel riscăm iar să fie prea târziu. Este responsabilitatea noastră, a forțelor politice pro-europene din acest Parlament, să punem pe masa viitoarei Comisii Europene prioritățile strategice ale Parlamentului. Trebuie să facem lucrul acesta acum, pentru că cetățenii europeni așteaptă o înnoire a modului în care se face politica europeană și această înnoire trebuie să plece de aici din Parlament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-017-0000" speaker_id="96648" name="Philippe Lamberts" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, je voudrais d’abord souhaiter la bienvenue aux deux tiers des membres qui arrivent ici pour la première fois. J’étais très ému, il y a dix ans, lorsque je me suis assis dans cette enceinte, l’émotion de représenter collectivement 500 millions de citoyens européens. Alors certes, à l’échelle du monde, c’est relativement modeste – 7 % – mais c’est la première fois que l’humanité s’essaye à la démocratie transnationale. Souvenez-vous, 26 mai, 200 millions d’Européennes et d’Européens participaient à l’élection de notre Parlement, le siège précisément de cette première démocratie transnationale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dans la foulée du scrutin, et pour répondre à la mobilisation citoyenne sans précédent, je me suis pris à rêver que des groupes politiques résolument engagés en faveur de la construction européenne décidaient de forger ensemble un contrat de projet. Ce projet de changements n’aurait d’autre but que de trouver, en cette enceinte, une majorité large et stable pour répondre ensemble à la triple urgence environnementale, sociale et démocratique et de la sorte, faire la démonstration que l’Union européenne travaille au service de toutes et de tous. Cet accord autour d’un contrat de projet aurait ensuite permis aux groupes impliqués de désigner une personnalité directement issue des élections pour l’incarner, comme président ou présidente de la Commission européenne. Un projet solide et cohérent, une personnalité crédible pour l’incarner, le tout porté par une majorité large, incluant les forces politiques gagnantes des élections. Face à cela, le Conseil européen n’aurait eu d’autre choix que d’accepter, au risque, dans le cas contraire, de se heurter à une confrontation stérile avec le Parlement, une confrontation dont il ne serait pas sorti gagnant. Dans un tel scénario, le Parlement européen aurait affirmé comme jamais auparavant, sa capacité d’être l’expression démocratique première des citoyennes et des citoyens de l’Union. Il aurait par la même occasion apporté une réponse au désenchantement à l’égard du politique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voilà chers collègues ce qu’aurait pu être la situation à l’ouverture de notre première session plénière. C’est à ce scénario que le groupe des Verts/Alliance libre européenne s’est préparé depuis plusieurs mois. C’est en vue de le réaliser que nous nous sommes engagés sans réserve au fil des semaines écoulées. Certes, le défi était énorme et le temps nous était compté, mais là où il y a la volonté, comme vous le savez, il y a un chemin. C’est ici même, au Parlement européen, que cette volonté a manqué. Une majorité de ce Parlement a en effet préféré un chemin qui l’amènera inéluctablement à devenir l’exécutante des décisions prises ailleurs, au Conseil européen, à moins bien sûr que les expressions martiales, que j’ai entendues à ma gauche et à ma droite, se traduisent dans les faits, mais permettez-moi, à ce stade-ci en tout cas, d’en douter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un Conseil européen, cinq jours de marchandages peu glorieux où les logiques partisanes et nationales ont pris le pas sur le projet et sur son incarnation. Tout cela pour aboutir à un casting dont on peut douter de la capacité à impulser le changement dont nos sociétés ont besoin et que nos concitoyens attendent. Et s’il est légitime – et je l’ai beaucoup entendu dans cette enceinte – de critiquer les chefs d’État et de gouvernement, je voudrais vous dire à toutes et à tous que si le Parlement sort affaibli de cet épisode, il devra d’abord et avant tout s’en prendre à lui-même.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je voudrais remercier ici le président Tusk pour les mots aimables qu’il a adressés de manière assez explicite à la famille politique que j’ai l’honneur de diriger ici au Conseil. Je crois vos mots sincères mais je dois constater que, autour de la table du Conseil – mais je dirais même ici dans cette enceinte – cette volonté d’associer la famille de l’écologie politique, à la gestion des cinq années qui viennent, ne semble pas uniformément partagée et je pense que c’est un euphémisme. Mais tout cela ne tempère pas notre enthousiasme, forts de la confiance renouvelée de nos concitoyens, nous ne baisserons pas les bras. Dans les cinq ans qui viennent, nous utiliserons le levier de nos 75 députés et de nos équipes pour faire avancer la cause d’une Europe plus juste, plus durable et plus démocratique. Une Europe à la pointe du combat pour la préservation de notre climat, de la biodiversité et de nos ressources naturelles; une Europe championne de la lutte pour la justice sociale, fiscale, économique et pour l’égalité de genre; une Europe à l’avant-garde de la défense des libertés des droits humains et d’une démocratie toujours plus participative. En bref, une Europe qui remette la dignité de tous les êtres humains au centre de ces politiques plutôt que la maximisation du profit de certains. Cette cause – et j’ai entendu certains d’entre vous le dire – ne se monopolise pas, elle se partage. Nous agirons de concert avec toutes celles et tous ceux qui, au sein de cette institution, dans les autres institutions européennes, dans les États membres, dans les gouvernements nationaux, régionaux, locaux et surtout dans la société civile avec toutes celles et tous ceux qui partagent cette cause.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ne nous y trompons pas, chers collègues, notre maison brûle. Face à la triple urgence environnementale, sociale et démocratique, seule une telle alliance pour le changement pourra nous sauver.</p>
      <a text="(Applaudissements)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-018-0000" speaker_id="124780" name="Marco Zanni" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ID. – Signor Presidente, Presidente Tusk, onorevoli colleghi, ancora una volta le istituzioni europee hanno offerto uno spettacolo indegno ai cittadini. Chi aveva, dopo la campagna elettorale, dopo le elezioni del 26 maggio, una minima speranza di cambiamento nei metodi e nei programmi è rimasto deluso.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lo spettacolo che è stato offerto e lo scontro interistituzionale che abbiamo visto andare avanti in questi giorni è un qualcosa che veramente i cittadini europei non saranno in grado di comprendere. Il Consiglio ha deciso di gettare nel cestino un metodo discutibile che il Parlamento ha tentato di difendere, quello del candidato guida (Spitzencandidaten) e oggi il Parlamento e i gruppi parlamentari si lamentano che nel pacchetto concordato tra i capi di Stato e di governo non ci sia stato alcun rispetto.</p>
      <p sl="en">E anche qui, dimostrate la vostra ipocrisia e la vostra poca coerenza nel dar seguito ai fatti con le parole. Se veramente il Parlamento si vuol far rispettare, se veramente il Parlamento, o la maggioranza in Parlamento, vogliono difendere il metodo del candidato guida, alle parole possono far seguire i fatti. Se veramente volete essere coerenti, potete votare contro la candidata che il Consiglio ha proposto per la Presidenza della Commissione. Se farete un gesto di questo tipo, potete essere considerati coerenti. Altrimenti le vostre rimarranno, come sempre e come spesso avete dimostrato, parole al vento, dimostrando una volta di più che questa Istituzione non vale niente e non ha voce in capitolo nelle decisioni europee.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda il pacchetto proposto dal Consiglio – e ovviamente aspettiamo quelle che saranno le linee programmatiche – i presupposti, come già detto, non fanno presagire un forte cambiamento, quello che ci hanno chiesto i cittadini europei il 26 maggio; non fanno presagire un cambio di linea che possa andare a risolvere i problemi che i cittadini europei stanno affrontando e dove la maggioranza, che ha governato in Europa fino ad oggi, ha fallito profondamente.</p>
      <p sl="en">La crisi economica: oggi l'Europa è il continente che cresce meno; è un continente che sta rimanendo indietro e questa è la conseguenza di scelte scellerate prese da queste istituzioni, che non solo non sono state in grado di aiutare i cittadini, ma molto spesso hanno aggravato i problemi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il tema della sicurezza interna: chi è stato presente nella scorsa legislatura ha dovuto vivere nelle due sedi del Parlamento due gravissimi attentati. Oggi i nostri cittadini non sono in grado di girare per le nostre città sicuri e, in questo, queste istituzioni non sono state in grado di dare una risposta.</p>
      <p sl="en">E il terzo punto riguarda la gestione dei flussi migratori: finché non saremo in grado di proteggere i nostri confini esterni, finché non saremo in grado di proteggere i nostri cittadini, queste istituzioni non solo non troveranno mai un accordo su come redistribuire chi ha diritto di entrare in Europa, ma il rischio è che questo continente venga schiacciato da flussi migratori che non sono sostenibili.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per quanto riguarda quello che farà il gruppo Identità e democrazia nei prossimi anni, nonostante il fatto che questa maggioranza o la maggioranza che verrà ha deciso, ancora una volta, di dimostrare che questa Istituzione non è un'Istituzione democratica, escludendo chi rappresenta il quasi 20% dei parlamentari di questa Assemblea, noi continueremo a lavorare per combattere una visione d'Europa fallimentare, per combattere la centralizzazione a Bruxelles e per stabilire che, se l'Europa vuole salvarsi, deve ripartire dagli Stati membri, dagli Stati-nazione, che sono l'unico spazio di vera democrazia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi continueremo a lavorare per mettere in discussione quella che è la retorica del "TINA" (There Is No Alternative), di quello che ci proponete ogni volta per risolvere i problemi europei, cioè dare sempre più poteri a burocrati lontani dai cittadini. No, questa non è l'Europa che vogliono i cittadini. Questa non è l'Europa che vogliamo e se continuerete in questa direzione, l'Europa rischia davvero la dissoluzione. Le divergenze tra gli Stati membri e tra le istituzioni continuano ad ampliarsi e non andremo in nessuna direzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il gruppo Identità e democrazia ripartirà da questa visione: un'Europa dove gli Stati membri guidano la cooperazione europea e tutelano le diversità che voi volete omologare per legge.</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-019-0000" speaker_id="96796" name="Ryszard Antoni Legutko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, congratulations and all the best. I think the most obvious conclusion that comes from the last Council is that the Spitzenkandidaten mechanism is dead. It is dead and gone. It’s even more dead than the parrot in the Monty Python sketch. I’m not sorry that it is dead because, look, there is nothing about Spitzenkandidat in the Treaties. Not a single sentence, not a single word, nothing. I know of course that the attitude of many people in European politics, including this Chamber, towards the rules and the Treaties has been consistently cavalier, to say the least. Mr Timmermans was not a candidate of the people, of the European people. Mr Timmermans was a candidate of the left-wing political establishment and it is good that he has gone. And I hope he will not return, because essentially the Spitzenkandidat process was to conserve the power of the existing political establishment in Europe, not to open the political space for the people. Far from it. On the contrary.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have problems with rules all the time, and the European Parliament has had consistent problems with respecting the rules. Yesterday we had a lamentable spectacle which showed how a lot of people here are openly disdainful of the rules. President Tusk, of course the Council has no right whatsoever to indicate the Vice-President of the Commission – that is a blatant violation of the Treaty. It is the sole discretionary power of the President of the Commission. So, as I say, the Council is not blameless either. But there is good news, I think. The good news from the last Council is that the EU big guys failed to achieve what they wanted – they wanted to impose their own concept, their own power structure, on the rest of the Member States, with the expectation that it would be humbly accepted. Well it was not, and I hope that some lessons were drawn from that and that it will result in a change of practice. The days when two or three governments and their acolytes could dictate the solutions – even the names – to the entire European continent, are gone.</p>
      <p sl="en">What I am worried about when I hear my predecessor here is that you, ladies and gentlemen, don’t seem to draw any lessons from what happened in the elections. You seem to be determined to continue the same strategy. The number of people who are openly critical of this strategy is increasing. There are more people critical of the strategy now than there were five years ago. And the number is continuing to rise. Yet you seem to be blind and deaf – you don’t hear any warning signals, but you should, because if you do not change course then the consequences will be disastrous. As I said, there is a slight signal from the last Council that things might get better – at least I was hopeful of that – but I lost a lot of hope when I came here and listened to what most of you have said. However, when the milk is spilt please remember that I warned you.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-020-0000" speaker_id="190517" name="Martin Schirdewan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Erst mal möchte ich Sie erneut beglückwünschen zu Ihrer Wahl, Herr Sassoli. Wir erwarten von Ihnen nichts weniger, als ein Präsident zu sein, der für Transparenz, für Überparteilichkeit steht und der auch die Rechte des Parlaments gegenüber dem Rat und auch gegenüber der Kommission zu verteidigen weiß.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das bringt mich zum eigentlichen Thema: Der Rat, Herr Präsident Tusk, hat ja jetzt eine Lösung im Personalpoker gefunden, und einige Kollegen haben sich über das Ergebnis beschwert, obwohl ihre Parteienfamilien daran intensiv beteiligt gewesen sind. Ich will Ihnen an dieser Stelle deutlich sagen, dass der eigentliche Skandal darin besteht, dass solche Lösungen in Hinterzimmern gefunden werden, dass intransparent an Lösungen gearbeitet wird, die das Parlament nicht mit einbeziehen und die der Demokratie in Europa tatsächlich Hohn sprechen. Das Vertrauen der Wählerinnen und Wähler wird dadurch enttäuscht, der europäischen Demokratie ein großer Schaden zugefügt.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
      <p sl="en">Die Leute außerhalb der Hinterzimmer und auch außerhalb der Edelrestaurants, in denen diese Gespräche ja stattgefunden haben sollen, kriegen den Eindruck, es geht nur noch um Posten und nicht mehr um Inhalte. Aber wir als Linke im Europäischen Parlament haben von Millionen Wählerinnen und Wählern den Auftrag bekommen, hier in Europa, in der Europäischen Union für einen progressiven Politikwechsel zu kämpfen. Und wir nehmen diesen Auftrag auch gern an.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nun haben ja einige Fraktionen, einige Kolleginnen und Kollegen in den letzten Wochen intensiv miteinander verhandelt und haben versucht, einen gemeinsamen Koalitionsvertrag auf die Beine zu stellen. Das ist ja auch angesprochen worden – also die Grünen, die Sozialdemokraten, auch die Liberalen und auch die Konservativen. Ich denke, dass Minimalkonsense den politischen Herausforderungen unserer Zeit nicht gerecht werden. Die Linksfraktion will effektive Maßnahmen gegen den Klimanotstand ergreifen. Dafür braucht es progressive Mehrheiten in diesem Haus. Wir wollen soziale Rechte in der EU stärken, wir wollen gegen Steuerdumping, Steuerhinterziehung und gegen Geldwäsche vorgehen. Auch dafür braucht es progressive Mehrheiten in diesem Haus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und, Herr Kommissar, die Kommission hat ja vor Kurzem groß das geplante EU-Mercosur-Freihandelsabkommen zelebriert. Ich will Ihnen sagen, dass es für meine Gruppe völlig inakzeptabel ist, dass dieses Abkommen unterzeichnet wird. Es kann doch nicht Politik der Europäischen Union sein, Menschenrechte, soziale Rechte, Umweltstandards für ein paar Euro über Bord zu werfen! Und außerdem soll dieses Abkommen auch noch mit der rechtsextremen Regierung in Brasilien unterzeichnet werden. Eine solche Politik ist es doch, die die Rechtsextremen erst salonfähig macht! Das findet unseren entschiedenen Widerspruch. Das versteht doch kein Mensch mehr! Ich fordere die Kolleginnen und Kollegen hier im Parlament auf, mit uns gemeinsam gegen dieses geplante Freihandelsabkommen Position zu beziehen.</p>
      <a text="(Beifall)"/>
      <p sl="en">Ja, die Linksfraktion tritt für eine humane Migrations- und Asylpolitik der EU ein, die universelle Menschenrechte garantiert. Und ja, wir freuen uns deshalb sehr, dass es in der Auseinandersetzung zwischen der Kapitänin Carola Rackete und dem selbsternannten Il Capitano eins zu null für Carola steht. Ich finde, so kann es weitergehen. Wir laden die progressiven Kräfte hier im Haus ein: Lassen Sie uns gemeinsam an einem progressiven Politikwechsel für die Europäische Union arbeiten! Wir als Linksfraktion haben unser Programm bekannt gegeben, wir stehen dafür bereit.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-021-0000" speaker_id="124777" name="Tiziana Beghin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, ho in mano una copia del Trattato sul funzionamento dell'Unione europea e invito tutti a leggerlo con attenzione. Scoprirete quante volte questo trattato sia stato tradito.</p>
      <p sl="en">È stato tradito negando la solidarietà all'Italia sui migranti. È stato tradito applicando alla lettera le regole per alcuni, mentre si chiudeva un occhio per gli amici degli amici. Qui si parla di trasparenza e poi ci sono riunioni in Consiglio a porte chiuse. Si parla di principio di precauzione e poi si autorizza l'utilizzo del glifosato. Si parla di difesa dei lavoratori e poi non esiste un salario minimo che garantisca i diritti di milioni di cittadini europei.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Presidente Conte allo scorso Consiglio ha messo il dito nella piaga: in Europa la macchina c'è, ma il motore si inceppa. Avete passato le ultime settimane a litigare per le poltrone ma vi garantisco che i cittadini non hanno capito nulla, perché avete parlato di tutto tranne che dei loro problemi, quelli veri!</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi, cambiamo il motore di questa Europa. Cambiamo insieme le regole: diamo più potere al Parlamento europeo nella scelta dei candidati. Fate come il governo Conte! Non accontentatevi del prendere o lasciare. Non siate spettatori di un'operetta scritta altrove. L'Europa più viva siamo noi: siamo noi che siamo legittimati dal voto popolare; siamo noi che abbiamo il peso di questo Trattato sulle spalle.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ritorniamo alle origini. Ritorniamo a questo Trattato: più solidarietà, più diritti, più sviluppo, meno lezioncine, meno direttori franco-tedeschi, meno arroganza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Insieme possiamo cambiare questa Europa. Ce lo chiedono i cittadini.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-022-0000" speaker_id="197744" name="Ann Widdecombe" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, it is a great honour to speak on behalf of the largest single party in this place. And may I say that if I needed any convincing at all that the best thing for Britain is to leave here as soon as possible it was the way that those elections were conducted yesterday: if that is this place’s idea of democracy, then that is a serious betrayal of every country that is represented here, because it is not democratic at all.</p>
      <p sl="en">And that is just one of many reasons why Britain is right to be leaving this place, hopefully at Halloween. It is right because there is a pattern consistent throughout history of oppressed people turning on the oppressors, slaves against their owners, the peasantry against the feudal barons, and colonies, Mr Verhofstadt, against their empires. And that is why Britain is leaving. And it doesn’t matter which language you use: we are going, and we are glad to be going.</p>
      <p sl="en">I represent the South West of the United Kingdom and I found, on my very first day, that this place has decided – or at least the powers-that-be have decided – actually to increase the size of fishermen’s meshes, thereby reducing their income by 40%. That’s what you do here, that’s why we’re going. Nous allons, wir gehen, we’re off!</p>
      <a text="(Applause from a section of the House)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-024-0000" speaker_id="124691" name="Κώστας Μαυρίδης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, στα πρόσφατα συμπεράσματα του Ευρωπαϊκού Συμβουλίου περιλαμβάνεται η νέα στρατηγική για την επόμενη πενταετία που έχει ως αφετηρία την προστασία των πολιτών και των ελευθεριών. Συγκεκριμένα, η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση δεσμεύεται να προασπίζει τα δικαιώματα και τις ελευθερίες των πολιτών της, όπως αναγνωρίζονται στις Συνθήκες, και να τους προστατεύει από υφιστάμενες και αναδυόμενες απειλές. Ο σεβασμός του κράτους δικαίου, λοιπόν, αγαπητοί συνάδελφοι, είναι το μέγιστο συμφέρον και ο ακρογωνιαίος λίθος του πολιτισμού μας, που μας κρατά ενωμένους απέναντι στις απειλές είτε εσωτερικές είτε εξωτερικές.</p>
      <p sl="en">Το Ευρωπαϊκό Συμβούλιο, λοιπόν, και η Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή σήμερα με τον εκπρόσωπό της –εύγε!– αναγνωρίζουν την ανάγκη να αντιμετωπίσουμε και τις παρανομίες και τις απειλές του Erdoğan στην Ανατολική Μεσόγειο εναντίον της Κυπριακής Δημοκρατίας με στοχευμένες κυρώσεις και χωρίς καθυστερήσεις. Εκεί κρίνεται το κράτος δικαίου της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης και, σήμερα, όλοι μας όσοι πιστεύουμε στην Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση δηλώνουμε Κύπριοι.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-025-0000" speaker_id="197755" name="Martin Horwood (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, as one of the large new group of British Members of the European Parliament,</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">both Liberal Democrat and Green and from other parties, who do not want to turn our backs on Europe,</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">can I tell you, Mr President, that what you heard from that back corner does not represent the views of everyone in the United Kingdom.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">And can I thank you, President Tusk, for your patience with our Government and national parliament, and can I ask you to ask your successor to continue that policy of time and patience and understanding, even when it appears our Government has no plan. Mr Bean or Monty Python might have done it better.</p>
      <p sl="en">But Brexit is not inevitable. Opinion is shifting in Britain, otherwise we would not be here,</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">and those of us who support Europe also need Europe’s support.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-026-0000" speaker_id="125064" name="Μαρία Σπυράκη" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, Πρόεδρε Tusk, Αντιπρόεδρε Šefčovič, η νέα αρχή που βλέπουμε σήμερα εδώ αποτυπώνει τη νέα συμμαχία του ευρωπαϊκού κέντρου που αποτελείται από το Ευρωπαϊκό Λαϊκό Κόμμα, τους Σοσιαλδημοκράτες, τους Renew Europe και τους Πράσινους. Μαζί, με μία κοινή διακήρυξη κατευθύνσεων, οφείλουμε να διασφαλίσουμε στους πολίτες μας, πρώτα από όλα, δουλειές και ανάπτυξη.</p>
      <p sl="en">Παρά το γεγονός ότι η ανεργία στην ευρωζώνη κινείται στο 7,5%, σύμφωνα με τα τελευταία στοιχεία, χώρες, όπως η Ελλάδα, χρειάζονται ένα «αναπτυξιακό σοκ», προκειμένου να προχωρήσουν. Χρειαζόμαστε δουλειές που θα συνδυάζουν την ψηφιοποίηση της οικονομίας, την αντιμετώπιση της κλιματικής αλλαγής και μέσω της κυκλικής οικονομίας, την εκπαίδευση αλλά και την επανεκπαίδευση. Χρειαζόμαστε, επίσης, να περιφρουρήσουμε τις ευρωπαϊκές αξίες της φιλελεύθερης δημοκρατίας χωρίς εκπτώσεις και χωρίς συμβιβασμούς.</p>
      <p sl="en">Σε αυτή την πενταετία δεν έχουμε κανένα άλλοθι. Βιώνουμε ήδη τις επιπτώσεις της κλιματικής αλλαγής. Γνωρίζουμε τον φόβο των ανθρώπων μπροστά στην ψηφιακή μετεξέλιξη. Ξέρουμε τι συμβαίνει στην Ουγγαρία, στην Πολωνία, στη Ρουμανία. Οφείλουμε να συζητήσουμε, να συμφωνήσουμε και να εφαρμόσουμε μια πολιτική που θα διατηρήσει για την Ευρώπη τη φήμη ότι η ήπειρος αυτή είναι το καλύτερο μέρος για να ζει κανείς στον πλανήτη.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-027-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Domnule președinte, domnule președinte Tusk, domnule comisar, dragi colegi, în primul rând, vreau să îi felicit pe cei noi aleși și da, e un bilanț, îl felicit și pe domnul Tusk, cel puțin din două puncte de vedere: longevitatea mandatului și faptul că a avut o reprezentare estică. Dar, domnule președinte Tusk, ce lăsați ca moștenire din partea Consiliului? Lipsă de transparență, total dezechilibru în instituțiile europene, între est și vest, și nu mă refer numai la liderii celor trei instituții, mă refer și la funcționarii care lucrează în instituțiile europene. Vă rog să vedeți care este echilibrul între angajații în instituțiile europene, între statele din est și vest.</p>
      <p sl="en">Și ce mai lăsați, domnule președinte? O strategie incoerentă legată de lărgirea Uniunii Europene, o procedură nespecifică democrației, și anume, majoritatea în Consiliu, și lăsați două state pedepsite - Bulgaria și România - deși avem rezoluția Parlamentului, domnule președinte, și ați promis de nenumărate ori că vă încheiați mandatul cu România și Bulgaria în Schengen, pentru că întrunim toate condițiile tehnice din 2011.</p>
      <p sl="en">Și ce mai lăsați, domnule președinte? Lăsați impresia că totul se aranjează în spatele unei cortine și asta nu încurajează cetățenii europeni pentru a crește încrederea în Uniunea Europeană. De aceea, dragi colegi noi, vă rog să înțelegeți că depinde de noi să creștem importanța și puterea Parlamentului European. Și domnule președinte Sassoli, vă felicit pentru alegere, dar nu uitați că avem niște sarcini extrem de grele în perioada următoare și vă rog să țineți cont de poziția Parlamentului în negocierea cu cele două instituții.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-028-0000" speaker_id="96812" name="Juan Fernando López Aguilar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, presidente Tusk, la ciudadanía europea existe, como ha escuchado usted muy bien. Lo afirman el Tratado de Lisboa y la Carta de los Derechos Fundamentales y la representa directamente este Parlamento Europeo desde hace cuarenta años ―la única institución directamente elegida por la ciudadanía. Solo que, en este momento de la última elección, es la primera vez en que la participación electoral ha subido por encima del 50 % después de haber declinado elección tras elección. ¿Por qué? Por la fuerza motivadora de que cuando la ciudadanía vota influye decisivamente en el liderazgo de la Comisión Europea, en su presidencia, y usted ha sido incapaz de ejercer su autoridad para preservar a los candidatos que dieron la cara ante el electorado, ni siquiera al candidato Frans Timmermans, que ha sido vetado por Estados que fueron puestos en su sitio, precisamente por la defensa de Timemermans del Estado de Derecho y de la democracia,</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero a este Parlamento le toca la última palabra no solamente en la investidura de la candidata a presidir la Comisión sino en la de todas y cada una de las candidatas y de los candidatos a integrar la Comisión, los veintiocho. Y hará bien en examinar con rigor y rechazar a aquellos que no se comprometan con el desafío social, climático, digital, pero también con la mirada migratoria, que debe ser cambiada para impedir que pueda ser posible que se criminalice a quien salva vidas en la mar —como se ha hecho con la capitana del Sea Watch—o con que la Unión Europea no esté a la altura de su acción humanitaria para impedir acciones de retorno a países inseguros como Libia —donde un campamento de refugiados ha sido bombardeado con un balance criminal de cuarenta víctimas mortales—.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-029-0000" speaker_id="4533" name="Neena Gill" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, delighted that you’re our new President and that’s about the only good news. To say I’m disappointed with the outcome of the Council would be an understatement. Mr Tusk, President Tusk, you know, under your watch we have widened the gap with the citizens of Europe. I think it’s really bad for democracy and the level of engagement we’ve had this last time it’s going to be very, very hard to repeat.</p>
      <p sl="en">My concern is that, you know, those who are against the rule of law have won. The Visegrád 4 have succeeded in morally bankrupting the entire European Council. You all signed up to the spitzenkandidat process and you have reined back and I think if this House capitulates with that, this would be, you know, arm twisting, and negative forces will take over, not just in the UK as they have, and you can see the evidence here, but elsewhere as well, so it’s really important that this House sticks with the spitzenkandidat process and rejects the proposals of the Council.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-030-0000" speaker_id="124873" name="Ангел Джамбазки" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Уважаеми г-н Туск, уважаеми г-н Шевчович, моята критика е към вас. Пакетът, който предлагате, е резултат не на политика, а на нечистоплътен, непочтен пазарлък и сделка без принципи и без открити лица. Вие, уважаеми, излъгахте своите избиратели. Издигнахте водещи кандидати, които после не предложихте на гласуване. Нарушихте собствените си правила. Това не е демокрация, уважаеми, това е подмяна. От вашата сделка липсват и Централна и Източна Европа и това също е позор.</p>
      <p sl="en">И сега искам да се обърна и към вас, уважаеми колеги. Вие всички сте против тази сделка, но всички вчера гласувахте за нея. Кого лъжете в случая, себе си или своите избиратели? Когато не ви хареса сделката, правите нещо много просто – издигате си г-н Вебер за председател на Комисията и гласувате за него. Или г-н Тимерманс и гласувате за него, но вие не го правите. Вие тук сте против, но иначе гласувате за сделката. Това е подмяна и това е позор.</p>
      <p sl="en">И още нещо, уважаеми. Вие всички говорите за правила, нито един от вас не спази времето. Говорите за права на жените, а когато една дама отзад изрази мнение, което не ви харесва, вие ѝ пречихте да говори. Къде тук е истината? Може да не сте съгласни с това мнение, но поне го уважавайте. Преди малко говорихте за демокрация, а вчера се обединихте всички, цялата дъга от крайно ляво до християндемократи и попречихте демократично да бъдат избрани в ръководството заместник-председатели на ЕКР и на „Идентичност и демокрация“. Това ли е демокрацията? Не, не е. Когато не ви харесва нечие мнение, вие не го приемате или заглушавате. Това не е демокрация.</p>
      <p sl="en">И още нещо. Одата на радостта е прекрасно класическо изпълнение, но аз имам свой химн, българския химн, казва се „Мила Родино“ и на него ставам.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-031-0000" speaker_id="96830" name="Enikő Győri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Képviselőtársaim! Azt gondolom, hogy komoly tanulságokkal lettünk gazdagabbak az elmúlt hetekben. Az első, hogy bukásra vannak ítélve azok a kísérletek, amelyek az emberek akaratát nem veszik figyelembe. Nem történhetett másként, mint ahogy végül történt, hogy az EP választásokon győztes legnagyobb pártcsalád, a Néppárt adja majd az Európai Bizottság elnökét.</p>
      <p sl="en">Öröm továbbá, hogy az uniós szerződéseknek meg nem felelő alkuk megsemmisülnek. A szerződéseken túl terjeszkedni, az intézmények közötti egyensúlyt felborítani ugyanis nem lehetséges. A csúcs előtti rendszeren a történelem túllépett, és azt gondolom, hogy ez így helyes.</p>
      <p sl="en">A harmadik, hogy nem érdemes egyes országcsoportokat megpróbálni erőből lenyomni, velük szemben kettős mércét alkalmazni. Az unió nem épülhet Közép-Európa, a visegrádi országok ellenében.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Képviselőtársaim! A Stratégiai agendával van új programunk, az állam és kormányfők egyhangúsággal fogadták el. Lesznek új vezetőink, van esély az új kezdetre. Erős tagállamoknak a szerződésekben lefektetett szabályok mentén kell együttműködniük, azon nem túlterjeszkedve, egymás alkotmányos identitását tiszteletben tartva, megőrizve a kontinens keresztény gyökereit és szembeszállva azokkal, akik azokat a bevándorlás révén meg akarják változtatni. Ilyen Európát szeretnénk közösen építeni! Köszönöm szépen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-032-0000" speaker_id="97968" name="Андрей Ковачев" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Компромис, самата дума, означава, че накрая никой няма да е доволен, някои по-малко, някои повече, но всички са недоволни. Ние предложихме един прозрачен, един демократичен принцип на водещите кандидати. Той не беше спазен от Съвета. Също така и нашите колеги от социалистите и от предишните, както се наричаха, либералите, не спазиха това, че партията, която е получила най-много представители в Европейския парламент на европейските избори, техният водещ кандидат да бъде председател на Европейската комисия. Това не се случи.</p>
      <p sl="en">Аз смятам, че сега г-жа Урсула фон дер Лeйен трябва да спечели доверието на политическите групи, да представи своите виждания и ние тогава ще решим, защото Европейският парламент е независима, самостоятелна институция, единствената директно избрана от европейските граждани и ние трябва да защитим нашето достойнство. Не може Съветът да налага решения, които не минават през демократичен и легитимен избор в Европейския парламент.</p>
      <p sl="en">Също така трябва да кажа, че аз съм горд, че съм българин, горд, че съм европеец и уважавам символите на Европа, европейското знаме, европейския химн и смятам, че това трябва да ни обединява, трябва да сме заедно за един добър, сигурен европейски дом.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-033-0000" speaker_id="197419" name="Valter Flego (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospodine predsjedniče, predsjedniče Tusk, da, Vijeće je završilo. Čitali smo rezultate, vidjeli smo stanje pregovora i ja bih rekao da sve skupa nije bilo najsretnije. Ali, iz svega toga definitivno trebamo izvući pouke. Kad kažem izvući pouke, onda definitivno mislim da se još puno stvari ovdje da promijeniti i ispraviti na način da očekujemo da ljudi koji će ovdje tražiti naše povjerenje dolaze ovdje, predstavljaju program, a mi kao Parlament im mjerimo prolazna vremena. Mislim da više nemamo vremena za pričati o podjeli fotelja , trgovati foteljama nego reći što konkretno će se raditi sljedećih pet godina i polagati račune ovom Parlamentu koji nudi suradnju da s Komisijom itekako učinimo sve da ne zaostajemo za Amerikom, za Kinom nego da budemo svjetski lider. Iz toga razloga, idemo završiti priču o podjeli fotelja, pričati o konkretnim rezultatima i to raditi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-034-0000" speaker_id="34578" name="Robert Hajšel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážený pán predsedajúci, ja by som len chcel povedať, že naozaj tento Parlament a jednotlivé politické frakcie nástojili na zachovaní a uplatnení princípu Spitzenkandidaten. Nepodarilo sa to. Európska rada tomuto procesu nevyhovela a nominácie sú výsledkom politiky za zatvorenými dverami. Horšie je, že sa hovorí veľa o geografickom zastúpení, o geografickej vyváženosti. K tomuto opäť takisto nedošlo. Ešte horšie je, že obeťou toho sú krajiny Vyšehradskej štvorky, ktoré mali dobrého nominanta, dobrého kandidáta, je tu, sedí tu spolu s nami. No a treba povedať, že možno takýto signál – ak je to pravda, že tento kandidát nebol vybratý len kvôli tomu, že je práve zástupcom tohto regiónu, tak je to veľmi zlý signál voličom, je to zlý signál občanom strednej a východnej Európy, a s týmto sa budeme musieť asi nejako vedieť k tomuto postaviť, aj v komunikácii k občanom, aby verili v demokratický princíp, aby verili v prehĺbenie participatívnej demokracie v Európe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-035-0000" speaker_id="197623" name="Thierry Mariani" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, je fais partie de ces nouveaux élus qui sont arrivés dans cet hémicycle avec encore quelques illusions. J’ai entendu ce matin de beaux discours sur les valeurs de démocratie, sur les valeurs de respect des minorités, bref sur ce qu’on classe parmi les valeurs sans jamais vraiment y mettre exactement du concret.</p>
      <p sl="en">Malheureusement, hier j’ai assisté, comme beaucoup, à l’exclusion de parlementaires qui représentaient 20 % de cet hémicycle parce que, comme l’a dit un autre orateur, qu’on soit du groupe ECR ou du groupe ID, on a le tort d’être attaché à une Europe mais peut-être pas à celle que vous proposez. Alors je dis simplement que défendre des grands principes, c’est bien, les appliquer, c’est mieux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour notre part, hier on a assisté à des arrangements entre amis pour exclure 20 % de ces parlementaires. Nous attendrons la semaine prochaine, sans trop d’illusions, pour voir si ces petits arrangements visant à exclure un représentant sur quatre ou sur cinq de cet hémicycle continuent dans la répartition des commissions. Si c’est le cas, alors je comprendrais que votre discours sur la démocratie et les valeurs n’est finalement qu’une simple imposture.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-036-0000" speaker_id="197838" name="Juozas Olekas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dėkoju, ponas pirmininke, už galimybę pasisakyti. Sveikinu Jus su Jūsų išrinkimu. Dėkoju ponui Tuskui ir ponui Šefčovičiui už pristatymą. Dėkoju visiems, kurie minėjo Rytų Europos valstybių nepakankamą atstovavimą Vadovų Tarybos pateiktam pasiūlyme. Ir iš tikrųjų, mes turime kalbėti apie tai, kaip visa Europa vieningai gali atstovauti, kaip žmonių valia išrinkti Europos parlamentarai gali pateikti savo pasiūlymą ir kaip šios institucijos gali bendradarbiauti. Manau, kad be tolygaus atstovavimo mes niekados negalėsime išspręsti tų problemų, kurios kamuoja įvairius Europos regionus: tai šalių vienodo pragyvenimo lygio suartinimas, demokratijos, socialinio teisingumo įteisinimas ir klimato kaitos įveikimas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mieli kolegos, aš manau, kad norint priimti bendrus sprendimus ir pasiekti tų užsibrėžtų tikslų iš tikrųjų reikia geresnio ir tarpinstitucinio bendradarbiavimo. Šiandieną mes matome, kad Vadovų Taryba to neparodė, tačiau aš tikiuosi, kad čia, šitoje demokratijos tvirtovėje, mes, Europos parlamentarai, tą galime padaryti ir pakviesti ateityje Europos Tarybą taip pat elgtis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-038-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Maroš Šefčovič" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Vice-President of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to thank all the honourable Members because they clearly have proved that they are back with new energy, high ambitions and great ideas.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am also very glad that, in all the speeches, I have heard clearly that there is enormous convergence between our institutions on the strategic agenda for the future. We have been working hard over the past five years to make sure not only that the EU will remain the leader in tackling climate change, but also that we are laying the ground for the new, modern, sustainable economy, and therefore one of the big responsibilities for all of us in this new period will be to make sure that we have correct and proper implementation of all the laws that have already been agreed.</p>
      <p sl="en">The cause advanced by Ms García, Mr Ciolos, Mr Pons and Mr Lamberts, to make sure that we use the next five years to build a social, green and fair Europe, is something we must bear in mind throughout the next steps and in planning our work for the future.</p>
      <p sl="en">I very much echo the calls made by many of the honourable Members who say this new economy must ensure that nobody is left behind, that energy poverty is properly tackled, that everyone will see their future in the new economy – including those who are living in coal regions today or in energy-intensive cities and towns built many decades ago – and that we know how to help, we know how to provide them with new hope and new economic plans for the future.</p>
      <p sl="en">What we need to underline – and again this point was made by Ms Iratxe García – is that to get to these very concrete measures we need quick decisions on the next Multiannual Financial Framework. We need to make sure that we do not waste time, that we do not waste weeks, months and days ensuring that all our programmes and ideas are properly financially supported.</p>
      <p sl="en">We know we are not that far from concluding the deal, and we need to make sure that we use the Finnish Presidency for a successful conclusion of the new European budget. We need to build an economy that is not only green and clean but also competitive, and it’s quite clear that, in addition to what we’ve been doing already, we need a new, ambitious approach to all the so-called technological mega-trends. Be it in clean mobility, artificial intelligence, super-computing or robotics, we need to make sure that we can be a strong competitor vis-à-vis the competition from the USA or China – and I’m sure we can do that in our European way, respectful of our citizens, respectful of the environment and respectful of international treaties, international rules and obligations.</p>
      <p sl="en">In that regard, I would also like to reassure Mr Shirdewan that all our new trade agreements, which will be discussed with all of you, respect high trade, environmental and labour standards, and that this is our European response to the creeping trade protectionism which we see around the world. Of course, we in the Commission will be ready to explain to you all the advantages of, and the philosophy behind, these trade deals.</p>
      <p sl="en">With all due respect to our British colleagues, I have to say that we in the Commission will be sorry to see you go, and we still hope that this will not happen.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">And to the colleagues up there, with all my diplomatic skills, I would just say that we would not take that leadership lesson from you.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
      <p sl="en">So, honourable Members, Mr President of Parliament, President of the European Council, I would like to conclude my first address to the new House with an appeal to all of us: let us make sure that we use the coming years to make this century a European one, or at least as European as it can be, because the world needs a strong, united, prosperous Europe.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-039-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Donald Tusk" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President of the European Council">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would very much like our two institutions to cooperate in the best way possible. So today I will refrain from making any comment. I hope that we will all take responsibility for the new leadership being well-balanced in every respect.</p>
      <a text="(Murmurs of discontent)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-5000" speaker_id="124696" name="Andrus Ansip (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjalikult. – Ma tunnustan nõukogus saavutatud kompromissi tippkandidaatide osas. Pean von der Leyenit tugevaks Euroopa Komisjoni presidendi kandidaadiks. Nõustun tema seisukohtadega ühise julgeoleku- ja kaitsepoliitika küsimustes. Tema tugevus on kindlasti ka Balti regiooni tundmine. Siiski on minu jaoks saavutatud kokkuleppes probleem – tippametikohtade jaotuses puudub geograafiline tasakaalustatus. Esindatud pole ei Kesk- ja Ida-Euroopa ega Põhja-Euroopa riigid.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-7500" speaker_id="96706" name="João Ferreira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – O processo de escolha dos ocupantes dos cargos de topo nas instituições da UE traduz, em primeiro lugar, uma afirmação de poder por parte do diretório de potências que sempre determinou o rumo da UE, nomeadamente do eixo franco-alemão, hegemonizado pela Alemanha, uim diretório que decide e impõe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na sequência dos resultados das eleições para o Parlamento Europeu, que evidenciaram uma erosão eleitoral dos partidos da direita e da social-democracia, membros respetivamente do PPE e do S&amp;D, tornou-se necessário reconfigurar o denominado «Consenso de Bruxelas», passando este a incluir com outro protagonismo os chamados «liberais», agora formalmente necessários à formação das maiorias necessárias para impor a continuidade das políticas vigentes.</p>
      <p sl="en">O compromisso alcançado confirma o embuste dos chamados «candidatos a Presidente da Comissão Europeia», manobra de manipulação política que procurou dar uma aparência democrática a um processo antidemocrático na sua essência, dando, ao mesmo tempo, cobertura aos esforços de aprofundamento do carácter federalista das instituições da UE e do próprio processo de integração capitalista.</p>
      <p sl="en">A perceção pública generalizadamente negativa face a este processo pode levar os seus protagonistas a contemporizações, ajustes e alterações pontuais, ou mesmo uma ou outra cambalhota, no consenso agora alcançado. Mas a intenção é clara: para lá dos personagens do momento, insistir nas mesmas políticas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-7812" speaker_id="197634" name="Pedro Marques" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – A realização de eleições constitui um momento maior das democracias, permitindo a expressão da vontade dos eleitores e a aproximação destes do processo político, aspeto essencial para a saúde das democracias e a legitimação das instituições.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nessa medida, o processo de «spitzenkandidaten» constituía um avanço muito positivo, aumentando a transparência das escolhas políticas na União Europeia e conferindo uma legitimidade reforçada à Comissão Europeia. A incapacidade demonstrada de concluir o processo de «spitzenkandidaten» com sucesso foi, por isso, bastante negativa para o necessário reforço da proximidade entre os cidadãos e as instituições.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não obstante, isso não nos deverá fazer desfocar daquilo que é mais importante para os cidadãos, que são as políticas concretas que devem ser concretizadas para que a União Europeia seja mais justa, coesa e sustentável.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-8125" speaker_id="129073" name="Urmas Paet (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjalikult. – Euroopa Liidu uute juhtide kokkuleppe suurimad võitjad on sooline tasakaal ning ALDE/Renew Europe. Euroopa Komisjoni presidendi ja Euroopa Keskpanga juhi kandidaadid on naised ning ALDE/RE sai Euroopa Ülemkogu eesistuja koha. Esmakordselt sai ALDE/RE koha ELi juhtimise tipus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sama hästi ei läinud geograafilisel tasakaalul, sest Ida-Euroopa ja Põhjamaade esindajaid tippametites pole, ning Euroopa Rahvaparteil, kes pidi taganema enda poolt tugevalt toetatud tippkandidaatide ehk Spitzenkandidateni süsteemist. Samas on muidugi kõige olulisem ehk see, milliseks kujuneb järgmisel viiel aastal Euroopa Liidu poliitikategemise sisu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="3-040-8750" speaker_id="197754" name="Sandra Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – O processo que conduziu ao desfecho verificado no Conselho Europeu, relativo à nomeação de cargos de direção das instituições da UE, expressou contradições indissociáveis da crise deste processo de integração capitalista, que não rompeu com o denominado «consenso de Bruxelas» entre o PSE e o PPE; antes o aprofundou, passando a incluir os chamados «liberais».</p>
      <p sl="en">O compromisso e os protagonistas encontrados confirmam a insistência no aprofundamento das políticas federalistas de afronta à soberania dos Estados; das políticas neoliberais de ataque aos direitos laborais e sociais, aos serviços públicos e às funções sociais do Estado; das políticas militaristas e securitárias, com expressões autoritárias e antidemocráticas – políticas que alimentam a extrema-direita.</p>
      <p sl="en">As decisões do Conselho Europeu comprovam a falsidade e o carácter manipulatório das tiradas eleitoralistas sobre «dimensão social», «contratos sociais», «alianças progressistas» ou «legitimação democrática» da UE.</p>
      <p sl="en">Foi novamente o diretório de potências da UE que ditou o desfecho político de um processo que continuará um caminho que já provou ser desastroso para os trabalhadores e os povos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pela nossa parte, continuaremos a defender, intransigentemente, os interesses dos trabalhadores, do povo e do País, apresentando propostas que permitam aproveitar todas as oportunidades em prol do desenvolvimento do País. Estaremos na linha da frente na rejeição de quaisquer medidas ou imposições que prejudiquem Portugal.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Approval of the minutes of the sitting and forwarding of texts adopted: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Composition of Parliament: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Dates of forthcoming sittings : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Adjournment of the session">
    <intervention id="3-048-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro interrotta la sessione del Parlamento europeo.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
