<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20201217.EN" lang="en" date="2020-12-17" place="Brussels" edition="Provisional edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Announcement of voting results">
    <intervention id="4-007-0000" speaker_id="204400" name="Adrián Vázquez Lázara" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="Chair of the Committee on Legal Affairs">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, pursuant to Rule 59(4) I request that the matter be referred back to committee for interinstitutional negotiations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-008-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pyynnöstä äänestetään komission ehdotuksesta toimitettavan äänestyksen jälkeen, ja päivän ensimmäinen äänestys avataan klo 9.45.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. EU Strategy on adaptation to climate change (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-010-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Esityslistalla on seuraavana keskustelu Lídia Pereiran, Marek Paweł Baltin, Fredrick Federleyn, Simona Baldassarren, Pär Holmgrenin, Alexandr Vondran ja Petros Kokkalisin ympäristön, kansanterveyden ja elintarvikkeiden turvallisuuden valiokunnan puolesta komissiolle laatimasta suullisesti vastattavasta kysymyksestä EU:n strategiasta ilmastonmuutokseen sopeutumiseksi (O—000075/2020 - B9-0029/20) (2020/2532(RSP)).</p>
      <p sl="en">Jäsenille ilmoitetaan, että tässäkään keskustelussa ei anneta pyynnöstä myönnettäviä puheenvuoroja eikä sinisen kortin kysymyksiä hyväksytä. Tässä käydään yksi kierros poliittisten ryhmien puheenvuoroja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Huomautan vielä, että puheenvuoroja voi käyttää etäyhteydellä jäsenvaltioiden yhteystoimistoista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Annan puheenvuoron kysymyksen esittäjälle Lídia Pereiralle viideksi minuutiksi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-011-0000" speaker_id="197738" name="Lídia Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, our efforts in climate change mitigation are noble. Our progress in defining new, bold and ambitious targets and goals in this parliamentary term is inspiring. We can be proud of having approved the first climate law in the world and of what we are doing to achieve climate neutrality in 30 years. We are doing what we were elected to do: to shape a better, brighter and cleaner future for us all, in particular for future generations. I am proud to be taking part in this challenge and, hopefully, in this accomplishment.</p>
      <p sl="en">But the planet is now waiting for us to do our part. We are already facing extreme weather events, devastating fires, severe droughts, floods and devastating storms. We need, quickly and effectively, to adapt our territory, our cities, our economies and our infrastructure. We need to invest in sustainable and nature-based solutions, protect the economy from climate problems, and improve the resilience of critical infrastructure, adding climate factors to risk management practices, stepping up prevention and preparedness efforts, and making use of technological advancements.</p>
      <p sl="en">But many are already suffering: Spaniards, Portuguese, Italians, Greeks, Cypriots, Bulgarians and Romanians. Our fellow Europeans living in these countries are already facing severe risks of desertification across over half of their territory. For example, in Spain, 75% of the country is at risk of desertification, and one-fifth of the territory is at a high risk of irreversibly becoming desert.</p>
      <p sl="en">If we are, rightly, financing climate mitigation and transition mechanisms for countries lagging in their energy transition from coal to renewable energy sources, why are we forgetting the countries that are already suffering from climate change, the ones among us who are already burdened by a non-recoverable debt that is maturing in their biodiversity? How does this make sense? We need to advance with adaptation funding, a sort of fair climate adaptation mechanism, to help these cities and regions.</p>
      <p sl="en">I’m sure I don’t need to explain how it is that everyone will lose if we don’t act now to adapt and reduce these climate change effects. Our food supply chains, our industries and our economies will be disrupted. We must fix the climate and the environment if we are to live better and have better jobs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rest assured, you will not find the EPP arguing in the trenches for the economy and being hostile towards the environment, nor fighting for the climate by shouting for the destruction of the economy or an end to the social market economy. We need both. We need the economy and the environment, and we need them to work together.</p>
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, caras e caros Colegas, as temperaturas médias globais europeias repetidamente quebraram recordes nos últimos anos. Em particular os 5 últimos anos foram os mais quentes já registados com ondas de calor, secas e incêndios florestais em toda a Europa, com centenas de mortos. E estes impactos são transfronteiriços, afetam a nossa saúde, destroem a nossa agricultura, limitam o comércio e obrigam a migrações e reduzem a nossa segurança.</p>
      <p sl="en">Precisamos, por isso, que a nova estratégia para a adaptação às alterações climáticas contenha respostas concretas relativas à desertificação e à degradação dos solos. Precisamos de novas construções e infraestruturas que sejam resistentes e eficientes. Precisamos de aproveitar melhor o potencial das florestas, que não só retiram o carbono da atmosfera como amenizam a temperatura e retêm a humidade. Precisamos de melhorar os sistemas de alerta rápido contra desastres, tirando partido do potencial das novas tecnologias e dos dados. Precisamos de investir na gestão eficiente da água, que se torna escassa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Da nossa capacidade e dos nossos esforços de adaptação de hoje depende um futuro mais saudável e mais pacífico na Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-013-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it is good to see you again. Honourable Members, the last five years were the hottest on record, with more frequent heatwaves, droughts and wildfires across Europe. Temporary drops in greenhouse gas emissions like those caused by the 2008 financial crisis and the current economic disruptions due to the COVID—19 pandemic have little effect on the evolution of the planetary climate, and emissions can bounce back quickly.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Special Report on Global Warming of 1.5° Celsius issued by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change demonstrates that even in a best case scenario of sustained emission limitations, there will be large stress on agri—food systems, infrastructure, ecosystems and human health.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Union was an early actor on adaptation, with the adoption in 2013 of a Strategy on Adaptation to Climate Change. This aimed to enhance the preparedness and capacity of all governance levels to respond to the impacts of climate change and make Europe more climate resilient. The new strategy will draw on its evaluation that was finalised in 2018 and, of course, will also take account of the European Green Deal ambitions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Efforts to measure resilience to climate change need to continue and to be upgraded and linked to a more ambitious monitoring and evaluation system.</p>
      <p sl="en">The 2013 strategy relied on the scoreboard to assess preparedness. The revised strategy could use a dashboard to assess resilience and subsequently monitor its strength over time, with regular progress reports on specific targets. At the same time, strengthening effective monitoring and evaluation tools for adaptation policies and measures in partner countries will continue to be of central interest for the Union’s international action and support.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission’s proposal for a European climate law provides a framework for progress in pursuit of the global adaptation goal established in Article 7 of the Paris Agreement. The adaptation strategy will be designed to support the achievement of the objectives of the proposal. The governance will include a citizens’ dimension through the recently—launched climate pact. The revised strategy will be accompanied by an impact assessment and will draw on the latest available research results. Adaptation action in general, and the strategy in particular, will benefit from the increased climate—related spending target in the next Union seven—year budget, while the European Investment Bank has committed in its recently—adopted climate roadmap to support its implementation. Stakeholders will be empowered to tackle climate impacts like desertification and land degradation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Climate change adaptation and disaster risk management will be a key priority for the European Regional Development Fund and the Cohesion Fund in the 2021—2027 period, with a place—based approach to improving the resilience of EU regions and cities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today, the speed of adaptation actions varies across the Union, with all Member States having adopted national adaptation strategies or plans. In the EU Member States, most vulnerability assessments are being made, and adaptations identified, in respect of agriculture, health, biodiversity, forestry, energy, oceans and seas.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Environment Agency concludes that even if the Union and some countries have started to monitor the implementation of adaptation activities, it’s not possible to determine with any certainty whether decisive progress in increased resilience at Union level has been achieved by 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">While building resilience and adapting to the impacts of climate change is a challenge for all regions of the world, it’s the poorest and most vulnerable who are least able to adapt, both with the Union and globally, for example because of limited resources, protracted crises or violence.</p>
      <p sl="en">Globally, the Union and its Member States remain the largest contributor of international public climate finance for adaptation purposes to developing countries, in particular least—developed countries and small island developing states. The Union and its Member States are committed to scaling up their financial assistance in the future.</p>
      <p sl="en">Water resources, forests and agricultural crops fulfil many critical productive and regulation functions upon which our societies depend, such as clean drinking water, carbon sequestration, abundant food, wood and forest products, outdoor recreation opportunities and habitat. Ensuring water, forests and agriculture can withstand a changing climate is critical to reaching essential goals, including preserving ecosystem services and not least the carbon sequestration potential of forests.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will take this issue up in all fora, including for cities in the global Covenant of Mayors. This issue is essential and the Commission welcomes Parliament’s early engagement and clear signal for ambition.</p>
      <p sl="en">We look forward to the upcoming parliamentary resolution on the new strategy and to engaging in fruitful discussion on implementation once the Commission adopts the new strategy. But may I say that we also have to take care that the issue of implementation is properly addressed in the different sectoral legislation. The reports I have received so far are not very promising, at this stage at least.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-014-0000" speaker_id="197495" name="Marek Paweł Balt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy S&amp;D. – Szanowna Pani Przewodnicząca! Projekt rezolucji w sprawie strategii w zakresie adaptacji do zmian klimatu dla Unii Europejskiej jest bardzo ważnym dokumentem dla przyszłości mieszkańców całej Unii Europejskiej. Cieszę się, że ruszyła ta ogromna zmiana zwana green deal, prowadzona przez pana Timmermansa, dlatego poza tymi działaniami, które mają zminimalizować zmiany klimatyczne, postanowiłem zająć się adaptacją do skutków zachodzących zmian klimatycznych, które codziennie odczuwamy. To naprawdę poważny problem, z którym musi zmierzyć się cała ludzkość. Decyzje, które podejmujemy teraz, będą kluczowe dla zapobiegania skutkom zmian klimatycznych.</p>
      <p sl="en">W rezolucji poruszone jest wiele istotnych kwestii. Proszę, aby Komisja się do nich odniosła. Najbardziej istotne propozycje to m.in. opracowanie strategii miejskich, w skład których będzie wchodziło wykorzystanie potencjału całej infrastruktury miejskiej, m.in. takiej jak ogrody miejskie czy zielone dachy i chodniki.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wiem, że wszyscy zdajemy sobie sprawę z tego, jak bardzo zmiany klimatyczne wpłyną na nasze życie i otoczenie. Zwracam szczególnie uwagę właśnie na miasta, ponieważ obecnie ponad dwie trzecie ludności Europy mieszka na obszarach miejskich, czyli ponad 350 milionów ludzi, i ten odsetek stale wzrasta. Rosnąca temperatura powietrza o ponad 1,5 stopnia Celsjusza może spowodować podniesienie temperatury przy gruncie do ponad 60 stopni. Dlatego tak ważne jest zazielenianie tych obszarów, czy to jeżeli chodzi o dachy, drogi, czy nawet przeszklone budynki.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zapewne właśnie w tym momencie w Europie trwają prace inwestycyjne, które są współfinansowane ze środków unijnych. Dlatego proszę o odpowiedź, czy te inwestycje w fazie projektowania uwzględniały skutki zmian klimatycznych. Jeśli nie, to apeluję wraz z moimi kolegami, aby zwrócić na to szczególną uwagę, ponieważ infrastruktura miejska może w znaczący sposób przyczynić się do zmniejszenia ogólnej wrażliwości Unii na zmiany klimatyczne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aby wprowadzić korzystne zmiany, musimy uwzględnić wiele ważnych ekologicznie aspektów. Plany inwestycyjne wszystkich państw członkowskich oraz wszystkich obszarów, które obejmują przeciwdziałania zmianom klimatu, w tym badań i rozwoju, muszą uwzględniać naszą strategię. Nie należy zapominać o opracowaniu odpowiednich planów szybkiego reagowania na wypadek katastrof klimatycznych, takich jak fale upałów, powodzie czy susze.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chciałbym się odnieść do wielu mylnych zarzutów, które mam okazję obserwować w mediach społecznościowych. Sugerują one, że skoro są obfite opady, wskutek których pojawiają się powodzie czy podtopienia, to nie można mówić o suszy czy ociepleniu klimatu. Szanowni Państwo! Wystarczy zapytać rolników, czy gwałtowne ulewy nawadniają uprawy, a otrzymamy odpowiedź, że gwałtowne i obfite deszcze nie dostarczają roślinom wystarczającej ilości wody, gdyż ta po prostu spływa z gruntu, bardzo często niszcząc uprawy. Dlatego chciałbym również zwrócić szczególną uwagę na rolnictwo, przed którym także stoi wiele wyzwań związanych z dostosowaniem do zmian klimatu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chciałbym zaapelować również do wszystkich europejskich samorządów, aby poszły w ślad za europejskimi miastami, które przyjęły prawo lokalne realizujące cele klimatyczne Unii Europejskiej. Osiągnięcie neutralności dla klimatu pod względem emisji gazów cieplarnianych wymaga aktywnego udziału zarówno rządu i władz samorządowych, jak i wszystkich sektorów gospodarki i całego społeczeństwa. Tym samym samorządy mogą być aktywnym partnerem dla sektora przemysłowego oraz budowlanego i poprzez realizację przedsięwzięć na poziomie lokalnym czynnie wspierać realizację unijnej strategii klimatycznej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Matka Ziemia reaguje na działalność człowieka, dlatego my wszyscy – niezależnie od profesji, którą reprezentujemy – musimy uświadomić sobie powagę problemu i razem starać się dążyć do zapobiegania zmianom klimatu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-015-0000" speaker_id="114268" name="Nils Torvalds" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Renew-ryhmän puolesta. – Arvoisa puhemies, terveisiä Helsingistä. Tässä vaiheessa siirryn puhumaan englanniksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">The effects of climate change will spread across our continent. Adaptation is required to make measures at all levels transformative enough to deal with the systemic changes our climate, environment and society are facing. Throughout history, people and societies have adapted to climate variability and extremes with varying degrees of success. Taking responsibility for climate—related risk requires decision—making in a changing world with continued uncertainty on climate impact and with limitation on how effective the adaptation will be.</p>
      <p sl="en">Climate change impacts are more and more visible, with heatwaves, droughts, and wildfires across Europe and no snow for Christmas in Helsinki. Climate change will continue to create significant difficulties in Europe in spite of mitigation efforts. Moreover, Europe is affected by indirect climate impacts occurring in other parts of the world in multiple ways, such as through trade and supply chains, spread of infections and threats to international security. It is therefore crucial that Parliament is in the forefront of pushing for stronger EU policies and adaptation.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to end with a note that the main work, for our part, was done by Fredrick Federley and his assistant Stina Jansson. I’m just sort of taking the leading points for the very last few minutes and seconds.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-017-0000" speaker_id="197398" name="Pär Holmgren" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för Verts/ALE-gruppen. – Fru talman! Klimatkrisen är här och nu. Vi har tyvärr redan väntat för länge med den radikala omställning som krävs för att bekämpa klimatförändringarna och minska våra utsläpp. Tyvärr kommer krisen därför att bli värre, och tyvärr räcker inte heller de förslag som nu till exempel diskuteras i klimatlagen för att få ner utsläppen tillräckligt mycket, tillräckligt snabbt.</p>
      <p sl="en">World Meteorological Organization visade i sin senaste rapport att det är 20 procents risk att vi når 1,5 grader redan 2024, det vill säga inom fyra år. Människor dör redan nu, människor flyr redan nu, och människor förlorar redan nu sina försörjningsmöjligheter, inte bara någon annanstans, långt bort, utan faktiskt också här i EU. Jag tänker särskilt på Sveriges ursprungsbefolkning, samerna, och deras renhjordar. Jag tänker på spanska vinodlare och italienska bönder. Jag tänker också på den biologiska massdöden, som innebär att en miljon arter globalt hotas av utrotning.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi behöver helt enkelt ett mycket, mycket mer motståndskraftigt Europa. Nyckeln är ett Europa där hållbar utveckling och biologisk mångfald alltid prioriteras, och där livskvalitet, folkhälsa, tillgång till mat och rent vatten säkras för alla medborgare. Vi behöver lösningar med helhetsperspektiv som både begränsar klimatförändringarna och anpassar sig till de utmaningar som vi har framför oss.</p>
      <p sl="en">Visst, det kommer att kosta pengar. Samtidigt vet vi att om vi inte gör tillräckligt mycket, så blir det mycket, mycket dyrare. Solidariteten blir viktigare än någonsin. Vi måste också klimatanpassa våra sociala system. Samhällets mest utsatta kommer att drabbas hårdast. Vi behöver ett jämställdhetsperspektiv. Vi behöver ett solidariskt EU. Vi vet vad som väntar oss. Att då inte förbereda och anpassa oss för att skydda våra samhällen och förhindra de värsta katastroferna vore inte bara ansvarslöst, utan det vore rent ut sagt kriminellt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-018-0000" speaker_id="197572" name="Anna Zalewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Aby działania na rzecz klimatu, człowieka, przyrody były skuteczne, muszą być spełnione co najmniej trzy warunki. Po pierwsze edukacja i świadomość obywatelska, po drugie spójne prawo, po trzecie pieniądze. I pozwólcie, że skoncentruję się na spójnym prawie. Strategia jest ważna i dziękujemy, że została poddana debacie. Natomiast widzimy, co się dzieje z prawem klimatycznym, z artykułem 4, który mówi o tym, że strategię należy przyjąć do 31 stycznia. Owszem, do 31 stycznia, ale prawo klimatyczne jest dopiero na wstępnym etapie dyskusji w rozmowach trójstronnych. Wszystko wskazuje na to, że będzie to trwało jeszcze wiele miesięcy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jednocześnie prawo klimatyczne i strategia na rzecz dostosowania się do zmiany klimatu oznaczają również zmiany w co najmniej trzech rozporządzeniach: ESR, LULUCF czy ETS. I też nie widzimy prac, które miałyby się tam toczyć. A przypomnę, że prawo klimatyczne mówi jednoznacznie, że do końca czerwca 2021 r. każdy przepis należy przeanalizować i dostosować do prawa klimatycznego.</p>
      <p sl="en">To bardzo ważne, bo jeżeli będziemy przyjmować przepisy, które będą się różnić i nie będą się widzieć nawzajem, zapanuje chaos prawny, a to naprawdę nijak nie pomoże. Jednocześnie w budżecie ogólnym i wieloletnich ramach finansowych, jak i w budżecie na odbudowę Europy pieniędzy na strategię dostosowania się do zmiany klimatu i na bioróżnorodność po prostu nie ma.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-019-0000" speaker_id="197743" name="Πέτρος Κόκκαλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας GUE/NGL. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κύριε Επίτροπε, αναμένουμε με μεγάλη αγωνία τις νέες προτάσεις της Επιτροπής για την αναθεώρηση της στρατηγικής για την προσαρμογή εν μέσω της κλιματικής κρίσης, που θέτει σε κίνδυνο τη συνέχεια του ανθρώπινου πολιτισμού.</p>
      <p sl="en">Είναι πλέον θανάσιμα σαφές ότι οι κακές μας πρακτικές έχουν παραβιάσει το πλανητικό όριο. Σήμερα βρισκόμαστε ήδη σε έναν άλλον κόσμο, 1,2 βαθμούς Κελσίου θερμότερο, έναν κόσμο που στην καλύτερη περίπτωση επιτυχούς παγκόσμιας συνεργασίας θα είναι τουλάχιστον 1,5 βαθμό θερμότερος. Όταν αναλογιστούμε ότι αυτή ακριβώς ήταν η διαφορά θερμοκρασίας ανάμεσα στην εποχή των παγετώνων και τη δικιά μας, αυτή που επέτρεψε την άνθηση του ανθρώπινου πολιτισμού, καταλαβαίνουμε πόσο γιγάντιο είναι το έργο της προσαρμογής.</p>
      <p sl="en">Δεν έχουμε πια άλλη επιλογή από το να λάβουμε τώρα τολμηρά μέτρα προσαρμογής, για να αντιμετωπίσουμε τις αναπόφευκτες κλιματικές επιπτώσεις για το κοινωνικό, οικονομικό και περιβαλλοντολογικό τους κόστος. Η νέα στρατηγική προσαρμογής θα πρέπει να είναι πολύ φιλόδοξη. Η κοινωνική συνοχή, η σαφής διάκριση των επενδύσεων που αφορούν την προσαρμογή από αυτές που απευθύνονται στον μετριασμό, η διάσταση του φύλου, οι κλιματικοί πρόσφυγες, η δημιουργία μηχανισμού απώλειας και ζημίας, η ενίσχυση της ανθεκτικότητας των νησιωτικών περιοχών είναι θεματικοί τομείς που πρέπει να καθοδηγούν τη νέα στρατηγική.</p>
      <p sl="en">Η ενισχυμένη διακυβέρνηση της προσαρμογής, τόσο σε επίπεδο Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης όσο και σε επίπεδο κρατών μελών αλλά και τοπικών κυβερνήσεων, όπως περιγράφεται στην πρόταση του Κοινοβουλίου στη νομοθεσία για το κλίμα, θα πρέπει να περιλαμβάνει νομικά δεσμευτικούς στόχους. Για εμάς, η προσαρμογή δεν σημαίνει ότι βασιζόμαστε στη φυσική επιλογή για να επιβιώσει ο πιο δυνατός. Αντιθέτως, είναι μια ευκαιρία για να αναλάβουμε αποτελεσματική και άμεση δράση για την οικοδόμηση μιας πιο ανθεκτικής και δίκαιης κοινωνίας. Περιμένουμε από την Επιτροπή να ανταποκριθεί στο κάλεσμά μας και να φανεί ακόμα πιο φιλόδοξη από όσο έχει υπάρξει στην Ευρωπαϊκή Πράσινη Συμφωνία.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-020-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I wish to thank Members for this short but intensive discussion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Certainly, we will continue to do our utmost to prevent the unadaptable, such as a global warming level of 3⁰ Celsius that will make life impossible in many places. We must also adapt to the unpreventable as we are now already at 1.2⁰ Celsius and the climate impacts are hitting us hard.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission welcomes very much Parliament’s early engagement on adaptation and the clear signals and encouragement it has given for increased ambition and adaptation.</p>
      <p sl="en">I fully agree with Mr Balt on the issue that cities play a crucial role in this, and I know that many, many cities have very elaborate and ambitious plans, ideas and concrete projects, but it’s also up to the national authorities to provide the necessary financial means. Here I can only plead to all of you to use the opportunities provided by the MFF and the different programmes.</p>
      <p sl="en">But it’s also on us to be engaged enough on this issue when it comes to agreeing on the different sectoral regulations, because it’s a horizontal issue and it’s not sufficient to be very committed within the climate and environmental caucus; it’s also important to be strict and ambitious across the board, if I may say so.</p>
      <p sl="en">Here I can only once again urge you to reach out to your colleagues in the different groups, when they are negotiating their sectoral programmes, to indeed address this issue and not to wait until certain modifications in the legislation is necessary, as already mentioned by Ms Zalewska.</p>
      <p sl="en">We’re looking forward to the upcoming resolution on the new Adaptation Strategy and also expect again not only a fruitful discussion on, but a very engaged and ambitious implementation of, this strategy across the different sectoral topics.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Keskustelu on päättynyt. Äänestys toimitetaan torstaina 17. joulukuuta 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kirjalliset lausumat (171 artikla)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-2500" speaker_id="96911" name="Tanja Fajon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pisno. – V Evropskem parlamentu bomo jutri razpravljali o strategiji EU za prilagajanje podnebnim spremembam.</p>
      <p sl="en">Glasovali bomo o resoluciji, v kateri vnovič poudarjamo vpliv podnebnih razmer na ekosisteme, zlasti na biotsko raznovrstnost; na socialni in gospodarski sektor, in s tem povezano poglabljanje neenakosti; in tudi na zdravje ljudi, ki je danes že tako zelo ranljivo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Opozarjamo tudi na ekstremne vremenske razmere, ki smo jim priča tudi v Sloveniji in ki predstavljajo okoljska, gospodarska in varnostna tveganja predvsem za lokalne skupnosti. Zahtevamo, da prihajajoča strategija to upošteva in predvidi ustrezne ukrepe in boljšo mobilizacijo sredstev. Naši cilji so jasni: do leta 2050 naj EU postane ogljično nevtralna vodilna sila zelenega gospodarstva in vzor svetu. Še prej pa moramo izpolniti vmesni cilj, da do 2030 zmanjšamo emisije toplogrednih plinov za vsaj 55 %.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pri skrbi za okolje se zavedajmo, da je večja ambicioznost vedno dobrodošla. Imamo samo en planet. Ravno ta teden smo Socialni demokrati tudi v slovenskem državnem zboru ponovno vložili predlog resolucije o razglasitvi izrednih podnebnih in okoljskih razmer v Republiki Sloveniji. Čas je, da Slovenija stopi na stran 33 držav, ki je to že storila, kot tudi Evropski parlament lani, in vzame svojo prihodnost in prihodnost naših otrok zelo resno.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-3750" speaker_id="197488" name="Guido Reil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – In dieser Sitzung hat das Parlament für ein starkes soziales Europa plädiert. Wie weit ist das Parlament eigentlich von der Realität entfernt? Die verschärften Klimamaßnahmen, die vom Europäischen Rat gebilligt wurden, werden unseren Wohlstand, worauf unsere Sozialleistungen beruhen, weiter untergraben. Diese Politik nimmt die energieintensiven Industrien in die Zange und beschleunigt die Deindustrialisierung. Nach einer Studie, die im September 2020 von der deutschen Industrie- und Handelskammer vorgestellt wurde, werden diese neuen Vorgaben zu einer weiteren Verschärfung des europäischen Emissionshandelssystems führen. Die hohen CO2-Preise haben eine große Einwirkung auf industrielle Unternehmen, die ja Teil dieses Emissionshandelssystems sind. Wenn nur Unternehmen innerhalb der Europäischen Union diese Kosten tragen müssen, gibt es ein sehr großes Risiko, dass diese Betriebe ihre Aktivitäten verlagern. Es droht also ein Verlust dieser Unternehmen für Deutschland und Europa und die Treibhausgasemissionen werden nicht reduziert, sondern nur verlagert. Die CO2-Zielsetzung als Treiber, die einseitige Fokussierung auf Elektrofahrzeuge mit dem Krieg gegen den Verbrennungsmotor hat schwerwiegende Folgen für unsere Beschäftigung. Der auferlegte Wandel zum Elektromotor ist nur mit drastischen Sparprogrammen und weniger Personal finanzierbar. Die EU-Klimapolitik ist verantwortlich für den Abbau tausender Stellen in der Industrie. Dies ist eine asoziale Politik.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-021-5000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ennen keskustelujen jatkamista ja ennen tämän päivän ensimmäisiä äänestyksiä antaisin puheenvuoron edustaja Gabriele Bischoffille, joka pyysi saada käyttää puheenvuoron työjärjestyksen 159 artiklan 4 kohdan mukaisesti mietinnöstään: ”Työjärjestyksen muuttaminen parlamentin toiminnan varmistamiseksi poikkeusoloissa” (2020/2098(REG)) - Perussopimus-, työjärjestys- ja toimielinasioiden valiokunta (A9-0194/2020).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-022-0000" speaker_id="197435" name="Gabriele Bischoff" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatterin. – Frau Präsidentin! Wir stimmen heute über die Änderung der Geschäftsordnung des Parlaments ab. Diese Änderung ist notwendig, weil wir bisher keine Regelung für Ausnahmesituationen haben, und seit der Pandemie befinden wir uns in einer schwierigen und auch langwierigen Ausnahmesituation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist dabei wichtig, dass die Funktionsweise des Europäischen Parlaments immer gewährleistet ist, denn wir sind ein besonderes Parlament. Hier kommen Kolleginnen und Kollegen aus 27 Mitgliedstaaten zusammen, und gerade auch am Anfang der Pandemie haben wir gesehen, dass wir durch Reisebeschränkungen und Grenzschließungen vor besonderen Herausforderungen standen. Aber Parlamente als Orte politischer Entscheidungsfindung müssen funktionsfähig sein. Es ist uns gelungen, in dieser Pandemie immer offen und auch tatsächlich arbeitsfähig zu sein, und ich denke, darauf können wir stolz sein. Der Präsident und auch die Gremien haben entsprechende Entscheidungen getroffen, damit das Parlament als Herzstück der europäischen Demokratie tatsächlich offen und funktionsfähig bleibt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben uns im Ausschuss für konstitutionelle Fragen seit dem Ausbruch der Pandemie damit befasst – und das ist uns gelungen –, gemeinsam neue Vorschläge zu erarbeiten, um eben auch für zukünftige Ausnahmesituationen jeder Art besser gewappnet zu sein. Wir haben es geschafft, fraktionsübergreifend einen Konsens zu finden für vier neue Regeln für die Geschäftsordnung, die heute zur Abstimmung stehen. Mit diesen Regeln wappnet sich das Parlament gerade auch für die digitale Arbeitsweise, die wir hier gerade erleben, für schnelle Entscheidungsfindung und bessere Legitimität dieser Entscheidungen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte den Kolleginnen und Kollegen danken für die kooperative und konstruktive Zusammenarbeit und empfehle, dem Bericht über die Änderung der Geschäftsordnung zuzustimmen. Damit garantieren wir den Bürgerinnen und Bürgern, dass das Parlament in jeder Ausnahmesituation voll funktionsfähig bleibt, und stellen sicher, dass wir zu jeder Zeit unsere Arbeit tun können. Und deshalb ist es wichtig, dass wir hier diese Regelungen der Geschäftsordnung entsprechend beschließen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-023-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kiitos kollega Bischoff. Nyt jatkamme keskusteluja.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. OLAF cooperation with EPPO and the effectiveness of its investigations (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-025-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Esityslistalla on seuraavana keskustelu talousarvion valvontavaliokunnan suosituksesta toiseen käsittelyyn OLAFin yhteistyöstä EPPOn kanssa ja sen tutkimusten vaikuttavuudesta (10008/1/2020 – C9-0393/2020 - 2018/0170(COD)) (Esittelijä: Marian-Jean Marinescu) (A8-0263/2020).</p>
      <p sl="en">Jäsenille ilmoitetaan, että tässä keskustelussa on yksi kierros poliittisten ryhmien puheenvuoroja. Tällä istuntojaksolla keskusteluissa ei anneta pyynnöstä myönnettäviä puheenvuoroja eikä sinisen kortin kysymyksiä hyväksytä.</p>
      <p sl="en">Huomautan vielä, että puheenvuoroja voi käyttää etäyhteydellä jäsenvaltioiden yhteystoimistoista.</p>
      <p sl="en">Annan puheenvuoron esittelijä Marinesculle kuudeksi minuutiksi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-026-0000" speaker_id="33982" name="Marian-Jean Marinescu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Raportor. – Doamna președintă, domnule comisar, acest dosar este un dosar, cred eu, extrem de important și sunt bucuros că am reușit să-l ducem la capăt într-un timp foarte scurt, comparat cu precedenta negociere - a durat doi ani, un an și jumătate față de șapte ani. Au lucrat foarte mulți colegi la acest dosar, eu am preluat acest dosar de la colega mea Ingeborg Grässle și îi mulțumesc pentru activitatea pe care a dus-o în acest dosar și, bineînțeles, și raportorilor din umbră.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cred că a reușit să facem, să aducem textul la o variantă foarte bună. Bineînțeles că am avut ca principal scop colaborarea între Parchetul European și OLAF, dar, în același timp, pe baza propunerilor Parlamentului European, am reușit să introducem lucruri care vor facilita și vor îmbunătăți activitatea OLAF-ului: în primul rând, transparența în cadrul OLAF-ului, accesul la dosare, dar, în același timp, și accesul la conturile bancare în statele membre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Avem un controlor, o structură independentă în cadrul comisiei de supervizare, care va verifica dacă sunt aplicate corect garanțiile procedurale. Avem proceduri, standarde de proceduri mai înalte pentru anumite activități. În același timp, statele membre sunt obligate să raporteze despre ceea ce-au făcut cu recomandările din cadrul rapoartelor OLAF, astfel încât să fie o colaborare cât mai bună atât între statele membre, cât și între instituții.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sper că acum, prin această colaborare OLAF -Parchet, să avem o activitate mult mai bună în apărarea, în lupta împotriva fraudei cu fondurile europene. Dosarul a fost votat în Comisia CONT cu mare majoritate și sper că se va întâmpla același lucru și în Parlament. Mulțumesc domnului comisar pentru colaborare și cabinetului domnului comisar, a fost o colaborare foarte bună și, în același timp, și OLAF-ului pentru că am colaborat foarte bine cu ei și cele două președinții croată și germană.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-027-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I am honoured to be here today to welcome the adoption of the revision of the OLAF Regulation, which sets the stage for the work of the Office in the years to come. As the rapporteur has already said, this marks the end of seven years of discussion and negotiations. I think it is worth mentioning this and stressing the energy that the current and previous rapporteurs put into these negotiations. Indeed, we had very intense and, ultimately, very fruitful negotiations on this significant piece of legislation. All the institutions showed commitment and resolve, and it has finally paid off.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank the European Parliament and the Council for their work on this initiative. In particular, I would like to recognise the role of the rapporteur, Marian-Jean Marinescu. Marian-Jean, your determination to close the deal proved pivotal. I would also like to thank the co-rapporteurs who supported you in all your efforts.</p>
      <p sl="en">The OLAF Regulation needed to be revised inter alia to adapt to the new anti-fraud architecture, which now also includes the European Public Prosecutor’s Office (EPPO). However, the Regulation that we have ended up with achieves much more. We have strengthened the European Anti—Fraud Office, further equipping it with the tools it needs to protect the Union budget. A reformed OLAF is key to ensuring that the next European budget and the recovery plan are subject to the best control mechanism. The revised OLAF Regulation ensures cooperation between OLAF and the European Public Prosecutor’s Office and reinforces OLAF’s investigative capacity.</p>
      <p sl="en">OLAF and the EPPO pursue the same objective of protecting the Union budget. While they do so within their own mandate, the revised OLAF Regulation ensures that they also do so in close cooperation. This cooperation relies on three pillars. First, the EPPO can rely on the support and expertise of OLAF in carrying out its tasks. Second, OLAF can launch investigations that are complementary to those of the EPPO to facilitate recovery or adopt administrative precautionary measures. Third, they exchange information before and during investigations through a mutual reporting mechanism.</p>
      <p sl="en">The reformed OLAF also has better tools to investigate fraud against the Union budget. It may access bank account information under the same conditions that apply to national competent authorities. It will conduct on-the-spot checks, pursuant to clearer rules, and benefit from an enhanced two-way cooperation with national authorities. These improvements go hand in hand with clearer procedural guarantees and the establishment of new functions to ensure their respect, like the Controller.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, the Commission welcomes the revision of the OLAF Regulation, which contributes to shaping a revamped EU anti-fraud architecture. I am looking forward to hearing the views of the political groups. May I add that I think it was very timely to have this revision adopted in the light of the now much bigger European budget, with all the possible implications this will have on where we need to protect European taxpayers’ money. Therefore, I am grateful for your commitment and, finally, all of your achievements.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-028-0000" speaker_id="124713" name="Tomáš Zdechovský" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu PPE. – Paní předsedající, vážený zpravodaji, pane komisaři, kolegové spoluzpravodajové, jestli příští Politico zveřejní žebříček nejvlivnějších politiků a nebude tam Marian-Jean Marinescu, tak ho přestanu odebírat. Protože ten, kdo udělal na této legislativě tolik práce, byl právě on. Mariane-Jeane, kdyby mi to nebylo trapné, tak před tebou a všemi tvými kolegy teď pokleknu, protože jste dotáhli legislativu, která se předtím připravovala sedm let, s pomocí pana komisaře za rok a půl. A jsem velmi hrdý na to, že když jsem se rozhodoval, komu svěřím zpravodajství jako koordinátor PPE, že to bylo právě tobě, protože opravdu, Mariane-Jeane, ty jsi jeden z nejlepších poslanců EP, které v této budově a v této místnosti máme.</p>
      <p sl="en">V této zprávě se podařilo Parlamentu dosáhnout úspěchů hned v několika věcech – byl vytvořen kontrolní orgán pro procesní záruky, který bude dohlížet i na zahrnutí DPH. Díky tomu OLAF dostane přístup i k bankovním účtům. Teď je nicméně důležité, abychom se soustředili na implementaci doporučení, která OLAF navrhuje. Pokud zjistíme, že doporučení úřadu OLAF nebyla brána dostatečně v potaz a nedošlo k žádnému zlepšení situace, budeme na to muset adekvátně reagovat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Musíme najít další řešení, jak efektivně bojovat proti finančním podvodům, nesrovnalostem, proti střetu zájmů a proti korupci. Nemůžeme dovolit žádná systémová pochybení ani nejasně nastavené podmínky, ať už jde o finanční, právní nebo disciplinární kontroly. Koneckonců jsou to naše peníze a jsou to peníze všech daňových poplatníků.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dámy a pánové, přeji vám požehnané Vánoce a v novém roce všechno nejlepší.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-029-0000" speaker_id="197845" name="Цветелина Пенкова" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">от името на групата S&amp;D. – Г-жо Председател, г-н Комисар, скъпи колеги, регламентът относно Европейската прокуратура беше приет и трябва да влезе в сила до 2020 г. От изключително значение е и регламентът за Европейската служба за борба с измамите или накратко ОЛАФ, също да бъде адаптиран, защото за нас е важно да осигурим едно гладко сътрудничество между тези два офиса по няколко причини.</p>
      <p sl="en">На първо място, Европейската прокуратура започва да функционира и е от съществено значение тя да има безпроблемни отношения с офиса на ОЛАФ. На второ място, обновеният регламент за ОЛАФ в момента укрепва съществуващите правомощия на институцията и същевременно затвърждава способността на ОЛАФ да извършва ефективно разследване с достъп, например, до банкови сметки, и на трето място, през следващите месеци ОЛАФ трябва да предостави уверения и актуализация относно независимостта на контролния орган и достъпа на заинтересованите лица до докладите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Мисля, че всички разбираме защо е изключително важно да засилим позицията на ОЛАФ, като подобрим ефективността на правната стабилност по разследванията. Това ще доведе до цялостни и по-ефективни разследвания. Властите на държавите членки също не бива да остават извън този процес, а напротив, те трябва да започнат да използват по-добре резултатите от разследванията на ОЛАФ и тук това е ключово, защото само и единствено по този начин ще могат да бъдат предотвратени текущи и бъдещи злоупотреби с европейски средства.</p>
      <p sl="en">Уважаеми колеги, през следващите години ще бъде отпуснат безпрецедентно голям обем от допълнителни средства за подпомагане на европейската икономика, за зеления преход и за всички наши стратегии, които сме развивали през последните години. Допълнителните средства ще се отпускат и за борба с последствията от Ковид кризата, но контролът на изразходването на тези средства е от ключово значение, за да могат те да бъдат изразходвани наистина по най-ефективния начин, и наистина да достигнат до европейските граждани и до най-нуждаещите се.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-030-0000" speaker_id="197588" name="Katalin Cseh" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Renew Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, first of all, let me congratulate the colleagues in this House, in the Commission and in the Council for updating the European Anti—Fraud Office (OLAF) regulation and legally fine—tuning the working relations between the European Public Prosecutor’s Office (EPPO) and OLAF. Now we have made the legal background ready for their effective functioning in the future. This is truly a great accomplishment.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, at the same time, in this discussion about the effectiveness of European anti—fraud efforts, let me highlight the very simple but still crucial concern: still insufficient funding. This may sound technical, but for my constituents it’s a painfully obvious problem. According to the latest report by OLAF, financial irregularities affect 4% of payments in Hungary. This is 10 times the EU average. But whenever I cite this number to my voters, they very often ask the question: wait a minute, only 4%? Then I explain that the capacity of OLAF only allows them to monitor a small fraction of payments – 5% or 10% – but in fact it is possible that this number is much higher, we just don’t know, and the fact that we don’t know is in itself very problematic.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now imagine that this already underfunded institution now has to administer EUR 750 billion in recovery funds. How can they do that?</p>
      <p sl="en">We have also launched the European Public Prosecutor’s Office with really ground—breaking powers but, also in EPPO’s case, inadequate staffing and funding is still a problem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let’s be clear: protecting our financial interests has costs. That’s a fact. But this cost is an investment in the future. It’s an investment in recovering this money, and spending more on anti—fraud operation is actually saving us money. So, let’s consider this in the future and let’s fight with every method possible for higher funding for these institutions in order for them to protect our European financial interests.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-031-0000" speaker_id="124770" name="Jean-François Jalkh" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, mes chers collègues, la proposition de règlement dont nous discutons aujourd’hui a pour but de définir quelle part du gâteau sera laissée à l’OLAF, l’Office européen de lutte antifraude, après la mise en place du Parquet européen. Elle s’efforce, par la même occasion, d’apporter des remèdes aux dysfonctionnements parfois graves constatés ces dernières années dans le fonctionnement de l’OLAF.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les plus attentifs se souviendront que les principaux acteurs de la lutte antifraude dans l’Union européenne n’ont pas ménagé leurs critiques envers l’Office, qu’il s’agisse de la Commission européenne, de notre Parlement dans ses différentes décharges, de la Cour des comptes européenne ou du comité de surveillance de l’OLAF.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si l’OLAF est théoriquement censé effectuer ses enquêtes en toute indépendance, la Cour des comptes n’a pas manqué de nous rappeler, par exemple, que la promotion professionnelle de ses agents était assurée par la Commission européenne. Drôle d’indépendance, en vérité! Dans un excellent rapport, le Parlement français avait aussi conclu que l’Office ne pouvait en aucun cas prétendre réunir les critères rigoureux exigés d’une autorité administrative indépendante.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous ferai grâce des noms d’oiseaux échangés entre l’Office et son comité de surveillance ces dernières années. Le peu de considération de l’Office pour son comité de surveillance augure mal de la sérénité des rapports futurs entre l’OLAF et le Contrôleur européen de la protection des données.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est promis, juré, craché: l’OLAF cessera de faire des écoutes illégales comme dans l’affaire sur l’enquête contre le commissaire Dalli, qui a abouti au renvoi en correctionnelle en Belgique de son ancien directeur. Finies, les perquisitions clandestines de nuit dans les bureaux de certains députés à l’insu de ces derniers.</p>
      <p sl="en">La mise en place du Parquet européen, si elle témoigne clairement d’un abandon de souveraineté des États nationaux, nous est aussi présentée comme une amélioration importante des droits de la défense pour les personnes mises en cause. Rien n’est moins sûr au vu des prérogatives totalement disproportionnées reconnues à l’Office futur: reconnaissance des dénonciations anonymes, possibilité pour l’Office, en dehors de toute enquête préliminaire ou de toute information judiciaire, d’accéder aux lignes téléphoniques privées et aux comptes bancaires des agents et des élus, acteurs de l’Union – ce qui révulsait la très respectée Mme Grässle, ancienne présidente de la commission du contrôle budgétaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Où est l’état de droit? Avant de faire la leçon à la Pologne, à la Hongrie, au monde entier, commençons par balayer devant notre porte! Certains États refusent de passer sous les fourches caudines du Parquet européen. Les ressortissants de ces pays disposeront pour leur part de moins de droits, au mépris des valeurs fondamentales de l’Union. De belles batailles juridiques en perspective.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. First voting session">
    <intervention id="4-034-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Avaan tämän päivän ensimmäiset äänestykset. Äänestämme tämän päivän esityslistalla ilmoitetuista menettelyistä, ja äänestykset ovat avoinna klo 9.45–11.00. Äänestysmenetelmä on sama kuin edellisissä äänestyksissä, ja kaikki äänestykset toimitetaan nimenhuutoäänestyksinä.</p>
      <p sl="en">Julistan siis ensimmäiset äänestykset avatuiksi. Voitte äänestää klo 11.00 asti. Ensimmäisten äänestysten tulokset ilmoitetaan klo 13.00.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. OLAF cooperation with EPPO and the effectiveness of its investigations (continuation of debate)">
    <intervention id="4-036-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Nyt jatkamme keskustelua Marian-Jean Marinescun mietinnöstä (A9—0263/2020) talousarvion valiokunnan suosituksesta toiseen käsittelyyn OLAFin yhteistyöstä EPPOn kanssa ja sen tutkimusten vaikuttavuudesta (10008/1/2020 – C9—0393/2020 – 2018/0170(COD)).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-037-0000" speaker_id="106936" name="Daniel Freund" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, yesterday we approved the EU budget and the corona recovery funds – EUR 1.8 trillion of European solidarity. But, we have to be honest: some of this money will be stolen. If we, the European Union, are going to spend almost twice as much, we should at least double the budget of our anti-corruption bodies: the European Public Prosecutor’s Office (EPPO) and the European Anti-Fraud Office (OLAF). I honestly do not understand why, in this situation, you, Commissioner Hahn, have not approved the EUR 10 million in additional funding that the EPPO requested to properly function.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maybe even more seriously, two thirds of the fraud that is uncovered by OLAF is simply ignored by the Member States. At this point in the EU version of Monopoly, we have to rename the Get Out of Jail Free card and call it the ‘Member States don’t cooperate with OLAF’ card. This has to stop. OLAF and the EPPO need to be properly funded and staffed. Member States urgently need to improve their cooperation with the anti-corruption bodies. Sweden, Ireland and Denmark need to join the European Public Prosecutor, because they are giving a cheap excuse to Poland and Hungary not to join. Finally, if Member States don’t cooperate with OLAF, we have to cut their funding under the Common Provisions Regulation, because it clearly means that the management and control systems are not working. It has to be clear: if EU money is stolen, we won’t let people get away with it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-038-0000" speaker_id="197501" name="Joachim Stanisław Brudziński" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Przyjęcie rozporządzenia, o którym w tej chwili rozmawiamy, w sprawie Prokuratury Europejskiej, spowodowało konieczność aktualizacji aktów prawnych przez Komisję Europejską oraz konieczność odpowiedniego dostosowania właściwych przepisów Unii Europejskiej regulujących obszar zwalczania nadużyć finansowych, zarówno w odniesieniu do wydatków, jak i dochodów budżetu Unii Europejskiej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kluczowe znaczenie miało zagwarantowanie, aby nowe ramy prawne OLAF zapewniały możliwość wywiązywania się ze spoczywających na nim obowiązków statutowych bez dublowania kompetencji z Prokuraturą Europejską, a także realizacji obszarów względem Prokuratury Europejskiej państw członkowskich oraz instytucji, organów, urzędów i agencji Unii. Dzięki wprowadzeniu nowych rozwiązań OLAF miałby prowadzić dochodzenia w skuteczniejszy i spójniejszy sposób, a tym samym przyczynić się do efektywnej ochrony budżetu w całej Unii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ale pojawiają się tutaj pewne wątpliwości. Otóż pierwsza z nich to możliwość naruszenia kompetencji państw członkowskich, kolejna – mimo wszystko możliwość powielania, dublowania uprawnień OLAF-u i Prokuratury Europejskiej, i dochodzeń krajowych. Mimo wszystko niejasna rola Prokuratury Europejskiej, a także możliwość rozciągania w przyszłości uprawnień obu organów, np. poprzez akty wykonawcze Komisji.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-039-0000" speaker_id="197935" name="Ivan Vilibor Sinčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, kada govorimo o ovoj današnjoj uredbi govorimo zapravo o podjeli posla između OLAF-a i Europskog ureda javnog tužitelja odnosno EPPO-a.</p>
      <p sl="en">Do sada u mnogim europskim zemljama, pa naprimjer tako i u Hrvatskoj, recimo Bugarskoj, novac je išao za prihranu političkog režima koji tamo vlada a učinkovite kontrole nema, niti je bilo. Možemo se tek nadati da će sada biti drugačije. To se u Hrvatskoj, recimo, vidi na natječajima za istraživanje i razvoj. Kriterij po kojem se dodjeljuje novac je čista sreća odnosno metoda najbržeg prsta. Nije bitna kvaliteta, ne radi se nikakva rang lista nego onaj tko prvi stisne enter, taj dobije novac za razvoj. Nije bitno imate li patente, jeste li ih donijeli, nego ide sve na „majke mi, da, imam, donijet ću jednog dana”. I na taj način se dodjeljuje. Tu se stvara mutna voda u kojoj jako dobro plivaju oni koji su bliski politici i vlasti. Ovdje je jako bitno kako će se birati tužitelj. On će se na žalost birati iz hrvatskog kadra, bit će integrirani u USKOK, predmeti će se dizati, optužnice pred našim sudovima, županijskim sudom u Zagrebu a novca će biti jedva za plaće.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ostaje nam zapravo jedino da se nadamo i vjerujemo u moralni integritet Laure Kovesi jer ćemo se ponovno vratiti na hrvatski pravosudni kadar kao i slučaju Europskog suda za ljudska prava u Strasbourgu, bojim se.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-040-0000" speaker_id="197584" name="Sándor Rónai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Történelmi jelentőségű a költségvetés elfogadása, többszörösen is, hiszen azon túl, hogy minden költségvetési ciklus tervezése és elfogadása óriási felelősség, idén drámai körülmények, a világjárvány is közbeszólt. Az unió történetében példátlan méretű segélycsomagot együtt kellett elfogadni a többéves költségvetéssel, és mindeközben az Európai Unió hatalmas lépést tett a közös értékeink és a pénzügyeinek védelmében. Ez a kifizetésekhez kötött jogállami feltételek elfogadása volt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ahhoz, hogy az Unió tagállamaiban minden, az EU törvényeivel, valamint alapértékeivel összhangban történjen, elengedhetetlen egy hatékonyan működő uniós nyomozóhatóság és ügyészség megléte. Különösen igaz ez akkor, amikor a közös pénzügyeinket tárgyaljuk, közös pénzünket használjuk. Az elmúlt években sajnos számlálhatatlan esetet tudunk felsorolni, Magyarországot, Lengyelországot, vagy éppen Csehország példáját, ahol az uniós értékeken átgázolva, a jogállamiságot leépítve, az uniós pénzeket ellopva éppen az Unió ellen uszítottak kormányok és kormányfők, miközben tartották a markukat az uniós pénzekért. Ennek azonban most vége. Végre a jogállami mechanizmus, az OLAF és az uniós ügyészség együttesen megállíthatja a gátlástalan lopást. Ehhez azonban elengedhetetlen az OLAF és az uniós ügyészség működésének összehangolása.</p>
      <p sl="en">Szükség van az OLAF vizsgálati jogköreinek kibővítésére, és az is fontos, hogy az OLAF jogosultságait erősítsük a vizsgálattal érintett személy eljárásában például. Ugyancsak erősítsük meg az eljárási garanciák védelmét egy eljárási ellenőri tisztség létrehozásával. A jogállami mechanizmus működése mellett az OLAF és az ügyészség hatékonyan tud együtt dolgozni, akkor Európa polgárai nyugodtabbak lehetnek, nagyobb biztonságban tudhatják majd saját pénzüket, pénzügyeiket, Európa pénzét. Az OLAF és az ügyészség sikeres együttműködéséért megéri komoly erőfeszítéseket tenni. Ahogy a sok munka árán most nagy öröm, hogy megszületett a jogállami mechanizmus, ugyanezért fontos, hogy létrehozzuk ezt a kiváló együttműködést, az OLAF és az európai ügyészség között, hogy hatékonyan tudja védeni az európai értékeket, európai érdekeket.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-041-0000" speaker_id="197482" name="Joachim Kuhs" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, lieber Herr Kommissar Hahn, werte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir reden heute über Betrugsbekämpfung, insbesondere über die Zusammenarbeit zwischen den beiden Behörden OLAF – der bisherigen Betrugsbekämpfungsbehörde – und der neu geschaffenen EPPO, der Staatsanwaltschaft.</p>
      <p sl="en">Betrugsbekämpfung ist essenziell. Warum ist das so wichtig? Nun, als gute Europäer kennen Sie ja bestimmt Dantes „Göttliche Komödie“. Dante ist sehr erstaunt, als er beim Besuch im Inferno im tiefsten Kreis der Hölle Menschen findet, nämlich – eingefroren ins ewige Eis – Betrüger und Verräter: Brutus und auch Judas Iskariot.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sind Betrug und Verrat denn so schlimm? Ja, denn Betrüger und Verräter zerstören das wichtigste Element des menschlichen Miteinanders: das Vertrauen in den guten Willen des Nächsten. Und deshalb ist es elementar wichtig, Betrüger ausfindig zu machen und einer gerechten Strafe zuzuführen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich erkenne allerdings in der Zusammenarbeit der beiden Behörden OLAF und EPPO mindestens zwei Probleme: Bereits bisher lag die Vorlagequote der Betrugsfälle bei den nationalen Behörden bei unter 30 %. Warum meinen Sie, dass diese Quote tatsächlich besser wird, wenn noch eine neue Behörde dazukommt und wenn es noch viel mehr Kompetenzgerangel gibt als schon bisher? Es ist auch nicht gut, dass die EPPO Personal und Know-how vom OLAF abzieht und dadurch die bisherige Betrugsbekämpfung schwächt. Bereits im ersten PIF-Bericht vor 31 Jahren hat die Kommission gesagt, dass eben die Zusammenarbeit der beteiligten Behörden ein Erfolgsfaktor ist. Das ist das Allerwichtigste.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sie möchten jetzt vielleicht nicht auf mich hören, ich bin ein einsamer Rufer in der Wüste. Doch wenn Sie in dieser Sache nicht auf mich hören, dann hören Sie wenigstens in dieser Adventszeit auf die Stimmen der Propheten des Alten Bundes und machen Sie Ihre Herzen bereit, um Jesus Christus – dem Kommenden – zu begegnen und den Heiland der Welt in Ihr Herz aufzunehmen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-042-0000" speaker_id="197619" name="Sabrina Pignedoli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il nuovo regolamento di OLAF si è reso necessario per adeguare il quadro legale a seguito della costituzione di EPPO e per determinarne le relazioni. Ma questo Parlamento ha fatto anche di più e mi ritengo soddisfatta dell'esito di questi negoziati, perché si è riusciti a mantenere l'indipendenza di OLAF e rafforzarne le procedure di indagine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infatti è stato migliorato il sistema di follow-up delle raccomandazioni tra OLAF e gli Stati membri. Per le investigazioni OLAF, è stata istituita la figura del controllore, che verificherà le procedure per assicurarne la correttezza ed è stata prevista la possibilità per le persone indagate di avere accesso alla relazione finale, tutti passi in avanti nella direzione da noi auspicata. Ottima anche l'introduzione della possibilità per OLAF di controllare i conti bancari e avviare controlli sull'IVA.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rimangono margini di miglioramento. Per esempio, il controllore dovrebbe essere una figura più indipendente con maggiori poteri. Inoltre la procedura di accesso ai documenti deve essere più semplice. Restano chiaramente il problema del budget per EPPO e OLAF e il fatto che le indagini OLAF devono essere portate avanti anche dagli Stati membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-043-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Johannes Hahn" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, I think we really can say that the European Parliament has profoundly influenced the revision of this OLAF Regulation. You have supported all the Commission proposals to strengthen the effectiveness of investigations, as well as our objective to base the relationship between OLAF and the EPPO on the strongest complementarity.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition, you have pushed to ensure that OLAF’s strong investigative tools co—exist with stronger procedural guarantees. In fact, the revised legislation establishes a controller to handle complaints by persons concerned. It allows the person under investigation to assess the final report under certain conditions and provides for respect of higher procedural safeguards when OLAF supports the EPPO.</p>
      <p sl="en">These amendments should increase the protection of persons subject to investigation and also increase the reliability of OLAF’s work even though the rules on admissibility of OLAF—collected evidence in subsequent criminal procedures will go unchanged.</p>
      <p sl="en">We should soon start implementing a new financial framework accompanied by an ambitious recovery plan. It’s crucial that the Union will be ready to protect European Union citizens’ money, ensuring that money is spent properly and effectively.</p>
      <p sl="en">Having said this, also in response to Mr Freund and others, I think we have now provided the necessary financial means to the different organisations. In particular, we constantly hear that the EPPO should get more money. I think even before they start working they have the same staff numbers as OLAF, because you have to include the decentralised prosecutors and then you certainly arrive at the same number. And may I say that the original concept of the EPPO was to focus very much on the work of the decentralised prosecutors, but now we see a very strong headquarters.</p>
      <p sl="en">Again, I think we should see how it works, how it comes into operational daily work and then, of course, we have to adapt to the needs and see what are the future needs. I was very clear in the discussions. There are opportunities like amending budgets, etc., where we can, so to say, react in case there are further needs.</p>
      <p sl="en">But first, I think, we should now really pay attention so that the EPPO can finally start – as soon as possible, hopefully in spring – its work, and then I think we can have a further assessment about the future needs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Please be assured that we have every interest not only to protect our money, but also to get it back in the case of fraud and criminal cases. So indeed – and I think this was said by Ms Cseh and others – this is something which should really pay off in the way that we get the money back. Both these institutions, but also others dealing with such issues, are indeed properly equipped, because they need it. We will certainly take care that at the end of the day we get the money back – and certainly more than we have to invest into the staffing and the financing of these institutions. But on the other hand, we have to see that everything is in balance and we really lead also by example.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, we are talking today primarily about OLAF and that’s why I would again like to highlight that the revised OLAF Regulation is a key element of the new EU Anti—Fraud architecture that we are building to achieve that objective. This is not only about the cooperation between OLAF and EPPO. Here, of course, it’s about the investigative and prosecutorial powers of EPPO which are now there, but we should not forget there is also Europol, and its analytical capacity has to be used. The same applies to Eurojust, which definitely has a coordinating role. So the reformed OLAF is a centrepiece, if you like, of this architecture to carry out even more effective</p>
      <p sl="en">investigations.</p>
      <p sl="en">What we have to achieve is proper coordination, cooperation amongst all these institutions. It’s not only about the two, and we should not forget Europol and Eurojust and cooperation with these organisations so as to have complementarity and avoid overlapping. This also would contribute to more effectiveness of these European institutions and instruments.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Marinescun mietinnön osalta käsiteltäväksi ei ole jätetty ehdotuksia neuvoston kannan hylkäämiseksi eikä yhtään tarkistusta työjärjestyksen 67 ja 68 artiklan nojalla.</p>
      <p sl="en">Säädösesitys katsotaan näin ollen hyväksytyksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Keskustelu on päättynyt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kirjalliset lausumat (171 artikla)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-044-5000" speaker_id="124861" name="Caterina Chinnici" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – Come segnalato da Europol, la criminalità organizzata è già all'opera per cercare di sfruttare le numerose opportunità offerte dal Recovery Fund e dai diversi fondi strutturali europei previsti, a sostegno degli Stati membri, per fronteggiare la crisi pandemica. In tale allarmante contesto, l'Unione europea deve dotarsi di efficaci organi di contrasto, e l'istituzione della Procura europea (EPPO). Nella lotta contro le frodi, a danno del bilancio dell'Unione, rappresenta sicuramente una tappa fondamentale dell'architettura antifrode europea. Conseguentemente, è stato altrettanto fondamentale, aggiornare il regolamento n. 883/2013, che disciplina l'Ufficio europeo per la lotta antifrode (OLAF), il cui compito è di svolgere indagini su comportamenti illeciti come la frode e la corruzione, che rappresentano spesso il primo passo di disegni criminosi più compositi, a danno del bilancio dell'Unione. Grazie all'impegno profuso nei complessi negoziati, che ho avuto l'onore di seguire in prima persona, posso affermare, con soddisfazione, che il nuovo quadro normativo che amplia la base giuridica di OLAF, aumentandone i poteri di indagine, garantirà la stretta cooperazione, scambio di informazioni e la complementarità delle indagini con la Procura europea, ma rappresenterà anche una tappa significativa, nell'ulteriore consolidamento del principio di legalità, nello Spazio europeo di libertà, sicurezza e giustizia.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Deliberations of the Committee on Petitions 2019 (debate)">
    <intervention id="4-046-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Puhemies" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Esityslistalla on seuraavana Kosma Złotowskin vetoomusvaliokunnan puolesta laatima mietintö vetoomusvaliokunnan vuonna 2019 käsittelemistä asioista (2020/2044(INI)) (A9-0263/2020).</p>
      <p sl="en">Jäsenille ilmoitetaan, että tällä istuntojaksolla keskusteluissa ei anneta pyynnöstä myönnettäviä puheenvuoroja eikä sinisen kortin kysymyksiä hyväksytä. Huomautan vielä, että puheenvuoroja voi käyttää etäyhteydellä jäsenvaltioiden yhteystoimistoista.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-047-0000" speaker_id="124884" name="Kosma Złotowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">sprawozdawca. – Szanowni Państwo! Komisja Petycji odgrywa szczególną rolę w pracach naszego Parlamentu. To jedyne forum, na którym obywatele Unii Europejskiej mogą nie tylko prezentować swoje problemy i wyzwania, z jakimi się mierzą, ale co najważniejsze, osobiście zabierać głos na posiedzeniach komisji. To zawsze bezcenne dla demokracji, kiedy osoby pokrzywdzone mogą same opowiedzieć o swojej trudnej sytuacji. Tym bardziej ubolewamy, że ten tak trudny rok pozbawił nas możliwości osobistych spotkań z petycjonariuszami.</p>
      <p sl="en">PETI to także najbardziej interdyscyplinarna ze wszystkich komisji. Program jej działania na bieżąco układają sami petycjonariusze, którzy się do nas zgłaszają. Wśród najczęściej poruszanych tematów w 2019 roku były kwestie dotyczące środowiska naturalnego, transportu, ochrony praw dzieci, trudności osób niepełnosprawnych czy budzący tak wiele obaw po obu stronach kanału brexit. Liczba petycji złożonych w porównaniu do 2018 roku wzrosła o ponad 11%. Więcej petycji zostało również uznanych za dopuszczalne. Niestety nadal ponad 30% petycji nie odnosiło się bezpośrednio do kompetencji lub obszaru aktywności Unii Europejskiej, co oznacza, że nie mogły być rozpatrzone. Brak wiedzy obywateli na temat podziału kompetencji pomiędzy Brukselą a państwami członkowskimi to wyzwanie dla procesu omawiania i reagowania na petycje, z którym musimy sobie poradzić w najbliższych latach.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kluczowym elementem dla sprawności i skuteczności działań podejmowanych przez Komisję Petycji jest współpraca z innymi komisjami parlamentarnymi. W 2019 roku 65 petycji wysłano do innych komisji w celu uzyskania opinii, a 351 przekazano im do informacji. Wkład i wiedza ekspercka kolegów z innych komisji są więc konieczne, aby wyczerpująco odpowiadać na pytania i prośby petycjonariuszy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wśród ważnych inicjatyw, które pośrednio zostały zainspirowane przez autorów petycji trafiających do Parlamentu Europejskiego, jest propozycja dyrektywy w sprawie zniesienia sezonowych zmian czasu i uchylenia dyrektywy 2000/84. Komisja Petycji przygotowała opinię do sprawozdania w tej sprawie, która bazowała na licznych zgłoszeniach obywateli apelujących o zlikwidowanie tego uciążliwego obowiązku. Należy również podkreślić dużą liczbę petycji w sprawie brexitu złożonych w 2019 roku, które w znacznej większości dotyczyły ochrony praw obywateli Unii przed i po wyjściu Zjednoczonego Królestwa. Komisja Petycji wykonała tutaj bardzo dobrą pracę, a jej działania przyczyniły się do tego, że prawa obywateli pozostały jednym z głównych priorytetów Parlamentu w negocjacjach między Brukselą a Londynem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Podsumowując prace Komisji Petycji w 2019 roku, trzeba wspomnieć o dwóch instytucjach, które odgrywają bardzo ważną rolę w procesie reagowania i odpowiadania na petycje. To oczywiście Komisja Europejska, która służy nam swoją wiedzą podczas wysłuchań i dyskusji z petycjonariuszami, jednak szczególne podziękowania należą się Europejskiej Rzecznik Praw Obywatelskich. Najlepszym dowodem na to, że ta współpraca układa się wzorowo, był ponowny wybór pani Emily O’Reilly na to stanowisko w grudniu zeszłego roku. To właśnie Komisja Petycji była odpowiedzialna za proces analizy i wysłuchania wszystkich kandydatów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rok 2019 był wymagający dla aktywności Komisji Petycji z powodu przerwy w naszych pracach związanej z wyborami i okresem konstytuowania się nowego składu Parlamentu. Jestem jednak przekonany, że czas który mieliśmy do dyspozycji, wykorzystaliśmy bardzo dobrze. To oczywiście zasługa naszej pani przewodniczącej Dolores Montserrat i zaangażowania wszystkich członków komisji, ale również profesjonalizmu pracowników naszego sekretariatu, którym należą się ogromne podziękowania. Mam nadzieję, że Parlament równie pozytywnie oceni ich pracę i przyjmie przedstawione sprawozdanie z działalności Komisji Petycji za rok ubiegły.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-048-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, I thank the rapporteur, Mr Złotowski, for this comprehensive report, which will contribute to further strengthening relations between the Commission and the Committee on Petitions (PETI).</p>
      <p sl="en">As discussed during our structured dialogue two weeks ago, we are constantly working to improve our cooperation. I strongly believe the ability to petition is a fundamental right for all citizens and a key element of parliamentary democracy. Today, more than ever against the backdrop of the ongoing COVID-19 crisis, petitions are an effective channel for direct contact and open dialogue concerning problems affecting the daily lives of Europeans.</p>
      <p sl="en">Even before the pandemic, the use of petitions was on the increase, up by 11.23% in 2019 compared to the previous year. This was due in part to the more visible and accessible European Parliament Petitions Web Portal. Many of the petitions were in the environmental, health and social sectors.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me assure you that the Commission takes the work of this committee very seriously. We continue our efforts to improve the speed, quality and pertinence of our contributions to your replies to petitioners’ concerns. This includes the modernisation of our IT tools for handling petitions and streamlining the underlying procedures.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition, the Commission is increasingly represented at your meetings by Commissioners and high-ranking officials, especially when it comes to sensitive petitions. To put it in numbers, in the first year of our mandate, two Commissioners, three directors-general, four deputy directors-general, 10 directors and 22 heads of unit participated in debates in the PETI Committee. This trend will continue in the coming year.</p>
      <p sl="en">I take note of the section of your report on the issue of petitions and infringement procedures. As you know, the primary purpose of the infringement procedure is to make sure that Member States comply with EU law. It cannot be used to alter the specific legal situation of an individual or provide for individual means of redress. Therefore, we believe that individual complaints pointing to the incorrect application of EU law are often better addressed by the appropriate mechanisms at national level. This approach leaves the Commission more able to focus its resources on addressing systemic issues. I can assure you that we remain fully committed to fruitful cooperation in addressing infringement-related petitions.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this spirit, the Commission welcomes the Committee’s opinion on identifying potential systemic breaches of EU law with the petitions it receives. However, the decision on whether or not to investigate and pursue an instance of suspected non-compliance with EU law must remain within the Commission’s discretionary power. The Commission holds the burden of proof in bringing cases before the Court of Justice, and it must focus its efforts on issues that will bring the most benefit to EU citizens. I stress that, where petitions are not within the remit of the European Union, we should be very honest and upfront in explaining this to petitioners.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-050-0000" speaker_id="96772" name="Peter Jahr" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich bedanke mich ausdrücklich bei meinem Kollegen Kosma Złotowski und den anderen Schattenberichterstattern für die gute Zusammenarbeit bei diesem Bericht. Wir haben es gemeinsam geschafft, einen objektiven Bericht zu erstellen, der nicht unnötig politisiert wurde, und die Arbeit des Ausschusses im Jahr 2019 wird sehr gut widergespiegelt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Petitionen sind Zeichen einer erwachsenen Demokratie. Jeder Bürger, egal welchen sozialen Standes, kann sich ohne Angst über Probleme bei der praktischen Anwendung des Unionsrechts beschweren. Petitionen sind sozusagen ein Seismograf der Stimmung der Bevölkerung und gleichzeitig Kontrollinstrument, das dazu beiträgt, die Transparenz und Rechenschaftspflicht der Institutionen zu stärken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Näher am Bürger als im Petitionsausschuss kann man im täglichen Parlamentsbetrieb kaum sein. Das Parlament hat im Jahr 2019 1 357 Petitionen erhalten. Das zeigt, dass die EU-Bürger und Einwohner der Europäischen Union trotz der Sitzungspause für die Europawahl weiterhin vom Petitionsrecht Gebrauch gemacht haben. Die Zahl der Nutzer, die eine oder mehrere Petitionen auf dem Internetportal des Parlaments für Petitionen unterstützten, ist im Vergleich zu 2018 sogar gestiegen und hat eine Gesamtzahl von 28 075 erreicht, was äußerst erfreulich ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Was können wir besser machen? Etwas bedauerlich ist es, dass die Petenten nach wie vor nicht ausreichend über die Gründe für die Unzulässigkeit einer Petition unterrichtet werden. Das kann ein Lernprozess für beide Seiten sein: für uns, aber auch vor allen Dingen für den Petenten. Der Bürger kann daraus lernen, was er das nächste Mal besser machen kann.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb ist eine kontinuierliche öffentliche Debatte über die Tätigkeitsbereiche der Union unerlässlich, um die Öffentlichkeit für das Petitionsrecht beim Europäischen Parlament zu sensibilisieren. Es sollte deshalb auch einen aktiven Presse- und Kommunikationsdienst und eine aktive Präsenz in den sozialen Medien des Petitionsausschusses geben, um die Sichtbarkeit der Arbeit des Ausschusses zu erhöhen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es liegt an uns, die Petitionen schnellstmöglich zu bearbeiten und angemessen zu beantworten. Und dies auch und gerade, wenn die Bürger sich an die falsche Stelle gewandt haben. Für den Bürger ist nicht immer ersichtlich, ob sein Problem die regionale, die nationale oder die EU-Ebene betrifft. Hier muss der Petitionsausschuss besser mit den nationalen Behörden, Petitionsausschüssen und Ombudsmännern kommunizieren und zusammenarbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Insgesamt möchte ich mich noch bedanken für die Arbeit des Sekretariats des Petitionsausschusses und bei meinen Kolleginnen und Kollegen. Ich wünsche allen ein gesegnetes Weihnachtsfest und ein gesundes neues Jahr. Und wie sage ich immer an anderer Stelle: Es gibt noch viel zu tun, packen wir es an!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-051-0000" speaker_id="197719" name="Cristina Maestre Martín De Almagro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D. – Señora presidenta, el artículo 227 del Tratado de Funcionamiento de la Unión Europea dispone, como uno de los derechos fundamentales de los ciudadanos, la capacidad para ejercer su derecho de petición ante esta Cámara sobre asuntos que les afecten en el ámbito de la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto le da un enorme valor a la Comisión de Peticiones, que es un instrumento de empoderamiento ciudadano y, también, es un instrumento democrático que defiende los valores europeos que inspiran a la Unión. Y, ciertamente, también nos da la oportunidad de conocer mejor los problemas de los ciudadanos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por lo tanto, debemos defender rotundamente el valor que tiene la Comisión de Peticiones y hacerlo sin menoscabo de ningún derecho, dando audiencia justa a los ciudadanos en virtud de las reglas que nos hemos otorgado, sirviendo de plataforma o de amplificador de las voces de quienes no siempre son escuchados, de quienes no son atendidos, de quienes sufren injusticias o desigualdades por negligencias o por indiferencias. Y tenemos que hacerlo de una forma ponderada, ajustada a criterios objetivos y no al albur de otro tipo de intereses tácticos que lo único que pueden conseguir es perjudicar a los ciudadanos y ciudadanas europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta Cámara ha aprobado importantes medidas, fruto de peticiones ciudadanas. Sirva como ejemplo, muy relevante, la Resolución sobre la financiación adicional para la investigación biomédica de la encefalomielitis miálgica, fruto de una petición que presentaron en el año 2019 los propios afectados. También hemos conseguido poner freno a abusos de algunas compañías aéreas o a otros abusos en materia de vulneración de derechos de trabajadores europeos. También les hemos puesto las pilas a instituciones, administraciones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, a este respecto y para finalizar, quiero agradecer el trabajo que hace la Comisión Europea y hacer extensivo mi agradecimiento a la comisaria Dalli, también por su implicación. Y quiero, incluso, pedirle un poquito más para poder agilizar aún más la tramitación de ciertas peticiones que requieren urgencia. Gracias, también, a los compañeros y a los servicios de la Cámara por su trabajo anual.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-052-0000" speaker_id="124862" name="Ulrike Müller" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Renew-Fraktion. – Sehr geehrte Frau Präsidentin, Frau Kommissarin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir schreiben den PETI-Jahresbericht nicht nur, um Daten präsentieren zu können, sondern vor allem, um daraus zu lernen. Die häufigsten Themen der Petitionen waren auch letztes Jahr wieder Umwelt, Grundrechte und Justiz. Das sind also Themen, auf die wir besonderen Wert legen müssen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir sehen auch, dass immer noch 30 % der Petitionen als unzulässig eingestuft werden. Das zeigt einerseits, dass vielen Bürgern nicht klar ist, in welchen Bereichen die EU tätig ist, und dass wir hier Aufklärungsarbeit leisten müssen. Es zeugt aber auch von großem Vertrauen und Hoffnung in das Europäische Parlament, wenn sich die Bürger mit Problemen aller Art an uns wenden. Diesem Vertrauen müssen wir gerecht werden; dieses Vertrauen dürfen wir nicht missbrauchen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Petitionsausschuss ist eine Brücke zwischen den Bürgern und den Entscheidungsträgern. Darum wäre es sinnvoll, den Petitionsausschuss direkt in den Gesetzgebungsprozess einzubinden, damit die guten Erkenntnisse aus den Petitionen nicht verloren gehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der Petitionsausschuss beschäftigt sich außerdem nicht ausschließlich mit Petitionen, sondern teilweise auch mit Europäischen Bürgerinitiativen, und es ist wichtig, dass sie ernst genommen werden. Wenn eine Million Unterschriften aus mindestens sieben Mitgliedstaaten gesammelt werden, dann zeugt das doch von einer wichtigen Angelegenheit, in der viele Bürger Erwartungen an die Europäische Union hegen. Wenn die gewählten Volksvertreter aus dem Europäischen Parlament diesen Vorschlag auch noch unterstützen, dann sollte die Kommission das als klaren Auftrag verstehen, hierzu einen Gesetzgebungsvorschlag vorzulegen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bedanke mich bei dem Berichterstatter Kosma Złotowski und bei allen Kollegen für die Zusammenarbeit und bitte Sie um Unterstützung für diesen gelungenen Bericht ohne weitere Änderungen. Danke schön!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-053-0000" speaker_id="28619" name="Tatjana Ždanoka" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Greens/ European Free Alliance Group fully supports the report as voted on in the Committee on Petitions. As already mentioned, precisely our priorities on environmental matters and fundamental rights are the topics where we have received the most petitions.</p>
      <p sl="en">One word on petitions on fundamental rights: to our regret, the famous Article 51 of the Charter on Fundamental Rights says it is applicable only as regards EU law and, therefore, we are very satisfied that the report urges the Commission to take steps to ensure that the interpretation of the scope of Article 51 is as coherent and broad as possible, and recalls that the expectations of most petitioners in relation to the rights conferred on them by the Charter are high and go beyond the current scope of application.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another key problem is the European citizens’ initiative. We know that there are very few successful petitions and that is why the latest one we discussed this Monday on the Minority Safepack was very important. However, regrettably, even successful petitions do not result in legislative proposals from the Commission. The report also mentions this problem. We call on the Commission to initiate a legislative proposal on the basis of any successful European citizens’ initiatives that are supported by the European Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">To our regret, two large groups in Parliament have asked for a split vote on this proposal and this sentence, as it is very troublesome. If this statement does not make it into the report as voted on by the Committee on Petitions, this will be a big mistake. I repeat – as mentioned in the report – only 43% of EU citizens trust the European Union. This is a very bad number and if we just dismiss the most important applications made to Parliament, that is the European citizens’ initiatives bearing more than one million signatures, representing at least seven Member States, this will be a big failure.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-054-0000" speaker_id="197829" name="Jorge Buxadé Villalba" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ECR. – Señora presidenta, señora comisaria, no puedo subir a este estrado sin empezar denunciando que en España se perpetrará un nuevo ataque a la vida y la dignidad del ser humano mediante la aprobación de una ley cruel e inhumana como es la ley de la eutanasia, ley de la muerte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este año pasará también a la historia de la Comisión de Peticiones por la ignominia de haber visto cómo determinados grupos parlamentarios de esta Cámara se oponían al esclarecimiento de 379 asesinatos producidos por la banda terrorista ETA, separatista y de extrema izquierda, incluso de aquellos que forman parte del Gobierno de España y tienen el deber de defender la memoria, la dignidad, la verdad y la justicia para todas las víctimas.</p>
      <p sl="en">También ha terminado el curso con otra petición que nos suplica al Parlamento Europeo que desentrañemos uno de los mayores escándalos políticos, que es la eventual existencia de una red criminal para el abuso y el acoso sexual de menores tuteladas en centros gestionados por la Administración en Baleares.</p>
      <p sl="en">Porque todas las víctimas importan, porque la violencia no tiene género, continuaremos vigilantes para desenmascarar la hipocresía de todos los grupos que se rasgan las vestiduras ante las falsas violencias y, sin embargo, callan cobardes y cómplices cuando la violencia es real y provoca muerte y desolación.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-055-0000" speaker_id="197684" name="Pernando Barrena Arza" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo GUE/NGL. – Señora presidenta, estamos, en líneas generales, satisfechos con el texto acordado, ya que refleja en su mayor parte lo realizado por la Comisión de Peticiones en el ejercicio 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, es claro y notorio el desconocimiento que sigue habiendo entre la ciudadanía sobre el alcance del derecho de petición, sus mecanismos y las competencias de la Unión, así como la necesidad de que la Comisión de Peticiones adopte una estrategia de comunicación más potente.</p>
      <p sl="en">También celebramos que en el texto se recoja la necesidad de que la Iniciativa Ciudadana Europea sea considerada para la participación, así como el llamamiento que se hace para que esta sea un mecanismo mucho más dinámico y atractivo para los colectivos y la ciudadanía en general.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, ya que hablamos de mecanismos de participación y democracia directa, quisiera aprovechar para remarcar la necesidad que tienen las naciones sin Estado de Europa de que se establezca un marco europeo para el ejercicio libre y con garantías de su derecho a decidir su futuro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para finalizar, el informe no recoge una de las peticiones que mayor demanda y controversia ha generado: la negación de su derecho a ser miembros de esta Cámara que han padecido los europarlamentarios catalanes, derecho que esta comisión ha denegado reiteradamente. Es una de las mejores muestras de la excesiva mano política en la decisión de cerrar o mantener abiertas las peticiones, sobre todo en esta nueva legislatura.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-056-0000" speaker_id="96829" name="Ádám Kósa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Gratulálok Zlotowski kollégámnak a jelentéshez. Ebben tulajdonképpen részletesen leírja a Petíciós Bizottság 2019. évi tevékenységét. Kérem Önöket, hogy szavazatukkal támogassák ezt a jelentést, különösen a 29-es paragrafusát, amely arra hívja fel a figyelmet, hogy az Európai Bizottság az Európai Parlament által támogatott sikeres európai polgári kezdeményezések alapján tegyen jogalkotási javaslatokat. Az állampolgárok szavát meghallgatjuk, és ha ez a szó erős, akkor nekünk ezt tovább kell vinnünk. Minket ezért választottak meg.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fontosnak tartom azt is, a jövőre tekintve, hogy a Petíciós Bizottság tevékenysége ne csak abból álljon, hogy megoldási javaslatokat tegyünk az állampolgárok által benyújtott petíciókra, és ezek ügyében eljárjunk. Fektessünk nagyobb hangsúlyt a jövőben saját állásfoglalásainknak hatékony végrehajtására is. Mondok egy példát: A 2019-es év végén megszavazott, az ombudsman 2018. évi tevékenységéről szóló jelentésben az szerepel, hogy az ombudsman vizsgálja meg az európai biztosok meghallgatásán tapasztalt anomáliákat. Ebben a kérdésben sajnos azóta sem történt előrelépés. Saját elért eredményeink jobb utánkövetésével javíthatunk a szakbizottság munkájának hatékonyságán is.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-057-0000" speaker_id="127096" name="Domènec Ruiz Devesa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, señorías, quiero en primer lugar agradecer al ponente Złotowski y también, en particular, a la ponente alternativa socialista, mi compañera y amiga Cristina Maestre Martín de Almagro, su excelente trabajo en este informe sobre las deliberaciones de la Comisión de Peticiones en el año 2019.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se ha dicho ya, pero conviene reiterarlo: el derecho de petición es uno de los derechos fundamentales de los ciudadanos de la Unión y constituye un elemento clave en el empoderamiento de la ciudadanía y la sociedad civil europea —también la que está organizada— y para el reforzamiento político del Parlamento en el marco de las instituciones europeas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Conviene subrayar un dato de este informe: en el año 2019, a pesar de la pandemia de coronavirus, el número de peticiones aumentó en más de un 11 % con respecto al año anterior, en materias tan importantes como el medio ambiente, el Brexit o el ejercicio de derechos o la discapacidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este dato pone de relieve los asuntos que importan y que preocupan a los ciudadanos, que reclaman también una mayor acción de la Unión Europea. Lo decía la comisaria: hay ámbitos en los que la Unión Europea no tiene competencia, pero, cuando los ciudadanos reclaman acción, también están mandando un mensaje político sobre aquello en lo que, en su opinión, la Unión Europea tendría también que empezar a trabajar. Y, en este sentido, me parece que la Conferencia sobre el Futuro de Europa es el ámbito para reflexionar sobre qué nuevas competencias debe ejercer la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señora comisaria, usted lo sabe: antes de la pandemia, nadie pensaba en Europa como el marco para actuar contra las crisis de salud pública, y ahora hemos puesto en marcha la Unión de la Salud en el marco del artículo 168 del Tratado. Pero podemos ir más allá.</p>
      <p sl="en">El trabajo de la Comisión de Peticiones denuncia incumplimientos y malas prácticas de los Estados miembros, y, a este respecto, también tenemos que recordar a la Comisión y al Consejo Europeo la obligación de respetar la literalidad de los artículos 15 y 17 del Tratado de la Unión Europea.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-058-0000" speaker_id="197510" name="Jarosław Duda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Szanowna Pani Przewodnicząca! Przede wszystkim pragnę podziękować i pogratulować koledze Złotowskiemu za przygotowanie tak wszechstronnego sprawozdania, w którym trafnie uwypuklił wszystkie aspekty działania Komisji Petycji oraz wyzwania na przyszłość.</p>
      <p sl="en">Komisja Petycji jako jedna z nielicznych ma bezpośredni kontakt z obywatelami. Toteż jej sprawne i efektywne działanie ma kluczowe znaczenie dla wizerunku Parlamentu Europejskiego i dla budowania zaufania do instytucji europejskich. W minionym roku udało nam się we współpracy z partnerami nie tylko rozpatrzyć wiele petycji, ale także doprowadzić do działań o charakterze ustawodawczym i politycznym.</p>
      <p sl="en">Komisja Petycji, wsłuchując się w głos obywateli, dokładnie bada wszystkie ich oczekiwania w tym zakresie. W minionym roku szczególnie ważne były kwestie środowiskowe i zdrowotne. Zapobieganie skażeniu środowiska, zmniejszenie ilości odpadów, zapobieganie chorobom związanym ze szkodliwymi substancjami zawartymi w żywności, glebie, powietrzu czy wodzie pitnej to sprawy kluczowe dla Europejczyków.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolejną ważną kwestią jest poszanowanie praw osób z niepełnosprawnościami oraz tworzenie warunków pełnego dostępu tej grupy obywateli do włączającej edukacji, doradztwa, zatrudnienia, praw obywatelskich i dóbr kultury. Komisja Petycji jest orędownikiem pełnego wdrożenia Konwencji ONZ o prawach osób niepełnosprawnych i efektywnej europejskiej strategii w sprawie niepełnosprawności na kolejne lata. Mam nadzieję, że o ile sytuacja pandemiczna na to pozwoli, za rok będziemy gościć piąty Europejski Parlament Osób z Niepełnosprawnościami.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dziękując bardzo Komisji Europejskiej za współpracę, pragnę poprosić, aby w przyszłości odpowiedzi dla autorów petycji były przygotowywane jak najszybciej i – co jeszcze ważniejsze – aby nie były ogólnikowe, ale dokładnie odpowiadały na skargi i pytania. Pragnę poprzeć zalecenia sprawozdawcy dotyczące większego zaangażowania służb odpowiedzialnych za komunikację w kampanie promocyjno-informacyjne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Na koniec pragnę na forum całego Parlamentu podziękować (słowa niedosłyszalne) i poszczególnych grup politycznych za ich niestrudzoną pracę i zaangażowanie. Bardzo dziękuję! Zdrowych i wesołych Świąt!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-059-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it is important that Europeans see how seriously we take their concerns. Our close cooperation can ensure that this is indeed the case. We are committed to continuing to provide detailed responses to petitions and possible solutions at European or national level. This is a concrete example of how we can collaborate to strengthen citizens’ confidence and trust in the European project.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-060-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet heute statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Debates on cases of breaches of human rights, democracy and the rule of law (debate)"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="8.1. The deteriorating situation of human rights in Egypt, in particular the case of the activists of the Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights (EIPR)">
    <intervention id="4-063-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über sieben Entschließungsanträge zur Verschlechterung der Lage im Hinblick auf die Menschenrechte in Ägypten, insbesondere zum Fall der Aktivisten der Ägyptischen Initiative für persönliche Rechte (EIPR) (2020/2912(RSP))*.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich weise die Mitglieder darauf hin, dass es bei allen Aussprachen dieser Tagung keine spontanen Wortmeldungen gibt und dass keine blauen Karten akzeptiert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Außerdem sind Zuschaltungen aus den Verbindungsbüros des Parlaments in den Mitgliedstaaten vorgesehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">_______________</p>
      <p sl="en">*Siehe Protokoll.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-064-0000" speaker_id="131507" name="Miguel Urbán Crespo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Señora presidenta, no recuento cuántas veces realmente en esta Cámara hemos condenado la dictadura de Egipto y las violaciones de los derechos humanos. Pero mientras condenamos esa dictadura, en Egipto se sigue reprimiendo, se sigue torturando, se hace desaparecer a todo aquel que piensa diferente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y mientras pasa esto, su presidente visita y se pasea por todas las alfombras rojas de Europa. Mientras asesinan a ciudadanos europeos, como Giulio Regeni, encarcelan a defensores, como Patrick Zaki, que por cierto cursaba estudios en Europa, Al-Sisi recibe las más altas distinciones de manos de Macron. No sé si le considerará un ejemplo o, simplemente, era una cuestión de negocios. Negocios como los que ha hecho Trump con su dictador favorito, Al-Sisi, que mata a su pueblo. Pero países como España, como Francia o como Italia ignoran las disposiciones internacionales y le siguen vendiendo armas y equipos para reprimir a su pueblo. Y esto es intolerable. Pero ojo, que luego decimos que somos los grandes defensores de los derechos humanos. Lo que somos es unos grandes hipócritas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Exigimos la libertad de Patrick Zaki, Ramy Shaat y de todos los presos políticos, que la cooperación europea se dirija solo apoyar a la sociedad civil y que se cancelen los acuerdos con una dictadura como la de Egipto. Menos palabras, más hechos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-065-0000" speaker_id="197623" name="Thierry Mariani" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">auteur. – Madame la Présidente, le groupe «Identité et démocratie» a déposé une résolution alternative au sujet des droits de l’homme en Égypte. Au moment de composer cette résolution, nous étions sûrs que nous ne trouverions pas une résolution commune; nous savions que nous trouverions une forme d’ignorance, si ce n’est de mépris.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’ignorance, d’abord, devant les dangers que les deux élections du président Sissi ont permis de combattre. Chers collègues, soyez-en certains, l’Égypte va beaucoup mieux avec le président Sissi à sa tête. Souvenez-vous de la situation quand M. Mohamed Morsi et les Frères musulmans dirigeaient le pays. D’ailleurs, nous avons appris que la Commission européenne avait financé des associations comme le Collectif contre l’islamophobie en France et nous sommes donc en droit de poser une question: quand l’Union européenne prendra-t-elle enfin conscience des dangers liés à l’organisation des Frères musulmans en Égypte, comme d’ailleurs dans certains pays de notre continent?</p>
      <p sl="en">L’ignorance, ensuite, de ce qu’est la société égyptienne. L’analphabétisme, l’extrême pauvreté, le travail de sape effectué par certains prédicateurs islamiques sont les urgences réelles auxquelles l’État égyptien est confronté. Faire croire que l’obsession du président Sissi serait de réprimer les militants des droits de l’homme est à mon avis totalement mensonger.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’ignorance, enfin, de l’importance de l’Égypte dans le combat contre l’islamisme. Pour contrer l’influence du Qatar et de la Turquie sur le monde méditerranéen et sur les musulmans, nous avons besoin de travailler en confiance avec Le Caire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chers collègues, cette résolution condamne un État qui essaie d’améliorer sa relation avec la communauté copte, qui combat l’islamisme sur son sol. Elle est choquante, déplacée, contre-productive et nous ne la voterons pas. J’en profite pour souhaiter un joyeux Noël à la communauté copte d’Égypte qui, grâce au président Sissi, peut le fêter en paix.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-066-0000" speaker_id="197500" name="Mounir Satouri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">auteur. – Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, après ce que je viens d’entendre, j’ai envie de dire à certains républicains en France que, quand on a les mêmes amis que l’extrême droite, ce n’est jamais très bon.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’attends de cette résolution qu’elle soit prise en compte et qu’elle fasse avancer le droit humain, si lourdement mis à mal en Égypte, avec ses dizaines de milliers de prisonniers politiques, ces journalistes, avocats, militants des droits humains emprisonnés arbitrairement, avec cette répression impitoyable. Nous parlons ici de vies brisées, supprimées, de familles séparées et d’injustices insupportables. Qui nierait ici que l’Égypte est purement et simplement une dictature?</p>
      <p sl="en">Et pourtant, impuissants, nous avons assisté en France à l’accueil en grande pompe du président al-Sissi. J’en suis outré. Je suis atterré que notre président français honore ainsi la violation du droit international. Je suis consterné qu’il refuse officiellement de conditionner l’accueil d’un chef d’État à son respect des droits humains. En agissant ainsi, M. Macron signale clairement que n’importe qui, quoiqu’il fasse, sera digne d’être reçu par la France et dénigre tout le travail effectué par l’Union européenne pour faire respecter les droits des Égyptiens. C’est une honte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je le disais, j’attends de cette résolution qu’elle fasse avancer les droits en Égypte. Mais j’attends aussi qu’elle nous fasse avancer, nous, Européens, car il est largement temps que nous mesurions les effets de nos politiques de financement et d’échanges commerciaux avec ce régime. Il est temps aussi que tombent les sanctions. Les rapports d’Amnesty International sont édifiants sur les violations des droits commises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pourquoi nos gouvernements tolèrent-ils ces crimes? Au nom des industries de l’armement française et allemande. Au nom des industries française et allemande, pour vendre 700 millions d’armes, le président Macron a décerné la semaine dernière à un dictateur notre Légion d’honneur et passé sous silence la souffrance de son peuple. Cet armement, de plus, finit dans les mains des forces de sécurité répressives. Quand cette industrie sera-t-elle contrôlée et transparente? M. Macron, là encore, s’organise pour ne pas avoir à répondre de ses responsabilités. C’est une honte, et l’Europe doit y remédier.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-067-0000" speaker_id="197592" name="Pierfrancesco Majorino" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autore. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, da questo Parlamento oggi diciamo con molta chiarezza e determinazione che non tolleriamo più la continua violazione dei diritti umani in Egitto e, anche in virtù della nostra grande amicizia con il popolo egiziano, che non possiamo restare fermi a guardare.</p>
      <p sl="en">Più di 60 000 persone sono detenute per motivi politici, in un clima di sistematica repressione di ogni forma di dissenso e libertà. E da qui diciamo basta! Pensiamo che la comunità internazionale, le istituzioni europee e gli Stati membri debbano reagire con grande compattezza. L'Unione europea deve chiedere l'immediata liberazione di Patrick Zaki, un giovane cittadino che ha fatto l'università a Bologna, in Europa, imprigionato senza alcuna spiegazione da più di 300 giorni, e con lui la liberazione di tutti coloro che, come lui, si trovano ingiustamente in carcere per le loro opinioni, per il loro lavoro, per l'espressione del loro pensiero, del loro orientamento sessuale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pretendiamo che si faccia giustizia sull'assassinio di Giulio Regeni, cittadino europeo, vittima di una violenza sconvolgente, insensata, e che si sostenga la giustizia italiana che ha avviato un processo a carico di quattro agenti dei servizi egiziani, nonostante i loro molti tentativi di depistaggio. Esprimiamo da qui, dal Parlamento europeo, la massima solidarietà con i genitori di Giulio Regeni e personalmente condivido totalmente anche la richiesta di richiamare l'ambasciatore italiano che loro hanno formulato.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Europa, in coerenza con i suoi principi e valori, non può permettersi titubanze. Questo riguarda anche i governi europei. Per questo diciamo che vanno applicate sanzioni mirate nei confronti dei funzionari egiziani colpevoli di violenze, vanno riviste profondamente le relazioni diplomatiche con l'Egitto, sospesa la vendita di armamenti ed evitato ogni atteggiamento pericolosamente ambiguo nei confronti di al-Sisi, come la scelta assurda, stupefacente del presidente Macron di conferirgli la Legione d'onore, che non c'entra niente con i nostri valori.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-068-0000" speaker_id="197432" name="Jan-Christoph Oetjen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser. – Hochverehrte Frau Präsidentin! Ägypten ist unfrei. Im Freiheitsindex steht das Land auf dem drittletzten Platz, verehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen. Und die Situation für Menschenrechtsaktivisten, Journalisten und Anwälte ist schwierig. Diese Menschen werden einfach zu Terroristen erklärt und eingesperrt. Das ist nicht hinnehmbar, und hier im Europäischen Parlament fordern wir die ägyptische Regierung auf, alle, die wahllos einfach verhaftet werden, freizulassen. Und wir fordern insbesondere die Freilassung von Patrick Zaki, und wir fordern – da schließe ich mich den Kollegen von der S&amp;D an –, dass der Fall von Giulio Regeni aufgeklärt wird und dass diejenigen vor Gericht gestellt werden, die diese Tat begangen haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais laissez-moi ajouter aussi très clairement une chose, chers collègues: quelqu’un qui bafoue les droits de l’homme, quelqu’un qui met en prison des personnes qui luttent pour leur liberté d’expression, quelqu’un comme ça n’a pas d’honneur.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-070-0000" speaker_id="28372" name="Ryszard Czarnecki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">autor. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Pani Komisarz! Byłem w Egipcie, także jako członek delegacji Komisji Spraw Zagranicznych Parlamentu Europejskiego. Jest to wielki kraj, a w naszym interesie leży jego stabilizacja, tak aby mieszkańcy Egiptu wybierali przyszłość właśnie w swojej ojczyźnie, a nie szukali szczęścia w Europie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oczywiście Unia Europejska ma instrumenty pozwalające wywierać presję, takie jak pomoc humanitarna i charytatywna czy Europejski Bank Inwestycyjny. Chodzi jednym słowem o presję finansową. Możemy ją stosować tak, aby przestrzegano tam praw człowieka, a także – o czym warto powiedzieć – praw chrześcijan, bo często bywało i tak, że władze przyglądały się dyskryminacji chrześcijan bez żadnej reakcji. Apeluję o solidarność z naszymi braćmi w wierze w tym kraju i przestrzeganie praw człowieka w Egipcie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-071-0000" speaker_id="204368" name="Christian Sagartz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser. – Frau Präsidentin, geschätzte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Menschenrechte sind ein wichtiges Thema für das Europäische Parlament. Wer, wenn nicht wir, sollte die Stimme für diejenigen Menschen auf der ganzen Welt erheben, die sich selbst nicht verteidigen können, und für ihre Rechte einstehen? Ich möchte aber auch ganz deutlich sagen: Es geht bei der heutigen Aussprache um eine konkrete Initiative – um die Ägyptische Initiative für persönliche Rechte –, wo drei Aktivisten eingesperrt wurden, in Untersuchungshaft sitzen und offensichtlich an ihrer Arbeit – an ihrer wichtigen Arbeit für die Zivilgesellschaft, für ganz Ägypten – gehindert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und es ist unsere Aufgabe als Parlamentarier, heute einmal mehr darauf aufmerksam zu machen, dass wir solchen Initiativen den Rücken stärken. Ich möchte aber ganz deutlich für meine Fraktion zum Ausdruck bringen: Wir sehen auch die Bedeutung Ägyptens als Partner. Die Europäische Union sieht Ägypten als Partner, vor allem im Kampf gegen den Terrorismus. Und ich möchte das auch deutlich hier sagen: Neben den berechtigten kritischen Punkten, die meine Vorredner angemerkt haben, und der Schärfe der Entschließung möchte ich anmerken – diesen Aspekt hier ganz bewusst einbringen –, dass es auch positive Aspekte gibt in der Zusammenarbeit mit Ägypten.</p>
      <p sl="en">In dieser Partnerschaft liegt der Schlüssel. Eine Partnerschaft darf aber nicht blind sein. Wir dürfen nicht blind sein auf einem Auge und sehend auf dem anderen. Das würde nicht passen, das passt auch nicht zur Europäischen Union, und deswegen ist es auch ganz klar, dass die EVP hier fordert, dass Menschenrechte geachtet werden, zu Unrecht Inhaftierte freikommen und die Rechte der Menschen in Ägypten auch durch die Machthaber gesichert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte aber nur anmerken: Auch wir haben immer wieder innerhalb Europas und an unseren Grenzen ähnliche Probleme. Ich denke nur an die Diskussionen, an die Demonstrationen in Belarus und glaube, dass es unsere Aufgabe und unsere Verpflichtung ist, hier ganz präzise zu sein. Was meine ich damit? Artikel 144, der Basis der heutigen Aussprache ist, spricht von Fällen von Verletzungen der Menschenrechte. Und ich möchte hier für meine Fraktion schon anmerken, dass die Länge der Entschließungen und auch die Balance der Entschließungen natürlich bedeutsam sind, wenn wir gemeinsam unsere Stimme erheben möchten, wenn wir hier überfraktionell – über alle Fraktionen gemeinsam hinweg – ein starkes Signal senden möchten. Und das hätte ich mir auch von dieser Entschließung gewünscht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ägypten hat das Potenzial, als Brücke zu dienen zur arabischen Welt und zu Afrika, und es ist an uns gelegen, eine funktionierende Zivilgesellschaft, ein funktionierendes Miteinander der Wirtschaftssysteme anzustoßen und als europäische Institutionen immer weiter nach unseren Möglichkeiten voranzutreiben. Und ich glaube, dass wir hier den Blick ganz scharf auf die Einhaltung der Menschenrechte richten müssen – vor allem als Parlamentarier ist das unsere Verpflichtung. Wir dürfen aber die Balance auch hier nicht vergessen. Und ich glaube, es ist hochnotwendig, auch die Partnerschaft in gemeinsamen Interessen mindestens ähnlich in den Fokus zu stellen wie alle anderen Bemühungen und alle anderen Probleme, die heute berechtigt und sehr deutlich zur Sprache gekommen sind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-072-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, overall, the EU has very good relationship with our southern neighbour, Egypt. The EU has displayed a strong commitment to continue its common work with Egypt in areas of crucial importance for the Egyptian people such as environment, energy and water management. Nevertheless, it is because of this common work that we must express our concern over the deteriorating situation of human rights in Egypt. The Egyptian government must comply with all national and international legislation when it comes to the protection and advancement of human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">Without the impartial rule of law, you cannot have well-functioning civil society, especially in countries where we hear of repeated reports of intimidation and prosecution of civil rights activists, journalists and other NGOs. I join the calls on the Egyptian government to pursue domestic reforms to protect civil right activists, journalists, as well as their families. This is clearly needed, as is evidenced by Egypt’s poor record of media freedom and the high number of imprisoned journalists. The fact that the director and several senior managers of the Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights have been arrested in Cairo are of significant concern. Therefore, the EU and this House will strongly convey a message to the Egyptian authorities that this is unacceptable. Egypt is an important neighbour and partner but our friendship cannot be sustained if the significant and legitimate human rights concerns are not addressed. For that reason, we appeal to Egypt today to heed our petition and to address these immediately so that our good relationship can continue, otherwise it will go backwards.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-073-0000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Madame la Présidente, lorsqu’en janvier 2011 la jeunesse égyptienne s’était mobilisée pendant des semaines sur la place Tahrir, elle cherchait à se libérer d’un État policier, d’un régime d’oppression qui ne laissait aucun espoir, aucune perspective à cet avenir.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dix ans plus tard, malheureusement, seul le visage du régime égyptien a changé alors que la réalité, elle, se détériore de jour en jour en matière de droits de l’homme. Alors que le président al-Sissi a reçu les honneurs de certains États européens, la population égyptienne fait l’objet d’une répression sans précédent dans l’histoire de l’Égypte moderne. Détentions, exécutions, disparitions forcées, tortures sont aujourd’hui monnaie courante en Égypte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Depuis l’arrivée au pouvoir de M. al-Sissi en 2013, le pays a plongé dans une répression totale. Journalistes, avocats, syndicalistes, activistes, défenseurs des droits de l’homme: les ONG estiment que les prisons égyptiennes détiennent plus de 60 000 prisonniers d’opinion. Récemment, de hauts fonctionnaires de l’Initiative égyptienne pour les droits personnels ont été incarcérés, tout simplement parce qu’ils ont rencontré des diplomates européens au Caire.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Union européenne et les États membres doivent réagir de manière unie et résolue pour combattre les violations des droits de l’homme en Égypte. Le récent outil de sanction qui a été accepté doit pouvoir être activé contre les personnes qui, aujourd’hui, violent les droits de l’homme en Égypte. L’Union européenne doit être avec le peuple égyptien et non pas avec le régime égyptien.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-074-0000" speaker_id="4344" name="María Soraya Rodríguez Ramos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo Renew. – Señora presidenta, «perdí la oportunidad de tomar mis exámenes del segundo semestre. Honestamente es uno de los problemas que más me preocupan. Quiero enviar un cariño a mis compañeros de la Universidad de Bolonia, de Granada y de Sevilla». Esto no ha sido escrito desde un hogar, desde una casa, sino desde una cárcel, desde la cárcel de Tora. Es Patrick Zaki, estudiante de Erasmus, que lleva trescientos días en prisión. Fue detenido cuando iba a ver a sus padres. Podría ser mi hijo; podría ser mi hija, la hija de cualquiera de ustedes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hablo de Patrick Zaki porque es la mejor forma de que veamos hoy el rostro del régimen de Al-Sisi, un régimen cada vez más oscuro, más cruel, que utiliza la represión y que considera enemigos del Estado a estudiantes Erasmus de cuestiones de género, como Patrick Zaki, blogueros, cantantes, periodistas, defensores de los derechos humanos …</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto tiene que parar: no es aceptable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-075-0000" speaker_id="197478" name="Lars Patrick Berg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ID-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Um zum konkreten Thema zu kommen, mit dem wir uns heute befassen: Die Führungskräfte der Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights sind freigelassen worden. Wie es scheint, sind sie zu jedem Zeitpunkt im Einklang mit ägyptischem Recht behandelt worden. Ich stelle mir deshalb die allgemeinere Frage, worauf die Feindseligkeit gegenüber Ägypten in diesem Parlament beruht. Wird an Ägypten ein viel strengeres Maß angelegt als an andere Länder oder liegt hier eine grundlegende Ablehnung des ägyptischen Staates vor? Ägypten stellt sich dem Extremismus entgegen, der uns alle bedroht – ein Extremismus auch, der die koptische Gemeinde in Ägypten gefährdet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Während die Türkei weiterhin im Nahen Osten und darüber hinaus für Instabilität sorgt, zählt Ägypten zu den wenigen standhaften Staaten, die sich dem türkischen Expansionsdrang tatsächlich entgegenstellen. Ägypten spielt eine entscheidende Rolle in Libyen, und es sind ägyptische Streitkräfte, die die von der Türkei eingeschleusten syrischen Milizen bekämpfen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ganz besonders Ägypten hat der islamistische Extremismus, der weltweit Tod und Zerstörung sät, tiefe Wunden zugefügt. Die Muslimbrüderschaft hat Ägypten beinahe in die Knie gezwungen. Gegen all diese Bedrohungen stemmt sich der ägyptische Staat, während er zugleich Fortschritte auf den Gebieten Wirtschaft und Bildung für seine Bürger vorantreibt, und er bildet Allianzen mit gleichgesinnten Ländern, um etwas mehr Stabilität in der gesamten Region zu erreichen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir hier führen aber endlose Diskussionen, um Ägypten kritisieren zu können. Ein Gerichtsverfahren ist uns nicht genug. Wir ermutigen die Opposition zur ägyptischen Regierung, einer Regierung, die in unserem Interesse handelt, im Interesse unserer Sicherheit. Und diese ununterbrochene Kritik belastet unsere Beziehungen zu Kairo, und das ist ganz sicher nicht in unserem Interesse. Deswegen müssen wir realistisch und pragmatisch denken. Ägypten ist ernsten Bedrohungen seiner Sicherheit durch Extremismus ausgesetzt – von innen wie von außen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb gilt es für uns alle, Ägypten konstruktiv kritisch – auch bei unterschiedlichen Meinungen – zu begleiten, anstatt es konstant abzuweisen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-076-0000" speaker_id="197464" name="Hannah Neumann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, dear colleagues, today, exactly 10 years ago, Mohamed Bouazizi set himself on fire starting what has long been called the Arab Spring, but was actually smashed with violence in so many places including in Egypt. In Egypt that is today run by a dictator – Mr Berg – a dictator that brands human rights’ defenders as terrorists, who puts people in jail for years for having not more than Whatsapp on their phones. And this dictator was received by President Emmanuel Macron last week who then officially announced that he will continue to supply this dictator with arms irrespective of his human rights record.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear colleagues, that is carte blanche for Macron to do even worse and it is a slap in the face of each and every one who has been fighting for freedom and democracy in the Middle East for the last 10 years, because we all know the arms of France, the arms of Germany and of so many other countries, have been used against the protesters. I don’t want us to go down this road. That is why we need a real arms embargo. We need to suspend any budget support to this regime, and we need to see all the political prisoners freed.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-077-0000" speaker_id="23788" name="Adam Bielan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, fundamental rights, such as freedom of expression and the right to a fair trial, must always be respected. I would like to express my concerns over the arrest and targeting of the Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights (EIPR) and, generally, over the systemic targeting of human rights defenders by the Egyptian authorities. As many of my colleagues have done, I call for the release of all EIPR staff.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, I would also like to note that Egypt remains an important partner for the EU in many areas. Unfortunately, the joint motion for a resolution neither recognises this, nor considers the severe terrorist threat from radical Islamist organisations that the authorities are trying to tackle. Additionally, the joint motion calls for sanctions that are too harsh, imposing monitoring measures coordinated by the EU, as well as for a complete review of all our existing relations. Thus I believe it goes beyond its original purpose. Therefore, my group won’t be able to vote in favour of the joint motion for a resolution.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-078-0000" speaker_id="197468" name="Özlem Demirel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der GUE/NGL-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Herr Berg von der AfD: Nein, das Regime in Ägypten vertritt mitnichten meine Interessen, denn ich stehe an der Seite der Menschenrechte, und die Menschenrechtssituation in Ägypten ist besorgniserregend.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb lassen Sie mich ohne Umschweife sagen: Die Zusammenarbeit mit dem Putschisten al-Sisi ist ein Verrat an jenen, die infolge der sozialen Aufstände monatelang für demokratische und soziale Grundrechte und Freiheiten demonstriert haben. Al-Sisi ist ein Vertreter der ägyptischen Oligarchie, der es geschafft hat, über die berechtigte Empörung über die Muslimbrüderschaft die soziale und demokratische Volksbewegung zu unterdrücken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist zynisch, dass Präsident Macron diese Menschenrechtsverletzungen relativiert und weiterhin Waffen an das Regime aus der Europäischen Union verkauft werden. Es ist heuchlerisch, dass Ägypten auch ein Partner der EU in der Flüchtlingsabwehr ist. Nein, elementare Menschenrechte sind mitnichten eine Frage von Meinungsverschiedenheiten. Dies ist nicht nur zynisch, sondern auch ein typisch unverfrorener Akt zur Legitimierung imperialer Interessen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-079-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Fabio Massimo Castaldo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, "ho visto Regeni in quell'ufficio 13 e c'erano anche due ufficiali e altri agenti. Entrando nell'ufficio ho notato delle catene di ferro con cui legavano le persone. Lui era mezzo nudo nella parte superiore, portava dei segni di tortura e stava blaterando nella sua lingua, delirava. Era steso a terra, con il viso riverso. L'ho visto ammanettato con delle manette che lo costringevano a terra". Questi, secondo il principale testimone oculare, sono stati gli ultimi fotogrammi della vita barbaramente spezzata di Giulio Regeni, cittadino italiano e cittadino europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questi i trattamenti subiti ogni giorno da migliaia di attivisti, in un paese in cui negli ultimi anni sono state condannate a morte 3 000 persone, più di 60 000 arrestate e incarcerate sulla base di prove inconsistenti e processi di massa, tra cui Patrick Zaki e gli operatori di EIPR.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quanto a lungo volete restare silenti, mentre un paese con il quale abbiamo legami politici e commerciali si trasforma in un regime del terrore? È in gioco la nostra credibilità. Al-Sisi deve rispettare i nostri principi, non esibire le nostre medaglie. Abbiamo un regime sanzionatorio da innescare in caso di violazioni severe dei diritti umani. Non possiamo permettere doppi standard. Se non ora quando? Verità e giustizia per Giulio Regeni!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-080-0000" speaker_id="127096" name="Domènec Ruiz Devesa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, ciertamente Europa no puede tolerar represalias contra aquellos que mantienen reuniones legítimas con diplomáticos europeos ni contra aquellos que luchan por la defensa de los derechos humanos o hacen uso de la libertad de expresión precisamente ahora —como ha dicho la diputada Neumann—, cuando se cumplen diez años de las primaveras árabes, que fueron precisamente una reclamación de libertad y de democracia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero expresar mi solidaridad con Patrick Zaki y con su familia, y unir mi voz a la llamada de este Parlamento para exigir —y usted lo tiene que hacer junto con la Comisión y el alto representante— su liberación inmediata, señora comisaria. Es inconcebible que un estudiante de Erasmus Mundus sea encarcelado y torturado por su trabajo de investigación.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero vamos a ver, oíamos a los señores de la ultraderecha felicitar a Al-Sisi, están encantados con Al-Sisi porque lucha contra el terrorismo islámico. Y yo les diría: señores de la ultraderecha, ustedes nos tienen acostumbrados a decir muchas barbaridades, pero realmente, ¿qué tiene que ver el señor Patrick Zaki con la lucha contra el terrorismo islámico? ¿Qué tiene que ver Gulio Regeni, que fue asesinado por las fuerzas de seguridad del señor Al-Sisi, con la lucha contra el terrorismo islámico? ¿Cómo pueden decir estas cosas? ¿Cómo puede el presidente de la República francesa, al que consideramos un líder europeísta y, por tanto, defensor de la Ilustración y los derechos humanos, darle la Gran Cruz de la Orden de la Legión de Honor al señor dictador Al-Sisi?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-081-0000" speaker_id="197588" name="Katalin Cseh (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, civil liberties are under systemic government crackdown in Egypt. The senior members of a highly respected human rights group, Karim Ennarah, Mohammed Basheer and Gasser Abdel—Razek, were arbitrarily detained and continue to be harassed by the authorities. Patrick Zaki is an Erasmus student, a participant in our very own flagship programme. He was tortured and continues to be in police detention. Giulio Regeni was an Italian journalist, tortured and murdered, and justice has not been served until this day. And there are so many more cases. We are way past the point of deep concerns.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have just rolled out the EU Magnitsky Act. It’s time for High Representative Borrell to finally put targeted sanctions on the table.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let’s review our EU aid programmes to make sure that no human rights abuser is propped up with EU taxpayers’ money but that we support civil society directly.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, every time we sit down to talk to Egypt over any issue, these people’s stories and their human rights belong right there at the negotiating table.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-082-0000" speaker_id="204346" name="Dominik Tarczyński" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, what a festival of hypocrisy from all of those coming from the left, from the liberals! You support Mr Macron and then you are the first to shout out that he’s selling arms to the Egyptian regime. So why do you support leftist ideology? Why do you support Mr Macron, who calls himself a liberal? Where are you liberals? First, you create a problem, and then you try to solve it.</p>
      <p sl="en">First of all, when discussing human rights in Egypt, the main problem is the rights of the Christians – when people are killed, when priests are hanged and beheaded. This is what is happening now in Paris. This is what is happening now in Egypt. So, first you create a problem, then you’re the first to shout about wanting to solve that problem.</p>
      <p sl="en">The main group facing prosecution is the Christians. So, I’m shouting in the name of the Christians in Egypt. Protect us! Protect us! Do not sell arms, or fight it with the political tools. Christianity and the Christmas season come from Christ, so Merry Christmas not ‘happy season’. Happy Christmas to you all.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-083-0000" speaker_id="197828" name="Manu Pineda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, nos dicen los colegas de la extrema derecha que hay que felicitar al dictador Al-Sisi porque lo que está practicando es la lucha antiterrorista.</p>
      <p sl="en">No podemos aceptar, no podemos permitir que se camuflen los crímenes como una lucha heroica, que se esté utilizando eso como una cortina de humo para encubrir detenciones masivas, torturas y asesinatos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señores, ¿qué tenía que ver Giulio Regeni con el terrorismo? Y fue detenido y torturado, y su cuerpo apareció en una cuneta seis días después, con una hemorragia cerebral, porque se pasaron con la tortura.</p>
      <p sl="en">¿Qué tiene que ver el activista por los derechos de las personas LGTBI con el terrorismo?</p>
      <p sl="en">Y lleva detenido y siendo torturado desde febrero.</p>
      <p sl="en">¿Qué tiene que ver la señora Mahienur al-Masri, abogada defensora de los derechos humanos, con el terrorismo? Y ha sido detenida tres veces en los dos últimos años por ese al que el señor Macron le da la medalla de la Legión de Honor. Menos hipocresía, señores, hay que romper lazos con esas … (la presidenta retira la palabra al orador).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-084-0000" speaker_id="204733" name="Dorien Rookmaker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, “Ik ga zaken van defensie en economische samenwerking niet afhankelijk maken van deze meningsverschillen.” Dat was het antwoord van Macron, de kleine Napoleon in het Elysée op vragen over de verkoop van wapens aan Egypte. Macron verkoopt wapens aan een dictator die niet zou aarzelen deze tegen zijn eigen mensen in te zetten. Ondertussen maakt het Europees Parlement zich druk over de strapatsen van de leiders in Hongarije en Polen en dat is klein bier in vergelijking met de ondermijnende acties van Macron.</p>
      <p sl="en">Een deplorabele economische situatie in Frankrijk dwingt de kleine Napoleon op de knieën. Gedwongen door oplopende schulden verkwanselt hij onze Europese waarden. Welke hoop kunnen de politieke gevangenen in Egypte nog hebben als Macron wapens verkoopt aan al-Sisi? Welke hoop kan Nasrin, de Iraanse mensenrechtenactiviste die al jaren vastzit hebben als ze hoort van de corrupte opstelling van Macron? De economische situatie als gevolg van de COVID-19-pandemie is zorgelijk. Maar de hypocrisie en het cynisme van Europese politieke leiders zijn desastreus.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-085-0000" speaker_id="840" name="Charles Goerens (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, je voterai bien entendu cette résolution, avec son lot de mises en garde, de protestations et de condamnations. Je le fais, comme la plupart de mes collègues, avec conviction, compassion et solidarité avec les victimes des exactions qui viennent d’être évoquées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Malheureusement, trop souvent, les autorités politiques responsables de l’arbitraire et des souffrances infligées à leurs victimes se sentent à l’abri de toute sanction parce qu’il y a les impératifs de la Realpolitik. Et puis il y a de nombreux partenaires qui autorisent les mêmes pratiques chez eux. Je vois Mme Arena acquiescer, ce qui me conforte dans mon propos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le monde libre est encore trop divisé parce que chacun suit, la plupart du temps, ses propres intérêts. C’est pourquoi je terminerai quand même sur une note d’optimisme: le sommet mondial sur la démocratie annoncé par Joe Biden devrait être l’occasion d’ouvrir la voie à une meilleure structuration de la réponse du monde libre aux dirigeants responsables de toutes ces exactions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-086-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, we pay close attention to human rights developments in Egypt and address them in various ways.</p>
      <p sl="en">Arrests and prosecution of civil society organisations, and people expressing themselves on social media remain a cause for concern.</p>
      <p sl="en">In September 2020 at the 45th United Nations Human Rights Council in Geneva, the EU raised various human rights issues in Egypt, under item 4, including a call to release human rights defenders.</p>
      <p sl="en">The recent arrests of the director and staff members of the Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights, the EIPR, underlined once more the worrying situation in this regard.</p>
      <p sl="en">We consider that the EIPR provides a critical service to the Egyptian people. We expressed our concern in a statement by the spokesperson of the European External Action Service on 21 November. We welcome as a first step, the release of the three EIPR staff members on 3 December, while reiterating our call for the release of Mr George Patrick Zaki, an EIPR researcher who has remained in detention since February 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have also noted that the challenges mentioned take place against positive developments in social and economic rights, such as the protection of women amid the COVID pandemic, as highlighted in the latest UNDP UN Women report that shows Egypt is the best performer in the region.</p>
      <p sl="en">Further, on 25 November the Egyptian Government approved the implementing regulations of the 2019 NGO Law, which is an improvement from previous legislation and gives more predictability to charity organisations.</p>
      <p sl="en">The protection and promotion of human rights, democracy and the rule of law are guiding principles of our external action and policies. The new action plan on human rights and democracy 2020—2024, approved in November, reaffirms the EU’s strong commitment to further advancing universal values for all.</p>
      <p sl="en">These commitments also have a central place in the framework of our political engagement and cooperation with Egypt. This was also discussed during High Representative Borrell’s latest visit to Cairo on 3 September of this year, as well as that of the President of the European Council, Mr Michel, in November. The EU Special Representative for Human Rights, Mr Gilmore, is also in regular contact with the relevant Egyptian counterparts.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU has a clear interest in Egypt’s long—term stability and security. This can only be achieved if human rights are fully implemented and upheld. This remains the guiding torch in our bilateral dialogue with Egypt within the framework of our partnership.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-087-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung über die Änderungsanträge findet heute statt, die Schlussabstimmung hingegen am Freitag, 18. Dezember 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-088-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">par écrit. – Il est consternant que d’aucuns, en France, se soient indignés de la visite à Paris du président égyptien Abdel Fattah al-Sissi, puisque ce dernier a été élu à la suite du renversement de son prédécesseur Mohamed Morsi, proche des Frères musulmans. Par ailleurs, Abdel Fattah al-Sissi a grandement contribué à l’amélioration de la condition des coptes égyptiens. En témoigne l’inauguration en janvier 2019 d’une impressionnante cathédrale de la Nativité dans la nouvelle capitale administrative égyptienne, ou encore la forte augmentation du nombre de candidats coptes aux élections parlementaires de 2020.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ces symboles forts d’œcuménisme ne sauraient être ignorés, à l’heure où, au Proche et Moyen-Orient, et même en Afrique subsaharienne, les communautés chrétiennes semblent être progressivement rayées de la carte. Au point que, dans un rapport remis à l’ex-ministre britannique des affaires étrangères, le terme de «génocide» n’était plus tabou. Ces actes doivent donc être pris en compte dans l’appréciation de ce régime, alors que la lutte contre l’islamisme occupe tous les esprits.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="8.2. Forced labour and the situation of the Uyghurs in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region">
    <intervention id="4-090-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über sechs Entschließungsanträge zu Zwangsarbeit und zu der Situation der Uiguren im Uigurischen Autonomen Gebiet Xinjiang (2020/2913(RSP))*.</p>
      <p sl="en">_______________</p>
      <p sl="en">*Siehe Protokoll.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-091-0000" speaker_id="197571" name="Nikolaj Villumsen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">stiller. – Hr. formand! Lige nu foregår der en bestialsk undertrykkelse af den uygurske minoritetsbefolkning i Kina. Tvangsarbejde, tvungen sterilisering og gigantiske fangelejre er desværre hverdagen for hundredtusinder af uygurer og andre muslimske mindretal i Kina. Vi har brug for målrettede sanktioner mod de ansvarlige for undertrykkelsen af uygurerne i det kinesiske regime.</p>
      <p sl="en">Indtil nu har EU desværre svigtet indsatsen mod det massive tvangsarbejde, som uygurerne udsættes for. EU har valgt at se passivt til, mens multinationale selskaber tjener stort på undertrykkelsen. Det skal stoppe. Vi har brug for gennemsigtige værdikæder, så virksomheder holdes ansvarlige, når de tjener profit på undertrykkelse. De multinationale selskaber skal mærke, at vi ikke accepterer, at der tjenes penge på undertrykkelsen af uygurerne og af de muslimske mindretal i Kina.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kære kolleger! Det kræver, at vi handler nu. Det kræver, at EU skærper indsatsen. Det kræver målrettede sanktioner mod de ansvarlige i det kinesiske regime, og det kræver, at vi sætter målrettet ind over for de multinationale selskaber, som tjener på undertrykkelsen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-092-0000" speaker_id="96739" name="Reinhard Bütikofer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser. – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Die Entschließung zur Lage in Xinjiang, über die wir heute debattieren, zeigt die große Übereinstimmung der demokratischen Fraktionen, und das ist gut so.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wo Menschenrechte mit Füßen getreten werden, zeigen wir gemeinsam Solidarität. Dass einige linksradikale Mitglieder dieses Hauses im Namen der GUE-Fraktion Anträge eingereicht haben, in denen sie sich statt mit den Opfern der Menschenrechtsverletzungen mit der autoritären KP-Propaganda aus Beijing solidarisieren, halte ich allerdings für einen Skandal. Die GUE sollte sich überlegen, wo sie eigentlich steht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir wollen die Verbrechen gegen die Menschlichkeit in Xinjiang, die gegen die Uiguren dort begangen werden, nicht nur verbal kritisieren. Wir wollen auch, dass Taten folgen. Diese Forderungen gehen vor allem an die Politik und die Wirtschaft. Um es klar zu sagen: Es muss Sanktionen geben gegen die Verantwortlichen in Xinjiang und gegen Firmen wie XPCC, die Zwangsarbeiter ausbeuten. Europas Firmen, die nicht sicherstellen können, dass sie zu Kollaborateuren des Unterdrückungsregimes werden, die nicht verhindern können, dass sie zu Kollaborateuren werden, sollen Xinjiang verlassen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Produkte aus uigurischer Zwangsarbeit dürfen nicht auf den EU-Markt gelangen. Beim Investitionsabkommen mit China muss die EU darauf bestehen, dass die Anti-Zwangsarbeit-Konventionen der Internationalen Arbeitsorganisation (ILO) ratifiziert werden. Ich kann mir nicht vorstellen, dass dieses Haus zustimmt, wenn es beim Investitionsabkommen dazu keine klaren Verpflichtungen gibt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-094-0000" speaker_id="37229" name="Kati Piri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Auteur. – Voorzitter, genadeloos onderdrukt de Chinese staat Oeigoeren en andere moslimminderheden in Xinjiang, al jarenlang, en een aantal Europese bedrijven is medeplichtig. De gruwelen van de Chinese staat zijn bijna niet te bevatten. Van de tien miljoen Oeigoeren in Xinjiang zit meer dan één miljoen in gruwelijke interneringskampen. 900 000 kinderen zijn bij hun ouders weggehaald en in staatsweeshuizen gezet, en stelselmatig worden Oeigoeren opgesloten, gemarteld, gesurveilleerd en gedwongen tot abortus en sterilisatie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Laten we dit noemen wat het is. De Chinese staat pleegt een misdaad tegen de menselijkheid en deze week kwam daar een extra cijfer bij. Meer dan een half miljoen: dat is het aantal Oeigoeren dat de Chinese staat dwingt tot dwangarbeid, om de katoen te plukken waarvan onze kleding wordt gemaakt, ook door Europese bedrijven. Waar we het hier over hebben, is moderne slavernij en iedere betrokkenheid bij dwangarbeid is absoluut onacceptabel. Het is onverteerbaar dat Europese bedrijven hierbij betrokken zijn. Dit kan niet zonder consequenties blijven.</p>
      <p sl="en">Onlangs is er een nieuw EU-sanctieregime aangenomen om de ernstigste mensenrechtenschenders snel en hard te treffen. Nu is die lijst nog leeg. Ik roep ertoe op om de Chinese officials en staatsbedrijven die verantwoordelijk zijn voor deze dwangarbeid, massale opsluiting en onderdrukking, daar als eerste aan toe te voegen. China moet deze misdadige campagne vandaag nog eindigen. Laat ik heel duidelijk zijn: in onze Europese winkels is geen plaats voor producten waaraan de smet van Oeigoerse dwangarbeid kleeft. Ieder product waarbij in de bevoorradingsketen mensenrechten worden geschonden, moet daarom worden verboden.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Europa zijn Oeigoeren, Hongkongers, Tibetanen en dissidenten veilig. In China loopt hun leven gevaar. Nooit zullen wij China’s wrede campagne van onderdrukking, dwangarbeid en religieuze vervolging door de vingers zien. Er is geen excuus meer. Treed nu op, de Oeigoeren hebben ons nodig.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-095-0000" speaker_id="197469" name="Assita Kanko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, can you imagine what it must be like to be forced to be sterilised, to be forced to undergo abortion, to be tortured, to be used as a slave, to have your children taken away from you? Because that is the reality for so many Uyghurs and other Muslim minorities in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region. Twenty percent of the world’s cotton production originates from Xinjiang, often harvested with the use of forced labour. The supply chain for textile products, including masks sold in our pharmacies here in Europe, are part of an economy that is based on forced labour and a lot of exploitation and suffering.</p>
      <p sl="en">Our companies cannot simply turn a blind eye and claim ignorance. They have a duty to better monitor their supply chains. China is not simply an economic partner; it is a country edging towards the definition of carrying out genocide. The EU and Member States must put in place effective controls and place an import ban on Chinese products made using forced labour. The EU should enforce targeted sanctions against Chinese officials responsible for overseeing these shocking crimes. It’s time to stop talking and practice what we actually believe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-096-0000" speaker_id="197430" name="Engin Eroglu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser. – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen, sehr geehrte Frau Kommissarin, sehr geehrte Zuschauer daheim an den Bildschirmen! Der Staudamm des Schweigens und der falschen Wahrheiten bekommt heute Risse.</p>
      <p sl="en">Täglich werden Männer, Frauen und Kinder mit Gewalt gebrochen mit dem einzigen Ziel, ihre eigene Identität, das eigene Leben aufzugeben. Was in Xinjiang stattfindet, ist ein systematischer Alptraum von Masseninhaftierungen, Menschenrechtsverletzungen und der Massensterilisation von uigurischen Frauen. Wir wissen aus einem Bericht von Adrian Zenz, dass über 500 000 Menschen in Xinjiang in der Baumwollindustrie Zwangsarbeit verrichten müssen. Die Produktion macht 20 % der weltweiten Baumwollproduktion aus.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir, wir heute im Europäischen Parlament, dokumentieren die aktuell größte Versklavung und Verletzung von Menschenrechten weltweit. Wir, wir hier im Europäischen Parlament, schließen heute die Reihen. Viel zu lange haben Entscheidungsträger geschwiegen. Dafür möchte ich mich persönlich entschuldigen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mit der heutigen Entschließung zum Schicksal der Uiguren wird aus Rhetorik endlich Praxis. Wir haben gezielte Sanktionen gegen die Verantwortlichen durch den Magnitsky Act der EU. „Schutz der Uiguren in der EU und in Drittstaaten“ steht in der Entschließung. Wir wollen keinen Gipfel mehr zwischen der Europäischen Union und China, auf dem nicht auch über Menschenrechte gesprochen wird. Am Ende des Tages fordern wir die Vereinten Nationen auf, eine unabhängige Untersuchungsmission in China zu machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber damit ist der Weg noch nicht zu Ende. Auch in Tibet, in der Mongolei und in Hongkong haben Menschen erhebliche Probleme mit der chinesischen Regierung und kämpfen für Freiheit. Wir müssen dazu Partner suchen wie Taiwan, die auch unter chinesischem Druck für Freiheit einstehen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-097-0000" speaker_id="204336" name="Miriam Lexmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, let me begin by thanking my colleagues and all the staff for the excellent cooperation in drafting the urgency resolution. Its strong message is a testimony to the cross-party commitment to stand with the Uyghurs and all those whose human dignity and freedoms are being violated every day.</p>
      <p sl="en">Just in the recent years, the Chinese Communist Party has built an Orwellian state that has introduced mass surveillance, engaged in forced organ-harvesting from prisoners of conscience, forced sterilisation, forced labour, and has placed over one million Uyghurs in the concentration camps. It systematically destroyed thousands of churches, mosques and other places of worship and culture. It behaves with increasingly brute force across mainland China and Hong Kong, and threatens and bullies Taiwan and countries around the globe. Moreover, Cardinal Bo said rightly that ‘it is the oppression, the lies and corruption of the CCP that are responsible’ for the current pandemics.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear colleagues, it is the right time to re-think our relationship with China, ensuring a value-based and consistent approach towards the Chinese Communist Party. We must understand that our values do not hinder our policies – but policies that ignore our values do. If the EU wants to have credibility as a global actor, it must ensure a consistent value-based foreign policy. That must mean seeing the Chinese Communist Party for what it is, while engaging positively with the Chinese people. That must mean standing with the Uyghurs, Hongkongers, Tibetans, and all those oppressed by the Chinese Communist Party. That must mean clear consequences for the suppression of human dignity and freedoms, such as imposing targeted sanctions. That must mean upholding corporate responsibility through due diligence in our supply chains and banning the import of all products made by forced labour. That must mean working closely with our democratic allies in addressing human rights violations across mainland China and Hong Kong, and coordinating our policies on sanctions, import bans and other measures to send a clear message: we will defend human dignity. We will defend freedom.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-098-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, recently I saw documentaries on RTE and the BBC highlighting that the Chinese Government has reportedly detained more than a million Muslims in re-education camps. The Presidency has amassed power, using more and more unapologetic means to suffocate internal dissent or desire for political reform. And like many in this House, I am deeply concerned about the increasingly suppressive regime in China and how many religious and ethnic minorities, in particular the Uyghurs and Kazakhs, face a violation of their human dignity, as well as a denial of their rights to freedom of speech, cultural expression and religious belief, as well as peaceful assembly.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chinese officials maintain that what they call ‘vocational training centres’ do not infringe on Uyghurs’ rights. They have refused to share information about their detention centres. Nevertheless, internal Chinese Government documents leaked in late 2019 have provided important details of how officials launched and maintained the detention camps, as do the RTE and BBC documentaries and satellite imagery.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Chinese authorities need to immediately, and unconditionally, release the Uyghur scholar and Sakharov Prize winner in 2019, Ilham Tohti.</p>
      <p sl="en">The global influence of China is clearly growing. It is because China is so economically influential that democracies who respect the rule of law and fundamental human rights need to coordinate more effectively in implementing sanctions and other measures to address human rights violations in mainland China and its other regions. Nothing else will suffice.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-099-0000" speaker_id="5729" name="Kathleen Van Brempt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de S&amp;D-Fractie. – Voorzitter, deze resolutie over dwangarbeid van de Oeigoeren in China komt meer dan op tijd. Eerder deze week publiceerde het Centrum for Global Policy een studie waaruit blijkt dat het probleem nog veel groter is dan we eigenlijk aanvankelijk dachten en dat dus heel wat van de katoen op onze markt geplukt is door dwangarbeid in China. Het moet duidelijk zijn dat internationale bedrijven, maar dus ook Europese bedrijven, eigenlijk hun ogen sluiten en niet kijken wat hun onderaannemers allemaal doen. Dus het voorstel van de Commissie over due diligence – het is hier al zo vaak gezegd – moet er heel snel komen. We moeten er heel snel werk van maken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar ook via handelsbeleid moet onze verantwoordelijkheid worden opgenomen. We onderhandelen op dit moment over een deal rond investeringen. Laten we ervoor zorgen dat er een “dd-chapter” in staat rond mensenrechten en dwangarbeid en dat dat afdwingbaar is. Handelsbeleid staat niet op zichzelf, maar moet een van onze krachtige instrumenten zijn om de wereld ten goede te veranderen. Laten we dat ook doen door ervoor te zorgen dat we ons economisch gewicht gebruiken om dwangarbeid uit de wereld te helpen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-100-0000" speaker_id="197543" name="Bernard Guetta" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Renew. – Madame la Présidente, des «camps de rééducation», disent les dirigeants chinois. Ah oui? Mais à quoi le travail forcé rééduque-t-il plus d’un million de Ouïgours enfermés dans ces camps de concentration? Eh bien, c’est à s’incliner devant un parti unique qui exige et voudrait imposer l’assimilation des minorités à l’ethnie majoritaire que sont rééduqués les Ouïgours comme, d’ailleurs, les Tibétains et les Mongols.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un seul peuple pour un seul parti, tel est l’objectif de ces ethnocides qui se déroulent sous nos yeux, sans que quiconque puisse les ignorer. On sait, tout le monde sait, mais le régime chinois ose présenter sa dictature comme préférable aux démocraties. Tout le monde sait, mais les gouvernements des pays musulmans se taisent, tandis que les mouvements islamistes, si prompts à dénoncer l’islamophobie partout ailleurs, ne disent mot. Pas un mot.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors Monsieur Xi, nous vous le disons de ce Parlement, l’Europe vous le dit: ce crime, vous en êtes personnellement responsable et nous vous en tenons pour personnellement coupable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-101-0000" speaker_id="197623" name="Thierry Mariani" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Que disait le général de Gaulle en 1964 quand il reconnaissait la République de Chine? Deux choses. Il estimait qu’il fallait reconnaître la Chine, car le poids de l’évidence et de la raison pesait chaque jour davantage. Et il ajoutait: «Il n’est pas exclu que la Chine redevienne, au siècle prochain, ce qu’elle fut pendant des siècles, la plus grande puissance de l’univers».</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous y sommes. L’émergence d’un monde multipolaire affaiblit considérablement la domination américaine sur le monde, et chaque information sur la Chine doit faire l’objet de notre esprit critique. Comme vous, j’appelle de mes vœux une Chine qui respecte la liberté religieuse et qui participe activement au concert des nations. C’est à cela que nous devons travailler efficacement, pas à la multiplication des déclarations de défiance vis-à-vis de Pékin. C’est l’intérêt de l’Europe et c’est l’intérêt de l’ensemble de nos pays.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a exactement un an, nous votions des résolutions sur Hong Kong. À quoi ont-elles servi? Qu’ont-elles changé? Si nous voulons engager un véritable dialogue avec Pékin plutôt qu’une politique de dénonciation permanente, alors peut-être pourrons-nous faire changer les choses.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-102-0000" speaker_id="197511" name="Salima Yenbou" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Madame la Présidente, 20 % du coton mondial est aujourd’hui produit dans la province du Xinjiang, province où – nous le savons depuis plusieurs années déjà – toutes sortes de violations des droits humains ont lieu dans une grande indifférence: travaux forcés, viols, tortures, surveillance de masse, stérilisations forcées, enfermement dans des camps de rééducation, harcèlement envers la minorité ouïgoure musulmane et intimidations de la presse et des activistes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous ne pouvons plus fermer les yeux sur ce qui s’apparente à des crimes contre l’humanité, comme le dit clairement la résolution d’aujourd’hui. Lorsque nos enfants nous interpelleront, nous ne pourrons pas dire que nous ne savions pas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je remercie et félicite Antoine Griezmann pour son courage et sa responsabilité d’annuler sa collaboration avec Huawei, accusé de participer à la surveillance des Ouïgours. Prenons exemple sur notre champion européen, car nous avons toutes et tous une responsabilité et un rôle à jouer.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’appelle donc toutes les entreprises, notamment européennes, à cesser tout commerce avec des biens produits dans le Xinjiang. L’histoire nous jugera. Si nous ne réussissons pas à faire cesser ces violations des droits humains, l’histoire nous jugera.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-103-0000" speaker_id="197773" name="Bert-Jan Ruissen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, geachte mevrouw de commissaris, het kan toch niet zo zijn dat we maar gewoon ongestraft handel blijven drijven met een land dat meer dan een miljoen mensen gedwongen heeft opgesloten in strafkampen, op grote schaal vrouwen steriliseert, massaal arbeiders gedwongen te werk stelt op katoenplantages en in fabrieken – en dat onder het mom van armoedebestrijding –, en haar Oeigoerse onderdanen systematisch observeert, infiltreert en intimideert, tot in de EU-lidstaten toe? En dan spreek ik nog niet eens over de toenemende druk op christelijke en andere religieuze gemeenschappen in de rest van China, of over de toenemende repressie in Hong Kong.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dit kan niet zo verder. De tijd van alleen praten is voorbij. Recente mensenrechtendialogen hebben geen vooruitgang gebracht. China transformeert van een strategische partner steeds meer naar een systematische rivaal. Het recent aangenomen Magnitsky sanctie-instrument moet daarom zo snel mogelijk ingezet worden tegen medeplichtigen in deze kwestie. De EU moet geen economische overeenkomsten meer sluiten zonder harde concessies van de Chinese zijde op het gebied van mensenrechten. Het wordt tijd om de daad bij het woord te voegen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-104-0000" speaker_id="197754" name="Sandra Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo GUE/NGL. – Senhor Presidente, Senhora Comissária, é preocupante que a União Europeia e as suas instituições, como demonstra o presente debate e a resolução neste Parlamento, se transformem em caixa de ressonância da estratégia de confrontação promovida pela Administração norte-americana de Trump contra a República Popular da China.</p>
      <p sl="en">O Parlamento Europeu não só se associa como se constitui promotor de uma inaceitável operação de desinformação que procura dar cobertura à campanha contra a China depois de falhada a tentativa de os Estados Unidos da América criarem um foco de desestabilização na região autónoma Uigur de Xinjiang.</p>
      <p sl="en">A alegação aos direitos humanos por parte de quem, como a União Europeia, tantas vezes os afronta, é, na verdade, um exercício de hipocrisia a que recorre na tentativa de travar e, se possível, impedir o rápido desenvolvimento económico e tecnológico avançado pela China.</p>
      <p sl="en">Votamos contra a presente resolução, que se inscreve numa política de confrontação, de ingerência e de agressão contra a República Popular da China e o seu povo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-105-0000" speaker_id="202351" name="Carles Puigdemont i Casamajó" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, no one can deny the evidence that China is committing serious massive human rights violations against the Uyghur people. We cannot continue to do nothing and accept a shameful situation committed by a country with which we have strong relations and exchanges. In this regard, the Uyghur World Congress urged the EU to take action to combat this crime and suggested several measures: sanctions for those mainly responsible for these violations (we know who they are); a cotton import ban from Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region; ensuring that companies do not benefit from forced labour; making all EU China investment agreements conditional on concrete advance on the respect for human rights; organising an independent fact-finding mission to Xinjiang; ensuring free and unrestricted access to the internment camps for any potential visit; and, of course, organising a visit to the political prisoner Ilham Tohti, 2019 Sakharov Prize winner, unjustly imprisoned in China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-106-0000" speaker_id="197421" name="Isabel Wiseler-Lima" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, nous les appelons «centres de détention», les autorités chinoises les appellent «centres de rééducation politique». Dans la région autonome du Xinjiang, ces camps d’internement sont en expansion. Des rapports considérés comme crédibles estiment que plus d’un million de Ouïgours sont détenus. De plus, des enquêtes rapportent que les Ouïgours sont forcés de travailler dans des chaînes de production de vêtements ou de produits technologiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">En mars 2020, l’Australian Strategic Policy Institute dénonçait le fait que ces usines fournissent un grand nombre de marques, notamment des multinationales européennes. Ce même mois, je posais une question à la Commission, demandant si elle pouvait fournir des informations sur ce travail forcé et sur les entreprises impliquées, si des produits pouvaient être identifiés et surtout si certains étaient exportés vers l’Union européenne. Je demandais, enfin, si la Commission envisageait des mesures s’il s’avérait que de tels produits avaient pénétré le marché européen. Dans sa réponse, M. le haut représentant se dit préoccupé. Il dit avoir fait part de ses inquiétudes aux autorités chinoises – allégations rejetées par ces autorités – et vouloir continuer à aborder le sujet. Enfin, il dit avoir exhorté la Chine à autoriser des observateurs au Xinjiang. Vous comprendrez ma déception à la lecture de la réponse.</p>
      <p sl="en">Toutefois, si les récents reportages diffusés sur nos chaînes nationales et autres médias ne mentent pas, la question qui se pose n’est plus de savoir si le marché européen est concerné, mais de savoir ce que va faire la Commission pour réagir face aux produits en lien avec le travail forcé sur nos marchés. Car il semble indéniable que nombre des masques fabriqués en Chine que nous portons ont été fabriqués dans le cadre du travail forcé, que la récolte du coton utilisé dans nombre de vêtements en vente en Europe a été faite avec du travail forcé. Donc, encore une fois, quelles mesures la Commission va-t-elle prendre en attendant de faire une proposition de législation sur le devoir de vigilance? Des réponses sont une demande pressante du Parlement européen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-107-0000" speaker_id="197694" name="Raphaël Glucksmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, j’accuse. J’accuse les dirigeants du parti communiste chinois du pire crime contre l’humanité du XXIe siècle: la déportation et l’éradication du peuple ouïgour.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’accuse. J’accuse la communauté internationale de consentir à ce crime par son silence et sa passivité.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’accuse. J’accuse les dirigeants de nombreux pays musulmans, du Pakistan à l’Arabie saoudite, qui brandissent d’un côté leur foi en étendard et de l’autre soutiennent la politique chinoise de destruction des mosquées et de profanation des cimetières.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’accuse. J’accuse les patrons cupides de Nike, de Zara et de tant d’autres multinationales qui bénéficient de la réduction en esclavage d’un peuple.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’accuse enfin les dirigeants européens de lâcheté et de veulerie. Ces dirigeants, nous les avons exhortés, il y a un an déjà, à prendre des actions pour faire fermer ces camps. Qu’ont-ils fait depuis un an? Rien. Rien du tout. Un footballeur comme Griezmann ou des milliers de jeunes sur les réseaux sociaux ont plus fait en un an pour les Ouïgours que tous nos dirigeants réunis.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, que les choses soient claires: si ces dirigeants s’assoient sur la résolution que nous votons aujourd’hui, s’ils refusent de sanctionner les dirigeants chinois, l’histoire les jugera complices de crime contre l’humanité et nous les jugerons avant elle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-108-0000" speaker_id="197818" name="Billy Kelleher (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">A Uachtaráin, go raibh maith agaibh as an deis a thabhairt dom labhairt ar an gceist thábhachtach seo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Is scannal agus smál ar an daonnacht atá i bpáirt againn é na milliúin de na hUigiúraigh a bheith faoi ghlas i gCampaí Géibhinn sa tSín. Is léir chomh maith go bhfuil eagla rómhór roimh an tSín ar fhormhór mhuintir an domhain aon rud a dhéanamh faoi sin. Maidir le comhshamhlú éigeantach na nUigiúrach i gcultúr Han na Síne, is rud é sin a bhaineann leis an am atá caite agus ní leis an mbliain 2020. An t-ábhar imní is mó atá ann, áfach, ná teip an phobail idirnáisiúnta an fód a sheasamh in aghaidh na Síne faoi sin, agus go deimhin, faoi go leor ábhar eile nach iad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Más féidir leis an réimeas Síneach a rialaíonn an tSín, agus is d’aon ghnó a úsáidim an focal réimeas, neamhshuim a dhéanamh den chuid eile den domhan, cén dóchas atá ag mionlaigh eitneacha amhail Críostaithe agus Búdaithe na Tibéide sa tír sin? Ní mór don Aontas Eorpach a chumhacht eacnamaíoch agus airgeadais a úsáid chun brú a chur ar an tSín. B’fhéidir go bhfuil gá le smachtbhannaí trádála. Nílim cinnte cad ba cheart a dhéanamh, ach is eol dom go bhfuil an méid atá ag tarlú do na hUigiúraigh mícheart ar bhonn morálta agus go bhfuil sé de dhualgas orainn gníomhú ina leith sin.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-109-0000" speaker_id="197788" name="Anna Bonfrisco" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la Cina ha aggiornato al 21° secolo gli strumenti per compiere un genocidio, usa la tecnologia biometrica e di sorveglianza per la pulizia etnica di milioni di uiguri alla velocità e con la precisione di un computer.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Partito comunista cinese agisce attraverso le macchine e pensa come le macchine. Nelle fabbriche sfrutta fino alla morte le minoranze, al motto di lavare i cervelli, pulire i cuori, sostenere il diritto, rimuovere ciò che è sbagliato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Colleghi, la schedatura del DNA, la scannerizzazione del viso, la registrazione di impronte e voci, le sterilizzazioni, il lavaggio del cervello – e c'è di peggio – di 82 aziende globali coinvolte nel silenzio generale, molte sono europee. Il 20 % del cotone mondiale arriva dal lavoro forzato degli uiguri. Gli Stati Uniti hanno sanzionato 24 aziende cinesi specializzate nell'intelligenza artificiale e nel controllo facciale e noi invece cosa abbiamo fatto?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-110-0000" speaker_id="96740" name="Yannick Jadot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">(début de l’intervention hors micro) … les crimes contre l’humanité, le génocide culturel, les camps de concentration, la stérilisation forcée, le travail forcé dans plein de secteurs économiques, dont le coton. Alors, oui, la Cour pénale internationale. Oui, les sanctions contre les dirigeants chinois impliqués. Bien sûr, l’embargo contre toutes les entreprises et les produits issus du Xinjiang. Mais à quelques centaines de mètres du Parlement européen, à Bruxelles, nous avons en ce moment une négociation sur un accord d’investissement avec la Chine, comme si toute cette réalité dramatique, comme si toutes les valeurs de l’Union européenne ne pesaient rien par rapport au business, par rapport aux investissements chinois dans notre économie comme aux investissements européens en Chine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Au nom des valeurs de l’Europe, au nom de la lutte contre ces génocides, au nom des valeurs de la démocratie, au nom des libertés fondamentales, j’appelle les dirigeants européens, j’appelle Emmanuel Macron pour la France, à suspendre toute négociation avec la Chine tant que l’absolue violence, tant que la répression, tant que les camps perdureront au Xinjiang comme dans les autres régions où les minorités sont maltraitées, réprimées, torturées. Alors, Emmanuel Macron comme l’ensemble des dirigeants européens, cessez le massacre, cessez les négociations avec la Chine tant que les libertés fondamentales ne s’y dérouleront pas convenablement.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-111-0000" speaker_id="197935" name="Ivan Vilibor Sinčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, ljudska prava i Kina su kao hrvatsko pravosuđe i pravda.</p>
      <p sl="en">U Kini se sistematski progone etničke, političke i vjerske manjine. Osim prisilnog rada, zatvaranja u koncentracijske logore, mučenja, možda je najgore prisilno vađenje organa, ponekad i na živo. Jedna od skupina, odnosno manjina, koji su najviše izloženi prisilnom vađenju organa je Falun Dafa ili Falun Gong zato što su u pravilu to vrlo zdravi ljudi, i psihički i fizički. A progon traje od 1999. godine kada su pali u nemilost Komunističke partije Kine. Zašto se to radi? Da se eliminira politički neprijatelj, da se zaradi na trgovini i da se pruži potpora zdravstvenom sustavu Kine. Podaci pokazuju da dvije trećine svih transplantacijskih turista ide u Kinu da bi dobili organ. Na organe se u Kini čeka tjednima ili čak danima dok se u Europi radi o godinama. Pokazalo se da Komunisitička partija Kine ne samo da zna za ovo nego da ima direktne koristi od svega. Postoji čak i popis europskih institucija i američkih odnosno firmi koje su vezane uz ovo i zarađuju na ovome. A sve će se to nastaviti zato što se Europa nažalost boji kineske ekonomske moći.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-112-0000" speaker_id="197650" name="Isabel Santos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, alguém nesta sala, tenho a certeza, que entre os componentes do seu vestuário não se encontra algodão produzido pelo trabalho forçado dos prisioneiros uigures nos cinicamente denominados “campos de reeducação” de Xinjiang? Qual é a sensação? Desconforto. Pois, só há uma forma de pôr termo a isto, adotar e aplicar o mecanismo de due diligence de modo a afastar das nossas cadeias de abastecimento produtos com origem em violações dos direitos humanos.</p>
      <p sl="en">A brutal repressão em Xinjiang contra as populações uigures e cazaque é ultrajante e não pode ficar impune. O regime global de sanções contra violações dos direitos humanos deve ser aplicado às autoridades chinesas implicadas na perseguição étnica, religiosa e política em Xinjiang, mas também no Tibete.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ontem foi dia de Prémio Sakharov, hoje é dia de lembrarmos que Islam Toti continua detido sem contacto com a sua família e sem o seu advogado, mas eu também não posso deixar aqui de relembrar o caso de Tsz Lun Kok, cidadão de Hong Kong, com dupla nacionalidade portuguesa, ou seja, cidadão europeu, detido desde agosto incommunicado na China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-113-0000" speaker_id="197868" name="Samira Rafaela (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Chinese Government is forcing hundreds of thousands of Uyghurs from Xinjiang to do forced labour. Chinese officials go door to door and select people for the cotton harvest. At least 570 000 people have had to undergo forced training before being sent into the cotton fields hundreds of miles away from home.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eighty-five percent of all Chinese cotton comes from Xinjiang, and this is a fifth of the world’s cotton supply. A majority of Chinese cotton ends up on the Asian market, where many clothes are made that are sold right here in the European Union. And that’s not all: new investigations confirm that medical masks and protective equipment made by Uyghurs are sold in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">This is unacceptable, just like the detention camps in which more than a million Uyghurs are detained. We must be able to make companies aware of their responsibility, and they must intervene when their production chain is not transparent. I urge the Commission to speed up the introduction of due diligence legislation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-114-0000" speaker_id="197478" name="Lars Patrick Berg" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, Frau Kommissarin! Selbstverständlich verurteile ich Zwangsarbeit, und ich verurteile Kinderarbeit. Es besteht kein Zweifel daran, dass die uigurische Minderheit Diskriminierung durch die chinesische Regierung ausgesetzt ist. Und aus meiner Sicht ist es offenkundig, dass sich die chinesischen Behörden gravierender Menschenrechtsverletzungen schuldig machen. Ich plädiere nicht dafür, über Zwangsarbeit oder andere Formen der Diskriminierung von Uiguren hinwegzusehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mehr Transparenz seitens der chinesischen Regierung über die inneren Bedrohungen, mit denen das Land konfrontiert ist, eine sofortige Abkehr von Zwangs- und Kinderarbeit und Umerziehungslagern und eine Differenzierung zwischen den überwiegend friedlichen Mitgliedern der uigurischen Minderheit und jenen wenigen, die sich dem Extremismus angeschlossen haben, könnten dazu beitragen, mehr Stabilität in die Region zu bringen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-115-0000" speaker_id="197457" name="Henrike Hahn" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! In China werden Uiguren, muslimische Minderheiten und Tibetaner dramatisch unterdrückt, und das ist bekannt. Hunderttausende Uiguren werden zwangsweise bei der Baumwollernte eingesetzt, und diese Baumwolle landet auch auf den Ladentischen in Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die EU und die nationalen Regierungen müssen diese Menschenrechtsverletzungen klar benennen, und Unternehmen, die in China produzieren, müssen ihre Lieferketten prüfen und neu ausrichten – da kommen sie nicht umhin. Apple, Nike, Adidas, Samsung, VW und BMW – diese Namen müssen für Verantwortung stehen. Wir haben in Europa etwas dagegen, wenn Huawei eine Gesichtserkennungssoftware entwirft, die die ethnische Zugehörigkeit von Minderheiten erkennt. Wir wollen in Europa mit Unternehmen, die aktiv Regime stützen, die massive Menschenrechtsverletzungen begehen, keine Geschäfte machen. Das ist nicht nur eine Sicherheitsfrage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die EU verhandelt jetzt mit China beim Investitionsschutzabkommen über faire Wettbewerbschancen und über besseren Marktzugang. Wir erwarten jetzt von der deutschen EU-Ratspräsidentschaft, dass sie das klar ausbuchstabiert. Wir wollen in Europa keine Produkte aus chinesischer Zwangsarbeit. China muss die zentralen ILO-Kernnormen ratifizieren, und Menschenrechte sind nicht verhandelbar!</p>
      <p sl="en">In keiner anderen Stadt in Europa leben so viele Uiguren wie in München – da, wo ich herkomme. Liebe Mehriban, das Schicksal und Wohlergehen der Uiguren kann uns nicht egal sein in Europa!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-116-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the European Union has spoken out clearly and repeatedly on the situation of Uyghurs, expressing grave concerns about political re-education camps, surveillance and restrictions on freedom of religion and belief. As HR/VP Borrell mentioned during the debate on the situation of the Uyghurs one year ago, the policies applied to Xinjiang appear disproportionate to the stated aim of fighting against terrorism and extremism.</p>
      <p sl="en">The conclusions of United Nations experts expressing serious concerns are, regretfully, still valid. During the past year, a number of reports have brought to light worrying allegations that Uyghurs and other minorities in China are subject to forced labour and forced labour transfer schemes, as well as forced sterilisation and forced birth control. They add to the gravity and magnitude of concerns we have already expressed.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU leaders raised these concerns in their meetings with Chinese leaders this year, at the EU-China Summit on 22 June and at the EU-China leaders’ meeting on 14 September. We also issued a comprehensive statement during the last UN Human Rights Council under item 4: debate on human rights situations that require the Council’s attention. We clearly highlighted the need for meaningful access to the region for independent experts. We will continue to call on China to uphold its national and international obligations and to respect human rights, including the rights of persons belonging to minorities, especially in Xinjiang and Tibet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Defending human rights and combating forced labour are priorities for the EU. As a key trading partner of the EU, China should ensure that business activities in its territory meet international standards on labour rights and responsible business conduct. We expect the Chinese authorities to implement those standards across all sectors of production and at all levels of supply chains. Responsible business practices by European companies working in China play a very important role.</p>
      <p sl="en">While the Commission is working on a legislative proposal on sustainable corporate governance, the EU already has mandatory standards in some sectors and actively promotes international guidelines. European companies are already encouraged to implement effective due diligence practices across their supply chains. The Commission and the European External Action Service will continue working with companies to underscore the importance of taking up international due diligence guidelines in all aspects, including human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">The new EU global human rights sanctions regime, adopted on 7 December, enables the EU to forcefully stand up for human rights. It allows the EU to target human rights violations and abuses worldwide, irrespective of where they occur. The regime does not contain any listings yet. However, we expect discussions on listings to start soon.</p>
      <p sl="en">I thank you all for your engagement in this debate and your contributions to further increase the awareness on this matter.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-117-0000" speaker_id="197525" name="Przewodnicząca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się dzisiaj.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem11" title="8.3. Iran, in particular the case of 2012 Sakharov Prize laureate Nasrin Sotoudeh">
    <intervention id="4-119-0000" speaker_id="197525" name="Przewodnicząca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Kolejnym punktem porządku dziennego jest debata nad siedmioma projektami rezolucji w sprawie Iranu, w szczególności przypadku laureatki Nagrody im. Sacharowa w 2012 r. Nasrin Sotoudeh (2020/2914(RSP))*.</p>
      <p sl="en">_______________</p>
      <p sl="en">* Patrz protokół posiedzenia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-120-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">auteur. – Madame la Présidente, le cas de Nasrin Sotoudeh souligne l’extrême précarité de la condition féminine dans tant de pays de par le monde, où la charia est élevée au rang de loi.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, le scandale de cette avocate condamnée à 38 ans de prison, notamment pour s’être montrée sans hijab, n’est pas spécifique à l’Iran. En témoigne le procès, cette semaine, devant un tribunal spécial contre le terrorisme, de l’activiste féministe saoudienne Loujain Al-Hathloul après deux ans d’une détention ponctuée, selon ses proches, de mauvais traitements et d’humiliations. Ce scandale n’aura toutefois pas empêché l’Arabie saoudite d’accueillir le mois dernier le sommet virtuel du G20, illustrant le double discours permanent des puissances occidentales en matière de droits fondamentaux et de cause féminine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si le débat de ce jour a un seul mérite, c’est de rappeler qu’à l’heure où l’on accable d’un mauvais procès en islamophobie quiconque rejette certaines pratiques d’un autre âge, les libertés les plus élémentaires des femmes ne relèvent, hélas, pas partout de l’évidence.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-121-0000" speaker_id="197571" name="Nikolaj Villumsen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">stiller. – Fru formand! I dag sender vi et klart budskab fra EU-Parlamentet: Stop undertrykkelsen i Iran! Det iranske præstestyre undertrykker groft den iranske befolkning og har sendt tusinder af politiske modstandere i fængsel eller i døden med henrettelser. Det er fuldstændig uacceptabelt. Men vi sender også vores solidaritet til den modige befolkning i Iran, som trodser undertrykkelsen i deres kamp for demokrati og retfærdighed. De modige iranske kvinder har brug for vores støtte, når de trodser de formørkede mullaher i kampen for retten til at bestemme over deres egen krop. Derfor siger vi: Løslad Nasrin Sotoudeh, løslad de politiske fanger, straf de ansvarlige for menneskerettighedskrænkelserne mod den iranske befolkning.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-122-0000" speaker_id="197464" name="Hannah Neumann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Nasrin Sotoudeh is a human rights lawyer. This means that she uses the laws of her country, Iran, to defend her clients, the people of Iran, against a regime that does not feel bound by any of these laws. The more Nasrin uses these laws, the more absurd become the charges of that regime. The latest one: 33 years and 148 lashes for defending women that took off their hijabs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nasrin has now been 10 years in and out of prison in one of the countries with the cruellest prison conditions, amidst the raging COVID pandemic. Nasrin Sotoudeh really pays a high price for her love of the law and of the people of Iran. I’m full of admiration for this unbreakable woman and I think she rightfully deserved the Sakharov Prize from this Parliament.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you all know, Nasrin is not the only one. The regime’s repression got a lot crueller recently, with arrests and executions. Ruhollah Zam was executed last week, while Ahmadreza Djalali is threatened with execution, and no justice has been done for the thousands of protesters in the streets of Iran last year.</p>
      <p sl="en">That is why I think it’s so important that we send two clear signals today. One signal to the regime that if they continue like this they will be even more isolated and subject to targeted sanctions. And one signal to the brave Iranians, the vibrant and diverse civil society. You have our full solidarity, our full attention, our full support, as long as this is needed. Because, just like Nasrin, I hope that one day all the prisons of Iran will be turned into museums and parks.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-123-0000" speaker_id="124991" name="Jytte Guteland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">författare. – Fru talman! Fru kommissionär! Läget vad gäller de mänskliga rättigheterna i Iran är mycket allvarligt. Sacharovpristagaren Nasrin Sotoudeh – advokat, förkämpe för mänskliga rättigheter, barns försvarare, kvinnors försvarare, journalisters försvarare – denna modiga kvinna som under 15 års tid har vigt sitt yrkesliv åt att hjälpa människor får straffet att bli fängslad. Nu behöver hon, som har givit röst åt så många andra, vår röst. Vi behöver visa att vi står på hennes sida, och att vi kräver ett omedelbart frisläppande.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi kräver också att Iran slutar upp med de attacker som sker mot iranier med dubbelt medborgarskap. Vi ser just nu forskare, journalister, miljöaktivister fängslade. En av dem som vi ömmar väldigt mycket för och som vi lyfter fram särskilt är doktor Ahmadreza Djalali. Hans familj lider, han lider, han står inför ett förmodat dödsstraff. Vi kräver att han frisläpps, och vi vill se att kommissionen agerar till stöd för hans fall.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-124-0000" speaker_id="130100" name="Hilde Vautmans" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, ever since I heard the horrible news that the execution of Djalali was a matter of hours or days away, I have thought: what more can I do? I wrote letters, I spoke to the ambassador, but nevertheless. Now we finally have this resolution, and it sends a strong message to Iran. We have the new Magnitsky Act and we will use it if Djalali is not freed.</p>
      <p sl="en">I’d like to convey a message from Djalali’s wife, with whom I spoke yesterday. She says: ‘Ahmadreza is nothing but an innocent scientist and father of two children. He worked to improve the lives of others through his research. If he is executed, nothing can bring him back. So please, put all your efforts in and make sure he’s freed before it’s too late.’ Colleagues, let us vote in favour of this strong resolution and make sure it’s not too late.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-125-0000" speaker_id="123562" name="Charlie Weimers" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="author">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the Swedish citizen Ahmadreza Djalali faces imminent execution in the Islamic Republic of Iran for refusing to spy on European institutions on behalf of the mullahs. On behalf of conservatives, I demanded sanctions against Iranian authorities. I thank the lead negotiator, MEP Lega, for his leadership.</p>
      <p sl="en">Swedes should note that a new conservative government in Sweden would bring hope for a less appeasing foreign policy. That shift is desperately needed. As my other Swedish colleague, MEP Guteland, exerted her and the Social Democrats’ influence to water down the text, MEP Guteland, I want you one day, as me, to clearly say that ‘I support the aspirations of the Iranian people who want to live in a free, stable, inclusive and democratic country.’ Please say it out loud. The Iranian people need it.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-126-0000" speaker_id="197421" name="Isabel Wiseler-Lima" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">auteure. – Madame la Présidente, Nasrin Sotoudeh est de retour en prison. Son crime? Avoir défendu, en tant qu’avocate, le droit des femmes, des enfants, des minorités religieuses, des journalistes, des artistes devant les tribunaux iraniens. Les autorités iraniennes l’ont condamnée à 33 ans de prison et à 148 coups de fouet pour cette raison. Nous, Parlement européen, lui avons décerné le prix Sakharov 2012 pour ses combats.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nasrin est une femme particulièrement courageuse et qui mérite que nous la soutenions, comme elle a soutenu ceux qui avaient besoin d’elle. Elle l’a fait au prix de sa liberté. Nous continuerons à la soutenir tant que les autorités iraniennes ne l’auront pas libérée.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nasrin Sotoudeh s’est toujours engagée pour que la peine de mort ne soit pas prononcée, pour qu’elle ne soit pas mise en œuvre. Il y a à peine cinq jours, le journaliste Rouhollah Zam a été exécuté par pendaison. La décision de la Cour suprême iranienne avait été prise seulement quatre jours plus tôt, sur la base de charges douteuses et d’aveux extorqués de force. Rouhollah Zam avait obtenu l’asile politique en France et a été kidnappé sur le territoire iraquien pour être amené en Iran. L’exécution de Rouhollah Zam est une violation flagrante du droit international et des droits de l’homme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a aussi Ahmadreza Djalali, ce médecin irano-suédois, professeur d’université à Bruxelles et en Italie. Soumis à des menaces de mort à l’encontre de lui-même et de sa famille en Suède et en Iran, il a été accusé d’espionnage. Des confessions ont été extorquées sous la torture et il a été condamné à mort. Il attend son exécution imminente. Nous demandons l’intervention urgente de l’Union européenne et des États membres auprès des autorités iraniennes afin de libérer Ahmadreza Djalali.</p>
      <p sl="en">J’ai nommé trois personnes, l’une emprisonnée, une autre exécutée, une autre dans le couloir de la mort. Pour ces trois-ci et pour beaucoup d’autres encore nommées dans notre résolution, combien d’anonymes, arrêtés par les autorités iraniennes pour avoir exprimé leur pensée, pour avoir défendu la liberté de pensée, pour avoir refusé de se soumettre, pour avoir simplement protégé une autre personne qui ne voulait pas entrer dans le moule imposé?</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous condamnons dans les termes les plus forts les atteintes aux droits de l’homme en Iran, les détentions arbitraires à la suite de manifestations pacifiques, les détentions de journalistes, de défenseurs des droits de l’homme. Nous demandons à ce que l’Iran respecte les droits des prisonniers, le droit à un procès équitable, le droit à choisir son avocat. Nous demandons la mise en œuvre du Pacte international relatif aux droits civils et politiques, pacte auquel l’Iran est partie. Nous demandons simplement que l’Iran respecte les droits humains, la dignité humaine inhérente à tous les êtres humains, égale pour tous les hommes et toutes les femmes.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Union européenne doit œuvrer pour mettre en œuvre tous les moyens dont elle dispose pour convaincre et amener les autorités iraniennes à changer de pratiques.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-127-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in October the High Commissioner asked us to take a holistic approach to Iran. This was particularly so in relation to preserving the nuclear agreement, which I agree with, and the result, of course, was a triumph for European diplomacy. The other side of the coin is the human rights record in Iran, which is not pretty – particularly the case of the 2012 Sakharov Prize winner Nasrin Sotoudeh. We have a duty to follow all laureates of this prize and to speak out when they are being persecuted. We did this in the case of Nasrin in 2018, and it is deeply regrettable that we must return to renew our call on the Iranian authorities to release her from her arbitrary detention.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today we call for the unconditional release of Nasrin Sotoudeh with renewed urgency. The people of Iran are struggling to battle the COVID—19 pandemic; prisoners – not just in Iran but around the world – are at an increased risk of infection. Nasrin unfortunately contracted the virus recently while she was granted temporary release. She was ordered to return to prison again against the advice of medical experts. Shameful – because this has the potential to be a fatal decision.</p>
      <p sl="en">I’m also dismayed by the continuously high use of capital punishment in Iran. This is not acceptable under any circumstances. Certainly a journalist should not be executed for expressing their views, and laureates should not be tortured and imprisoned for peacefully working to preserve human rights. I call on Iran to call a halt to this practice immediately.</p>
      <p sl="en">While we focus on the case of Nasrin, we must also think of all the other peaceful campaigners and activists, some of whom worked with her and who are facing a similar plight in Iran.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tá súil agam go n-éireoidh linn Nasrin, agus daoine nach í, a shaoradh agus a thabhairt ar ais dá dteaghlach roimh Nollaig.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-129-0000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Madame la Présidente, hier, nous remettions le prix Sakharov au mouvement pour la démocratie en Biélorussie. Nasrin Sotoudeh est notre prix Sakharov depuis 2012 et, depuis 2012, Nasrin Sotoudeh est en prison.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nasrin Sotoudeh – j’avais pris une photo que je ne peux pas vous montrer –, c’est une femme souriante, une femme forte. Nous avons eu l’occasion, pendant les deux semaines de répit que lui a octroyées la République islamique iranienne, de l’avoir dans la sous-commission DROI de ce Parlement. C’est toujours une femme forte, une femme souriante, mais c’est une femme terriblement affaiblie par le COVID et par l’emprisonnement qu’elle est en train de subir.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nasrin Sotoudeh, on l’a dit, a défendu les droits des femmes, les droits des hommes, le droit à la justice dans ce pays. Nous exigeons que tout dialogue avec l’Iran ait pour prérequis la libération de Nasrin Sotoudeh. Je pense à son mari et à ses enfants. Courage.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-130-0000" speaker_id="4253" name="Frédérique Ries" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Renew. – Madame la Présidente, Madame la Commissaire, c’est une année particulière qui s’achève. 2020 s’efface et tout a changé.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout a changé – ou presque. À Téhéran, c’est business as usual: répressions et exécutions qui s’enchaînent inexorablement. Nous écrivions, en début de semaine, cette résolution sur Nasrin Sotoudeh, notre prix Sakharov 2012, quand nous avons appris lundi la condamnation d’une jeune femme à dix années de prison pour avoir posté sur Instagram un selfie controversé aux traits d’Angelina Jolie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deux jours plus tôt, deux crans plus haut dans la barbarie, les mollahs faisaient exécuter Rouhollah Zam, en vitesse, après un simulacre de procès. Le journaliste était coupable de dire la vérité. Le journaliste était coupable de débusquer les corruptions. Pour Téhéran, toujours business as usual et pas de raison de s’inquiéter que cela ait des conséquences sur les relations avec l’Union européenne. Et pourtant, le jour même, l’Union européenne annulait un forum économique Europe-Iran.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est ce que nous devons faire très clairement: retirer nos investissements, sanctionner économiquement, cibler les responsables. Il n’est pas trop tard pour libérer Nasrin Sotoudeh. Il n’est pas trop tard non plus pour le professeur Ahmadreza Djalali, qui attend son exécution en prison. 2020 s’efface, il faut que cela change.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-131-0000" speaker_id="35016" name="Marco Campomenosi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ID. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissione europea, il testo che affrontiamo oggi è assolutamente condiviso da tutti. Non è la prima volta che ci troviamo a redigere e votare risoluzioni contro regimi sanguinari, contro chi reprime la libertà di giornalisti, avvocati, uomini e donne che si battono per la libertà.</p>
      <p sl="en">E io mi domando e vi domando, riflettiamo insieme se noi avremmo avuto il coraggio di questi uomini e di queste donne. Io vengo da una famiglia che ha combattuto il fascismo e mi immedesimo in chi combatte e ha combattuto in passato per la libertà. Oggi l'attualità è talmente rapida che avevamo già stabilito di lavorare sul caso di Nasrin Sotoudeh – che ovviamente speriamo sia presto liberata – ma dobbiamo affrontare anche la vicenda di Ruhollah Zam, il giornalista che è stato ucciso, la vicenda del dottor Djalali che attende una condanna a morte, che speriamo non avvenga.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il caso di Nasrin Sotoudeh somiglia molto a quello di Nasibe Semsai, una donna arrestata in Turchia poche settimane fa, o di Fariba Adelkhah. Donne e uomini che hanno un coraggio che spesso manca anche a noi. Quindi, domandiamoci anche questo, anche per non rendere inutile un dibattito e una risoluzione che spero siano importanti e magari aiutarci – ne parlavamo con l'Alto rappresentante, qualche settimana fa – per capire cosa fare di questo accordo sul nucleare, cosa fare delle relazioni con gli Stati Uniti, che a mio avviso, non cambieranno tantissimo nella loro opposizione al regime iraniano, perché se il fronte occidentale è diviso, rischiamo di non essere efficaci nella lotta contro un regime che va combattuto e possibilmente abbattuto.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-132-0000" speaker_id="197831" name="Hermann Tertsch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ECR. – Señor presidente, hoy vamos a exigir aquí la libertad del premio Sájarov de 2012, la abogada Nasrín Sotudé, presa en su patria, en Irán, pero sobre todo vamos a denunciar la conducta del régimen que tortura a los iraníes, invade la región, promueve el terrorismo, proclama querer exterminar a los judíos, como Hitler, y amenaza con su programa nuclear la paz en todo el mundo. Y penetra y sabotea las democracias en Iberoamérica y aquí en Europa, en España, financiando a un partido del Gobierno, a Podemos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Denuncio también aquí la condescendencia europea con ese régimen asesino. En diciembre pasado, el régimen asesinó en sus calles a 1 500 jóvenes que pedían libertad. Dos meses más tarde, el señor Borrell, en Teherán, daba la mano sonriente a la cúpula de los verdugos, en busca del negocio europeo. Y, en esta Cámara, yo creo que la mayoría estuvo en su día a favor de levantar el embargo y volver corriendo a Irán a hacer negocios, mientras se insultaba a Trump por mantener el bloqueo a ese régimen criminal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso, lo contrario de lo que se hace es lo correcto. Vayamos a un cerco real del régimen, a un frente de firmeza con los Estados Unidos, para que Irán sepa que tiene que dejar de hacer lo que hace.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-133-0000" speaker_id="197817" name="Mick Wallace" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the GUE/NGL Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, these urgencies are the epitome of what you like to call disinformation.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the US— and NATO—funded reports that are the basis for the Uyghur resolution, there’s not one named person interviewed who says that there is forced labour in Xinjiang, not to mention the completely fraudulent report by the American National Endowment for Democracy—funded Chinese Human Rights Defenders, which claimed there was a million Uyghurs in detention.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s just a weapon against China – the same with Iran. This is the fourth human rights—centred attack on Iran in just over a year. I’ll take these things seriously when we stop doing them selectively.</p>
      <p sl="en">Where are the four resolutions addressing the European and US—supported genocide in Yemen? America is separating children from their mothers, and keeping them in cages by the thousands and has over two million mostly coloured people in prison carrying out forced labour. France is passing anti—Muslim legislation and still behaving like a colonialist in the Sahel, while Israel shoots children in Palestine. But that’s all okay.</p>
      <p sl="en">When we stop weaponising human rights in this place, we might have a bit more credibility.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-134-0000" speaker_id="197548" name="Radosław Sikorski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Iran claims to be an Islamic republic. Yet, as this resolution makes clear, it is also one of the world’s most repressive regimes. I therefore have a question for the mullahs in Tehran.</p>
      <p sl="en">If you represent a God that is good, powerful and merciful, then why do you need to repress, torture and murder your people to this extent? No. Your regime is blasphemous and an abomination to every decent Muslim, every person of faith and every person of conscience. You have brought your country to such desperate straits that you are now signing agreements with China to give away your energy sector and your critical infrastructure. They will not complain about your human rights abuses, but I’m not sure Allah will be pleased that you are becoming vessels to a godless Communist regime. However, if you want better relations and the easing of sanctions with us, stop this repression now! What you’re doing to your own people is inhumane.</p>
      <p sl="en">And one last thing. I have a request to the diplomats from our nation states and from our European External Action Service. Next time you meet with Mr Zarif, who is a smiling Ribbentrop, just remember what kind of nasty regime he represents.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-135-0000" speaker_id="197392" name="Evin Incir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, dear friends, human rights is the radical notion that all people are born equal and that we will never compromise on neither civil rights nor social rights. It is radical because we still see oppression in way too many countries. Yes, it is a paradox because, on the one hand, humanity is able to fly to the moon and back, but, at the same time, some people do not know how to respect all peoples, freedom and dignity.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the current worst oppressing regime is the Iranian one, but we will never be silent. Ahmadreza Djalali and Nasrin Sotoudeh, and other human rights defenders’ struggle for human rights, democracy and the rule of law, will continue being at the centre of everything we do.</p>
      <p sl="en">To the Iranian regime, my message is very clear: we will continue to be vocal. We will continue to demand the release of all prisoners of conscience, the abolishment of the death penalty, and the time for an end to impunity will also come in your case. If history has taught us something, it is that dictators and oppressive regimes always fall – but the people always prevail.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-136-0000" speaker_id="124766" name="Petras Auštrevičius (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, it is already the third resolution of this Parliament addressing the gross human rights violations in Iran. There is no change or improvement in the situation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The mullahs’ regime continues the fight against its own society and remains the main threat to the Iranian people.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today we mourn Iranian journalist Ruhollah Zam, who was executed on Saturday. We worry that the Iranian-Swedish academic Ahmadreza Djalali might be the next, and express concerns over the deteriorating health of imprisoned Sakharov Prize laureate Nasrin Sotoudeh.</p>
      <p sl="en">We deplore the oppressive actions of the Iranian regime, which is nothing more but weak in its incapacity to face critical political competition and embrace differences in opinion of people.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have to insist on a full and impartial UN—led investigation of the 1988 massacre of thousands of political prisoners in Iran and secure accountability by prosecuting perpetrators.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-137-0000" speaker_id="197788" name="Anna Bonfrisco" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, dedico oggi le mie parole alla signora Nasrin Sotoudeh.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gli ayatollah alla guida della Repubblica islamica dell'Iran discreditano, offendono persino l'Islam. Nei loro documenti scrivono nel nome di Dio, il più compassionevole e il più misericordioso, ma la loro maligna e destabilizzante azione quotidiana si basa solo sull'oppressione. Sono uomini carichi di ira, sprezzanti della dignità umana e della ricchezza che viene dalla diversità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Come Unione europea dobbiamo ammettere che è stato miope e anche un po' naif pensare di limitare l'accordo P5+1 alla sola questione nucleare, avremmo dovuto inserire anche la libertà di pensiero e i diritti umani. Noi pensiamo che governare uno Stato moderno con la religione sia da insani mentali. Non integrare la dignità umana nella propria azione di governo è da assassini e noi dobbiamo combattere gli assassini e stare dalla parte del popolo di Israele.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-138-0000" speaker_id="23788" name="Adam Bielan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, fundamental rights such as freedom of expression and assembly must always be respected. I strongly condemn the steadily deteriorating human rights situation in Iran, including for persons belonging to ethnic and religious minorities suffering from systematic political and social discrimination. We deplore Iran’s abuse of the criminal justice system to repress peaceful activities that promote and defend human rights. I call on the Iranian authorities to live up to their international obligations.</p>
      <p sl="en">In this context I welcome the adoption of the Magnitsky Act by the Council as an important EU instrument to sanction violators of human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">While maintaining the joint comprehensive plan of action and EU-Iran high-level political dialogue, the EU, and especially the High Representative, should continue raising human rights concerns with the Iranian authorities in bilateral and multilateral fora.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-139-0000" speaker_id="185341" name="Željana Zovko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, yesterday we gave the Sakharov Prize to a woman, and to all those women who are opposing an authoritarian regime.</p>
      <p sl="en">I grew up in a communist regime and remember when I had the right to vote for the first time. Now I’m standing here in the Parliament, as a woman, as a Member of Parliament, looking at you, as a Commissioner, a woman, and the President, who is a woman, and all these women who are fighting for the freedom of somebody when we still don’t know whether she is alive or dead or if she’s ill. She was the winner of our Sakharov Prize in 2012 and we are still negotiating and we are still talking to the regime that is holding this woman, scared, alone, forgotten by all of us.</p>
      <p sl="en">I feel ashamed. I feel ashamed as a woman and I feel ashamed as somebody who is looking at all of you, divided by ideology: Who are we going to judge and condemn? Which regime, and who, are we going to talk to? There is no negotiation with the people who are holding women in prison. As women, they have the courage to defend and to defend against all those who are oppressing people, who are oppressing minorities and who are oppressing all those who have different beliefs to their beliefs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Please let us fight for this woman. Let us fight for this man who is was waiting for his death sentence. Let’s use our instruments. Maybe we don’t have heavy weapons, but we have a new act that puts sanctions on all these regimes. Let’s use them in a proper way without discrimination and without division. Let’s use them and let’s make everybody not lose hope.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-140-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Nicola Beer (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Wie viele Menschen noch müssen ihr Leben verlieren? Das war mein erster Gedanke, als ich von der Hinrichtung von Ruhollah Zam hörte. Mein zweiter? Das Regime der Mullahs kennt offenbar auf zunehmende Kritik und Druck aus der Bevölkerung keine andere Antwort als brutale Gewalt. Deswegen war es ein wichtiges Zeichen der betreffenden Mitgliedstaaten und von Josep Borrell, ihre Teilnahme am EU-Iran Business Forum am Montag abzusagen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Doch ich vermisse deutliche Worte – vor allem Taten. So wurde vom EEAS mit keiner Silbe erwähnt, dass es sich bei der Hinrichtung um einen politischen Gefangenen handelte, dessen Hinrichtung die Meinungsfreiheit, Pressefreiheit, unsere europäischen Werte und die Menschenrechte mit Füßen tritt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Herr Borrell, werte Vertreter der Mitgliedstaaten, wir müssen verhindern, dass weitere politische Gefangene hingerichtet werden. Legen Sie beim nächsten Austausch mit dem Regime Ihren Finger in die Wunde, sprechen Sie an, was gegen die Menschenrechte verstößt. Sprechen Sie direkt mit der demokratischen Opposition. Lassen Sie uns Vorbilder wie Nasrin Sotudeh oder die vierzehn Frauen, die Chameneis Rücktritt forderten, in ihrer Opposition zu dem Regime direkt unterstützen. Denn für eine friedliche Zukunft und ein Kräftegleichgewicht im Nahen Osten brauchen wir einen demokratischen Iran, der Menschenrechte verteidigt und nicht mit Füßen tritt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb hoffe ich, dass wir im nächsten Jahr guten Grund haben, die iranische Opposition zum Sacharow-Preis auch entsprechend vorzuschlagen und ihr den Preis zu verleihen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-141-0000" speaker_id="197582" name="Gianna Gancia" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissione, Nasrin Sotoudeh, Ahmad Reza Jalali: i loro nomi sono un monito per noi europei. La loro vita è appesa a un filo e ogni giorno può essere l'ultimo, così come può esserlo per migliaia di oppositori politici e membri dell'opinione pubblica detenuti nelle carceri iraniane.</p>
      <p sl="en">Noi dobbiamo dare voce anche a quelli che la voce non ce l'hanno più: 30 000 prigionieri politici massacrati nel 1988, 1 500 dimostranti assassinati nel novembre 2019. Tutto questo non può lasciarci indifferenti: il regime degli ayatollah continua a rifiutare di applicare le sessantasette risoluzioni delle Nazioni Unite sui diritti umani nel paese. Non è accettabile. Teheran continua a negare le evidenze, a disattendere gli impegni presi, a violare i trattati internazionali, non solo in materia di diritti umani.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'Unione europea deve spingersi oltre il regime delle sanzioni, mettendo in campo ogni mezzo diplomatico affinché venga istituita una commissione d'inchiesta internazionale sul massacro del 1988 e si ponga fine a questo incredibile terrorismo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-142-0000" speaker_id="197516" name="Patryk Jaki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Po pierwsze to bardzo dobry zwyczaj, że monitorujemy to, co dzieje się z osobami, którym Parlament Europejski przyznał Nagrodę im. Sacharowa. Jest to również pozytywne w kontekście laureata z tego roku, czyli białoruskiej opozycji, która będzie jeszcze potrzebowała tego wsparcia, choć mam nadzieję, że jak najkrócej.</p>
      <p sl="en">A wracając do Iranu, rzeczywiście reżim posuwa się coraz dalej, dlatego trzeba poprzeć wszystkie starania instytucji europejskich w walce z tym reżimem, w walce o wolność słowa. Dotarły do nas fatalne wiadomości o wykonaniu kolejnej kary śmierci za przestrzeganie podstawowych wartości i zasad w Iranie. Dlatego apeluję do Wysokiego Przedstawiciela Unii, by zintensyfikować wszystkie działania, naciskać na irański reżim i bronić tych najważniejszych zasad i podstawowych wartości. Poza tym musimy oczywiście zrobić wszystko, aby Nasrin Sotoudeh jak najszybciej opuściła więzienie. To jest wielkie zadanie dla instytucji unijnych.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-143-0000" speaker_id="197401" name="Karin Karlsbro (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! Medborgaren Ahmadreza Djalali är läkare och forskare i katastrofmedicin. Han har suttit fängslad i Iran sedan 2016. År 2017 dömdes han till döden. Den 24 november i år ringde han till sin hustru, här i Sverige. Han lät henne förstå att detta förmodligen var deras allra sista samtal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ahmadreza Djalali är en av alla dem som fallit offer för det brutala ökade politiska förtrycket i Iran. Med denna resolution vill vi uttrycka vår avsky mot den iranska regimens övergrepp som riktas mot enskilda individer, mot kvinnor, mot män. Nu måste förföljelser av journalister och forskare och dem som bara utnyttjat sin yttrandefrihet få ett slut. De oskyldigt fängslade måste friges. Dödsstraffet måste avskaffas. Nu måste Ahmadreza Djalali få återvända hem till Sverige, till sin familj, till sin fru, till sina barn, där han hör hemma.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-144-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Nasrin Sotoudeh has been recently returned to prison and is facing clear health difficulties. Once again, we have asked that she be released and reunited with her family.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Union is closely following human rights developments in Iran, and we are acutely aware of the deterioration that has occurred over the past year. Iran’s execution of dissident Ruhollah Zam last Saturday is of course deeply worrying. As noted in the statement issued by the spokesperson for the High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, the European Union condemns this act in the strongest terms and recalls once again its irrevocable opposition to the use of capital punishment under any circumstances. Iran continues to execute more than 200 individuals every year. We believe that it is imperative for the Iranian authorities to uphold the due process rights of accused individuals and to cease the practice of using televised confessions to establish and promote their guilt.</p>
      <p sl="en">All individuals found to have been involved in serious human rights violations, including during the response to the November 2019 protests in Iran, should be held accountable. While we recognise that Iran continues to host hundreds of thousands of refugees, the human rights situation in Iran remains deeply concerning. The authorities’ repression of peaceful protest and other gatherings continues unabated. Such repression, the restriction of fundamental freedoms, and discrimination against religious and ethnic minorities are features of life for too many Iranian citizens. Iran also continues to hold a number of EU—Iranian dual nationals on doubtful grounds, following trials where the due process rights of the accused were not respected in full.</p>
      <p sl="en">This includes Ahmadreza Djalali – whose situation many Members of this House are following – who remains at risk of imminent execution and whose life we ask be spared.</p>
      <p sl="en">We regularly engage with the authorities to urge improvements in the human rights situation in Iran as part of our comprehensive policy towards Iran. This includes asking that the repression of human rights lawyers and defenders, peaceful protesters, ethnic and religious minorities cease, and that individuals detained as a result of their advocacy for universally recognised human rights be freed.</p>
      <p sl="en">Iran should uphold its domestic and international commitments on human rights, including the International Covenant of Civil and Political Rights, to which it is party. We have been vocal in this demand, including at international forums such as the United Nations Human Rights Council and through public statements whenever justified.</p>
      <p sl="en">As the EU, we will continue to call for the release of all arbitrarily detained EU-Iranian dual nationals and Iranian human rights defenders. We also call on Iran to ensure that no individual is detained arbitrarily, that those who are detained are not subject to any form of mistreatment. All detained individuals should also have timely access to a lawyer of their own and to adequate medical care. This is particularly relevant to the cases of the eight environmentalists who have been detained since January 2018. One of these individuals, Morad Tahbaz, continues to experience severe health problems.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are encouraged by the attention paid to these issues by individual Members of the European Parliament, and we will continue with our efforts to work together with you in order to promote access to fundamental human rights in Iran and across the world.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-145-0000" speaker_id="197525" name="Przewodnicząca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Zamykam debatę.</p>
      <p sl="en">Głosowanie odbędzie się dzisiaj.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oświadczenia pisemne (art. 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="4-145-5000" speaker_id="197578" name="Silvia Sardone" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">per iscritto. – L'incarcerazione dell'avvocatessa Nasrin Sotoudeh, è la dimostrazione più evidente ,del carattere dittatoriale e contro la libertà, della Repubblica islamica d'Iran. Ci chiediamo fino a quando l'Europa starà zitta, di fronte alle reiterate violazioni dei diritti umani, portate avanti dall'Iran. La Commissione non ha fatto nulla per l'immediato rilascio di Nasrin Sotoudeh e di tutti i prigionieri politici nelle carceri iraniane Inoltre, non dimentichiamolo, l'Iran non rispetta i diritti fondamentali delle donne ma li calpesta in nome della religione. Noi siamo fermamente dalla parte degli attivisti che lavorano per difendere i diritti e che gridano al mondo, l'urgenza di libertà per le donne e per tutti gli oppressi. L'Europa troppo spesso per buonismo e paura, non ha condannato apertamente il trattamento subito dalle donne in molti Paesi islamici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non è più accettabile questo silenzio!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem12" title="9. Announcement of voting results: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="10. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="11. Amendment of the agenda : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="12. Composition of committees and delegations : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="13. Second voting session">
    <intervention id="4-155-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Wir kommen nun zur zweiten Abstimmungsrunde des heutigen Tages.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Dossiers, über die wir nun abstimmen, sind wie gewohnt der Tagesordnung zu entnehmen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmungsrunde beginnt nun und ist bis 15.00 Uhr geöffnet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es kommt dasselbe Abstimmungsverfahren zur Anwendung wie in den vorangegangenen Abstimmungsrunden. Alle Abstimmungen erfolgen namentlich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die zweite Abstimmungsrunde für eröffnet. Sie können bis 15.00 Uhr abstimmen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Ergebnisse der zweiten Abstimmungsrunde werden um 16.30 Uhr bekannt gegeben.</p>
      <a text="(Die Sitzung wird um 13.47 Uhr unterbrochen)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="14. Resumption of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="15. Announcement of voting results: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem19" title="16. Explanations of vote: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem20" title="17. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem21" title="18. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem22" title="19. Petitions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem23" title="20. Modified referrals to committees (Rule 56): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="21. Associated committees (Rule 57): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="22. Decision to apply the joint committee procedure (Rule 58): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="23. Decision to draw up own-initiative reports: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem27" title="24. Consent Procedure (Rule 105): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem28" title="25. Agenda of the next sitting : see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="26. Closure of the sitting">
    <intervention id="4-171-0000" speaker_id="2323" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Sitzung wird morgen um 8.45 Uhr wieder aufgenommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Tagesordnung wurde veröffentlicht und ist auf der Website des Europäischen Parlaments verfügbar.</p>
      <a text="(Die Sitzung wird um 16.37 Uhr unterbrochen)"/>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
