<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20210913.EN" lang="en" date="2021-09-13" place="Strasbourg" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro ripresa la sessione del Parlamento europeo interrotta giovedì 8 luglio 2021.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting">
    <intervention id="1-006-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">(La seduta è aperta alle 17.04).</p>
      <p sl="en">Presidente. – Saluto le colleghe e i colleghi che sono in presenza e collegati dagli EPLO. Spero che sia stata una buona estate e una buona vacanza per tutti, anche se per tutti molte vicende hanno impegnato tutti i parlamentari con delle questioni che, come sappiamo, influiscono pesantemente su questo tempo.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Approval of the minutes of the previous sittings">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il processo verbale e i testi approvati delle sedute del 5, 6, 7 e 8 luglio sono stati distribuiti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi sono osservazioni?</p>
      <p sl="en">Non vi sono osservazioni e il processo verbale è approvato.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Request for waiver of immunity">
    <intervention id="1-010-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le autorità competenti della Grecia mi hanno trasmesso una richiesta di revoca dell'immunità parlamentare dell'onorevole Emmanouil Fragkos al fine di avviare procedimenti penali nei suoi confronti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Conformemente al regolamento tale richiesta è inoltrata alla commissione giuridica del Parlamento che è competente in materia.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Composition of political groups">
    <intervention id="1-012-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La deputata non iscritta onorevole Lucia Vuolo ha aderito al gruppo PPE a decorrere dal 10 settembre di quest'anno.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Composition of committees and delegations">
    <intervention id="1-014-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">I gruppi PPE, ID ed ECR mi hanno comunicato alcune decisioni di modifica relativamente alle nomine nelle commissioni e nelle delegazioni. Queste decisioni saranno incluse nel verbale della seduta odierna ed entreranno in vigore alla data del presente annuncio.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Council positions at first reading">
    <intervention id="1-016-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ho ricevuto dal Consiglio la sua posizione in prima lettura riguardante il regolamento del Parlamento europeo e del Consiglio che istituisce uno strumento di assistenza preadesione IPA III nonché i motivi che hanno indotto il Consiglio ad adottarla e le posizioni e i pareri della Commissione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il titolo completo sarà elencato nel verbale della presente seduta. Il periodo di tre mesi di cui dispone il Parlamento per pronunciarsi inizia a decorrere da domani, 14 settembre. La raccomandazione per la seconda lettura sarà inclusa all'ordine del giorno di questa tornata, fatta salva la sua adozione da parte della commissione AFET.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Negotiations ahead of Parliament's first reading (Rule 71)">
    <intervention id="1-018-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Le commissioni ITRE ed ECON hanno deciso di avviare negoziati interistituzionali a norma dell'articolo 71 del regolamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le relazioni, che costituiscono i mandati per tali negoziati, sono disponibili sul sito della plenaria e i loro titoli saranno pubblicati nel processo verbale della seduta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Un numero di deputati o uno o più gruppi politici pari almeno alla soglia media possono chiedere per iscritto, entro la mezzanotte di domani, martedì 14 settembre, di porre in votazione le decisioni sull'avvio dei negoziati.</p>
      <p sl="en">Qualora entro il termine suddetto non siano presentate richieste di votazione in Aula, le commissioni potranno iniziare i negoziati.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Calendar of part-sessions">
    <intervention id="1-020-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vorrei informare l'Aula che, durante la Conferenza dei presidenti del 9 settembre, ho deciso, insieme ai presidenti dei gruppi politici, che il 27 gennaio 2022 si terrà una tornata straordinaria per rendere omaggio alla memoria delle vittime dell'Olocausto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa tornata sarà organizzata come ogni anno in occasione della Giornata internazionale della memoria delle vittime della Shoah. Il calendario provvisorio riveduto per il 2022 sarà disponibile sulla pagina web della plenaria.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Signing of acts adopted in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 79)">
    <intervention id="1-022-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vorrei informare l'Aula che, in seguito all'interruzione della sessione l'8 luglio, ho firmato insieme al Presidente del Consiglio cinque atti approvati nel quadro della procedura legislativa ordinaria conformemente all'articolo 79 del regolamento del Parlamento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vorrei informare l'Aula che mercoledì firmerò insieme al Presidente del Consiglio un atto approvato nel quadro della procedura legislativa ordinaria. I titoli di questi atti saranno pubblicati nel verbale della presente seduta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-023-0000" speaker_id="125045" name="Clara Aguilera" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señorías, quiero mencionar en la apertura de este Pleno lo que está sucediendo en mi región, en Andalucía: un incendio realmente excepcional y grande en Sierra Bermeja, en Málaga. Ya, desgraciadamente, ha muerto un bombero; hay dos también muy graves. Hay más de 1 600 personas desalojadas de sus casas y casi 8 000 hectáreas quemadas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero —y termino brevemente, señor presidente— reconocer, saludar y trasladar el afecto de esta Cámara a la familia del bombero, a todas las familias que están sufriendo este grave incendio de Málaga, en Sierra Bermeja, a todos los medios técnicos que están luchando para ello y, por supuesto, a los ayuntamientos, a la Junta de Andalucía y al Gobierno de España.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-024-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Grazie onorevole Aguilera. Naturalmente siamo tutti molto vicini alla vittima, ma anche a tutte le persone che hanno subito dei disastri per questo incendio così devastante.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Action taken on Parliament’s resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Order of business">
    <intervention id="1-029-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Passiamo ora all'ordine dei lavori. Il progetto definitivo di ordine del giorno, fissato dalla Conferenza dei presidenti, ai sensi dell'articolo 157 del regolamento, nella riunione di giovedì 9 settembre, è stato distribuito.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sono state presentate le seguenti richieste di modifica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lunedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Vorrei informarvi che ho ricevuto una richiesta di applicazione della procedura d'urgenza a norma dell'articolo 163 del regolamento relativo al seguente documento legislativo sulla proroga della validità dei certificati di sicurezza e delle licenze delle imprese ferroviarie che operano nel tunnel sotto la Manica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa richiesta sarà votata oggi. Ai sensi del regolamento potranno essere ascoltati l'autore della richiesta e un oratore contrario nonché il presidente o un relatore della commissione competente. Se c'è qualcuno in Aula che desidera intervenire su questa richiesta di procedura d'urgenza ne ha facoltà. Sia per intervenire a favore sia per intervenire contro. Ma vedo che non ci sono richieste.</p>
      <p sl="en">Martedì</p>
      <p sl="en">Quindi, a seguito delle consultazioni con i gruppi politici, desidero sottoporre all'Aula anche un'altra proposta di modifica al progetto definitivo di ordine del giorno. Riguarda la giornata di martedì e le scadenze relative alle dichiarazioni del vicepresidente della Commissione/Alto rappresentante per gli affari esteri sui seguenti temi: situazione in Afghanistan e situazione in Libano.</p>
      <p sl="en">I termini sono i seguenti: proposte di risoluzione martedì 14 settembre alle ore 19; emendamenti alle proposte di risoluzione e proposte di risoluzione comune mercoledì 15 settembre alle ore 10; emendamenti alle proposte di risoluzione comune mercoledì 15 settembre alle ore 11; votazioni per parti separate mercoledì 15 settembre alle ore 19.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desidero informarvi che le votazioni sono state distribuite in diversi turni di voto, tenendo conto del numero di emendamenti presentati e del numero di richieste di votazione per parti separate e distinte. Questa distribuzione però come sapete può essere soggetta a modifiche. Le informazioni relative alla distribuzione delle votazioni saranno disponibili sul sito web del Parlamento europeo nella sezione "Informazioni e documenti prioritari".</p>
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno si considera pertanto approvato. L'ordine del giorno è così fissato.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vorrei informare l'Aula che ho ricevuto due mozioni di procedura e darò la parola ai due colleghi che hanno chiesto la parola: onorevole Joachim Kuhs ne ha facoltà, prego.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-030-0000" speaker_id="197482" name="Joachim Kuhs" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ich bin in großer Sorge wegen der Pläne über die Einführung eines COVID-19-Zertifikats, das den Zugang zum EP regeln soll. Herr Präsident, Sie betonen doch immer, wie wichtig es ist, dass das Parlament arbeitsfähig bleibt. Und nun wollen Sie für unsere Mitarbeiter den Zugang zum Arbeitsplatz beschränken? Das kann doch nicht Ihr Ziel sein!</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich beantrage deshalb erstens Aufklärung darüber, was wirklich geplant ist, und zweitens fordere ich Sie doch dazu auf, alles dafür zu tun, damit auch künftig ungeimpfte Mitarbeiter stets im EP für uns arbeiten können. Denn sowohl die Impfung als auch ein PCR-Test sind doch medizinische Eingriffe. Es muss die freie Entscheidung jedes einzelnen Menschen bleiben, ob er dieses Risiko auf sich nimmt oder nicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein Impfskeptiker darf keine Nachteile erleiden! Sonst spalten wir die Gesellschaft. Ich bitte Sie inständig, Herr Präsident, dafür Sorge zu tragen, dass diese Freiheitsrechte auch in Ihrem Hause gewahrt bleiben.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-031-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione sul certificato vaccinale è una discussione aperta e oggi pomeriggio sarà affrontata dal Bureau del Parlamento, che è l'organo competente per questa discussione. Quindi vedremo quale sarà la discussione e quali saranno le misure che verranno richieste.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-032-0000" speaker_id="197483" name="Sylvia Limmer" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident! Ja, heute soll wohl hinter verschlossenen Türen in der Konferenz der Präsidenten über den Zugang zum Parlament entschieden werden, und der soll künftig nur mit einem COVID-19-Pass oder mit einer entsprechenden 3G-Regel möglich sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Weil das erstens zu einer Diskriminierung zwischen Geimpften und Ungeimpften führt und dies auch bereits als inakzeptabel und inadäquat von den entsprechenden Gewerkschaften eingestuft wurde, zweitens weitreichende Konsequenzen für den Zugang hätte und auch die Ausübung des freien Mandats eklatant behindern würde und drittens diese Art von Hinterzimmergebaren, heimlich zu entscheiden, nicht oder unmöglich diese vielgepriesene Vorstellung von Transparenz sein kann, beantrage ich vor einer eventuellen diesbezüglichen Abstimmung, dass sich alle Betroffenen in einer Aussprache Gehör verschaffen können. Denn da weiterhin infektiöse Geimpfte für Ungeimpfte viel gefährlicher sind als andersherum, macht diese Diskriminierung auch medizinisch keinen Sinn.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-033-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Come dicevo prima, queste sono discussioni che sono aperte, non c'è stata nessuna decisione al momento.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ed è giusto discuterne, però invito anche i colleghi a conoscere le competenze dei nostri organi del Parlamento, perché a porte chiuse la Conferenza dei presidenti non discute di questo: le competenze sono del Bureau del Parlamento, che ha la competenza di discutere di misure e organizzazione, per cui inviterei i colleghi a precisare le competenze dei nostri organi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questo è molto importante, perché parlare della Conferenza dei presidenti e confonderla con il Bureau del Parlamento, e cioè la Conferenza dei vicepresidenti, è un errore, personalmente un po' inaccettabile.</p>
      <p sl="en">La discussione si farà in quella sede e naturalmente tutti i parlamentari e tutti i gruppi politici saranno interessati a portare il loro contributo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Se devo annunciare qualcosa, lo annunceremo secondo le competenze che i nostri organismi hanno di direzione del Parlamento. Vi ringrazio.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control - Serious cross-border threats to health (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca, in discussione congiunta,</p>
      <p sl="en">la relazione di Joanna Kopcińska, a nome della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare, sulla proposta di regolamento del Parlamento europeo e del Consiglio recante modifica del regolamento (CE) n. 851/2004 con il quale si crea un Centro europeo per la prevenzione e il controllo delle malattie (COM(2020)0726 - C9-0366/2020 - 2020/0320(COD)) (A9-0253/2021), e</p>
      <p sl="en">la relazione di Véronique Trillet-Lenoir, a nome della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare, sulla proposta di regolamento del Parlamento europeo e del Consiglio relativo alle gravi minacce per la salute a carattere transfrontaliero e che abroga la decisione n. 1082/2013/UE (COM(2020)0727 - C9-0367/2020 - 2020/0322(COD)) (A9-0247/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Meine sehr geehrten Damen und Herren, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich muss Sie wiederum, obwohl Sie es schon wissen, darüber informieren, dass es bei allen Aussprachen dieser Tagung, solange wir hybrid verfahren, keine spontanen Wortmeldungen geben kann und keine blauen Karten akzeptiert werden. Außerdem sind wie bei den letzten Tagungen Zuschaltungen aus den Verbindungsbüros des Parlaments in den Mitgliedstaaten vorgesehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die gemeinsame Aussprache über die Gesundheit und Prävention von Krankheiten. Das Thema, das uns alle in jeder Region, in jeder Gemeinde, in jedem Mitgliedstaat und weltweit betrifft. Und ich darf mit der Berichterstatterin beginnen, Frau de la Pisa Carrión. Sie wird aus Madrid zugeschaltet. .</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="204414" name="Margarita de la Pisa Carrión" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente suplente. – Señor presidente, hoy tomo la palabra en nombre de la señora Kopcińska, ponente de este informe. Ella no puede estar presente debido al fallecimiento de su madre. Desde aquí le mando un fuerte abrazo y todo mi apoyo en estos momentos difíciles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Han pasado exactamente veinticinco semanas desde que empezamos a trabajar en el Parlamento sobre el mandato revisado del Centro Europeo para la Prevención y el Control de las Enfermedades. Ha sido un tiempo de mucho trabajo, con muchas ideas para mejorar la propuesta de la Comisión. Ideas que se han debatido con mucha franqueza durante las reuniones y, a pesar de las diferencias entre los grupos políticos, hemos conseguido encontrar un sólido enfoque común.</p>
      <p sl="en">La pandemia de la COVID ha demostrado claramente que nuestra disposición para gestionar las amenazas sanitarias emergentes debe ser más estructurada y ofrecer acciones precisas para futuras crisis sanitarias a nivel de la Unión. Por ello, los trabajos sobre el mandato ampliado del ECDC se han convertido en una preocupación central.</p>
      <p sl="en">La señora Kopcińska, ponente de este informe, quiere agradecer a la comisaria Stella Kyriakides el proyecto de propuesta que se ha presentado en el marco del paquete de la Unión de la Salud. La señora Kopcińska es una firme defensora de esta propuesta y, en su opinión, la posición del Parlamento complementa constructivamente este texto que añade propuestas importantes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Citando a Benjamin Franklin, los mejores médicos dan el menor número de medicinas. Guiada por este principio, Joanna Kopcińska, también médico de formación, ha intentado por tanto encontrar soluciones adecuadas y lograr sinergias entre el ECDC, la Comisión y los países, asegurando al mismo tiempo que los recursos se ajusten a nuestras capacidades reales.</p>
      <p sl="en">En cuanto a las prioridades, el Parlamento se ha centrado en varios elementos claves: reforzar la preparación del Centro, mejorar la notificación de datos y garantizar la evaluación fiable del riesgo epidemiológico.</p>
      <p sl="en">En cuanto al refuerzo de la preparación, creemos que los planes de preparación y las recomendaciones para las crisis sanitarias y las pandemias en la UE deben respetar las competencias y responsabilidades establecidas en los Tratados de la UE y basarse en indicadores desarrollados en cooperación con los Estados miembros. Por eso, hacemos hincapié en la responsabilidad y la competencia dentro del informe, ya que en última instancia realmente son los Estados miembros los que tendrán que aplicar estas recomendaciones del Centro.</p>
      <p sl="en">En cuanto a la mejora de la notificación de datos en toda la Unión, la ponente considera que, para reforzar la vigilancia epidemiológica, los Estados miembros deberían intentar intensificar las notificaciones de los indicadores del sistema sanitario. Solo así, intensificando el análisis y la movilización mediante la recogida y el tratamiento de más datos de los Estados miembros, podremos mejorar realmente la seguridad.</p>
      <p sl="en">En el contexto del trabajo de la evaluación de riesgos, también fue muy importante la Decisión del Defensor del Pueblo Europeo en la investigación estratégica OI/3/2020 sobre el trabajo del Centro. Uno de los problemas claves identificados en la Decisión era la subestimación de la capacidad de los Estados miembros para prevenir y controlar los brotes de enfermedades. Por ello, hemos actuado sobre el trabajo del Defensor del Pueblo y hemos tratado de aumentar la transparencia y la responsabilidad, así como de dotar al Centro de las herramientas que necesita para cumplir su mandato de prevenir y controlar próximas pandemias.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cuando hablamos del apoyo real a las actividades del Centro, es fundamental referirse a los planes nacionales de preparación de los Estados miembros, ya que las recomendaciones del Centro se utilizarán para adoptar planes más amplios a nivel de todos los Estados, alineados con un marco de información y control presupuestario completo y transparente.</p>
      <p sl="en">En cuanto a la aplicación del mandato para abarcar las enfermedades no transmisibles —el tema candente durante los trabajos en comisión—, estamos de acuerdo en que el Centro podría convertirse en una ventanilla única para la información sanitaria a nivel de la UE y para el intercambio de datos entre los Estados miembros. Esto permitiría nivelar el campo de juego de toda la Unión a través de un mayor apoyo técnico, creación de capacidades, intercambio de conocimientos y actividades coordinadas. Sin embargo, esta tarea va mucho más allá de las actividades actuales del Centro, y debemos abordar esta nueva responsabilidad con cautela para no obstaculizar el trabajo de control de las enfermedades transmisibles, que debe seguir siendo la actividad principal de la agencia.</p>
      <p sl="en">En conclusión, la ponente Joanna Kopcińska desea reiterar, al debatir el aumento de la preparación de la UE, especialmente en el contexto de la Unión Europea de la Salud, que debemos ser prácticos y gestionar las expectativas cuando se trata del Centro Europeo para la Prevención y el Control de las Enfermedades. Como se ha mencionado anteriormente, debemos reflexionar cuidadosamente sobre la incorporación de las nuevas tareas en el contexto de su limitada capacidad financiera y organizativa. Por otra parte, debemos esforzarnos por lograr sinergias entre el Centro, la Comisión y los Estados miembros para conseguir los mejores resultados posibles.</p>
      <p sl="en">Como observación final, existe un claro solapamiento entre esta propuesta y el trabajo de la señora Trillet-Lenoir sobre las amenazas transfronterizas graves para la salud. En la nueva estructura propuesta por la Comisión, este Reglamento es la columna vertebral de la Unión de la Salud, mientras que el Reglamento ECDC actúa como su ejecutivo. Esto debería tenerse en cuenta en la medida que avancen los trabajos de estos expedientes bajo la Presidencia de Eslovenia.</p>
      <p sl="en">La ponente, una vez más, desea agradecer a sus colegas y los demás grupos políticos su fructífera colaboración y confianza mutua, y espera seguir colaborando durante las próximas negociaciones interinstitucionales.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-039-0000" speaker_id="197593" name="Véronique Trillet-Lenoir" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteure">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, Monsieur le représentant du Conseil, depuis début 2020, l’Union européenne a entamé un long combat contre l’une des plus graves pandémies de l’histoire.</p>
      <p sl="en">La crise du COVID-19 a révélé notre fragilité en matière de santé publique. Face à ce test grandeur nature, nos systèmes de santé nationaux se sont trouvés dépassés et cette impuissance a d’abord poussé nos gouvernements vers des réflexes de protection sanitaire. Ici même, dans ce Parlement, nous avons appelé à la mise en place d’un mécanisme européen de réponse coordonnée, à l’harmonisation des données épidémiologiques et nous avons soutenu la convergence des actions pour l’achat des vaccins. Les tentations de repli sur soi ont rapidement laissé place à la solidarité et à la coordination européennes qui portent aujourd’hui leurs fruits. Nous sommes indéniablement plus forts ensemble, mais des menaces sanitaires ultérieures sont encore à craindre et la réaction remarquable que nous avons improvisée dans l’urgence doit à présent ouvrir la voie d’une Europe de la santé solidaire, coordonnée, indépendante et durable.</p>
      <p sl="en">En publiant le paquet «Construire une Union européenne de la santé», vous avez souhaité, chère Stella, apporter une cohérence à notre politique d’anticipation, de préparation et de gestion des crises sanitaires. Dans notre projet de rapport, nous souhaitons renforcer votre proposition sur quatre points.</p>
      <p sl="en">Point numéro un: promouvoir la solidarité. Il faut lutter contre les inégalités de santé au sein de l’Union en accentuant la coopération entre les systèmes nationaux. Il faut renforcer la collaboration avec les pays tiers, surtout les plus démunis, en matière d’échange de connaissances et de bonnes pratiques. Il faut insister sur la coopération internationale, notamment par le soutien à l’élaboration d’un traité international sur les pandémies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxième point: renforcer la coordination opérationnelle. Nous devons préparer l’Union à tout type de danger futur pour la santé publique en mettant en œuvre les concepts de «santé globale» et de «santé dans toutes les politiques». Bien sûr, nous devrons être prêts à affronter de nouveaux problèmes infectieux – nouveaux virus, risque d’antibiorésistance –, mais nous devrons aussi pouvoir réagir à d’autres menaces, connues ou pas – environnementales, alimentaires, biologiques, chimiques, nucléaires, etc. Nous devons soutenir les États membres dans la collecte et le partage des données, domaine où ils ont fréquemment été pris en défaut pendant la crise. Nous avons par ailleurs mesuré les conséquences tragiques du COVID-19 sur les personnes porteuses de maladies chroniques. Nous devons élargir la surveillance de l’ECDC à l’impact des maladies transmissibles sur les maladies non transmissibles. Le même ECDC doit assurer la communication aux citoyens européens et contribuer ainsi à la lutte contre la désinformation dont nous avons eu encore une illustration au début de cette séance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Point numéro 3: assurer l’indépendance européenne sur les produits de santé. Cela passe par une implication plus forte de l’Agence européenne des médicaments, la prise en compte des produits de santé dans les ressources répertoriées pour les plans nationaux et un recours plus systématique aux procédures d’achats groupés négociés d’une seule voix, y compris en dehors des crises. Et, bien évidemment, nous attendons avec impatience votre proposition pour la mise en place de l’autorité HERA.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quatrième et dernier point: instaurer une gouvernance sanitaire inclusive. Les citoyens européens réclament plus de transparence et de participation dans le processus décisionnel. Je propose de donner au Parlement un rôle d’observateur au sein du comité de sécurité sanitaire, que vous avez bien fait de renforcer, et d’accorder une part importante à des représentants de la société civile au sein du comité consultatif. Je plaide également pour l’implication des autorités régionales dans la mise en œuvre des plans européens et nationaux, afin de favoriser les expériences de coopération sanitaire dans les régions transfrontalières et d’instaurer une véritable planification interrégionale. Cela permettra aux États membres de mobiliser des financements de manière proportionnée et de partager des coûts d’infrastructures et de personnel.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les attentes des Européennes et des Européens sont fortes. Cette proposition législative ainsi que la révision des mandats de l’EMA et de l’ECDC posent les premiers jalons d’une véritable Europe de la santé. Doté de 5,1 milliards pour la période 2021-2027, le programme européen pour la santé EU4Health nous donne les moyens de privilégier cohérence et efficacité dans notre politique sanitaire. Malgré le titre de ce règlement sur les menaces transfrontières graves pour la santé, que je trouve peu lisible, notre équipe de négociation cent pour cent féminine – et je salue ici ses représentantes, avec une pensée très amicale pour mon amie Joanna – défendra ce programme pour ce qu’il est en réalité: un véritable plan européen de réponse aux crises sanitaires.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stella Kyriakides" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first of all, I want to express my condolences to MEP Kopcińska for the loss of her mother, and I want to take this opportunity to thank both the rapporteurs for an excellent cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="en">The COVID—19 pandemic has now been part of our lives – and is still part of our lives – for the last 18 months, and we are continuing to fight what all of us call an unprecedented health threat. Throughout these 18—19 months, we have learnt, and are learning, a great deal. Perhaps what we have learned – and this is one of the clearest messages that I also heard Véronique say – is that the European Union works and does better when we are stronger together, when there is collaboration.</p>
      <p sl="en">We’ve learnt a great deal and we now have a European vaccine strategy that has resulted in about 72 percent of the adult population of the EU being fully vaccinated. We now know that all the approved vaccines protect against the COVID variants that we have so far, they save lives and they protect against serious disease.</p>
      <p sl="en">But perhaps the clearest message that we have received, and that we are all looking at and discussing here today, is that the European Union needs to be better prepared for future health emergencies and to deliver a post-COVID recovery that makes Europe healthier, more inclusive, more resilient and more sustainable. We need to take bold action across the board, and this action includes building a strong European Health Union.</p>
      <p sl="en">To do that, we have three key proposals: the proposal to strengthen the European Medicines Agency, which we discussed early in July, along with the two proposals I want to discuss with you now. One seeks to reinforce the mandate of the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) and the other proposes a regulation on serious cross-border threats to health. These proposals will be complemented by the European Health Emergency Preparedness and Response Authority (HERA), which will be presented this week. This adds to the importance and the urgency of a swift political agreement on these files.</p>
      <p sl="en">The current pandemic has shown us that we need a stronger ECDC as it has to deal with the lack of access to crucial data and limited capacities to respond to this large—scale outbreak. The progress on the ECDC proposal in Parliament is taking us in the right direction, and I really want to thank you for your active engagement. Your amendments retain the level of ambition of the original proposal and do not mark significant departure from its policy objectives, a level of ambition that I have often stood here and said I totally share.</p>
      <p sl="en">However, we believe that some of the amendments need to be – or should be – reconsidered, especially as regards extending the ECDC’s mandate to cover non-communicable diseases, and this is for two reasons. Firstly, this might lead to duplication with work carried out in Member States and increase the burden on their already limited resources. Secondly, it would substantially stretch resources within the Agency, therefore weakening its focus rather than strengthening it.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would, however, say here that, looking at your amendments, I will look into your proposal for audits every two years and also look into the possibility of the yearly reporting of Member States.</p>
      <p sl="en">The pandemic has shown us that collaboration is vital. In response, the new regulation on cross-border health threats would give the EU a more comprehensive set of tools and enable it to better support Member States in facing such threats. It would introduce an audit process for preparedness and response planning to address existing shortcomings. The proposal gives a stronger legislation that we need to act together, rather than in national silos. To respond to emergencies as a team, we need to work as a team to prepare for them, and that is the purpose of the EU preparedness plan. The Health Security Committee (HSC) has played an enormous role in this pandemic, and a stronger committee would support a common EU response and improve our risk communication.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lastly, the new advisory committee is another crucial component, offering independent advice to make for evidence-based agile responses to health threats. I am very pleased that the Parliament’s amendments preserve the EU health security framework that has been envisioned, and this brings us a step closer to a healthier future for our citizens.</p>
      <p sl="en">I have often referred to the European Health Union package as ambitious with good reason. I believe in this. I believe that all of us who have been working together throughout these last 18 months know how important this is, and we know that this pandemic has given us an opportunity. This is an opportunity that we can make things different and better for European citizens in the area of health. The proposals of the ECDC and cross-border health threats are central to realising our ambition and emerging from this pandemic stronger, emerging wiser, emerging more resilient and emerging better prepared.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I welcome all the work on these proposals, I thank you for your efforts to reach agreement on them, and I am confident that in the fruitful autumn trilogues, we can have an agreement before the end of the year. With your support and all of us working together, we can translate these two proposals into concrete and long—lasting protection for our citizens against health crises.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="197448" name="Rasmus Andresen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser der Stellungnahme des mitberatenden Ausschusses für Binnenmarkt und Verbraucherschutz. – (Beginn des Redebeitrags bei ausgeschaltetem Mikrofon) … anfällig und schwach unser europäisches Gesundheitssystem ist. Jetzt ist es an der Zeit, dass wir die richtigen Lehren daraus ziehen. Uns nützt die beste Gesundheitsversorgung nichts, wenn die Gesundheitssysteme in unseren Nachbarländern zusammenbrechen. Deshalb brauchen wir stärkere Zusammenarbeit.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pandemien lassen sich nicht durch Abschottung bekämpfen. Die Corona-Pandemie muss und kann eine Blaupause für die EU-Gesundheitspolitik werden. Durch Zusammenarbeit und eine Stärkung der EU werden wir eine bessere Gesundheitsversorgung bekommen und niedrigere Preise bei Medikamenten durchsetzen können. Dazu müssen vor allem die Mitgliedstaaten bereit sein, mehr und zeitnah Informationen über die Gesundheitslage an die EU zu geben und den Weg für gemeinsame Beschaffung freizumachen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und um es ganz deutlich zu sagen: Parallelverhandlungen, wie wir sie auch während Corona durch einzelne Mitgliedstaaten erlebt haben, schaden der Europäischen Union. Die Gefahr, dass unsere Verhandlungsposition schlechter wird und wir uns gegeneinander ausspielen lassen, steigt. Deshalb wollen wir Parallelverhandlungen durch einzelne Staaten unterbinden. Aber auch Geheimverträge wie bei den Coronaimpfstoffen müssen der Vergangenheit angehören. Bürgerinnen und Bürger haben ein Recht darauf, zu erfahren, was mit ihren Steuergeldern passiert. Deshalb fordern wir volle Transparenz über die Verträge, die die EU und die Mitgliedstaaten mit den Pharmakonzernen eingehen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir dürfen niemanden durchs Raster fallen lassen, und gerade uns im Ausschuss für Binnenmarkt und Verbraucherschutz war es besonders wichtig zu erwähnen, dass bis zu 37 Millionen Europäer und Europäerinnen unter seltenen Krankheiten oder durch seltene Krankheiten leiden. Für viele der Krankheiten gibt es keine oder nur sehr teure Medikamente. Wenn das ökonomische Interesse bei den Pharmakonzernen fehlt, wird vielen Menschen nicht geholfen. Und gerade deshalb ist es uns wichtig, dass wir es durch gemeinsame Beschaffung auch attraktiver machen wollen und Medikamente für Menschen, die unter seltenen Krankheiten leiden, günstiger machen wollen,. Wir müssen alles dafür tun, den Betroffenen zu helfen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Ausschuss für Binnenmarkt und Verbraucherschutz war es für uns ebenfalls wichtig, dass wir uns hier noch einmal ganz deutlich gegen geschlossene Grenzen aussprechen. Denn geschlossene Grenzen machen Krisen größer und nicht kleiner. COVID-19 hat uns das gezeigt, und wir haben vor allem auch die ökonomischen Konsequenzen dadurch am Anfang gespürt. Und deshalb ist es uns besonders wichtig, darauf hinzuweisen, dass die Grenzen in der EU – auch und gerade für den Warenverkehr – auch in einer Pandemie offenbleiben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lassen Sie uns jetzt gemeinsam dafür sorgen, dass die gute Position, die wir ausschussübergreifend im Parlament verhandelt haben, auch im Trilog übrig bleibt, und dass wir es schaffen, die Mitgliedstaaten von unseren Inhalten zu überzeugen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="38398" name="Esther de Lange" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, colleagues, when the first wave of corona hit our continent, my grandmother, who was 99 years old at the time, was being cared for in a care home in the southern part of the Netherlands, just a few kilometres away from the German border. When an outbreak appeared just across that border in Germany, of course Germany was on high alert. The Netherlands, however, took no measures for the moment, as we were at that time supposedly Covid-free – as if a virus stops at the border.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear colleagues, it is exactly to break through this national bias that we are here today. Next time we face a pandemic or any other cross-border health threat, the reflex should not be purely national thinking, but it should be European cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="en">As directly elected representatives, our first responsibility here in this House lies with the citizens. First of all, with those citizens who are vulnerable and who need to be protected against these cross-border health threats. Therefore, the report proposes that national preparedness plans should always also include a component of cross-border cooperation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, we have a responsibility towards our freedoms – the freedom of movement, as previous speakers said. Although North Rhine-Westphalia kept the border with the Netherlands open, the one with Belgium was closed for months. Yes, I say to our colleagues in the Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection (IMCO Committee) that, of course, that has huge economic consequences, but also at a human level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me give you one example: a father living in Belgium who could not see his children. A divorced couple, in this case, who were living just across the border – four kilometres away – in the Netherlands. This is what we need to prevent.</p>
      <p sl="en">What I also support in this report, and I am concluding, Mr President, is the fact that Europe can now declare its own health emergency, therefore being able to act more quickly. But with this increased capability also comes increased responsibilities, and I say this already with a little wink towards the Council, with whom we still need to negotiate: neither this Parliament, nor its citizens, will in a future pandemic accept a purely national approach.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-0000" speaker_id="197391" name="Heléne Fritzon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">för S&amp;D-gruppen. – Herr talman! Fru kommissionär! När pandemin bröt ut blev det tydligt att EU inte hade de verktyg som krävdes för att hantera en pandemi. I vissa fall fanns verktygen, men de användes inte på bästa sätt. Vi har ställts inför tuffa utmaningar, och ingen kunde vara förberedd.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu vet vi mer. Vi vet vad en global pandemi kan innebära och vilka krav det ställer på EU, på våra medlemsstater och på våra medborgare. Vi har också en gemensam vaccinstrategi. Samtidigt vet vi också att det finns mycket som vi inte vet. Vi kan inte förutse allt, men vi kan förbereda oss för mycket. Vi kan förbereda oss för framtida pandemier och utmaningar. Jag tycker att EU ska ta ansvar för de brister som har blivit tydliga under pandemin och de kunskapsluckor som vi har sett.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi i S&amp;D-gruppen ser att vi behöver ett starkare EU. Vi behöver ta vara på kunskap och data för att på ett effektivt sätt kunna förebygga, förbereda och agera. EU:s smittskyddsmyndighet har spelat en viktig roll under pandemin när det gäller att tillhandahålla vetenskaplig rådgivning, vilket är bra. Data från medlemsstaterna är ju emellertid sällan standardiserad eller jämförbar. Därför är det viktigt att vi nu tar ytterligare ett steg för att stärka det arbetet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det är nödvändigt med mer samordning mellan EU:s organ, mellan de nationella och internationella motsvarigheterna. Hanteringen av den pågående pandemin och hanteringen av de framtida hoten mot människors hälsa blir avgörande för vår framtid. Vi behöver en god EU-samordning och en gemensam beredskap för framtiden. Det är faktiskt så att våra medborgare i EU förväntar sig detta, och det är också, för att ta steget fullt ut, viktigt för hela världens folk.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="58766" name="Nicolae Ştefănuță" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Renew Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, healthy citizens are the greatest asset any country can have, said Churchill. But how about the European Union? Do we have a European health for all our citizens? Seventy-four per cent of Europeans want the EU to have more competences to deal with crises such as the COVID-19 pandemic. The crisis needs to be turned into an opportunity to build a strong European Union for Health. You heard Ms Véronique Trillet-Lenoir saying it.</p>
      <p sl="en">In the wake of the pandemic, we saw more clearly the limits of the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control. The agency was created to mirror the US CDC but lacks its powers and funding. The European CDC has an inconsistent access to data and is critically unmanned. It is named like the US CDC, tries to act like it, but lacks almost everything to do so. We have to make sure that the ECDC is not an empty shell, but a strategic instrument the EU has in dealing with future health crises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Could it happen again, that a pandemic or another health threat brings us to our knees? I think the answer is 100% yes. Would we be forgiven a second time for not being prepared? I think the answer is: impossible.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think here in the EP we have made great progress with the competences allotted to this agency. First, one critical issue is the quality and quantity of the information that the agency can access, so we want to grant specific powers to ensure that the quality of data the ECDC receives is good.</p>
      <p sl="en">Second, it is important that the ECDC has the ability to arrange inspections in the Member States. Inspections are not about poking our noses in. Inspection means first-hand help and means testing in peace what will be essential in war.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, the new variants prove to be challenging in the race to beat COVID-19 so it’s key for the Centre to provide technical and scientific assistance and to help in the detection and sequencing capacities. My country surely needs it.</p>
      <p sl="en">Time cannot be lost when faced with a public health threat or pandemic. You only get to be the firefighter once.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="28161" name="Margrete Auken" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, COVID—19 has highlighted serious shortcomings at both EU and national level. With the new European Health Union package we should be better prepared in the future, but only if the Council agrees on stepping up efforts. I believe Parliament has done a great job. Let me highlight the most important improvements to the Commission proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, future decision—making has to be more inclusive and involve public health experts, healthcare professionals and consumer organisations. Decision—making needs to be fully transparent and with conditions on rules of conflict of interest, particularly for members of the Health Security Committee. We need much better accountability than what we have seen around the procurement of COVID—19 vaccines.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, on transparency, we cannot continue with ‘business as usual’. The procurement of vaccines remains a scandal. We still don’t know how more than EUR 2.7 billion from the EU Emergency Support Instrument has been spent, and still contracts with industry remain redacted. As we move on from a state of emergency, we need much more transparency and better accountability in the future. The European Parliament should be regularly informed about ongoing negotiations, and up—to—date information about jointly procured products should be provided to consumers, including details of liability and legal protection.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thirdly, I am confident that our improvements on the high level of data privacy and security will be carried in the coming negotiations.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lastly, we need to improve the EU’s global approach to the pandemic and step up cooperation with the WHO as well as secure access to medical counter—measures for low— and middle—income countries as part of joint procurement. To this end, compulsory and voluntary technology transfer pools and licensing agreements need to be considered seriously as tools to address the global supply of medical counter—measures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="124765" name="Joëlle Mélin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, les deux textes présentés aujourd’hui entrent dans le grand paquet santé que la crise du COVID a accéléré et, surtout, poussé à des extrêmes. Car au motif de trouver des parades à une crise sans précédent que nul n’a vu venir en Europe et, surtout, dont la gestion a été chaotique, l’Union européenne propose des règlements aux effets potentiellement inquiétants.</p>
      <p sl="en">En sus du renforcement du rôle de l’EMA dans la gestion des pénuries de médicaments, sur lesquelles d’ailleurs les États membres ont beaucoup de mal à se mettre d’accord, il nous est proposé le renforcement de l’Agence de surveillance des maladies infectieuses. Pourtant, c’est celle-là même qui a accusé 22 jours de retard avant de s’exprimer sur la nouvelle pandémie, en niant ses risques jusqu’à la mi-mars 2020. Un copier-coller sur le modèle de l’OMS, qui a échoué et dont on connaît les conséquences gravissimes. Et on voudrait maintenant lui confier la coordination des systèmes de réaction de chacun des États membres, sans en augmenter ni les moyens humains ni les moyens financiers.</p>
      <p sl="en">De même, il nous est proposé un nouveau règlement sur les menaces transfrontières graves pour la santé, qui n’est ni plus ni moins que la reprise dogmatique d’éléments déjà traités dans d’autres textes sur la gestion des stocks, les bases de données informatiques, la transparence des échanges et, surtout, la confirmation de la négation du rôle protecteur des frontières. Ce dernier texte est, selon nous, particulièrement dangereux en ce qu’il établit les bases de la future agence ERA, calquée sur la BARDA américaine, destinée à lutter contre les risques de guerre bactériologique. Mais in fine, c’est l’affaiblissement de l’article 168 du traité FUE, sur la santé publique, qui risque de se produire, venant mettre ainsi la main sur toutes les prérogatives nationales en matière de santé et sans apporter, bien au contraire, la moindre plus value.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il s’agit là d’une nouvelle instrumentalisation de la crise au profit, il faut bien le dire, des européistes. C’est pourquoi ces deux textes nous semblent peu acceptables.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="23788" name="Adam Bielan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the ECR Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the COVID—19 pandemic has unveiled new and unexpected threats to public health, but also highlighted and exacerbated existing weaknesses in the healthcare system of many Member States as well as beyond EU borders. It has demonstrated how a public health problem can affect the proper functioning of all European sectors and has shown that efforts to combat health emergencies require better coordination at EU level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Looking at this from an internal market perspective, the regulation on serious cross—border threats to health issues raises three important issues: supply chains, procurement and data sharing.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mainly, the pandemic has exposed the limited diversity of suppliers and over—reliance on a few particular supply chains. Such vulnerabilities need to be addressed by encouraging broader participation of small and medium—sized enterprises in joint procurement procedures.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU should pay particular attention to providing technical assistance and reducing administrative burdens, to boost SMEs’ engagements in the process.</p>
      <p sl="en">Last but not least, the new regulation should ensure that data sets are equally accessible and usable across the EU for better coordination.</p>
      <p sl="en">I do hope that the proposed solution will contribute to the improvement of operational coordination in the EU. In this regard, I support the creation of the Health Emergency Response and Preparedness Authority.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="136236" name="João Pimenta Lopes" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo The Left. – Senhor Presidente, sobressai nestes relatórios a ausência de referências aos serviços públicos de saúde. Serviços públicos que foram fundamentais na resposta à COVID-19, pesem as políticas de desinvestimento público sistémico imposto por políticas neoliberais e constrangimentos económicos e políticos da União Europeia aos Estados-Membros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Não surpreende, tendo em conta os objetivos em torno da dita União Europeia da Saúde, o mercado europeu de saúde, que não aponta no sentido da capacitação e do necessário reforço dos serviços públicos de saúde, mas, antes, procuram abrir campo a projetos de liberalização, privatização e concentração deste setor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Simultaneamente, insiste-se num modelo de contratação pública que procura condicionar a capacidade de Estados de diversificar a aquisição de medicamentos, a opção que bloqueou o avanço mais rápido da vacinação e que amarrou Estados aos interesses das multinacionais farmacêuticas, impedindo a aquisição de vacinas reconhecidas pela Organização Mundial de Saúde.</p>
      <p sl="en">A resposta a situações de saúde emergentes não pode constituir pretexto para a transferência de competências dos Estados para a esfera supranacional. O que é necessário é o reforço dos serviços públicos de saúde e o seu carácter universal e gratuito, é a capacitação dos Estados na investigação pública, na produção de medicamentos e outros produtos médicos, eliminando dependências do exterior.</p>
      <p sl="en">O reforço da cooperação no domínio da saúde deve ser promovido na base do respeito pela soberania dos estados e sua autonomia, valorizando as suas autoridades nacionais e tomando como referente os interesses públicos e o das populações.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="202352" name="Antoni Comín i Oliveres" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, la pandémie a été sans doute une immense tragédie humaine, avec des conséquences sociales et économiques que nous connaissons tous. Cependant, l’Union a su tirer des leçons utiles pour l’avenir.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parmi elles, la nécessité de progresser dans la construction d’une politique de santé commune européenne, dans les domaines spécifiques où cette plus grande intégration nous permettra de faire plus et mieux. Ce règlement sur les menaces transfrontalières est bien entendu l’un des piliers de cette nouvelle Union européenne de la santé et nous sommes satisfaits de la quantité et la qualité des contributions que nous avons pu apporter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Citons la définition de besoins réels de santé dans toutes les politiques, l’élargissement de la surveillance épidémiologique des maladies transmissibles à leurs conséquences sur les maladies non transmissibles, en particulier la santé mentale, la prise en compte des régions, et particulièrement des régions transfrontalières, dans les plans de prévention et de transparence, ou encore la publication de la liste des membres du Comité de sécurité sanitaire de l’Union, pour éviter tout conflit d’intérêt avec l’industrie pharmaceutique.</p>
      <p sl="en">En conclusion, plus d’Europe dans le domaine de la santé afin que les États membres et les régions de l’Union puissent garantir davantage et mieux le droit à la santé de leurs citoyens.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="197839" name="Радан Кънев" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-н Председател, уважаема г-жо Комисар, колеги, в този общ дебат за европейската здравна политика основната политическа тема е докъде се простират компетенциите на националната държава и откъде започват тези на Съюза. Допуска ли принципът на субсидиарност европейските институции да се ангажират с проблеми на здравеопазването в отделни държави членки?</p>
      <p sl="en">Общата поръчка на ваксини, въпреки началното забавяне, е безспорен успех. Днес Европейският съюз е с най-високи нива на ваксинация, при най-добри цени и максимални гаранции за безопасност в световен мащаб, но изчерпва ли това възможностите на Съюза да влияе на здравната политика? Моят отговор е категорично не. Нужно е много повече, защото принципът на субсидиарност допуска, но и изисква намеса тогава, когато отделна държава не се справя с кризата и застрашава здравето и живота на своите граждани, а през отворените ни граници и на всички европейци.</p>
      <p sl="en">И аз ще дам конкретен пример, който дълбоко ме тревожи, който засяга моите близки, колеги и съседи. Второ правителство и трети парламент в България се провалят в организацията на ваксинационна кампания, в пресичането на антинаучната пропаганда, която ни доведе до позорния резултат от около 20% ваксинирани при 70% средно за Съюза, в провеждането на политики, които да насърчат ваксинацията и да защитят гражданите. Провалят се, защото политическата криза и постоянната предизборна кампания ги превръщат в заложници на страхлив популизъм.</p>
      <p sl="en">Преди дни всички други партии отхвърлиха предложението на Демократична България да се включат в бюджета средства за публична кампания за ваксинации. Но жертви на този провал не са политиците, жертви са възрастните, болните, слабите, жертва е малкият и семейният бизнес, самонаетите лица, тези, които са се ваксинирали, за да защитят другите, но днес им затварят бизнеса, жертви са децата, пак заплашени от дистанционно обучение.</p>
      <p sl="en">Така че отговорът е, че правомощията на Европа стигат дотам, докъдето е нужно, ако националните правителства се провалят да защитят нашите граждани.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="124991" name="Jytte Guteland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr talman! Förhoppningsvis går vi nu mot ljusare tider med mindre ansträngd intensivvård och lättade restriktioner. Det är emellertid nu vi måste dra lärdomarna från pandemin. Runt hörnet lurar nämligen inte bara en risk för en fjärde våg eller nya mutationer av viruset, utan det handlar också om vårt sätt att leva, i obalans med naturen, vilket ökar risken för framtida pandemier. Det krävs nu internationellt samarbete, bland annat inom EU, för att vi aldrig mer ska behöva återuppleva det vi har gått igenom de senaste 18 månaderna.</p>
      <p sl="en">I början av sommaren röstade vi i Europaparlamentet för en förstärkt läkemedelsmyndighet. På så vis kan vi undvika den brist på skyddsutrustning och mediciner som rådde i början av pandemin. I dag tar vi emellertid nästa steg mot en europeisk hälsounion. Särskilt stärker vi det preventiva arbetet med ett tidigt EU-gemensamt varningssystem, oavsett var nästa smittsamma sjukdom kan uppstå. Den mörkläggning av pandemin som rådde i början, av Kina, och som bromsade viktiga åtgärder i ett tidigt skede, får aldrig inträffa här i EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">Förutom det förebyggande så har vi nu också nya verktyg för att i realtid följa och förutspå utvecklingen av framtida virus. Vi tar också ställning för ett nytt globalt ramverk för samarbete mot pandemier, inom ramen för Världshälsoorganisationen. Oavsett om det är antibiotikaresistens, vaccinmotstånd eller en osund djurhållning som ligger bakom nästa pandemi, så måste EU alltid vara rustat och redo. Det här blir nu mer möjligt, när vi tar ställning för ett samarbete kring gränsöverskridande hälsohot och en upprustad europeisk smittskyddsmyndighet. Vi har nog med kriser att hantera. Låt pandemier tillhöra det förflutna.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="197608" name="Gianantonio Da Re" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, il Centro europeo per la prevenzione e il controllo delle malattie è stato istituito nel 2005 con lo scopo di creare una rete di sorveglianza delle malattie infettive.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oggi discutiamo la proposta della Commissione europea di potenziare questo Centro, affidandogli nuove competenze e compiti che vanno ben oltre il monitoraggio delle malattie infettive, prevedendo ispezioni e controlli serrati nei sistemi sanitari nazionali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ciò significherebbe una grave intromissione dell'Unione europea nelle politiche sanitarie degli Stati membri, una sorta di commissariamento dei sistemi sanitari nazionali, in palese violazione del principio di sussidiarietà previsto dai trattati.</p>
      <p sl="en">È bene ricordare che la competenza e la responsabilità primaria per la tutela della salute dei cittadini europei è e deve rimanere agli Stati membri. In materia sanitaria infatti l'Unione europea non ha una competenza esclusiva né una competenza concorrente con gli altri Stati membri, ma solo una competenza limitata per completare, entro limiti ben precisi, l'azione degli Stati.</p>
      <p sl="en">In altre parole l'Unione europea non ha la competenza legislativa in materia, potendo solo adottare delle raccomandazioni senza carattere vincolante. Lo stesso articolo 17 del trattato stabilisce che la Commissione europea è la guardiana. Sia quindi la Commissione per prima a dare il buon esempio.</p>
      <p sl="en">La pandemia di COVID-19 non può e non deve diventare l'ennesimo pretesto per l'Unione europea per assumere nuove e ulteriori competenze che non le spettano. La sanità nazionale non si tocca.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="221463" name="Ladislav Ilčić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, u potpunosti podržavam izvješće kolegice Kopćinske u izvornom obliku.</p>
      <p sl="en">Suradnja na području zdravstva izrazito je važna i zato imam jedan ozbiljan apel. Danas u Europskoj uniji, ovisno od zemlje, imamo od 30 do 50% ljudi koji se ne žele cijepiti protiv Covida. To je jednostavno činjenica i mi je moramo sagledati što god tko mislio o tome. Imamo ljude koji su se dva puta cijepiti pa su dobili koronu, imamo ljude koji se ne smiju cijepiti protiv korone.</p>
      <p sl="en">No, postoji nešto što je svima zajedničko bez obzira što postoje podijeljena mišljenja o cijepljenju. Mi svi želimo i trebamo pomoći u liječenju svih ljudi koji dobiju koronu. Zato apeliram na Europsku komisiju, uložite velika sredstva u razvoj lijekova. Mi jednostavno u to moramo uključiti sve europske zdravstvene institucije poput ovog Europskog centra i mi možemo omogućiti veliki znanstveni napredak i na tom području.</p>
      <p sl="en">Već sad postoje tretmani u svijetu koji su pomogli mnogim ljudima da lakše ozdrave. Jednako kao što ste uložili u razvoj cjepiva, sad uložite i u razvoj lijekova. Sad imamo ogromne probleme u gospodarstvima, imamo podjele među ljudima i ograničavanje temeljnih ljudskih sloboda. Zato uložite u lijekove i pomozite ljudima da se vrate normalnom životu.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="197438" name="Mislav Kolakušić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, Europa je danas podijeljena više nego što je bila u proteklih 30 godina.</p>
      <p sl="en">Danas se građani Europe dijele na one koji vjeruju političarima na vlasti i koji su u sebe unijeli farmaceutske proizvode protiv Covida 19, smatrajući da su oni za njih manja opasnost od same bolesti, iako je bilo nemoguće skoro pronaći osobu mlađu od 70 godina koja je preminula od Covida 19.</p>
      <p sl="en">S druge strane, nalaze se građani koji opravdano smatraju da su cjepiva neusporedivo opasnija od same bolesti Covid 19, posebice svi mlađi od 50 godina. Milijun i dvjesto tisuća nuspojava, četrnaest tisuća umrlih je prijavljeno samo u Europskoj uniji, Ujedinjenom Kraljevstvu i Sjedinjenim Američkim Državama.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-055-0000" speaker_id="1927" name="Peter Liese" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir brauchen mehr Zusammenarbeit in der Europäischen Union bei der Bekämpfung von Pandemien und anderen Herausforderungen. Und wir brauchen mehr Unabhängigkeit von China und anderen, um als Europäer handeln zu können und unsere Bürgerinnen und Bürger zu schützen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und entgegen dem, was hier teilweise gesagt wurde, erlauben uns die europäischen Verträge, weiter zu gehen als bisher. Hier gibt es einen guten Vorschlag der beiden Berichterstatterinnen, und ich danke allen, die dabei geholfen haben, insbesondere für die EVP Esther de Lange und Radan Kanev. Die EVP wird beide Berichte morgen unterstützen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir müssen weiter aus den Fehlern lernen, die während der Pandemie gemacht wurden, und Lehren ziehen. Deswegen begrüße ich sehr, Stella Kyriakides, die Ankündigung der Kommission, diese Woche einen Vorschlag zu HERA vorzulegen, damit wir schneller die notwendigen Materialien wie Impfstoffe kaufen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und hier möchte ich noch einmal ganz deutlich etwas sagen: Ich habe ganz viel Unsinn gerade gehört in der Debatte über den mangelnden Nutzen von Impfstoffen und die nicht vorhandene Gefahr von COVID-19 bei unter 70-Jährigen. Ich weiß es leider anders. Ich rede mit Intensivmedizinern, und die Kliniken sind voll, die Intensivstationen sind voll von jungen Leuten, die nicht geimpft waren und unter 70 sind. Und ich war vor kurzem in meiner alten Klinik, in der ich gearbeitet habe, in der Kinderklinik. Und da ist eben leider auch des Öfteren schon vorgekommen, dass Schwangere einen schweren Verlauf hatten und dass auch Neugeborene betroffen waren. Also die Impfung ist wichtig. Das sollte auch eine Botschaft dieser Debatte sein.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-056-0000" speaker_id="197641" name="Sara Cerdas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhor Presidente, Senhora Comissária, Presidência do Conselho, hoje o Parlamento Europeu dá mais um passo para a proteção da saúde dos europeus. A COVID-19 mostrou-nos muitas coisas e a principal é que os microrganismos não conhecem fronteiras entre países.</p>
      <p sl="en">Um trabalho coordenado dentro e fora da União Europeia entre Estados-Membros e agências internacionais, como a Organização Mundial de Saúde é, assim, urgente. Este relatório é também mais um passo para reduzirmos as desigualdades sociais e garantirmos a distribuição equitativa de medicamentos, vacinas, dispositivos médicos e equipamentos de proteção durante as crises de saúde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esta pandemia foi também um verdadeiro teste de stress aos nossos sistemas de saúde. O que queremos com esta legislação é que estes testes sejam feitos de forma controlada para identificarmos as falhas e corrigi-las atempadamente. A chave para estarmos preparados para futuras ameaças reside também na formação de profissionais de saúde e dos serviços sociais, bem como num reforço da literacia em saúde dos cidadãos, para os cidadãos, para que estes melhor compreendam as indicações das autoridades de saúde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Precisamos também de sistemas de informação robustos, desde a recolha de dados à sua análise e interpretação, tirando o maior proveito da nova era digital para reduzir a carga administrativa e a duplicação de recursos neste que é um processo muito moroso. O reforço do ECDC, da sua competência e da sua capacidade de análise de risco rápida terá como resultado uma maior capacidade de mitigação das consequências das futuras crises de saúde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eu quero finalizar recordando que a saúde não se limita apenas aos sistemas de saúde. A saúde tem impacto em todos os setores da nossa sociedade e requer um trabalho coordenado entre todos para a promoção da saúde, prevenção da doença e preparação de crises. Este desígnio é alcançado apenas com uma verdadeira abordagem de saúde em todas as políticas e de uma só saúde.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="197538" name="Beata Mazurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Panie Przewodniczący! Na tej sali wielokrotnie mówimy o rozwoju Unii Europejskiej, skupiamy się na cyfrowej rewolucji, gospodarczej odbudowie po kryzysie, zielonej transformacji. To dobrze, że tak się dzieje. Ale czy uda nam się to wszystko osiągnąć bez sprawnego i zdrowego społeczeństwa?</p>
      <p sl="en">Środki ochrony zdrowia publicznego muszą być spójne, konsekwentne i skoordynowane. Pandemia COVID-19 zmieniła życie nas wszystkich, zostawiła trwały uszczerbek na zdrowiu wielu mieszkańców Unii Europejskiej, ujawniła niedociągnięcia w unijnych mechanizmach zarządzania zagrożeniami zdrowia. Mechanizmy te wymagają uporządkowania podejścia do przyszłych kryzysów zdrowotnych na szczeblu Unii opartego również na europejskiej solidarności.</p>
      <p sl="en">To wszystko powoduje, że konieczne jest wzmocnienie bezpieczeństwa zdrowotnego oraz sprawniejsze reagowanie na zagrożenia zdrowotne, które mogą pojawić się w najbliższej przyszłości. Modyfikacje, które zostały wprowadzone do rozporządzenia o Europejskim Centrum do spraw Zapobiegania i Kontroli Chorób, pomogą wzmocnić bezpieczeństwo zdrowotne Europejczyków, przyczynią się do lepszej koordynacji działań i szybszej wymiany informacji pomiędzy państwami członkowskimi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Działania te, miejmy nadzieję, pomogą w skutecznej walce nie tylko z COVID-19, ale również z innymi zagrożeniami zdrowotnymi, na które umiera wielu Europejczyków. Choroby nowotworowe, choroby układu krążenia, serca, choroby na tle psychicznym były, są i będą. Nie zapominajmy o tym dla naszego zdrowia i zdrowia przyszłych pokoleń.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-058-0000" speaker_id="197455" name="Cindy Franssen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, commissaris, collega's, als we iets geleerd hebben uit deze COVID-19-crisis, is het wel dat lappendekens aan maatregelen in de verschillende lidstaten geen oplossing bieden. Integendeel, we hebben op het vlak van volksgezondheid meer Europa nodig, meer coördinatie, snellere afspraken, betere voorbereiding en vlottere samenwerking. Samen kunnen we meer levens redden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wat we nog geleerd hebben, is dat de energie en de tijd die nodig zijn om een dergelijke gezondheidscrisis het hoofd te bieden, immense gevolgen hebben voor de reguliere gezondheidszorg in de lidstaten. In de meest kritische fase van deze crisis werd reguliere zorg stopgezet. Kankerscreenings, urgente behandelingen of operaties werden uitgesteld, met alle gevolgen van dien. Dit moeten we in de toekomst ten stelligste vermijden. De continuïteit van de kankerzorg en de screenings moet gegarandeerd blijven, ook tijdens de pandemie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Door nauwer samen te werken kunnen we bij pandemieën sneller reageren en voorkomen dat we de reguliere zorg al te lang moeten uitstellen. Daarom vragen we bijzondere aandacht voor deze kwetsbare doelgroepen en moet het garanderen van de reguliere zorg integraal deel uitmaken van elk paraatheids- en responsplan. Want ook dat zal levens redden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel Schaldemose" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Hr. formand! Vi har lært af corona-krisen. Pandemien udstillede og understregede både styrkerne og svaghederne i det europæiske fællesskab. Da coronaen ramte Europa, var vi for langsomme til at reagere. Vi var for dårligt forberedte og havde for få værnemidler, og en stor del af vores sundhedsproduktion var lagt ud til lande uden for EU. Det forværrede situationen. Aldrig før i EU's historie har vores samarbejde stået over for så stor en udfordring. Men det sidste halvandet år har vi fået nye indsigter om, hvad vi kan i samarbejdet. Både hvad vi kan gøre i fællesskabet, og hvilket ansvar medlemslandene har for fællesskabet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi kan ikke politisk bestemme, hvordan eller om den næste pandemi skal ramme os, men vi kan politisk sørge for, at vi er bedre rustet. Det er der brug for. De initiativer, som vi stemmer om i denne uge, forbedrer vores europæiske sundhedssamarbejde, og det er nødvendigt og godt. Vi styrker Det Europæiske Center for Forebyggelse af og Kontrol med sygdomme ECDC. Det betyder, at vi kan opdage sundhedskriser hurtigere og bedre kan nå at reagere på det i tide sammen. Vi forbedrer koordinationen mellem EU's medlemslande. Vi er forbundet, og det giver mening, at vi koordinerer indkøb af værnemidler, vacciner og den slags ting sammen. Sammen kan vi sikre en bedre forsyning hele vejen igennem produktionskæden, og det synes jeg er ganske afgørende, nødvendigt og en god lære. I denne uge stemmer vi altså for at ruste EU bedre mod nye sundhedskriser, og det stemmer jeg for.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-0000" speaker_id="125106" name="Johan Van Overtveldt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, commissaris, collega's, COVID-19 houdt ons nu al anderhalf jaar in de ban. De pandemie heeft heel wat pijnpunten blootgelegd, in het bijzonder dat de EU absoluut niet klaar was voor een crisis van deze omvang en de meeste lidstaten trouwens ook niet. We betalen hiervoor een hoge prijs met veel menselijk leed en zware sociaal-economische kosten. Een betere samenwerking en coördinatie over de grenzen heen, met respect voor de bevoegdheden van lid- en deelstaten, is zeker nodig. Wat we nodig hebben is een eenvoudig gaas dat efficiënt werkt, transparant is en hoge prestaties levert.</p>
      <p sl="en">We moeten daarbij absoluut vermijden te vervallen in wat wij in Vlaanderen “koterij” noemen, waarbij steeds opnieuw structuren worden gecreëerd en bijgebouwd om tot een totaal onoverzichtelijk geheel te komen. In deze context steunen wij zeker de versterking van bestaande structuren, zoals het Europees Geneesmiddelenbureau en het Centrum voor ziektepreventie en -bestrijding. We zijn het aan onszelf verplicht deze instanties te versterken en beter te maken.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dit valt absoluut te verkiezen boven het mordicus willen creëren van nieuwe instellingen. Ik kijk in die zin met bezorgdheid uit naar de voorstellen inzake HERA, die de Commissie morgen publiceert. De Commissie haalt hiervoor de mosterd in de VS, maar zoals u weet, zijn de verschillen tussen de Europese Unie en de VS op bepaalde vlakken – gelukkig maar – nog altijd groot. Ik hoop dat de Commissie het devies “eenheid in verscheidenheid” trouw blijft, focust op het vervolmaken van wat we hebben en dus inderdaad koterij achterwege laat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="197536" name="Nathalie Colin-Oesterlé" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, des pandémies futures vont apparaître plus souvent, se propageront plus rapidement, causeront plus de dommages à l’économie mondiale et tueront plus de personnes que la COVID-19, si rien n’est fait. Ces mots alarmants sont ceux d’experts scientifiques et sont sans appel. L’Europe doit s’armer face au risque de nouvelles pandémies et c’est ce qu’elle fait: cette semaine, et dans l’attente du renforcement des pouvoirs de l’Agence européenne des médicaments, nous adopterons les positions du Parlement sur les règlements visant à renforcer le rôle de l’agence européenne en charge de la prévention et du contrôle des maladies et à modifier la législation européenne sur les menaces transfrontières pour la santé.</p>
      <p sl="en">En tant qu’élue d’un territoire frontalier, je souhaite saluer tout particulièrement certaines mesures: le renforcement indispensable de la coopération et de la coordination entre États membres, avec notamment le partage de données et la constitution de stocks de médicaments essentiels, la garantie de libre circulation des travailleurs frontaliers et des biens essentiels en cas de rétablissement des contrôles aux frontières intérieures, l’interdiction pour tout État membre de restreindre ses exportations de médicaments et matériel médical sans autorisation préalable de la Commission. À l’avenir, nous ne verrons plus d’États membres interdire des exportations de médicaments et de matériel médical, ni de travailleurs frontaliers empêchés de se rendre sur le lieu de travail. Ce sont de véritables avancées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je le répète, nous ne pourrons être forts qu’en renforçant la coopération et la coordination entre les États membres. C’est là que l’Union européenne de la santé prend tout son sens et s’impose chaque jour comme le tremplin indispensable vers une souveraineté sanitaire retrouvée.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="197735" name="Adriana Maldonado López" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, señora comisaria, tenemos que aprender las lecciones que nos ha dejado esta crisis de la COVID-19 y, sin duda, una de ellas es que tenemos que prepararnos sanitariamente para afrontar, desde la Unión Europea, las futuras crisis sanitarias de una forma mucho más efectiva, más optimizada y mucho más coordinada.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quiero, en primer lugar, poner en valor la compra conjunta de vacunas que se ha hecho de forma coordinada por parte de la Unión Europea, que nos ha permitido a todos los Estados miembros acceder a la vacunación y tener los ratios de vacunación que se registran hoy en día.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pero me quiero centrar en tres elementos importantes: el primero de ellos es que creo que hay que mejorar el procedimiento de compra conjunta por parte de los Estados miembros. Por otra parte, debemos mejorar los requisitos de transparencia en los procedimientos de adquisición conjunta y, para terminar, potenciar el rol de control de este Parlamento Europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Desde una perspectiva del mercado interior, es importante que apoyemos la creación de un stock mínimo de reservas de productos estratégicos para que, en futuras crisis como la que hemos vivido, la Unión Europea y todos los Estados miembros tengamos un stock mínimo de productos sanitarios, de productos relacionados con los medicamentos, los EPI, la vacunación …, para que en una crisis futura la Unión Europea esté mucho mejor preparada.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="197515" name="Pernille Weiss" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Hr. formand! Det er nu, mens vi mange steder i Europa stadigvæk går rundt med masker, og mange lande endnu kæmper med at få antallet af vaccinerede op, at vi skal aftale, hvordan vi aldrig nogensinde står på samme måde i enten chok, panik eller nød over for en epidemi, og hvordan vi i EU undgår at bidrage til, at en pandemi aktiveres. Dét er opgaven.</p>
      <p sl="en">Derfor er det godt, at ECDC, Det Europæiske Center for Sygdomsforebyggelse og kontrol, nu får et stærkere mandat, så det kan blive bedre til at understøtte medlemslandenes samarbejde og Kommissionens handlekraft, når menneskeliv skal reddes og vores økonomiske muskel holdes i gang.</p>
      <p sl="en">ECDC skal hjælpe os med at kunne regne mere og bedre med hinanden. Det burde egentlig være en selvfølgelighed, men det er det ikke, når national forfængelighed kommer i spil, og angsten næres for, at nogen skulle få lov til at tage noget fra en, man hellere vil gemme til sig selv.</p>
      <p sl="en">Så der bliver nok for ECDC at knokle med at få til at fungere. Især fordi der er forslag i teksten, der udfordrer det suveræne nationale ansvar for ikke-smitsomme sygdomme. Måske det vil vise sig, at det er bedre for EU's forsvar mod grænseoverskridende smitsomme sygdomme at fokusere på dem og ikke alle mulige andre. Bliver det nødvendigt, så må mine mere føderalistisk orienterede kollegaer ikke hænge sig i de ideologiske detaljer. EU skal – hele vejen rundt i medlemslandene – være klar til næste pandemi. Dét stemmer jeg naturligvis for!</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Voting session">
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Bevor wir mit den Aussprachen fortfahren, werde ich die heutige Abstimmungsrunde eröffnen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Dossiers, über die wir abstimmen, sind der Tagesordnung zu entnehmen. Die Abstimmungsrunde ist von 18.30 Uhr bis 19.45 Uhr geöffnet. Es kommt dasselbe Abstimmungsverfahren zur Anwendung wie bei den letzten Tagungen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Über die Immunitätsangelegenheit wird in geheimer Abstimmung abgestimmt. Die Mitglieder geben ihre Stimme in herkömmlicher Weise ab, allerdings ist aus dem Stimmzettel, den sie erhalten und unterschreiben müssen, nicht ersichtlich, wie sie abgestimmt haben, sondern nur, dass sie abgestimmt haben.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alle übrigen Abstimmungen sind namentliche Abstimmungen. Erklärungen zu Abstimmungen können schriftlich eingereicht werden. Ausnahmsweise dürfen die Erklärungen zur Abstimmung höchstens 400 Wörter umfassen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die Abstimmungsrunde für eröffnet. Sie können bis 19.45 Uhr abstimmen. Die Ergebnisse der Abstimmung werden morgen um 9.00 Uhr bekannt gegeben.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control - Serious cross-border threats to health (continuation of debate)">
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Wir setzen nun unsere gemeinsame Aussprache über:</p>
      <p sl="en">den bericht über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates zur Änderung der Verordnung (EG) Nr. 851/2004 zur Errichtung eines Europäischen Zentrums für die Prävention und die Kontrolle von Krankheiten [COM(2020)0726 - C9-0366/2020- 2020/0320(COD)] - Ausschuss für Umweltfragen, öffentliche Gesundheit und Lebensmittelsicherheit. Berichterstatterin: Joanna Kopcińska (A9-0253/2021) und</p>
      <p sl="en">den bericht über den Vorschlag für eine Verordnung des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates zu schwerwiegenden grenzüberschreitenden Gesundheitsgefahren und zur Aufhebung des Beschlusses Nr. 1082/2013/EU [COM(2020)0727 - C9-0367/2020- 2020/0322(COD)] - Ausschuss für Umweltfragen, öffentliche Gesundheit und Lebensmittelsicherheit. Berichterstatterin: Véronique Trillet-Lenoir (A9-0247/2021)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="197718" name="Nicolás González Casares" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, los dos Reglamentos que debatimos hoy —el ECDC y las amenazas transfronterizas— se unen al Reglamento de la EMA, del que soy ponente, para conformar este primer avance de la Unión Europea de la Salud, una verdadera política europea de salud.</p>
      <p sl="en">Hemos visto como al inicio de la pandemia le exigíamos al ECDC datos, información, etc. y no era capaz de darlos porque no había una verdadera coordinación europea y no tenía los recursos ni la robustez suficiente. Faltaba, entre otras cosas, personal. Debemos dotarlo de personal, y este Reglamento avanza en esa vía.</p>
      <p sl="en">También en las amenazas transfronterizas hay un espacio para políticas europeas de salud. Lo han dicho la ponente, Véronique Trillet-Lenoir, y Sara Cerdas: es necesario avanzar en políticas europeas de salud. Hay espacio para ello sin asumir competencias de los Estados miembros.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tenemos que avanzar en la creación de esos planes de salud de los Estados, coordinarlos y, por qué no, avanzar hacia posiciones conjuntas para tratar las pandemias e incluir las enfermedades no transmisibles. «Más Europa» está significando estar mejor preparados en materia de salud. Ese es el camino. Sigamos avanzando por ahí.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-0000" speaker_id="197417" name="Tomislav Sokol" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovani predsjedavajući, do danas je u Europskoj uniji zabilježeno više od 759 tisuća smrtnih slučajeva povezanih s bolešću Covid 19.</p>
      <p sl="en">U takvim okolnostima, čak 66 posto naših građana smatra da Europska unija treba imati veće ovlasti u području zdravstva. Ipak, čak i unutar postojećih ovlasti, Europska unija može i mora učiniti više u suzbijanju zdravstvenih prijetnji koje nadilaze državne granice. Upravo Uredbom o ozbiljnim prekograničnim prijetnjama zdravlju stvaramo europsku zdravstvenu Uniju i štitimo naše građane od sadašnjih i budućih zdravstvenih ugroza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Danas je sasvim jasno da je Svjetska zdravstvena organizacija kasnila s proglašenjem pandemije. Donošenjem ove Uredbe dobivamo instrument kojim možemo proglasiti izvanredno stanje u području javnog zdravlja neovisno o Svjetskoj zdravstvenoj organizaciji.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kao izvjestitelj Europske pučke stranke u Odboru za unutarnje tržište i zaštitu potrošača predložio sam mehanizam prethodnog odobrenja od strane Europske komisije za uvođenje izvoznih ograničenja na medicinske protumjere. Ponosan sam što je taj prijedlog usvojen kao dio ovog izvješća. Uvođenjem izvoznih ograničenja u jeku pandemije, suprotno načelu solidarnosti, naši građani bili su izloženi nestašice ključne opreme poput maski i rukavica a posebno u onim državama članicama koje nemaju razvijenu vlastitu proizvodnju medicinske opreme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Uvođenjem ovog mehanizma onemogućuje se da u kritičnom trenutku zdravstvene ugroze bude dovedeno u pitanje funkcioniranje naših zdravstvenih sustava. Pandemija nam je pokazala da zdravstvene prijetnje poput zaraznih bolesti ne poznaju granice. Temeljem naučenih lekcija sada gradimo sigurnu i zdravstvenu otpornu Europsku uniju za dobrobit svih njenih građana.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="124799" name="Alessandra Moretti" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signor Presidente, signora Commissaria, onorevoli colleghe e colleghi, in questi mesi difficili di pandemia finalmente abbiamo chiara una cosa: c'è bisogno di più Europa, anche nell'ambito della salute.</p>
      <p sl="en">I cittadini ci chiedono che sia l'Europa a gestire le grandi questioni di salute pubblica e di sanità. I cittadini non capiscono come sia possibile che in un continente ormai interconnesso sotto tutti i punti di vista, ci siano oggi così grosse disparità e disuguaglianze in un ambito così delicato e decisivo per la vita delle persone.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bene quindi le relazioni oggi in discussione, che rilanciano le competenze europee, con un maggior ruolo di responsabilità per il Centro europeo per la prevenzione e il controllo delle malattie e per un coordinamento più forte del contrasto alle minacce transfrontaliere.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si tratta di due tasselli in più per l'obiettivo finale: un'Unione europea della salute che garantisca i diritti e le prestazioni minime per tutti i cittadini europei. Un'Europa che garantisca un sistema sanitario pubblico di qualità per tutte e tutti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="197841" name="Liudas Mažylis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gerbiamas Pirmininke, gerbiama Komisijos nare, kolegos, didesnė sveikatos sistemų integracija yra labai sveikintina. Pritariu, kad Europos ligų prevencijos ir kontrolės centro funkcijos būtų išplėstos ir jis būtų įpareigotas stebėti kaip infekcinių ligų plitimas daro įtaką lėtinių ligų situacijai. Mokslu grįsti rezultatai ne tik turėtų būti skleidžiami profesionalams viešai, bet ir pateikiami piliečiams prieinama forma, kad didintų visuomenės sveikatos raštingumą. Centro funkcijos turi būti perorientuotos taip, kad atsirastų galimybė modeliuoti ligų plitimo situacijas ir atskirose valstybėse, ir visoje Europos Sąjungoje, kad būtų įmanoma prognozuoti plitimo scenarijus. Nereikia naujų pandemijų, kurioms mes, esą, pasiruošime geriau. Mes COVID-19 valdymą sumodeliuokime šiandien čia ir dabar, ir hepatito C, apie kurį ne kartą esu jau kalbėjęs. Statistikos suvienodinimas įvairiose valstybėse, moderniųjų technologijų pasitelkimas, įskaitant ir dirbtinį intelektą, leistų galų gale sumažinti administracinę naštą bei taupyti resursus. Eidami tuo keliu Europoje išgelbėtume tūkstančius gyvybių. Dėkoju.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-0000" speaker_id="197846" name="Иво Христов" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-н Председател, пандемията драматично подрони доверието между гражданите и държавите в сферата на здравето. Милиони европейци се тревожат дали здравето не е повод за трайно ограничаване на права. Всички си задаваме въпроса къде свършва грижата за здравето и къде започва злоупотребата със страха, защото болестите са разход за социалните системи, но и доходоносен бизнес за корпорациите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Европейският здравен съюз е призван да въведе механизми за съгласуваност и солидарност в превенцията и управлението на кризи. Здравната солидарност предполага гражданите, бедни и богати, жители на коя да е страна от Съюза, да могат да разчитат на удовлетворяващи грижи за здравето си. Категорично подкрепям равния достъп до лечение да е водещата идея в регламента за сериозните трансгранични заплахи за здравето.</p>
      <p sl="en">Новата нормалност не е тази на маските, локдауните и поредните дози ваксини. Tова е новост, но не е нормалност. Новата нормалност трябва да се основава на прозрачна лекарствена политика и ценообразуване, на достоверната научна информация, здравната грамотност, осъзнатата лична отговорност и солидарността.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-0000" speaker_id="197414" name="Λουκάς Φουρλάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κύριε Πρόεδρε, κυρία Επίτροπε, άκουσα πάρα πολλά από τους συναδέλφους, ότι η πανδημία μας έμαθε πάρα πολλά πράγματα. Μας έμαθε το πιο σημαντικό: μόνο μαζί και ενωμένοι μπορούμε να αντιμετωπίζουμε τέτοιες καταστάσεις. Οφείλουμε όχι μόνο να παρακολουθούμε, αλλά να προλαβαίνουμε και να αντιμετωπίζουμε τα σοβαρά θέματα υγείας ενωμένοι. Η Ευρώπη πρέπει να λειτουργεί αυτόνομα και να είναι σε θέση να χειρίζεται τα θέματα υγείας. Κυρία Επίτροπε, σας οφείλουμε ευχαριστίες. Ως Κύπριος, αισθάνομαι υπερήφανος για το συλλογικό, ψύχραιμο και αποτελεσματικό τρόπο με τον οποίο αντιμετωπίσατε την πανδημία. Το ότι έχουμε εμβολιαστικό πρόγραμμα, το ότι έχουμε εμβόλια οφείλεται εν πολλοίς και σε σας. Οφείλουμε να συνεχίσουμε ενωμένοι, διότι η υγεία αφορά όλους μας και δεν έχει σύνορα.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Danke. Das Lob ist eine schöne Brücke zu den abschließenden Bemerkungen von Frau Kommissarin Stella Kyriakis.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Stella Kyriakides" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Thank you, President, but I think the praise should be extended to almost everyone in this European Parliament for the work that we have been doing together for the last 18 months.</p>
      <p sl="en">I began by underlining the need for bold action, and I very much welcome hearing all your interventions today. It’s clear that you share our level of ambition and the need for quick and decisive action. The health union will have to ensure, as many of you have said, that we need a strong common response, but recognising specific needs and contexts.</p>
      <p sl="en">When protecting our citizens, we need to be one step ahead; we cannot be running behind and trying to catch up. The progress made so far in Parliament on these proposals is definitely taking us in the right direction, but we need to move faster towards adoption.</p>
      <p sl="en">The number of citizens that we have lost to this virus in the past year is a wake-up call to us all. The Council has already made considerable progress and adopted its general approach on 23 July. Now we start the interinstitutional negotiations, and let me assure you that the Commission will play its part in reaching quick and meaningful agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">I heard some colleagues speak about the need to have more work done on therapeutics. We have been working on an EU therapeutic strategy for the last few months, and I am in a position to tell you that we have launched this strategy and are expecting the European Medicines Agency’s assessment of three new therapeutics in October.</p>
      <p sl="en">So we are leaving no stone unturned. But on the other hand, I have also heard many raise the subject of national competences – a taboo subject in the area of health. What we seem to forget is that the world after COVID-19 is fundamentally different. We cannot treat public health matters as we did before. We need a strong EU legal framework. We need to be able to act at EU level while respecting Member States’ competences.</p>
      <p sl="en">A strong European Health Union is not about, as I have heard, using the COVID-19 crisis to grab power. It is about using this crisis to turn it into positive action. It is using this crisis to bring about positive change for EU citizens, all within the Treaty framework.</p>
      <p sl="en">So let’s all work together. Let’s press ahead with these ambitious and much-needed proposals so we can adopt them at the end of this year. This is what this European Union needs. This is what our citizens expect from us and we should not deliver anything less.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die gemeinsame Aussprache ist geschlossen. Die Abstimmungen über die Änderungsanträge finden morgen, Dienstag, 14. September 2021, die Schlussabstimmung am Mittwoch, 15. September 2021, statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-2500" speaker_id="26837" name="Λευτέρης Χριστοφόρου" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">γραπτώς. – Η πανδημία και τα νέα δεδομένα κατέδειξαν ότι οφείλουμε να εγκαταλείψουμε τη μέχρι σήμερα πολιτική της ΕΕ, όπου τα θέματα υγείας δεν αποτελούν αρμοδιότητα της ΕΕ. Πολύ ορθά η Ευρωπαία Επίτροπος Στέλλα Κυριακίδη και η Πρόεδρος της Ευρωπαϊκής Επιτροπής στη ομιλία της στο Ευρωκοινοβούλιο τόνισαν την αναγκαιότητα για δημιουργία Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης Υγείας. Πιστεύω ότι το μεγάλο στοίχημα, με την πανδημία, όπου εφαρμόστηκαν κοινές πολιτικές για την αντιμετώπιση της μεγάλης υγειονομικής κρίσης, πέτυχε. Πιστεύω επίσης ότι και οι πολίτες της ΕΕ υποστηρίζουν μια ενιαία πολιτική της ΕΕ για θέματα υγείας. Επιβάλλεται, λοιπόν, η ΕΕ να προχωρήσει άμεσα στην υλοποίηση αυτού του μεγαλεπήβολου και σημαντικού στόχου, που μόνο ευεργετικά οφέλη θα έχει για την υγεία, τους ευρωπαίους πολίτες και την ίδια την ΕΕ.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-5000" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – EU on ottanut isoja harppauksia parempaan päin unionin yhteisen terveyden edistämisessä ja suojelussa. Tämä on positiivista, sillä on monia asioita, joihin kansallinen sote-uudistus ei riitä. Meidän pitää ottaa käyttöön kaikki se osaaminen, jota 27 jäsenmaan unionillamme on tarjota. On tärkeää toimia yhdessä mahdollisten koronaviruspandemioiden kaltaisten kriisien estämiseksi ja hallitsemiseksi, mutta kriisitilanteiden lisäksi tarvitsemme enemmän myös normaaliajan yhteistyötä. Euroopan tartuntatautiviraston ECDC:n mandaatin vahvistaminen on ehdottoman tärkeää, jotta Euroopan laajuinen epidemiologinen seuranta, valvonta sekä varautuminen on yhtenäistä ja koordinoitua. Emme voi antaa covid-19-katastrofin sekaannuksen toistua.</p>
      <p sl="en">Olen jo pitkään peräänkuuluttanut vahvempaa EU:ta terveyden osalta. Komission terveysunioniesityksessä kaikki jäsenmaat valmistautuisivat ja reagoisivat terveyskriiseihin yhdessä, edulliset ja innovatiiviset lääkintätarvikkeet olisivat kaikkien saatavilla ja maat yhdessä parantaisivat syövän ja muiden sairauksien ennaltaehkäisyä, hoitoa ja jälkihoitoa. Tämä on askel oikeaan suuntaan. Tarvitsemme normaaliaikojen yhteistyötä, panostamista perussairauksien hoitoon, terveydenhuollon investointeihin ja henkilökunnan kouluttamiseen. Suurten kansansairauksien kuten sydän- ja verisuonitautien ja diabeteksen vastainen työ on yhä tärkeämpää väestön ikääntyessä. Esimerkiksi harvinaissairauksien osalta referenssikeskukset kokoavat alan parasta osaamista samaan paikkaan, ja niiden riittävästä resursoinnista pitää huolehtia. Samaa osaamiskeskusmallia on syytä laajentaa myös muiden yleisten sairauksien osalta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-0000" speaker_id="27714" name="Edina Tóth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – A koronavírus járvány mindenki életét gyökeresen felforgatta, ezért most van a leginkább szükség megvalósítható célokra és hatásos egészségügyi programokra. Nagyobb hangsúlyt kell helyezni a jövőben az egészségügyre, és gyorsabban kell reagálni az előre nem látható egészségügyi veszélyekre. Az Európai Betegségvédelmi és Járványügyi Központ fejlesztésével képesek lehetünk arra, hogy az uniós intézmények a tagállamokkal együttműködve a jövőben biztosítani tudják az európai polgárok egészségének védelmét. Fontos, hogy a józan ész diktálja a szabályokat és az egészségügy tagállami hatáskör kell, hogy maradjon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Az Uniónak az általános célok mentén kell nagyobb erőkifejtést tanúsítania: erősítenie kell a lakosság védelmét a határon átnyúló egészségügyi veszélyekkel szemben, támogatnia kell a gyógyszerek, orvostechnikai eszközök hozzáférhetőségét és megfizethetőségét. Éppen ezért nem támogatható a Központ hatáskörének kiterjesztése a nem-fertőző betegségek monitorozására. Fontos még megjegyezni, hogy 2020 elején, amikor már egyértelmű volt a koronavírus jelentette egészségügyi fenyegetettség, a Központ nem elemezte megfelelően a helyzetet és nem tett ajánlásokat a tagállamok számára, ezzel is bizonyítva, hogy a legfontosabb most a Központ eredeti szerepének megerősítése, nem pedig a hatáskörök bővítése lenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">A magyar kormány számára az emberélet, emberek élete és biztonsága az első, ezért is tartom aggályosnak a Parlament azon javaslatait, amelyek új struktúrákat hoznának létre, jelentősen megnehezítve, vagy adott esetben gátolva ezzel a tagállamok válságkezelését.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. Fair working conditions, rights and social protection for platform workers - New forms of employment linked to digital development (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="4246" name="Der Präsident" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Sylvie Brunet im Namen des Ausschusses für Beschäftigung und soziale Angelegenheiten über das Thema „Gerechte Arbeitsbedingungen, Rechte und soziale Sicherung für auf Online-Plattformen beschäftigte Arbeitnehmer – Neue Beschäftigungsformen im Zusammenhang mit der digitalen Entwicklung“ [2019/2186(INI)] (A9-0257/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0000" speaker_id="197576" name="Sylvie Brunet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteure">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire – cher Nicolas qui arrive au bon moment –, chers collègues, je souhaite tout d’abord remercier mes collègues, plus particulièrement les rapporteurs fictifs des différents groupes politiques, mais aussi mes collègues de la commission des transports, qui ont, tout comme moi, travaillé sur ce dossier ces derniers mois afin de pouvoir définir une position commune et ambitieuse du Parlement européen sur ce sujet majeur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le sommet social de Porto a été l’occasion d’identifier les priorités immédiates de la mise en œuvre du socle européen des droits sociaux, au titre desquels figurent ceux des travailleurs des plateformes. Je souhaite également mentionner la seconde phase des consultations des partenaires sociaux, qui se terminera mercredi. Je suis sûre qu’elle sera riche d’enseignements. Dans ce contexte, je me réjouis que la majorité des groupes politiques se soient pour l’instant retrouvés sur la nécessité d’une action européenne et sur les besoins spécifiques des travailleurs des plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vais prendre quelques instants pour vous préciser les priorités de mon rapport. Premier point: un accès renforcé à la protection sociale. Je souhaite que, quel que soit leur statut, les travailleurs des plateformes bénéficient d’une protection sociale minimale. Cela veut dire notamment que tous les travailleurs des plateformes devraient avoir le droit de recevoir une indemnisation en cas d’accident du travail ou de maladie professionnelle et bénéficier d’une protection sociale comprenant une couverture d’assurance maladie et invalidité. Nous appelons également à étendre les droits à la protection sociale aux travailleurs des plateformes indépendantes, y compris aux personnes qui passent d’un statut à un autre ou qui ont les deux statuts, afin de garantir la portabilité des droits et des prestations. Nous avons déjà un instrument européen allant dans ce sens: la recommandation du Conseil sur l’accès des travailleurs salariés et non salariés à la protection sociale. Je souhaite souligner son importance pour les États membres, lesquels doivent la mettre en place sans tarder.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxième point: des conditions de travail améliorées, justes et transparentes. Les plateformes numériques de travail devraient garantir la communication des informations essentielles concernant les conditions de travail et les règles de coopération, la méthode de calcul du prix et l’attribution des tâches. Elles devraient également assurer la transparence en cas de modification des règles et avoir recours à des consultations. Il est également important que les travailleurs puissent avoir un droit de recours en cas de suspension de compte. Travailler pour plusieurs plateformes doit être aussi un droit pour eux, de même qu’avoir accès à leurs données.</p>
      <p sl="en">Troisième élément majeur: la représentation collective. La négociation collective est un élément clé pour l’amélioration des conditions de travail de ces travailleurs. Les travailleurs des plateformes, même indépendants, doivent pouvoir s’organiser et négocier collectivement. J’appelle la Commission européenne à préciser que les conventions collectives ne relèvent pas de l’interdiction du droit de la concurrence, afin de garantir que ces travailleurs des plateformes puissent se syndiquer, être représentés et participer aux négociations collectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quatrième élément: plus de sécurité juridique pour les travailleurs des plateformes et les plateformes. Cela a été un grand point de débat pour nous. Notre objectif devrait être d’aller vers plus de sécurité juridique pour les travailleurs des plateformes. Cela sera également favorable aux plateformes qui pourront se développer avec plus de clarté, mais aussi à l’économie dite traditionnelle, en garantissant des conditions de concurrence équitables. Une présomption réfragable d’une relation de travail encadrée devrait s’appliquer aux travailleurs qui contestent leur statut lors d’une procédure. Elle ne doit toutefois pas conduire à considérer automatiquement tous les travailleurs des plateformes comme des travailleurs salariés. Les travailleurs véritablement indépendants le resteront. Ce qui est également important est que nous proposons un renversement de la charge de la preuve afin que lorsqu’un travailleur de plateforme conteste son statut professionnel, ce soit à la partie dont il est allégué qu’elle est l’employeur de prouver qu’il n’existe pas de relation de travail. Enfin, soyons clairs, nous ne souhaitons pas de troisième statut pour les travailleurs des plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cinquième élément: un lieu de travail sain et sûr. Les travailleurs des plateformes, sur site, doivent être équipés d’équipements personnels de protection adéquats et être couverts par une assurance contre les accidents lorsqu’ils travaillent dans les secteurs du transport et de la livraison. Ils doivent également pouvoir se déconnecter de la plateforme sans subir de conséquences négatives. Nous souhaitons protéger les travailleurs des plateformes et les clients contre les risques de violence et de harcèlement en mettant en place des mécanismes de signalement efficaces sur les plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sixième élément: le développement des compétences – point très important aussi. Une formation devrait être dispensée aux travailleurs par la plateforme de travail numérique elle-même sur l’utilisation de son site ou de son application, les tâches à effectuer et la santé et la sécurité au travail. Les travailleurs des plateformes, en particulier les moins qualifiés, devraient accéder à des formations permettant d’acquérir des compétences et d’améliorer leur employabilité.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, septième élément, et non des moindres: une gestion algorithmique transparente, non discriminatoire et éthique. La gestion algorithmique a révolutionné le monde du travail. Il est clair que nous souhaitons assurer l’utilisation d’algorithmes qui soient transparents, non discriminatoires, éthiques et fiables. Pour réaliser cet objectif, il faut s’assurer que les informations principales sur les conditions de travail soient expliquées de manière intelligible. Il s’agit de paramètres de l’algorithme qui influent sur la répartition des tâches, les notations et les interactions, la procédure de désactivation et la tarification. De plus, cela paraît peut-être une évidence, mais la gestion algorithmique doit être contrôlée par des humains pour que les travailleurs puissent contester une décision via des procédures efficaces.</p>
      <p sl="en">En conclusion, chers collègues, clarifier les droits, augmenter les protections là où elles manquent, trouver le point d’équilibre entre les avantages et les inconvénients du travail de plateforme sont, je crois, autant d’objectifs qui ont été atteints avec ce rapport. Je salue à nouveau l’annonce de l’initiative législative de la Commission européenne pour améliorer les conditions de travail des travailleurs des plateformes, prévue pour le 8 décembre. Cela représentera une brique supplémentaire pour la construction de l’Europe sociale. Nous pouvons dire que le Parlement européen y contribue de manière volontaire, avec ce rapport, et nous espérons que la Commission en prendra note lorsqu’elle finalisera sa proposition.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Commissaire, agissons ensemble pour adapter le cadre européen aux nouvelles réalités du monde du travail en nous assurant que les valeurs européennes soient ancrées dans l’économie numérique et afin que les possibilités offertes par les nouvelles formes de travail restent durables et équitables. Oui au «digital», mais pas au détriment des conditions de travail des travailleurs des plateformes en Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Nicolas Schmit" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Monsieur le Président, Madame la rapporteure, je tiens d’abord à vous remercier pour ce rapport. Je dirais que ce Parlement adopte énormément de rapports importants qui contribuent au développement de notre vie économique et sociale, mais aussi à notre action internationale. Ce rapport s’inscrit dans une logique nouvelle qui est celle d’un développement économique particulier. C’est le numérique, c’est le «digital», ce sont des activités qui se sont développées, notamment, dans le contexte de la pandémie, avec une rapidité étonnante. Je dirais donc que ces activités et ces services que fournissent les plateformes correspondent à une demande réelle, puisque pratiquement chacun d’entre nous utilise de temps en temps, certains plus souvent – les jeunes, beaucoup – ces plateformes. Mais je sais aussi que ce sont les jeunes, précisément, puisque ce sont principalement des jeunes qui travaillent sur les plateformes, avec ou pour les plateformes, qui vont suivre nos débats et qui, surtout, ont des attentes par rapport aux conclusions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette Commission a pris un engagement fort. Madame la rapporteure, vous l’avez bien dit, il s’agit de développer l’économie numérique, et ce dans des conditions de respect des règles sociales, de la protection sociale, du droit du travail fondamental. Et donc, aujourd’hui, nous voyons que beaucoup de jeunes qui parcourent nos villes avec leurs vélos, leurs bicyclettes ou leurs motocyclettes parfois, n’ont aucune protection, aucune garantie. Et s’il leur arrive – et ça arrive souvent – un accident, ils se retrouvent sans rien et n’ont pas de protection santé. La pandémie, d’ailleurs, a fait apparaître plein de situations comparables en Europe, mais surtout aussi hors d’Europe. C’est pour cela que ce que nous faisons aujourd’hui avec votre rapport et ce que nous ferons avec une proposition sur les plateformes, ce sera pour l’Europe, mais ça ira au delà.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous voyons que les mêmes problèmes, les mêmes soucis et les mêmes demandes s’expriment un peu partout, y compris d’ailleurs, comme je l’ai dit, dans la partie du monde où, finalement, on a inventé l’économie numérique: en Californie. C’est pour cela que maintenant, il est temps d’agir. Il ne s’agit pas de diminuer l’importance de l’économie des plateformes, il s’agit de lui donner un cadre. Il s’agit tout d’abord de lui donner de la certitude juridique, parce qu’il n’est pas normal que, dans un marché intérieur, les règles soient telles dans certains pays et très différentes dans un autre, surtout quand il y a aussi des échanges par delà les frontières. C’est donc le premier élément.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le deuxième, c’est de donner de la certitude, de la garantie, de la sécurité à ceux qui travaillent pour les plateformes. Pour toutes ces centaines, voire ces millions de jeunes qui, peut-être pas principalement, mais occasionnellement, et souvent beaucoup, travaillent pour ces plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous avez bien énuméré les différentes dimensions qui sont d’abord le statut. Et là, je suis d’accord avec vous. Il ne s’agit pas d’imposer un statut. Il s’agit de garantir que, quel que soit le statut, chaque travailleur des plateformes ait des garanties en matière sociale. Et puis, nous ne pouvons pas être les objets de robots ou d’intelligence artificielle. Notre demande, c’est que l’intelligence artificielle ait une dimension humaine. Nous ne pouvons pas accepter que des travailleurs soient pilotés, jugés, évalués et, parfois, perdent leur emploi simplement parce que l’algorithme est programmé de telle manière.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons donc besoin d’un cadre pour que ce qu’on appelle la gestion par algorithme soit claire et que les droits des travailleurs soient établis, qu’il y ait de la transparence à cet égard. Donc, voilà des sujets dont nous aurons à traiter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je dois vous dire, Madame la rapporteure et tous ceux qui ont travaillé à ce rapport, que vous nous avez aidés. Vous avez identifié les questions, les problèmes, et vous avez ébauché les bonnes solutions, comme le renversement de la charge de la preuve, qui est un instrument pour apporter clarté et droits pour tous ceux qui travaillent sur les plateformes. Merci beaucoup, encore une fois.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vous savez qu’on est pratiquement, dirais-je, quotidiennement au travail. Aujourd’hui, j’avais deux réunions sur ce sujet et la Commission va venir à la fin de cette année avec une proposition qui, sûrement, s’inspirera du travail que vous avez accompli.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="199941" name="Marianne Vind" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ordfører for udtalelse fra Transport- og Turismeudvalget. – Hr. formand! I mere end 100 år har lønmodtagere over hele Europa kæmpet for retten til et godt arbejdsliv, men desværre er mange af de helt store landvindinger ved at blive rullet tilbage. Platformsvirksomheder som Uber, Wolt og det Deliveroo har nemlig ikke kun bragt innovation og nytænkning med sig, de har med i bagagen også taget usikre arbejdsforhold, der mest af alt ligner noget fra gamle dage. Det har i den grad ramt transportbranchen. Når chauffører og bude kører rundt uden forsikringer eller sikkerhedsudstyr, udsætter de sig for seriøse farer. Når tusindvis af mennesker sidder fast på uforudsigelige nultimerskontrakter, mister de jo muligheden for at planlægge deres egen hverdag, liv og økonomi. Det er simpelthen ikke godt nok. Vi kan gøre det meget bedre. Men nu drømmer platformsvirksomhederne om, at vi opretter en såkaldt "tredje kategori" imellem lønmodtagere og arbejdsgivere, så de kan fortsætte med at undvige almindeligt arbejdsgiveransvar. Den form for "lønmodtager light"-kategori vil være gift for Europas sociale arbejdsmarkedsmodel, og det skal vi som Parlament lægge skarp afstand til. Vi skal undgå A- og B-hold og slå fast, at en arbejdstager er en arbejdstager.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="197839" name="Radan Kanev" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I do generally support the idea of this report, and yet I see risks that I would like to share with you, especially vis-à-vis the legislative work that we will have at the end of this year and the beginning of the next.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, we are all committed to improving working conditions. We are all looking forward to quality employment and fair incomes on our continent. We share the same concerns that more and more of our younger citizens are sometimes working in insecurity and often even falling out of the social security and health systems, which is a great risk both for them and for the solidarity model as a whole. And yet we could not and we should not fight the achievements of digital technology through outmoded regulations.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have to see the risk that this Parliament might try to impose 19th-century metrics over 21st-century social relations. What is really most important for us is that we must accept the realities of the 21st-century labour market and then adjust our regulations to life rather than doing it the other way around.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="197618" name="Elisabetta Gualmini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, platform workers represent maybe the newest form of work of the new millennium. Their numbers have increased with no bounds. Let me say that we are not afraid of innovations. We are not afraid of these disturbing and dystonic times in which you click a button and a pizza meravigliosa arrives directly in your kitchen. We are not afraid even of flexibility – if it is a good thing.</p>
      <p sl="en">But innovations and transformations in the labour market have to move forward with social protection – the safeguarding of the dignity and safety of workers. Social rights are, at the very end of the day, human rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have been ambitious here. There is a three—step revolution going on. The rebuttable presumption of the employment relationship – if you have an obligation as an employee, you must have a right as an employee. There is no third way.</p>
      <p sl="en">We have put the burden and charge of solving eventual court conflicts between a platform and workers on the shoulders of platforms, of employers.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, transparency and clear information coming from algorithms. We do not want to see any more shameful salaries in what we call a ‘democratic Europe’. We don’t want to see new forms of slavery in what we call a ‘social Europe’. We don’t want to see forms of labour force exploitation and abuse in what we call a ‘fair Europe’.</p>
      <p sl="en">We do not ask much. We ask simply for a good balance between rights and duties, between economic growth and social compensation. We ask to build a new social, progressive, compassionate Europe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-0000" speaker_id="197663" name="Dragoş Pîslaru" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului Renew. – Domnule președinte, domnule comisar Nicolas Schmit, dragi colegi, vreau să încep prin a o felicita pe colega noastră din grupul Renew Europe, Sylvie Brunet, pentru munca excelentă pe care a depus-o pe acest raport de inițiativă. A reușit să găsească un echilibru excelent între două laturi ale unei dezbateri spinoase și cred cu tărie că acest text trebuie să ne servească drept exemplu pentru viitor. Cu siguranță trebuie să-i servească Comisiei Europene pentru propunerea legislativă la care lucrează.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cuvântul-cheie aici este echilibru. Echilibru între drepturile sociale solide, pentru care europenii s-au luptat zeci de ani, și spiritul de inovație și antreprenoriat în tehnologie, pentru care sper să nu fie nevoie să ne luptăm alte zeci de ani ca să îl păstrăm și să îl dezvoltăm.</p>
      <p sl="en">Adevărul pentru platforme este că spațiul legislativ vag a început să fie tot mai problematic. Niște principii generale care asigură o protecție de ambele părți ale relației de muncă sau colaborare sunt vitale pentru evitarea erorilor, abuzurilor, dar și a atacurilor împotriva platformelor digitale. Trebuie păstrat echilibrul și între tipurile de platforme, iar cerințele către companii trebuie adaptate la dimensiunile acestora.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sigur, e bine să avem principii generale de protecție și reprezentare pentru lucrătorii care colaborează cu ele, dar și spațiu pentru subsidiaritate pentru statele membre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cu siguranță, elementele cheie sunt transparența și accesul la deciziile de operare, la cadrul în care colaborarea cu platformele digitale este oferită și gestionată de către acestea. Cu scopul clar, și asta trebuie să o spunem foarte clar și răspicat, de a proteja lucrătorii și drepturile acestora.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dar la fel de importante sunt și predictibilitatea legală pentru antreprenori și investitori și spațiul de libertate pentru inovare. Flexibilitatea platformelor este ceea ce le face atractive pentru lucrători, dar și pentru utilizatori, și acestea nu trebuie îngrădite artificial sau din cauza fricii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Să nu uităm că platformele digitale au fost vitale în timpul pandemiei. Ele au ținut în viață zeci de mii de restaurante europene, de furnizori de servicii, au furnizat locuri de muncă și venituri, iar tocmai flexibilitatea lor a fost factorul-cheie în reziliența domeniului.</p>
      <p sl="en">Așteptăm, așadar, din partea Comisiei, o propunere care să fie atentă la aceste componente și care va fi gândită pentru viitor și pentru cetățeni, și nu motivată de fricile trecutului. Felicitări Silviei Brunet.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-0000" speaker_id="197870" name="Kim Van Sparrentak" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de Verts/ALE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, beste collega’s, geachte commissaris, ik wil eerst even de FNV en de Nederlandse Uberchauffeurs van harte feliciteren met de overwinning die ze vandaag behaalden in de rechtszaak tegen Uber. Uber moet zijn chauffeurs in dienst nemen en bovendien het achterstallige loon uitbetalen. Dit is een geweldig resultaat.</p>
      <p sl="en">I will now continue in English. The verdict in the Netherlands adds to over 100 court cases across the EU, and with these court cases platform workers simply ask to be treated the same way as other workers, with the same social benefits and opportunities, and the cases have overwhelmingly been won by the platform workers. You might think that Uber, Glovo, Deliveroo and other platforms would then bury the hatchet, play nice and hire their workers. But instead they do everything to keep operating outside of the law or to even change the rules in their favour with workers paying the price. And in the long run we actually all risk paying the price because this business model undermines our social security system.</p>
      <p sl="en">Platform workers going to court are fighting an uphill battle against the platforms’ army of lawyers and resources, and that is why we, the lawmakers, need to step in, and that is why I am very pleased with this report because we give a clear mandate to the European Commission for strict rules and to once and for all tell these platforms how we protect their workers and that we have a model based on solidarity. That’s why I also really would like to thank my shadow co-rapporteurs and the rapporteur for the great cooperation while writing this report, because if we stand together we can really make a social Europe happen.</p>
      <p sl="en">So what do we want? We start by putting in place a presumption of employment relationship for platform workers. This may sound complicated but it simply means that it should be up to platforms to prove that someone is really an entrepreneur instead of the workers. And for me, it’s quite simple. If it looks like a duck and quacks like a duck, it’s likely a duck. So why give workers some basic rights rather than the full rights of an employee? It shouldn’t matter when you are cleaning someone’s house if you’ve been hired through a platform or an agency: you should have the same rights. And next it is important to clarify what distinguishes these platform workers from other workers and namely the fact that an algorithm dictates what happens. A Dutch judge explained today being subject to an algorithm is modern employers’ control. Workers are constantly tracked, monitored, evaluated and even fired by algorithms without even knowing why the algorithm assigns them certain tasks and what the price is actually based on, and as a result platform workers are under extreme stress.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need to protect workers against algorithmic management. Workers must be able to know that not only does an algorithm exist, but also how it assigns tasks and sets the prices. Important HR decisions should always be made by a person and not a computer. These issues are not sufficiently dealt with in the AIF and have to be addressed in the Directive on platform work.</p>
      <p sl="en">Colleagues, it is important that we have this legislation and when it comes to the future of work and the future of a social model this is one of the first battlegrounds; the outcome will be important for how we will regulate the labour market in the future.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="189065" name="France Jamet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Monsieur le Président, Madame le rapporteur, mes chers collègues, quand je vous entends, quand j’entends ce catalogue de vœux pieux: clarifier les droits des travailleurs sur les plateformes, trouver des points d’équilibre, garantir la protection sociale, gérer les algorithmes, vous me faites penser à la citation célèbre de Jean Cocteau: «Ces mystères nous dépassent, feignons d’en être les organisateurs». Mais le scandale de la condition des travailleurs des plateformes n’est pas seulement une affaire de droit du travail. C’est d’abord et surtout un choix de civilisation.</p>
      <p sl="en">À l’ère du progrès technique, les plateformes dont l’ère numérique a permis l’avènement déstructurent les institutions, déconstruisent les conventions et désintègrent les avancées sociales. Sous couvert de liberté et d’auto-entrepreneuriat, leurs promoteurs osent vanter un nouvel esclavagisme qui ne dit pas son nom.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’État nation seul peut mettre au pas ces grands féodaux. L’État nation seul permettra à un peuple de décider comment l’économie et le progrès technologique doivent servir nos forces vives et non le contraire. L’État nation seul permettra l’exercice réel de la démocratie et de la souveraineté populaire face aux multinationales qui entendent nous imposer leurs choix mortifères. L’État nation seul permettra de se tourner vers l’avenir et non de revenir à des modèles d’exploitation d’un autre temps. L’État nation, c’est la liberté et c’est cette liberté pour laquelle nous nous battons et nous devons nous battre. C’est un combat que l’Union européenne a vraisemblablement abandonné. C’est peut-être même un combat que l’Union européenne a tout simplement refusé de livrer.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="197544" name="Elżbieta Rafalska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Brak jest dokładnych danych na temat skali zjawiska pracy na platformach. Jednocześnie popyt na takie elastyczne rozwiązania rośnie bardzo dynamicznie, a pandemia jeszcze przyspiesza ten proces. Wiele osób pracujących na platformach to pracownicy zależni lub osoby samozatrudnione w innych dziedzinach, wykonujące drobne prace lub prace na żądanie. Powinny one korzystać z praw pracowniczych, jeżeli zgodnie z prawem danego państwa członkowskiego wykonywana przez nie praca spełnia warunki właściwe dla stosunku pracy. Kwestie stosunku pracy regulowane są przez krajowe kodeksy pracy. Proponowany jest wzruszalny, domniemany stosunek pracy. Tym samym grupa osób, tj. osoby świadczące usługi za pośrednictwem platform cyfrowych, byłaby wyróżniona, inaczej traktowana w stosunku do innych osób świadczących usługi, w szczególności samozatrudnionych, wobec których takiego domniemania się nie stosuje.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ogranicza się również swobodę wyboru umowy przez strony. Nie nakładajmy dodatkowych obowiązków na państwa członkowskie, zmniejszając konkurencyjność ich gospodarek. Nie możemy ingerować w kształt systemu zabezpieczenia społecznego. Prawo pracy to kompetencja państw członkowskich. Unia Europejska może interweniować tylko w zakresie swobodnego przepływu pracowników i równego traktowania. W związku z tym działania w zakresie platform powinny być rozwiązywane na szczeblu państw, a nie Unii Europejskiej.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-092-0000" speaker_id="197529" name="Leila Chaibi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe The Left. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, nous devons mettre un terme à une situation frauduleuse où des plateformes se présentent comme des simples intermédiaires entre un travailleur indépendant et un client, alors qu’en réalité elles décident des tarifs, elles décident des sanctions et elles décident des méthodes de travail, tout ça sans assumer leurs obligations d’employeur. Pour y remédier, le Parlement fait dans ce rapport une proposition. Il faut une présomption de salariat pour les travailleurs des plateformes numériques. Une présomption de salariat liée à un renversement de la charge de la preuve.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et la définition du mot présomption est sans ambiguïté. Du latin praesumere, prendre d’avance, la présomption de salariat signifie que les travailleurs sont considérés comme salariés des plateformes numériques dès le premier jour de la relation de travail, sans qu’ils aient besoin d’aller devant les tribunaux pour faire valoir leurs droits. Cela ne signifie pas, bien évidemment, que tous les travailleurs des plateformes doivent être des employés. Il existe des cas où les plateformes sont réellement des intermédiaires, je pense par exemple à la plateforme Doctolib. Dans ce cas, c’est à la plateforme d’apporter les preuves qu’elle n’exerce sur les travailleurs aucun lien de subordination et ils gardent alors leur statut d’indépendant.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si nous vous demandons d’agir, Monsieur le Commissaire, ce n’est donc pas pour forcer les indépendants à se salarier. Si nous vous pressons, c’est d’abord pour remédier à l’extrême précarité des chauffeurs VTC et des livreurs de repas en deux-roues. Mais c’est aussi, et surtout, pour l’ensemble du monde du travail: si aujourd’hui, nous permettons à Uber d’avoir des travailleurs sous ses ordres sans assumer sa responsabilité d’employeur, demain, c’est tous les salariés dont le statut sera menacé de remplacement par un faux indépendant.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="197792" name="Daniela Rondinelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la risoluzione che ci apprestiamo a votare ha una valenza storica, perché il Parlamento prende una posizione netta a difesa dei lavoratori delle piattaforme, vittime di sfruttamento e precarietà basati su indeterminatezza giuridica, salari indecenti, algoritmi opachi e pervasivi.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo è fondamentale una direttiva europea che sancisca in modo inequivocabile che i lavoratori delle piattaforme sono lavoratori subordinati, invertendo l'onere della prova in capo alle aziende, esigendo trasparenza e accessibilità sugli algoritmi ed eliminando ogni riferimento a un "terzo status" che potrebbe aprire la via a nuove forme di dumping fiscale e salariale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Come Movimento 5 Stelle esprimiamo soddisfazione per aver contribuito in modo decisivo alla versione finale di questa risoluzione, grazie ai nostri emendamenti che sono stati tutti inclusi nei compromessi.</p>
      <p sl="en">La nuova direttiva sarà l'architrave, insieme a quelle su diritto alla disconnessione e salario minimo, su cui edificare una ripresa socialmente equa, assicurando tutele al passo con le trasformazioni del mercato del lavoro per realizzare il nuovo modello sociale europeo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-0000" speaker_id="197672" name="Eugen Tomac" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamnă președintă, domnule comisar, felicit raportorul pentru că răspunde prin acest document unei urgențe și cred că este esențial să tratăm cu multă responsabilitate, atât noi, cât și Comisia, pentru că acest domeniu are nevoie de o reglementare urgentă. Avansul tehnologic a permis economiei digitale să se dezvolte într-un timp rapid. Însă nu sunt puține vulnerabilitățile pe care le observăm cu toții.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tocmai de aceea cred că este esențial ca Comisia Europeană, într-un timp cât mai scurt, să vină cu o inițiativă legislativă pentru a le putea oferi celor care desfășoară activități în acest domeniu garanții reale. Acești oameni desfășoară activități lucrative și au nevoie de reglementări foarte clare pentru a fi protejați.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dar nu doar cei care desfășoară și dezvoltă platforme online au nevoie de aceste reglementări legale. Este vital ca și consumatorul final să fie protejat de reglementările pe care statele membre le așteaptă din partea Uniunii Europene. Cred că este absolut esențial să înțelegem că avansul tehnologic ne-a pus în față noi provocări, iar noi trebuie să ținem pasul cu aceste așteptări pe care le are societatea din partea noastră.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-0000" speaker_id="125021" name="Agnes Jongerius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, commissaris, we staan hier op wat mij betreft een prettige dag, omdat we vandaag in Nederland een belangrijke overwinning hebben behaald voor de bescherming van platformwerknemers. De rechtbank van Amsterdam oordeelde dat Uber zijn chauffeurs als werknemer in dienst moet nemen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nu moeten we doorpakken met regelgeving voor alle platforms zoals Uber, Temper en Deliveroo, want ze rollen allemaal hetzelfde verdienmodel in één keer uit over heel Europa en dus moeten we voor een Europees antwoord zorgen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Voor ons is het duidelijk dat platformwerkers recht hebben op een eerlijk loon, op sociale bescherming en op pensioen. We kunnen dit bereiken door de bewijslast om te draaien. Niet langer de platformwerkers moeten naar de rechter stappen, maar het platform. Platformwerkers zullen automatisch gewoon werknemers zijn en zullen niet langer individueel hun rechten moeten gaan opeisen. Op deze manier is het voor iedereen duidelijk dat ze goed beschermd worden. Zo sturen we de platformeconomie de eerlijke kant op.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik reken op een sterk voorstel van de commissaris. Begin december gaan we door met dit debat, maar eerst gaan we woensdag stemmen en met veel plezier in de goede richting.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="197848" name="Атидже Алиева-Вели (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Г-жо Председател, уважаеми колеги, г-н Комисар, на първо място, бих искала да поздравя докладчика Силви Бруней. С огромно желание подкрепям доклада относно справедливите условия на труд, права и социална закрила на работещите през платформи, защото той предоставя актуалните предизвикателства и възможности за такъв вид работа и необходимостта от осигуряване на подобрени и прозрачни условия на труд за работещите.</p>
      <p sl="en">Работата през платформа обхваща различни реалности и се характеризира с висока степен и разнородност в извършваните дейности. COVID-19 ни изправи пред много предизвикателства, едно от които бе да запазим колкото се може повече бизнеси и да им създадем възможности за по-лесна, бърза и успешна адаптация към пандемичните и постпандемичните условия. Огромна част от успелите да продължат дейността си предприятия използваха различни цифрови платформи, за да избегнат временни затваряния и фалити. Вярвам, че работата на платформа засяга огромен дял от работниците. Немалка част от хората загубили работата си се преориентираха към заетост през различни платформи. Други, които имаха временна или непълна заетост, също успяха да се възползват от избора и безпрецедентната гъвкавост, която този вид заетост предлага.</p>
      <p sl="en">Разбира се, не по-малко достоен за отбелязване е фактът, че работата през платформи предлага предимства за учащите, за тези, които желаят да съчетаят учене и работа. В период, когато младите бяха засегнати изключително много и когато всеки шести младеж беше останал без работа заради пандемията, този тип заетост създаде възможности за тях. За съжаление работниците през платформи обикновено биват определяни като формално заети или самонаети лица, независимо от действителното им положение по отношение на заетостта. Поради това много на брой работещи не се ползват от еквивалентна социална закрила, трудови права или разпоредби за здраве и безопасност. В така актуалния преход към цифровизация е от съществено значение да се гарантира, че новите форми на труд ще останат устойчиви, прозрачни и справедливи, а работата през платформа ще се ръководи от ценностите на Съюза и от ориентиран към човека подход.</p>
      <p sl="en">Моята делегация винаги е подкрепяла обещаващи и иновативни политики за бъдещето, които представят нови възможности за социално включване на всички работоспособни лица без място за дискриминация. Ще продължим да работим за създаване на още повече възможности, които новите условия на труд и форми на работа да предлагат, като в същото време се спазват социалните и трудовите права.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-0000" speaker_id="197500" name="Mounir Satouri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, Madame la rapporteure, chers collègues, le 6 mai 2021, Chahi, livreur, livre un repas près de Rouen, à vélo, sous la pluie. Il travaille pour Uber Eats. Chahi, sous pression, est renversé.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce père de famille aurait-il perdu la vie si la plateforme avait assumé ses responsabilités d’employeur? Si la plateforme avait assuré la sécurité du vélo et de son équipement? Si elle lui avait permis de travailler non pas au rabais, à la course, mais avec une garantie de salaire?</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous, législateurs, avons une responsabilité envers Chahi et les 24 millions de personnes qui travaillent pour des plateformes numériques de ce type: celle de rendre effectif le droit du travail, des droits acquis de haute lutte, pour elles et pour eux. Je me félicite que ce Parlement s’apprête à appeler la Commission européenne à introduire une présomption de relation de travail et à renverser la charge de la preuve devant le juge.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quand on voit que les travailleurs sont aux ordres d’algorithmes qui les mettent en compétition avec d’autres travailleurs, quand on voit qu’ils sont soumis à des pressions de temps de plus en plus fortes et à des prix dictés toujours vers le bas, nous devons imposer aux plateformes de prendre leurs responsabilités. Ce n’est pas aux travailleurs de prouver le salariat, c’est à la plateforme de s’en défendre. Oui au numérique pour le progrès social. Non à la gestion du travail par des algorithmes sans surveillance humaine et dans l’exploitation des plus vulnérables. Oui, au travail réellement indépendant, non aux salariés déguisés et à la «disproportionnalisation» des employeurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Derrière ce rapport, de nombreuses personnes espèrent que l’Europe va enfin freiner la libéralisation irresponsable de leur travail. Pour eux et pour les victimes comme Chahi, soyons à la hauteur.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-0000" speaker_id="197586" name="Stefania Zambelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, sono oltre 10 000 in Italia i lavoratori delle piattaforme digitali, i cosiddetti rider.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si parla di un giro d'affari da 900 milioni di euro. In Europa ce ne sono più di 100 000, è un lavoro in continua espansione e di facile accesso per tutti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia le persone impegnate in questo tipo di lavoro, la maggior parte delle volte sono ragazzi molto giovani, devono lavorare con lunghissimi turni notturni, vengono pagati 2 euro a consegna, non hanno nessun giorno di malattia, non hanno nessun giorno di ferie e non sono assicurati in caso di incidente. Pensate, sono sulla strada 10 o 12 ore tutto il giorno. Non c'è Pasqua, non c'è Natale, non c'è l'ultimo dell'anno, lavorano il sabato e la domenica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Purtroppo, a causa di questa crisi economica e della disoccupazione, ci sono molti padri di famiglia costretti a fare questo tipo di lavoro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dobbiamo garantire tutti insieme maggior dignità per questi lavoratori e soprattutto maggiori diritti. Tutto ciò deve essere fatto nel rispetto delle norme europee e degli ordinamenti dei singoli Stati membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-0000" speaker_id="197538" name="Beata Mazurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Nowe technologie ułatwiają nam życie w wielu aspektach. Tak też jest z platformami internetowymi. Ich funkcjonowanie przynosi wiele korzyści zarówno dla klientów, jak i osób, które na nich zarabiają. Popyt na pracę na platformach online rośnie bardzo szybko i szacuje się, że coraz więcej osób będzie szukać pracy za ich pośrednictwem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Informacje, które posiadamy są jednak niewystarczające. Nie ma dokładnych danych na temat rzeczywistej skali pracy na platformach. Dodatkowo pandemia i praca zdalna znacząco zmieniły naszą rzeczywistość.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sprawozdanie zwraca uwagę na wprowadzenie zharmonizowanych przepisów na poziomie Unii Europejskiej, które swoim zakresem obejmą zawody wykonywane za pomocą platform internetowych. Musimy jednak zadać sobie pytanie, czy takie działania, które narzucą dodatkowe obowiązki na państwa członkowskie, nie obniżą konkurencyjności ich gospodarek i nie będą ingerować w kształt systemów zabezpieczenia społecznego, bo te są kompetencją wyłącznie państw członkowskich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oczywiście należy chronić każdego pracownika niezależnie od tego, w jaki sposób podejmuje pracę. Trzeba się jednak zastanowić, czy działania podejmowane w stosunku do pracowników platform powinny być wdrażane na szczeblu unijnym. To po pierwsze. Po drugie, jeśli istniejące instrumenty prawne nie są stosowane – co wybrzmiało w trakcie prac nad sprawozdaniem – to najpierw należy zrobić wszystko, by stosować istniejące prawo, a nie przygotowywać nowe.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="197571" name="Nikolaj Villumsen (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Ingen ret til dagpenge, ingen ret til pension, ingen beskyttelse hvis uheldet er ude. Det er virkeligheden for millioner af europæiske lønmodtagere, der arbejder på digitale platforme. Det er virkeligheden for budene hos Wolt. Det er virkeligheden for chaufførerne hos Nemlig.com. Mens ejerne har tjent milliarder og atter milliarder under Coronakrisen, har bude, chauffører og rengøringsfolk knoklet under kummerlige vilkår. Alt for mange arbejdsgivere gemmer sig bag platformenes digitale slør. De nægter deres ansatte helt grundlæggende rettigheder. De fratager dem sågar retten til at stå i fagforening, når de fejlagtigt påstår, at deres ansatte er selvstændige. Derfor er mit budskab til arbejdsgiverne bag det digitale slør i Nemlig.com og i Wolt i dag klart: Stop brugen af falske selvstændige, giv jeres ansatte de rettigheder, de fortjener. Respektér retten til faglig organisering!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="197734" name="Λευτέρης Νικολάου-Αλαβάνος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, η παρούσα έκθεση μαρτυρά ότι δεν σας προβληματίζουν οι τραγικοί όροι εργασίας στις πλατφόρμες αλλά το γεγονός ότι οι όμιλοι Ηνωμένων Πολιτειών, Αμερικής και Κίνας καρπώνονται τη μερίδα του λέοντος από τα κέρδη στον κλάδο της ψηφιακής οικονομίας. Γι’ αυτό προωθείτε το αίσχος της λεγόμενης ευέλικτης εργασίας, με στόχο να ενισχύσετε την κερδοφορία των ευρωπαϊκών ομίλων. Αυτό που είναι ανάγκη να κατοχυρωθεί είναι τα πλήρη εργασιακά και ασφαλιστικά δικαιώματα, επτάωρο – πενθήμερο – τριανταπεντάωρο, με αύξηση των αποδοχών. Η ελευθερία συνδικαλιστικής δράσης, οι συλλογικές συμβάσεις εργασίας, το δικαίωμα στην απεργία, ειδικά μέτρα υγιεινής κι ασφάλειας ανάλογα με τη φύση της εργασίας, όλα όσα δηλαδή η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση συστηματικά ξηλώνει, με τις «βέλτιστες πρακτικές» της που αποτυπώνονται σε νομοθετικά εκτρώματα, όπως ο νόμος Χατζηδάκη της Κυβέρνησης της ΝΔ.</p>
      <p sl="en">Μπροστά στις απαιτήσεις των ομίλων, με όπλο και την τηλεργασία, για εξουθενωτική δουλειά, χωρίς δικαιώματα, τις οποίες υλοποιούν όλα τα αστικά κόμματα, οι εργαζόμενοι πρέπει να οργανώσουν την πάλη τους φέρνοντας στο προσκήνιο τις σύγχρονες ανάγκες τους, για να μείνουν στα χαρτιά τα αντεργατικά εκτρώματα, για να μπουν εμπόδια στον εργασιακό μεσαίωνα που προετοιμάζετε!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="197692" name="Στέλιος Κυμπουρόπουλος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κύριε Επίτροπε, όπως όλοι κατανοούμε, η φύση της εργασίας αλλάζει, με την τεχνολογία να παρέχει σε εργαζόμενους σε πλατφόρμες δυνατότητα ευελιξίας σχετικά με τον τύπο και τον χρόνο της εργασίας τους, αλλά και ένα πρόσθετο εισόδημα. Ταυτόχρονα, η αξιοποίηση εφαρμογών αλγορίθμων και της τεχνητής νοημοσύνης δημιουργούν καινοτόμες υπηρεσίες προς όφελος καταναλωτών και επιχειρήσεων. Φάνηκε περίτρανα, κατά τη διάρκεια της πανδημίας, όταν χιλιάδες εργαζόμενοι σε πλατφόρμες κράτησαν στη ζωή αρκετές επιχειρήσεις, όπως στον τομέα της εστίασης. Ωστόσο, αυτό που δεν πρέπει να αλλάξει είναι η βούλησή μας να διασφαλίσουμε ότι αυτοί οι εργαζόμενοι θα έχουν τα ίδια δικαιώματα με εκείνους στην παραδοσιακή οικονομία. Οφείλουμε να διασφαλίσουμε την υγεία και ασφάλεια των εργαζομένων σε πλατφόρμες, την πρόσβαση τους σε ιατροφαρμακευτική περίθαλψη και σε υπηρεσίες κοινωνικής πρόνοιας αλλά και την αποτελεσματική εφαρμογή των δικαιωμάτων τους στη συλλογική εκπροσώπηση. Κυρίως όμως εμείς, ως νομοθέτες, θα πρέπει να φροντίσουμε ώστε η νομοθεσία να συμβαδίζει με την ταχύτητα των τεχνολογικών εξελίξεων αλλά και να κατανοήσουμε την ευρύτητα των πλατφορμών, μέσω της συλλογής επικαιροποιημένων στοιχείων για αυτή τη μορφή απασχόλησης. Κλείνοντας λοιπόν, καλώ την Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή να καταθέσει άμεσα νομοθετική πρόταση, η οποία θα αποσαφηνίζει τις υπάρχουσες νομικές αβεβαιότητες, διασφαλίζοντας παράλληλα δίκαιες συνθήκες εργασίας για τους εργαζόμενους σε πλατφόρμες.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-0000" speaker_id="202073" name="Marc Angel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in the European Union too many workers are living in poverty and they suffer because of social exclusion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Work, platform work included, must become the tool again for all to combat poverty. Today this is not yet the case. The growing digital economy has great potential for job creation, but these jobs must be quality jobs instead of precarious jobs. New forms of work must become a synonym of equal rights and better work—life balance.</p>
      <p sl="en">We Socialists and Democrats, together with the trade unions and civil society, will never accept that platform workers are a sub—category or a new category of workers. To prevent social dumping, platform workers deserve social rights, health and safety protection, fair working conditions and the right to collective bargaining – and therefore we need ambitious EU legislation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Here we have the opportunity to make social progress for the next generation by empowering platform workers. Our aim is a more resilient and a more social Union where vulnerable categories of workers have no place.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="197502" name="Marie-Pierre Vedrenne (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, tout d’abord, je remercie chaleureusement Mme la rapporteure, Sylvie Brunet, pour le travail qu’elle a accompli. Le Parlement européen, avec elle, avec vous tous, chers collègues, envoie un message clair: les travailleurs des plateformes ne doivent pas être des laissés-pour-compte du droit du travail. Qu’ils aient un statut d’indépendant ou de salarié, il est temps d’être à la hauteur du modèle social européen et de garantir à tous ces travailleurs des conditions de travail décentes, une rémunération juste et équitable, ainsi que l’accès à la protection sociale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a déjà près de trois ans, les États membres ont adopté au Conseil une recommandation pour garantir à tous les travailleurs, salariés ou non, l’accès à la protection sociale. Malheureusement, malgré les engagements pris, cette recommandation est restée lettre morte. Que constatons-nous? La précarité de nombreux travailleurs des plateformes. Vous l’avez dit, Monsieur le Commissaire: à nous d’agir, de changer cet état de fait. Mais ne jetons pas l’opprobre sur les plateformes qui peuvent permettre l’entrée sur le marché du travail d’Européens qui pouvaient en être éloignés. Il nous revient, à nous législateurs, d’encadrer cette nouvelle forme de travail pour que travailler pour Uber ou Deliveroo soit synonyme d’accès aux droits sociaux, à la protection sociale et à une rémunération décente.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cette directive à venir devra en effet non seulement offrir un ensemble de droits, comme le congé de maladie, mais également penser le travail de plateforme comme un possible tremplin vers d’autres emplois. Cela signifie que les travailleurs doivent avoir un compte formation qui leur permettra d’acquérir de nouvelles compétences et d’évoluer vers de nouveaux emplois.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons dit et répété que la transition vers un monde numérique ne doit laisser personne sur le bord du chemin. À nous de le prouver. Conditions de travail décentes, droit du travail, droits syndicaux, accès à la protection sociale, accès à la formation: autant de droits que nous devons garantir à tous, quel que soit le lien contractuel qui unit ces femmes et ces hommes à leur employeur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Soyons à la hauteur de nos promesses et démontrons à nos concitoyens que nous nous battons pour notre modèle social, pour un modèle social qui ne soit pas réservé à une partie seulement des travailleurs européens. Tous doivent être protégés. Il s’agit d’un impératif social. Par ailleurs, qu’aurions-nous fait sans ces travailleurs de première ligne lors de la crise du COVID?</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, Monsieur le Commissaire, je vous sais de notre côté, faisons honneur à nos valeurs et à notre engagement pour le progrès social. La balle est maintenant dans votre camp. Le rapport de Sylvie Brunet est une excellente base, utilisons-le.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-0000" speaker_id="208722" name="Sara Matthieu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, collega's, commissaris, een fietskoerier is onderweg met een pizza naar jouw thuis, maar krijgt een ongeval en heeft geen verzekering. Een Uberchauffeur wordt op staande voet ontslagen omdat hij eventjes niet online was en heeft geen recht op een uitkering. Platformwerkers hebben vandaag amper bescherming, want het zijn zogezegd zelfstandigen. Maar collega's, niets is minder waar. Nochtans hebben alle werknemers in de Europese Unie recht op gelijke arbeidsrechten en op bescherming van veiligheid en gezondheid op het werk. Althans in theorie. Onze koeriers en onze maaltijdbezorgers zijn geen zelfstandigen. Zij werken in dienst van grote multinationals. Die ongelijke behandeling is niet te verantwoorden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ik roep de Commissie op om het standpunt van het Parlement te steunen en eindelijk werk te maken van die gelijke bescherming. De update van de regels rond bescherming van veiligheid en gezondheid op het werk is daarvoor een unieke kans. Collega's, het gaat over 24 miljoen mensen die soms door weer en wind gaan voor hun job en die vandaag bescherming verdienen. Een taxi nemen of een pizza bestellen, dat moet in Europa zonder schuldgevoel kunnen, maar met een correct statuut voor de platformmedewerkers. Laten we daar dan ook samen eindelijk werk van maken.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="197488" name="Guido Reil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir reden heute über die sogenannte Plattformarbeit. Dabei geht es um Menschen, die zum Beispiel für die Apps Lieferando oder MyHammer arbeiten, aber auch um Menschen, die Businessübersetzungen anbieten und komplexe IT-Lösungen. Die allermeisten von ihnen bieten das als Nebentätigkeit an. Und genau diese Menschen hat die Europäische Kommission jetzt als die neuen Arbeitssklaven des 21. Jahrhunderts erkannt. Und genau diese Menschen müssen geschützt werden – natürlich muss die Kommission neue Regeln fordern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dumm ist nur, dass in Deutschland zum Beispiel die Bertelsmann Stiftung genau in diesem Bereich überhaupt keine Probleme sieht. Die Bertelsmann Stiftung sagt: Diese Menschen sind jünger, besser ausgebildet und verdienen auch mehr als andere. Und auch die Verbandsvorsitzenden der Plattformarbeiter sehen überhaupt keine Probleme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich sehe ein Problem. Ich sehe ein Problem in diesem Bericht, denn ich vermisse einen ganz wichtigen Faktor in diesem Bericht. In diesem ganzen Bericht steht nicht ein Wort über LGBTIQ und über Gender! Dabei heißt die wichtigste App, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, my-hammer.de! My-hammer.de – ich kann es kaum ertragen! Und es gibt keinen Aufschrei, keine Demonstration, keine hüpfenden Teenager. My-hammer.de, dafür steht die Plattformarbeit, und trotzdem nicht ein Wort über LGBTIQ und nicht ein Wort über Gendergerechtigkeit in Ihrem Bericht. Das ist ein Skandal. Ich fordere Sie auf: Lassen Sie uns gemeinsam – unterm Regenbogen – für die LGBTIQ-Gerechtigkeit und Gendergerechtigkeit bei der Plattformarbeit sorgen!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-0000" speaker_id="197785" name="Eugenia Rodríguez Palop (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, señor comisario, oímos hablar de flexibilidad y optimización, de recursos, de desarrollo tecnológico y nuevas fórmulas de empleo, pero la realidad pulveriza la ingeniería publicitaria de la economía de plataformas, un modelo construido para el dumping fiscal y el dumping social, o sea, a partir de la negación de los derechos laborales y la elusión de impuestos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por eso, en primer lugar, hay que reconocer la presunción de laboralidad de nuestros trabajadores en línea con la jurisprudencia europea: que, a estas alturas de la lucha, nuestra lucha no sea ampliar nuestros derechos, sino reconocernos como trabajadores, ya nos dice algo. Los abultados beneficios de estas empresas salen de la precariedad y la temporalidad de sus contratos, es decir, de la explotación de sus trabajadores.</p>
      <p sl="en">En segundo lugar, la gestión de los algoritmos tiene que ser transparente, porque esos algoritmos hoy vigilan, discriminan y vulneran derechos individuales y colectivos, pero nadie responde por ellos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y, en tercer lugar, con la economía de plataformas se están reduciendo nuestros ingresos fiscales y por cotizaciones. O eso se corrige o no habrá equilibrio financiero ni protección social para nadie.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-108-0000" speaker_id="96829" name="Ádám Kósa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Asszony! Szükség van az innovatív megoldásokra és a fogyasztók is szívesen használnak applikációkat különféle szolgáltatások megrendelésére. A platform-munkavállalóknak is joga van az egészséges és biztonságos munkakörülményekhez, a szociális ellátáshoz, továbbképzéshez, valamint méltányos és átlátható fizetésekhez. Ugyanakkor sokszor önfoglalkoztatók ők, figyelni kell arra, hogy ez részükről ne kényszer legyen, ugyanakkor tiszteletben kell tartani azoknak a döntéseit is, akik így akarnak dolgozni. Ne feledjük, hogy a Covid-világjárvány alatt sokak életét segítette meg ez a foglalkoztatási forma, sokan így jutottak jövedelemhez.</p>
      <p sl="en">Végül jobban figyelembe kell venni a kkv-k érdekeit, mert ezek képezik az európai gazdaság gerincét, az összes uniós vállalkozás 99 százalékát. Ezért sajnálatosnak tartom, hogy a jelentés mindössze két helyen említi meg a kkv-kat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="188945" name="Dennis Radtke" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Vizepräsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! In den letzten Jahren ist eine Menge über die fundamentalen Veränderungen in der Arbeitswelt geredet worden, die durch Digitalisierung und Plattformökonomie schlicht und ergreifend stattgefunden haben. In dieser Woche haben wir aber die Chance, nicht nur über diese wichtigen Veränderungen zu reden, sondern auch ein echtes Ausrufezeichen zu setzen und der Kommission gegenüber unsere Erwartungshaltung deutlich zu machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">In den letzten Wochen und Monaten haben wir in der Arbeit an deinem Bericht, liebe Sylvie, in der Mitte dieses Hauses einige gute Kompromisse gefunden, die aus meiner Sicht, wenn die Kommission auch bereit ist, sie in ihrem Vorschlag aufzugreifen, ein echter game changer sein könnten, weil sie auf der einen Seite dazu führen, dass wir die Dynamiken in der Plattformökonomie nicht abwürgen, dass gerade die Hochqualifizierten, die als Selbstständige unterwegs sind und auch Selbstständige bleiben wollen, sozusagen außen vor bleiben, während wir auf der anderen Seite jetzt endlich, endlich für all diejenigen, die regelrecht in die Scheinselbstständigkeit gepresst worden sind, rechtliche Mittel zur Verfügung stellen, um ihnen den Status und den Schutz zukommen zu lassen, der ihnen gebührt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Denn das, was wir da in vielen Bereichen sehen können, das hat doch nichts mit Unternehmertum zu tun. Also dort, wo ein Algorithmus sozusagen den Arbeitsalltag von Menschen bestimmt, kann man ja nicht von echter Selbstständigkeit und echtem Unternehmertum sprechen, sondern hier geht es schlicht und ergreifend darum, unternehmerisches Risiko auf andere abzuwälzen. Und solche Modelle können und wollen wir nicht tolerieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und auch hinsichtlich des Algorithmus wollen wir mehr Transparenz gegenüber den Beschäftigten haben. Das, was wir hier vorgelegt haben, ist eine echte Steilvorlage für dich, lieber Nicolas, und deswegen werbe ich nicht nur um Zustimmung, sondern bitte auch wirklich um ein deutliches Signal. Nicht knappe Mehrheiten werden bei der Kommission verstanden, sondern nur deutliche Mehrheiten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="198329" name="Estrella Durá Ferrandis" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, señor comisario, la digitalización y la aplicación de la inteligencia artificial en el contexto laboral están generando nuevos modelos que conllevan una clara precarización, hiperconexión, control y vigilancia o decisiones algorítmicas sin supervisión humana.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las implicaciones a nivel de salud mental y bienestar emocional de los trabajadores son ya evidentes, y necesitamos ya nueva legislación: una directiva para prevenir los riesgos psicosociales en el contexto laboral y una directiva que regule el uso de la inteligencia artificial en los lugares de trabajo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para ello, la Comisión debe escuchar y reunirse con todas las partes, empresas y sindicatos, porque los trabajadores no necesitan psicólogos, sino condiciones de trabajo dignas, trabajo seguro y de calidad. La digitalización del contexto laboral no puede ser un proceso exclusivamente tecnológico; debe ser un proceso sociotécnico, donde tecnología y humanismo vayan de la mano.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="197593" name="Véronique Trillet-Lenoir (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, cher Nicolas Schmit, je tiens tout d’abord à m’associer aux félicitations qui ont été faites et à saluer l’excellent travail de notre rapporteure et amie Sylvie Brunet. Le texte que nous nous apprêtons à voter est important pour des millions de travailleurs des plateformes, souvent des jeunes. Il propose une voie à suivre pour que la flexibilité de travail inhérente aux plateformes rime aussi avec sécurité. Il encourage à accompagner les mutations au travail sans sacrifier les avancées sociales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parmi les mesures proposées, je tiens à saluer l’accent mis sur la santé au travail. Les travailleurs des plateformes peuvent être exposés à des risques accrus. Il ne s’agit pas seulement d’accidents, mais aussi de leur état de santé. Alors que le monde entier était confiné du fait de la pandémie, ils ont pour la plupart continué à travailler, exposés en première ligne. La santé mentale peut être affectée par l’imprévisibilité et l’intensité de leurs conditions de travail, mais aussi par la compétition accrue entre eux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les règles élémentaires de santé et de sécurité au travail, qui sont un exemple concret de l’Europe sociale que nous voulons construire, doivent donc s’appliquer à tous les travailleurs européens. Une protection sociale adéquate garantissant une assurance en cas d’accident ainsi qu’une couverture maladie et invalidité doit être garantie. Certaines plateformes le font déjà et une généralisation est possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il nous faut maintenant, chère Sylvie, un cadre législatif, car il ne peut y avoir de travailleurs de seconde catégorie, surtout lorsqu’il s’agit de santé.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="193292" name="Tilly Metz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, on 6 May a deliveryman lost his life on a bicycle in Normandy. After a rainy and cold day, he was delivering a meal under pressure, fatigued and overworked. Unfortunately, this drama is not the first, but hopefully it is the last. Platform workers have become a rapidly growing part of the transport sector and this is precarious self-employment, especially in driving and delivery services. Algorithmic management so often used by platforms can put excessive pressure on workers, with implications for road safety.</p>
      <p sl="en">The COVID-19 pandemic clearly shows a lack of social protection for these workers. Many of them lost their source of income from one day to another, but could often not access the income measures, neither for employers nor for self-employed. Platform workers should enjoy equal access to decent working conditions, including a fair income, social security and protection for unemployment and sickness. Work tasks should be predictable and transparent, and algorithms must always have human oversight. Those working in the driving and delivery services need adequate protective equipment and accident insurance. We need to ensure that all workers are treated equally in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">With this report, the European Parliament sends a strong signal in favour of platform workers’ rights. It’s now up to the Commission to deliver a progressive legislative proposal.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="124771" name="Dominique Bilde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, seule la France peut décider de modifier son propre Code du travail. Voici une affirmation qui ne sera peut-être plus une vérité demain. En atteste ce rapport sur les travailleurs des plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Les conditions de travail épouvantables et la précarité des livreurs à vélo qui parcourent les rues de nos villes sont d’autant plus de signes qui montrent que la mondialisation sauvage produit une véritable jungle économique que nous devons combattre. Voici que ni une ni deux, l’Union européenne, touchée par le syndrome du sauveur, accourt à leur chevet. En vain.</p>
      <p sl="en">En effet, comme chaque fois, le bureaucratisme bruxellois, dont la lenteur d’action n’est plus à démontrer, est là encore dépassé: l’Espagne, la France, mais surtout la Suisse et le Royaume-Uni, en dehors de l’Union, s’activent déjà pour remédier aux problèmes de faux indépendants. Nos nations le font en promulguant des décrets ou en laissant les tribunaux agir souverainement. La requalification des contrats est en cours et c’est une bonne chose. Par conséquent, ne laissons pas l’Union européenne profiter du malheur des gens pour s’immiscer dans des matières dont elle n’a pas la compétence. La France agit et doit agir davantage pour salarier ceux qui doivent l’être.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il faut aussi en finir avec l’utilisation scandaleuse d’illégaux dans l’économie des plateformes. Nous refusons l’immigration qui provoque le dumping social. Nos emplois doivent être réservés aux nôtres avant tout. Si la mondialisation rime avec précarisation, faisons de la nation le levier qui permettra de lutter efficacement contre ces pratiques indignes.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-114-0000" speaker_id="88715" name="José Gusmão (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, as plataformas são vendidas como um mundo mágico de inovação e empreendedorismo. Mas, mas para lá do marketing e do deslumbramento, aplicações de telemóvel, os serviços que são prestados, mesmo os algoritmos, estão longe de ser hoje inovações. A única magia que as plataformas oferecem é o truque de fazer desaparecer o patrão e a correspondente relação de trabalho. A única inovação que disponibilizaram é a capacidade de viajar no tempo, para o século XIX, e para o quadro de direitos sociais e laborais que aí vigorava.</p>
      <p sl="en">O único empreendedorismo realmente existente é a transferência do risco económico da empresa que contrata para o trabalhador que trabalha e que passa a arriscar tudo. O que precisamos é de tratar os trabalhadores de plataformas como trabalhadores, contratação coletiva, contratos de trabalho, proteção social. Já agora, para esses e para todos os trabalhadores.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="197414" name="Λουκάς Φουρλάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κύριε Επίτροπε, κυρία εισηγήτρια, τα συγχαρητήρια μου. Σήμερα, στα περισσότερα κράτη μέλη, δεν υπάρχουν σαφείς ρυθμίσεις για τους εργαζόμενους σε ψηφιακές πλατφόρμες. Δεν υπάρχουν κανόνες που ρυθμίζουν ούτε τα δικαιώματα αποζημίωσης σε περίπτωση ασθένειας ή ατυχήματος, ούτε την κοινωνική ασφάλιση αυτών των ανθρώπων. Οφείλετε και οφείλουμε να θεσπίσουμε ένα νομικό πλαίσιο που εξασφαλίζει ίσους όρους για δίκαιη και ίση μεταχείριση των εργαζομένων σε αυτές τις νέες μορφές εργασίας. Δεν μπορούμε να μιλούμε για ομαλή ψηφιακή μετάβαση στην Ευρώπη χωρίς διαφύλαξη των θεμελιωδών δικαιωμάτων αυτών των εργαζόμενων, οι οποίοι έχουν ίσα δικαιώματα με τους υπόλοιπους. «Τα πολλά λόγια είναι φτώχεια», λέμε στα ελληνικά. Η πανδημική κρίση επιτάχυνε την ανάγκη για ψηφιακή μετάβαση και εμείς οφείλουμε να ακολουθήσουμε, χωρίς όμως να επιβαρυνθεί κανένας εργαζόμενος.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-0000" speaker_id="197446" name="Milan Brglez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Gospa predsednica, komisar, kolegice in kolegi. Platforme predstavljajo tudi priložnost za ranljive skupine, njihovo vključenost na trg dela. Gre za mlade, starejše, ženske, dolgotrajno brezposelne in priseljence.</p>
      <p sl="en">Toda tehnologija ne preprečuje diskriminacije. Enako velja za razporejanje dela s pomočjo umetne inteligence.</p>
      <p sl="en">Temna plat brez regulacije je predvsem nelojalna konkurenca in pretirano izkoriščanje ljudi. Tudi v Sloveniji se ljudi sili v samozaposlovanje, celo med pandemijo ljudje ostajajo brez zdravstvenega in socialnega zavarovanja, zaščite pri delu, neustreznega delovnega okolja in možnosti napredovanja oziroma usposabljanja.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato je poročilo dobra priložnost in pomoč Komisiji, da v direktivo vključi močne varovalke proti prekarizaciji dela in to je tudi ključno sporočilo moje poslanske skupine. Hvala.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="197611" name="Elena Lizzi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, il voto in plenaria della relazione su condizioni di lavoro eque, diritti e protezione sociale per i lavoratori delle piattaforme segna un traguardo importante per le nuove forme di occupazione legate allo sviluppo digitale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Infatti il lavoro su piattaforma digitale ha sollevato preoccupazioni su precarietà, cattive condizioni di lavoro, assenza di protezione sociale adeguata o difficoltà di accesso alla stessa, concorrenza sleale, lavoro non dichiarato, redditi e orari di lavoro frammentati e imprevedibili, mancanza di meccanismi di risoluzione delle controversie, dequalificazione e mancanza di opportunità di carriera, nonché assenza di misure in materia di salute e sicurezza sul lavoro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Devo tuttavia richiamare alcuni aspetti che non ci convincono nella relazione e chiedo quindi al Commissario nei futuri atti di approfondire l'invito alla Commissione a scrutinare i progressi negli Stati membri nell'ambito della protezione sociale e nell'ambito del semestre europeo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Inoltre è condivisibile sottolineare l'importanza della formazione, anche se poi si chiede alla Commissione di affrontare il problema dell'educazione e della formazione dei lavoratori delle piattaforme digitali, cosa che non è di sua competenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Inoltre l'invito alla Commissione a considerare di istituire una "etichetta di qualità europea" per le piattaforme digitali: oltre a spingersi un po' oltre, a cosa serve un'etichetta di qualità europea? Non dovrebbero essere tutte le piattaforme in condizione di rispettare e garantire gli stessi diritti? Si vogliono creare piattaforme di serie A e piattaforme di serie B?</p>
      <p sl="en">Su questo noi cercheremo di fare la nostra opera di stimolo, siamo confortati dal fatto che spesso la cronistoria extraparlamentare ci restituisce la ragione che in Aula ci viene negata.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-0000" speaker_id="197754" name="Sandra Pereira (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, estamos aqui a discutir as condições de trabalho dos trabalhadores das plataformas digitais. Podem vir falar de novas formas de emprego ou novas realidades do mundo do trabalho, mas a forma da exploração é a mesma, e velha, lembrando as praças de jorna, a remuneração à peça e acenando com a liberdade sob a forma de flexibilidade para aumentar a desregulação laboral e a precariedade.</p>
      <p sl="en">As plataformas digitais recorrem, sobretudo, à utilização de falsos trabalhadores independentes que, muitas vezes, trabalham com a farda e as regras da plataforma e o fazem por uma comissão ou pagando uma percentagem do valor cobrado sempre sob as regras determinadas pela plataforma. Não há outra solução que não o reconhecimento da relação de trabalho existente, nos termos da legislação nacional de cada país.</p>
      <p sl="en">É inaceitável que, no século XXI, o desenvolvimento técnico e científico alcançado não seja posto ao serviço da melhoria das condições de vida e de trabalho dos trabalhadores e que, pelo contrário, sirva para aumentar a sua exploração.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-0000" speaker_id="24594" name="Anne Sander" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, depuis plus d’une dizaine d’années, nous voyons se développer une forme de travail nouvelle offrant de nombreuses opportunités économiques pour nos entreprises, nos entrepreneurs et nos emplois. Avec la pandémie que nous venons de traverser, ces emplois liés au numérique ont pris une toute autre mesure. Les travailleurs des plateformes ont ainsi permis de sauver certains restaurateurs en leur permettant de continuer à fonctionner un minimum pendant ces mois de crise sanitaire. Ces hommes et ces femmes aux profils parfois très différents se trouvent parfois dans des conditions de travail difficiles et c’est notre rôle de les protéger, de garantir qu’ils aient accès au statut juridique adéquat et aux droits qui en découlent, tout comme il nous revient d’assurer une concurrence loyale à nos entrepreneurs vis-à-vis des plateformes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le rapport du Parlement exprime ici la nécessité de protéger les travailleurs des plateformes, en considérant en particulier que ceux-ci sont par défaut salariés. Concrètement, en cas de conflit, ce sera donc à la plateforme de prouver que le travailleur est indépendant si elle estime que c’est le cas. Ce mécanisme viendrait donc répondre aux problèmes de qualification existants, tout en laissant une flexibilité pour les plateformes faisant travailler de véritables indépendants. Je me réjouis donc de l’adoption de ce rapport qui protège les travailleurs et laisse la possibilité d’opportunités économiques.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-0000" speaker_id="197435" name="Gabriele Bischoff" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar! Ich glaube, diese Debatte zeigt ganz deutlich, dass wir es nicht zulassen können, dass wir sklavenartige neue Arbeitsformen haben, die aber sozusagen im hippen Gewand daherkommen. Aber es ist nichts anderes als ein Rückfall in vormoderne Zeiten, im Prinzip vor der Industrialisierung. Und Arbeitsrechte und Mitbestimmung haben wir, haben die Generationen vor uns erkämpft, und sie sind gesetzlich geschützt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber was stellen wir fest? In meinem Wahlkreis in Berlin – ich will ein Beispiel geben – kämpfen Fahrerinnen und Fahrer vom Lieferdienst Gorillas dafür, einen Betriebsrat einzurichten. Die Realität ist, dass diese Plattformen oft Kompetenzzentren sind, wie man Mitbestimmung, wie man Arbeitsrechte, wie man Arbeitssicherheit umgeht, aushebelt und einfach nicht anwendet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Man hat Menschen befristet angestellt, und wenn einer einen Betriebsrat gründen will, dann läuft der Vertrag aus, der wird einfach nicht weiterbeschäftigt. Dieser Bericht, lieber Nicolas Schmit, ist eine super Chance für die Kommission, hier tätig zu werden, eine Richtlinie vorzulegen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und ich wollte dem Kollegen Reil – er ist nicht mehr da – noch sagen: So eine Studie, die muss man auch zu Ende lesen. Denn bei Bertelsmann findet man gute Vorschläge, was man ändern kann.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-0000" speaker_id="197701" name="Κωνσταντίνος Αρβανίτης (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, εδώ δεν συγκρούονται οι φίλοι της πλατφόρμας με τους εχθρούς της πλατφόρμας. Εδώ δεν συγκρούονται οι φίλοι της προόδου με τους άλλους που είναι στον προηγούμενο αιώνα. Εδώ μπαίνει το θέμα ποιοι να είναι εκείνοι που δεν θέλουν δικαιώματα για τους εργαζόμενους. Ο φόβος του παρελθόντος, που άκουσα πολλές φορές, είναι να έχουν οι άνθρωποι δικαιώματα και οι άνθρωποι πρέπει να έχουν δικαιώματα στις νέες συνθήκες. Χρειάζεται ένα νομοθετικό πλαίσιο λοιπόν που θα προστατεύει τους εργαζόμενους. Αυτορρύθμιση, που ακούω πολύ συχνά τα τελευταία χρόνια, σημαίνει ότι θα κερδίζει ο ισχυρός. Πλαίσιο λοιπόν, που θα προβλέπει συλλογικές συμβάσεις εργασίας και εκπλήρωση των ασφαλιστικών και φορολογικών υποχρεώσεων των πλατφορμών. Δεν θα μπορεί να απολύει και να προσλαμβάνει ο αλγόριθμος αλλά θα έχει την ευθύνη ο άνθρωπος και θα ρυθμίζει τον τρόπο με τον οποίο οι πλατφόρμες διαχειρίζονται τα δεδομένα που παράγουν οι εργαζόμενοι και οι καταναλωτές, ενώ οι εργαζόμενοι θα διατηρούν τον έλεγχο των δεδομένων τους, είτε εργάζονται ακόμη στις πλατφόρμες, είτε έχουν αποχωρήσει από αυτές. Θα υπάρχει συνδικαλιστική εκπροσώπηση. Είναι προϋπόθεση εύρυθμης λειτουργίας της δημοκρατίας. Εδώ λοιπόν, μπορούμε να συμμαχήσουμε με αρκετούς και είναι βέβαιο ότι θα συγκρουστούμε με κάποιους άλλους.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="124895" name="Krzysztof Hetman" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Mam wrażenie, że o pracy za pośrednictwem platform internetowych wciąż dyskutujemy jako o swego rodzaju nowości, podczas gdy tak naprawdę towarzyszy nam ona już od dłuższego czasu i co dziesiąty obywatel Unii Europejskiej ma już za sobą takie doświadczenie. Należy się też spodziewać, że jej popularność będzie tylko rosnąć, gdyż platformy oferują wiele szans dla rozwoju biznesu i są cenione przez konsumentów. Pandemia COVID-19 pokazała też, że ta dość elastyczna forma zatrudnienia dobrze sprawdziła się w trudnych czasach i pozwoliła zachować bądź znaleźć nowe zatrudnienie wielu pracownikom.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wciąż jednak brakuje jasności prawnej co do statusu pracowników platform, co stanowić może zagrożenie dla ich ochrony socjalnej, pewności i przewidywalności zatrudnienia. Dlatego też cieszę się, że Komisja zapowiedziała komunikat w tej sprawie, a nasze sprawozdanie i dzisiejsza debata przychodzą we właściwym czasie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Przede wszystkim uważam, że praca za pośrednictwem platform nie jest jednolitym pojęciem i w chwili obecnej obejmuje zarówno osoby świadczące de facto usługi wyczerpujące znamiona umowy o pracę, jak i samozatrudnionych, którzy pragną takimi pozostać. Wszelkie nowe przepisy muszą więc uwzględniać tę specyfikę i zapewniać odpowiednią elastyczność. Dlatego też popieram zapisy wynegocjowane w sprawozdaniu. W sytuacji, w której dojdzie do sporu między pracownikiem a pracodawcą, to na tym ostatnim będzie ciężar przedstawienia dowodów co do statusu zatrudnienia. W drugiej możliwości – zachowanie statusu zatrudnionego dla osoby, która preferuje taką formę pracy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="197391" name="Heléne Fritzon" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! Herr kommissionär! Den ökande digitaliseringen innebär ju att plattformsekonomin växer, och det blir en allt viktigare del av vår europeiska ekonomi. Det öppnar upp nya möjligheter, men det finns tyvärr många exempel på missbruk och osäkra förhållanden. Man kringgår gällande regler och standarder på arbetsmarknaden, vilket är fullständigt oacceptabelt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Utgångspunkten måste vara att motverka all form av social dumpning. Oavsett var och hur ett arbete utförs, så ska våra arbetstagare ges bra och likvärdiga villkor. Bara så kan ju den fria rörligheten fungera.</p>
      <p sl="en">I mitt land, Sverige, har vi kollektivavtal som reglerar för plattformsarbetare. Jag ser hur viktigt detta är. Jag vet och förstår att det behövs åtgärder på EU-nivå för att hantera de gränsöverskridande problemen. Samtidigt är det klart att det alltid måste ske i respekt för de nationella arbetsmarknadsmodeller som visar sig fungera väl.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-0000" speaker_id="4560" name="Antonius Manders" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, commissaris, vandaag hebben in Nederland twee heuglijke feiten plaatsgevonden. Ten eerste worden over twee weken alle COVID-19-beperkingen opgeheven omdat meer dan tachtig procent van de bevolking is gevaccineerd. Ten tweede heeft de rechtbank Amsterdam besloten dat Uber-chauffeurs moeten worden beschouwd als werknemers en niet als zelfstandigen. We hebben het vandaag over de sociale omstandigheden van werknemers bij platformdiensten.</p>
      <p sl="en">De economische ontwikkelingen van vandaag botsen duidelijk met de Europese beschaving. De normen en waarden die wij in Europa hebben opgebouwd worden omgezet in moderne slavernij. Daar moeten iets worden gedaan.</p>
      <p sl="en">Het is wellicht goed om na te denken over een modernere vorm van sociale zekerheid, aangezien deze werknemers enerzijds duidelijk behoefte hebben aan flexibiliteit en anderzijds aan zekerheid en verzekering. Het voorstel zou zich bijvoorbeeld kunnen richten op een hybride aanpak met een basis die zekerheid biedt in het oude systeem en waarvan de andere helft of de overige 25 procent een flexibel systeem vormt dat de werknemer meer keuzes biedt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dit probleem komt blijkbaar in vrijwel elke lidstaat voor. Wellicht kunt u dus met een voorstel komen voor een verordening die de bescherming van werknemers in heel Europa regelt en niet alleen per lidstaat. We hebben het immers over Europese normen en waarden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-0000" speaker_id="197732" name="Manuel Pizarro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, nos nossos dias, como sempre na história, os socialistas defendem os direitos dos trabalhadores, desde logo os que estão mais desprotegidos. Há hoje um exército de pessoas que trabalham através de plataformas digitais e que, na sua esmagadora maioria, não têm direito a uma pensão, nem à baixa médica, trabalhando em média 60 horas por semana. Esta desproteção e precariedade aparecem camufladas de trabalho independente, quando todos sabemos que a relação é de dependência, muitas vezes extrema. A única forma justa de resolver esta situação é determinando a existência de uma relação laboral de subordinação com a plataforma a ter de provar que assim não é. Se, como alguns querem, criarmos uma categoria intermédia de proteção, estaremos a abrir caminho a uma proteção minimal e à degradação da proteção laboral. Em nome da dignidade do mundo do trabalho e de uma economia que funcione para as pessoas, temos o direito de lutar pelos direitos destes trabalhadores.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="202036" name="Sunčana Glavak" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, povjereniče, izvjestiteljice, pandemija COVID-19, naravno, dodatno je aktualizirala tematiku rada preko platformi, novog oblika zapošljavanja povezanog s digitalnim razvojem. Svjedočimo naravno digitalnoj transformaciji rada i društva i toga smo svi svjesni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Slažem se, potrebno je podrobnije regulirati rad preko platformi kako bi se radnicima osigurali pravedni radni uvjeti, prava i, naravno, socijalna zaštita. Rad putem platformi u porastu je, a 60 % stanovnika Europske unije kaže da ni nakon korona krize neće odustati od korištenja internetskih usluga.</p>
      <p sl="en">Međutim, postoji određena pravna nesigurnost jer oni koji rade preko platformi u različitim državama članicama ili kombiniraju redovan radni odnos s radom putem platformi često podliježu posve različitim propisima za isti rad. Takvu pravnu nesigurnost naravno treba riješiti uz poštivanje načela supsidijarnosti i različite pristupe država članica.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dijelim zabrinutost jednako tako i oko regulacije algoritama. Potrebno je naglasiti važnost digitalnih kompetencija. U tom kontekstu pozdravljam javna ulaganja u strukovno obrazovanje i cjeloživotno učenje koji su izrazito važni kako bi se radnici spremili za digitalno doba.</p>
      <p sl="en">Prema podacima Eurofounda 10,7 % populacije iz Hrvatske, zemlje iz koje ja dolazim, odnosno 440 tisuća stanovnika susrelo se s radom putem platformi. Isto tako, budući da je Hrvatska turistička zemlja, zalažem se za posebnu zaštitu radnika putem platformi u sektoru turizma i prometa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tradicionalna organizacija rada radikalno se promijenila. Budućnost radnika ovisi o nama i zato se slažem da je moramo dodatno dobro promisliti.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127-0000" speaker_id="197702" name="Lina Gálvez Muñoz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, señor comisario, a principios de septiembre vimos una fotografía impactante: mientras el huracán Ida provocaba graves inundaciones y decenas de muertos en los Estados Unidos, un repartidor de comida a domicilio continuaba trabajando, pedaleando con dificultad con el agua hasta la cintura. Es una imagen chocante, pero también indignante, y que nos ayuda a enfrentarnos a las nuevas desigualdades emergentes, como la de los trabajadores sin derechos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si bien es cierto que los nuevos tipos de empleo y trabajo de plataforma pueden ayudar o tienen el potencial de ayudar a conciliar la vida laboral y familiar, eso no quita que muchos sean trabajos precarios y estén por debajo de los estándares laborales, y esto no es tolerable.</p>
      <p sl="en">Europa debe caracterizarse por respetar los derechos de los trabajadores y trabajadoras y las libertades fundamentales, también en el ámbito digital. Y así, desde el Parlamento, instamos al control humano detrás de los algoritmos, a que las empresas tengan la obligación de informar sobre los algoritmos utilizados y a velar por la transparencia en relación con los datos personales utilizados.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello, nos posicionamos claramente contra el capitalismo de la vigilancia también en el ámbito laboral.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-128-0000" speaker_id="197403" name="Alex Agius Saliba" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il-Pjattaformi għall-Ekonomija Kollaborativa llum saru parti integrali fil-ħajja tagħna, u dan qed joħloq sfidi ġodda – sfidi għar-relazzjonijiet industrijali, sfidi għas-sigurtà soċjali, sfidi għal qafas regolatorju tal-Istati Membri tagħna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il-prekarjat illi qed jaffaċċjaw il-ħaddiema tal-pjattaformi hija sfida reali u bil-pandemija COVID tkompli tesponi numru ta' vulnerabbiltajiet illi dawn il-ħaddiema kienu qegħdin diġà jaffaċċjaw fil-passat: self-employment falz, nuqqas ta' kundizzjonijiet tax-xogħol, dħul baxx jew frammentat, riskji għas-saħħa u s-sigurtà, protezzjoni soċjali insuffiċjenti, status tal-impjieg mhux ċar.</p>
      <p sl="en">U għalhekk il-wegħda tal-Kummissjoni illi tintroduċi miżuri ta' infurzar sabiex tassigura l-integrazzjoni tas-suq tax-xogħol u twarrab l-inugwaljanzi fis-settur tal-ekonomija tal-pjattaformi huwa proġett illi ilna wisq issa nistennew.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dak illi huwa illegali fuq bażi offline għandu bl-istess mod ikun ikkunsidrat bħala illegali fuq bażi online, u dan huwa prinċipju illi jien naqbel miegħu mija fil-mija. Il-ħaddiema fis-settur diġitali għandhom igawdu mill-istess drittijiet u trattament daqs ħaddiema oħra. Il-pjattaformi diġitali ma għandhomx ikomplu japprofittaw minn inċertezzi legali sabiex jabbużaw mid-drittijiet fundamentali illi kull ħaddiem għandu jgawdi.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-0000" speaker_id="38542" name="Johan Danielsson" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! ”Det har kommit till vår kännedom att du har skrivit om fackliga frågor i en av företagets chattgrupper.” Så löd första raden i ett mejl där ett svenskt gigföretag kallade upp en anställd till områdeschefen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolleger! För hundra år sedan stod Europas arbetare med mössan i hand i väntan på arbete – utan trygghet, utan rättigheter, utan en stabil inkomst. Genom facklig kamp vanns rätten till anständiga arbetsförhållanden. Nu är mössan tillbaka. Den här gången är det i form av en mobiltelefon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Visst kan det finnas anledning att prisa gigföretagen för innovativa appar, men det är inte innovation att motarbeta facklig organisering. Det är inte en innovation att betala svältlöner. Det är inte en innovation att låta anställda ta den ekonomiska risken för uteblivna körningar. Det är inte framtiden. Det är att backa bandet i hundra år.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU kan inte och ska inte lösa alla problem. Men EU måste garantera medborgares grundläggande rättigheter. I det ingår även rätten att organisera sig fackligt. Det är en rätt som också plattformsarbetare ska ha möjlighet att förverkliga.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Nicolas Schmit" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members, I think your message was more than clear, and again this debate underlines the importance of the issue, the importance of the question, but also the line you have taken in your report very clearly corresponds to a very, very, very large majority of those who have expressed themselves today.</p>
      <p sl="en">Just a few remarks.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yes, we should not go back with the economy of the 21st century to social conditions of the 19th century. That’s clear.</p>
      <p sl="en">And innovation, nobody opposes innovation. Nobody opposes technological progress, but we always have to ask the question, who should innovation serve? Should it just serve the shareholders of the platforms, eventually the consumers? What about those who are running the whole scene and the workers? And I think this is the issue, and it cannot be that the world of flexibility, and I understand that this is a business model, this is a system which needs some flexibility. And even those working on the platforms sometimes asked for some flexible arrangements. But flexibility cannot mean very low pay, no social protection, very low cost. And this low cost has to be borne by the worker. This cannot be a sustainable economic or business model, and that has to be clear.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now, some say, well most of the platform workers just do that as an additional work. Why should an additional work not be protected? Why should an additional work not be correctly paid? There is no reason for that. So it is important that these rules apply to all workers, even if they are at platforms as an additional activity.</p>
      <p sl="en">I think what has been said on collective bargaining – and we are working also on this side – there is an imbalance in the relationship between the platform and the worker, and we have to redress, we have to correct this imbalance. And there has to be a real representation. There has to be the possibility to have collective agreements.</p>
      <p sl="en">By the way, if we accept this, we turn to 19th century practices. It will not just happen with platforms. It will happen everywhere because it will create a new dynamic, a new competition between platforms and more traditional businesses. Why should traditional businesses comply with rules, social protection, social rules, and platforms they just need not to respect that? So it is also an issue of fair competition between different business models.</p>
      <p sl="en">And at the European level just to finish, well we all have heard what has happened in the Netherlands today in Amsterdam. This has happened already more than 100 times all over Europe and also outside Europe. There have been American courts having exactly decided the same or similar things. And therefore we have to introduce more security, more legal safety, clarity, and that’s why the Commission is committed to come up with a balanced proposal, respecting the social protection, the social rights of all workers, including the workers on platforms.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="197433" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen. Die Abstimmung findet am Mittwoch, 15. September 2021, statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Fishers for the future (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="197433" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die kurze Darstellung des Berichts von Manuel Pizarro über das Thema „Fischer für die Zukunft: eine neue Generation von Arbeitskräften für die Fischerei gewinnen und Arbeitsplätze in Küstengemeinschaften schaffen“ [2019/2161(INI)] (A9-0230/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-0000" speaker_id="197732" name="Manuel Pizarro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, o relatório «Fishers for the Future» foi aprovado por unanimidade na Comissão das Pescas. Este é um facto raro no Parlamento Europeu, o qual mostra bem o amplo consenso que se reuniu em torno da gravidade da situação, dando-nos as medidas necessárias para a corrigir.</p>
      <p sl="en">Agradeço a todos os meus colegas, em especial aos relatores-sombra de todos os grupos políticos, os seus valiosos e construtivos contributos. Agradeço, em especial, à coordenadora do Grupo S&amp;D na Comissão das Pescas, a minha colega Clara Aguilera, a sua solidariedade e confiança. Agradeço os muitos contributos recebidos do sector, que provam que esta questão é entendida por todos como sendo decisiva para o futuro da profissão.</p>
      <p sl="en">Em 2017, o primeiro relatório de avaliação dos dados sociais no setor da pesca contabiliza cerca de 150 mil pessoas empregadas na frota de pesca da União, 63% dos quais com idade superior a 40 anos. Estes números dão razão ao que a generalidade dos Estados-Membros e dos parceiros de fileira afirmam há, pelo menos, duas décadas. Os pescadores têm idade cada vez mais avançada e é cada vez mais difícil atrair as novas gerações para a pesca. O diagnóstico está feito há muito, mas tardam medidas para contrariar a situação. É isto que justifica este relatório de iniciativa.</p>
      <p sl="en">É tempo de agir. A política comum das pescas tem como objetivo garantir a sustentabilidade social, económica e ambiental da pesca a longo prazo. Em muitas comunidades, a importância social dos setores da pesca e da aquicultura supera mesmo a sua contribuição económica direta. No tempo escasso de que disponho, procurei destacar os aspetos mais importantes. A melhoria das condições de trabalho, habitabilidade e segurança a bordo são fundamentais.</p>
      <p sl="en">Apesar da adesão da União Europeia às convenções internacionais relacionadas com a segurança dos navios, a verdade é que muitas das regras não se aplicam diretamente aos navios de pequena escala, os quais constituem 85% da frota comunitária. Realça-se ainda a necessidade de ter em conta as especificidades do trabalho a bordo dos navios de pesca.</p>
      <p sl="en">É imperioso obrigar ao cumprimento dos quadros legais laborais e conseguir que todos os Estados-Membros ratifiquem a Convenção n.º 188 da OIT. A melhoria da formação e o reconhecimento da formação a nível europeu são essenciais. O reconhecimento da formação obtida em diferentes Estados-Membros é penoso e burocrático e prejudica o direito à livre circulação. Sem esquecer a importância do conhecimento prático, a atração de novas gerações de pescadores depende também da certificação formal que ajuda à valorização pessoal e ao reconhecimento social.</p>
      <p sl="en">É imperioso assegurar o equilíbrio de género e valorizar o papel desempenhado pelas mulheres em todo o setor das pescas. Apenas 4% dos pescadores da União Europeia são mulheres. Há muito a fazer para reconhecer o papel das mulheres. Para garantir a renovação geracional, essencial à continuidade da atividade da pesca, impõe-se um maior reconhecimento social da atividade e da sua importância para o fornecimento de alimentos saudáveis, provenientes de produção sustentável em habitats em bom estado ambiental e que contribuam para a saúde dos europeus. Há que combater o preconceito de que os pescadores são predadores interessados apenas em explorar os recursos sem pensar no futuro. Os pescadores são e serão cada vez mais, na verdade, guardiões do mar.</p>
      <p sl="en">Apelo à aprovação deste relatório por todos os colegas na próxima quarta-feira. Senhor Comissário, dirijo-me diretamente a si: é imperioso que as recomendações concretas que apresentamos tenham seguimento e resposta. Este tema tem sido debatido já há mais de duas décadas sem que tenham sido tomadas medidas concretas e a situação é, naturalmente, pior do que era há duas décadas. Repito, Senhor Comissário, e sei que tenho o seu apoio nesta questão: é tempo de agir em favor dos pescadores e do setor pesqueiro da União Europeia.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Nicolas Schmit" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I would first like to congratulate Mr Pizarro for this very comprehensive report. I fully agree that the diminishing attractiveness of the fishing sector is a major challenge we need to address. In addition, other important challenges for the sector come along with the issue of ageing.</p>
      <p sl="en">This report of the European Parliament also comes at a crucial point in time when the Commission is starting its preparations for a report on the functioning of the common fisheries policy to be adopted in 2022. This report will address issues not sufficiently covered in the current common fisheries policy, also including the social dimension. Let me reassure you that the Commission has already addressed many of the issues outlined in the Parliament’s report, and I would like to mention the main ones.</p>
      <p sl="en">Firstly, the report rightly points to the importance of data collection. To strengthen our policies it is vital that we have the right data and gain a better understanding of the workforce in fisheries, of the ageing patterns, education and the role of women. Together with the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF), the Commission has already started to enhance the analysis of social indicators for the EU fishing fleet. This will be pursued in the future and a report examining the social situation of the EU fisheries sector will be published in 2022.</p>
      <p sl="en">Secondly, a better knowledge is also required of casualties in the fishing sector, of which there are sadly still far too many. In line with the suggestions in the report, the Commission is currently examining the possibility of extending the Maritime Accident Investigation Directive to smaller fishing vessels below the length of 15 metres. Even though EU legislation already contains important health and safety standards applicable to fishermen and women, like the Directive on work on board fishing vessels and the Framework Directive of 1989 on the safety and health of workers, which is applicable to all sectors, the report rightly recalls that a major step towards better working conditions was taken in 2017. This was the year of the entry into force of Directive (EU) 2017/159, which implements the so—called Work in Fishing Convention of the International Labour Organization into EU law. This has given a boost to the improvement of living and working conditions of fishing crews across the EU, and will certainly help increase the attractiveness of the fishing sector in the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">I carefully take note of the criticism in your report regarding the alleged contradiction between the required capacity limitations under the common fisheries policy and the need to increase capacity in order to meet other requirements related to safety and decent working conditions. However, I would like to point out that the capacity limitations under the common fisheries policy apply to national fleets as a whole. Therefore, there is indeed room for necessary capacity increases of individual vessels as long as the Member States concerned respect the overall ceilings and the principles of the entry—exit regime.</p>
      <p sl="en">Another important point in your report touches upon training and the mutual recognition of certificates as an important factor for increasing not only the attractiveness of the fishing sector, but also the mobility of crew and the safety of fishing vessels. The Commission is therefore closely following the current revision of the International Maritime Organization’s Convention on Standards of Training, Certification and Watchkeeping for Fishing Vessel Personnel (STCW-F). Once this Convention is updated, the Commission will examine whether to propose its incorporation into EU law. In the meantime, the Commission continues to promote the ratification of all relevant international conventions by our Member States and our international partners. This will not only improve the situation of fishers in the EU, but will also ensure a level playing field between fishing operators within the EU and internationally.</p>
      <p sl="en">In several instances, the report points to the importance of the good use of EU funding for the proposed actions. The new European Maritime, Fisheries and Aquaculture Fund (EMFAF) will indeed provide the necessary funds to help make the fishing sector more attractive and more resilient. The Fund can support young fishers to acquire a first vessel, provide for training opportunities and support the role of women in local fishing communities. Under specific conditions the Fund can also support investments in low—impact fishing techniques, safety on board and energy efficiency. The Commission’s services are now working with Member States to ensure they reflect these ambitions in their operational programmes and that the programmes are adopted as soon as possible.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me conclude by again thanking the rapporteur, Mr Pizarro, and all the shadow rapporteurs for this important work. The report is an encouragement for the Commission to pursue its actions to strengthen the social dimension of our common fisheries policy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione si svolgerà mercoledì 15 settembre 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="197510" name="Jarosław Duda" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Napięcia gospodarcze spowodowane pandemią stanowią szczególne zagrożenie dla sektorów, które wcześniej borykały się z trudnościami. Należy do nich sektor rybołówstwa, mający kluczowe znaczenie dla obszarów przybrzeżnych, zarówno w wymiarze ekonomicznym, jak i ochrony dziedzictwa kulturowego.</p>
      <p sl="en">Starzenie się siły roboczej w tym sektorze wynika zarówno z trudnych warunków pracy, jak i niepewności dochodów i braku gwarancji ciągłości kariery. Konieczne są zachęty dla młodych ludzi, w szczególności dostęp do doradztwa, szkoleń i wysokiej jakości staży, tak aby mogli jak najlepiej skorzystać z szans, jakie niosą transformacja zielona i cyfrowa, a także dostosować swoją ofertę do trendów, takich jak promocja żywności ekologicznej, produktów lokalnych, sprzedaży bezpośredniej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ponadto niezbędne jest wspieranie osób, które z powodów zdrowotnych czy rodzinnych pragną kontynuować pracę na lądzie, w zdobywaniu odpowiednich kwalifikacji, znajdowaniu pracy lub założeniu firmy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Warto podkreślić, że wrażliwość młodych ludzi na kwestię poszanowania środowiska, w połączeniu z dostarczeniem odpowiedniej wiedzy i umiejętności, może dopomóc w przygotowaniu nowego pokolenia rybaków do roli strażników morza i jego zasobów.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. Towards future-proof inland waterway transport in Europe (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la breve presentazione della relazione dell'on. Caroline Nagtegaal, a nome della commissione per i trasporti e il turismo, Verso un trasporto per vie navigabili interne adeguato alle esigenze future in Europa [2021/2015(INI)] (A9-0231/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="190519" name="Caroline Nagtegaal" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Rapporteur. – Voorzitter, de binnenvaart staat aan de vooravond van een aantal ingrijpende veranderingen die worden voortgedreven door verduurzaming en digitalisering. Waar liggen de behoeften van de binnenvaartsector, welke problemen moeten er worden opgelost en aangepakt, en hoe maken we deze sector toekomstbestendig?</p>
      <p sl="en">Eindelijk mag ik met trots het verslag presenteren, dat het eindresultaat is van intensieve raadplegingen en gesprekken met belanghebbenden uit alle hoeken van de binnenvaartsector, van schippers tot onderzoeksinstituten en van binnenhavens tot innovatieve binnenvaartondernemers. Eén ding werd mij al snel duidelijk en staat als een paal boven water: deze sector zit boordevol motivatie en energie om te vernieuwen. Voor de totstandbrenging van deze toekomstbestendige sector zijn echter een aantal ingrediënten nodig. Allereerst goede infrastructuur, waaronder bruggen, sluizen en wegen. Deze infrastructuur is onmisbaar om de modal shift-doelen te verwezenlijken. Verder spelen ook automatisering en digitalisering een wezenlijke rol.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarnaast wordt een zeer realistische routekaart opgesteld voor de verduurzaming van onze vloot en onze havens, waarbij meerdere opties worden geboden voor alternatieve brandstoffen en rekening wordt gehouden met de uiteenlopende scheepstypes. Deze opgave van de energietransitie is misschien wel de grootste kluif, aangezien de sector uit kleine familiebedrijven, zelfstandigen en kmo’s bestaat en dit nu net de hardwerkende ondernemers zijn die letterlijk en figuurlijk op hun pensioen varen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Het is dan ook van belang dat er een hele groene businesscase komt te liggen. De schippers moeten er immers vanuit kunnen gaan dat zij de flinke investering die zij zullen en moeten doen ook kunnen terugverdienen, waarbij zij wel wat hulp kunnen gebruiken. Daarom wordt in het verslag ook gepleit voor een Europees Binnenvaartfonds, om de sector zowel tijdens de groene als tijdens de digitale transitie financieel te kunnen ondersteunen. Dit fonds moet juist voor kleine ondernemers toegankelijk zijn. Ik ben dan ook blij dat de Commissie het belang van voldoende financiële steun reeds heeft erkend in het onlangs gepubliceerde actieprogramma voor de binnenvaart, NAIADES III.</p>
      <p sl="en">Erkenning alleen volstaat echter niet; er moet ook actie worden ondernomen. Ik wil u dan ook vragen voor dit verslag te stemmen en de energie die momenteel door de sector vloeit om te vergroenen, te verbeteren en te vernieuwen niet verloren te laten gaan. We hebben als Parlement met dit verslag een instrument in handen waarmee we kunnen bouwen aan de binnenvaart van morgen en de sector klaar kunnen stomen voor een duurzame en nog efficiëntere toekomst.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Nicolas Schmit" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, first I want to thank the rapporteur, Ms Caroline Nagtegaal – I hope I pronounced it more or less correctly – for her presentation and annual report. The Commission warmly welcomes the EP recommendations on how to shape the EU’s inland waterway transport for the future. As one of the most efficient forms of transport we need to unlock more of its untapped potential.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today’s share of inland waterways in freight movement across the EU stands just above 6%. The Green Deal communication calls for a substantial part of the 75% of inland freight transport carried by road to be shifted to inland navigation and rail, and for measures to increase the capacity of inland navigation from 2021. With that in mind, the Commission adopted on 24 June an ambitious new NAIADES programme – the Inland Navigation Action Plan for 2021—2027 – which is aligned to the new Multiannual Financial Framework. It builds on the December 2019 recommendations of the NAIADES Expert Group and shares the objectives laid out in our Smart and Sustainable Mobility Strategy.</p>
      <p sl="en">The NAIADES III Action Plan focuses on two core objectives: shifting more freight transport to inland waterways and setting the sector on an irreversible path to zero emissions. This must be underpinned by a paradigm shift towards further digitalisation, as well as accompanying measures to support the current and future workforce.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am pleased to see that our reports are aligned on objectives, but also on many of the proposed measures – from supporting the development of multimodal nodes and interoperable data platforms, to accelerating the rollout of sustainable alternative fuels, and alternative propulsion systems for vessels, but also on the need to better mobilise and combine existing EU and national financing instruments, as well as other private and public investments, to support the many smaller private vessel operators in the sector to access financial support for the transition to a zero—emission fleet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Substantive action is also needed to reduce the overlapping legal frameworks in order to improve operating conditions. Over 75% of inland navigation in the EU involves cross—border transport, so EU coordinated actions are needed to reinforce the EU single market. Over the years, different rules have been developed for various international basins. EU actions will result in fewer barriers, better cross—border traffic and wider EU digital and environmental harmonisation, and this will then clear the way for inland navigation to claim a larger share of travelling individuals and goods.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, like all other sectors of the economy, inland waterway transport has felt the impact of the COVID—19 crisis. The pandemic is estimated to have cost the sector around EUR 2.7 billion in lost turnover in 2020 due to a 70% reduction in passenger transport and an 8% reduction in freight transport. It is nonetheless worth noting that the sector proved to be more COVID—19 resilient for the transport of goods – an aspect worth taking into account when developing future transport crisis contingency strategies.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maximising the potential of inland waterway transport and meeting the core objectives set out in the NAIADES Action Plan will require an integrated approach and a basket of measures incorporating transport, environmental, digital skills, energy and fiscal policies, backed up with financial incentives.</p>
      <p sl="en">A stronger inland navigation sector also needs to be able to offer quality jobs, career opportunities and high social, safety and security standards to attract well—trained people. The proposed actions will ensure smart and flexible EU crewing rules and provide inland transport crews with adequate working conditions and the right skills to deal with the green and digital transition, among other things.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission encourages the EP to help us make sure that Europe’s inland waterway transport network is fit for the future. We need not only to overcome the challenges ahead, but also raise the profile of our inland waterway transport network while increasing its attractiveness for investors and for innovation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione si svolgerà martedì 14 settembre 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-144-0000" speaker_id="124887" name="Karol Karski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – Drogi wodne i żegluga śródlądowa odgrywają w transporcie równie istotną rolę, jak pozostałe środki transportu. Jest to jeden z najbardziej przyjaznych dla środowiska rodzajów transportu, o bardzo niskiej emisyjności i małym zużyciu energii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niestety ograniczenia nakładów na rozwój dróg wodnych oraz zaniedbania w ich utrzymaniu doprowadziły do kompletnej marginalizacji żeglugi śródlądowej jako alternatywnego środka transportu. Dlatego niezwykle pilne jest określenie priorytetów i stworzenie długookresowego planu inwestycyjnego oraz zapewnienie wystarczających źródeł finansowania zarówno na poziomach krajowych, jak i w ramach funduszy europejskich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Istotne jest kompleksowe zagospodarowanie systemu dróg wodnych, przy jednoczesnym uwzględnieniu zarówno ich potencjału transportowego, jak i turystycznego. Moje regiony – województwa warmińsko-mazurskie i podlaskie – to obszary niezwykle bogate, jeśli chodzi o możliwości w dziedzinie żeglugi śródlądowej i rozwoju turystyki wodnej, a ich siła koncentruje się wokół polskiego odcinka Międzynarodowej Drogi Wodnej E70. System Wielkich Jezior Mazurskich oraz Kanał Elbląski wraz Kanałem Ostródzkim i Iławskim stanowią ważne śródlądowe drogi wodne.</p>
      <p sl="en">Niestety, mimo to transport wodny nie stanowi obecnie kluczowego elementu systemu komunikacyjnego. Dlatego nadchodzący proces rewizji rozporządzenia TEN-Ts powinien umożliwić włączenie polskich odcinków międzynarodowych dróg wodnych E30, E40 oraz przebiegającej przez mój region E70 do sieci bazowej, co zagwarantowałoby dostęp do funduszy europejskich i efektywną modernizację dróg śródlądowych.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Towards a stronger partnership with the EU outermost regions (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-146-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la breve presentazione della relazione dell'on. Stéphane Bijoux, a nome della commissione per lo sviluppo regionale, Verso un rafforzamento del partenariato con le regioni ultraperiferiche dell'Unione (2020/2120(INI)) (A9-0241/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="197551" name="Stéphane Bijoux" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chère Elisa Ferreira, chers collègues, hier encore à la même heure, j’étais chez moi sur l’île de la Réunion, dans l’océan Indien, avec le ministre français de l’Europe. Nous avons donné le coup d’envoi de la Conférence régionale sur l’avenir de l’Europe. Nous avons rencontré beaucoup de citoyens et ils nous ont confié une question. Elle ressemble à de la géométrie, mais c’est bien une question politique fondamentale: comment faire pour être à la fois à la périphérie et dans le cœur de l’Europe?</p>
      <p sl="en">En ce moment même, 5 millions d’Européens vivent dans l’océan Indien, dans les Caraïbes et dans l’Atlantique. Ils attendent notre réponse à leurs espoirs et à leurs urgences. Notre réponse, c’est ce rapport que je défends devant vous aujourd’hui. Je réclame une nouvelle stratégie européenne pour les régions ultrapériphériques (RUP). Ce sont neuf territoires français, espagnols et portugais: La Réunion, Mayotte, la Guyane, la Guadeloupe, Saint-Martin, la Martinique, Madère, les Açores, les Canaries. Je veux toutes les citer, parce que je veux redire ici que chacune de ces régions est une chance pour l’Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Elles sont en première ligne des grands défis européens: le climat, la cohésion, la santé et bien évidemment l’environnement, puisque les RUP concentrent 80 % de la biodiversité européenne. Ce rapport est un appel à l’action, à l’action urgente pour construire ensemble un nouveau modèle de développement pour les outre-mer, pour les régions ultrapériphériques. Je veux d’ailleurs remercier ici tous mes collègues et leurs équipes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons coconstruit cette stratégie en trois axes, protéger, développer, valoriser. Cette nouvelle stratégie, il faut qu’elle soit plus verte, bien évidemment, plus bleue, plus juste aussi. Il reste encore tellement de retard à rattraper; la pauvreté, le chômage, la précarité qui font que nos jeunes disent que leur horizon est cassé. Nous avons impérativement besoin d’un nouvel engagement européen volontariste et efficace. Alors, comment faire pour être efficace? C’est d’abord respecter l’article 349 du traité FUE et instaurer un véritable réflexe RUP dans toutes les institutions européennes. Je vais vous dire, nous oublier, c’est oublier que nous faisons partie des solutions européennes. Nous oublier, c’est oublier l’engagement qui est le nôtre de ne laisser personne sur le bord du chemin.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce réflexe RUP, c’est faire la preuve de l’intelligence collective face aux défis communs qui sont les nôtres. À l’urgence climatique qui exige la réconciliation de l’humain et de la nature, s’ajoutent aussi les urgences sociales et économiques. Face à ces fragilités, l’Europe agit avec sa politique de cohésion, son soutien aux agriculteurs, aux pêcheurs, aux éleveurs, ainsi qu’avec ses programmes de mobilité Erasmus. Notre nouvelle stratégie RUP appelle à consolider les acquis, à respecter les spécificités et surtout, à ouvrir de nouvelles perspectives pour nos jeunes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cela signifie créer des campus d’excellence, développer le numérique pour trouver des emplois. Cela signifie aussi faire de nos RUP des territoires moteurs de l’innovation, de la transition énergétique ou de la recherche.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors oui, je le redis ici, l’Europe est une chance pour les RUP. Mais chacun de nos territoires ultramarins est une chance pour l’Europe. Il faut de l’audace et de la détermination. C’est l’ambition que je porte ici dans cette nouvelle stratégie changer votre regard, changer notre regard. Parce que les RUP sont des territoires de solutions, des territoires avec des atouts géostratégiques, avec nos forces et avec nos faiblesses, avec nos fragilités et avec nos atouts, avec nos exigences et avec nos espoirs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous sommes en quelque sorte le miroir de votre relation avec les plus éloignés, les plus fragilisés, les plus résilients aussi. Alors, je vous le dis, face aux défis climatiques et sociaux, peut-être aussi que nous sommes votre futur. Alors voilà, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, chers présidents, la balle est dans votre camp et partout, nous savons que nous pouvons compter sur vous.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Elisa Ferreira" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, honourable Members, ladies and gentlemen, I start with very sincere thanks to Mr Stéphane Bijoux and to all the Members who have contributed to this report.</p>
      <p sl="en">We in the Commission share the Parliament’s commitment to the outermost regions and we welcome this timely report, which actually arrives just as the Commission is running consultations on a new strategic approach for the outermost regions. This is part of our closer look to our territories. The need to be more aware of that diversity, endogenous assets and challenges, opportunities as well of course.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need to constantly remember that our policies are not territorially neutral and that it is incumbent upon us to make sure that they promote the long-term development of all our regions. This is what we wish to do with our revised strategy of the outermost, to consider and discuss how we can be more relevant and supportive in the areas of social matters, health, education, training, but also taking a fresh look at agriculture and fisheries and energy transition, thinking anew about the role of administration.</p>
      <p sl="en">At this critical juncture of recovery we need to deepen the reflection and adjusted approach for solutions to be adequate, to be fit for purpose. Let me assure you that we in the Commission are carefully examining your detailed suggestions set out in this report, and we will take them into account in shaping the new strategic approach.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are very aware that COVID has fallen particularly hard on the outermost regions. We have commissioned a study on this topic, which will be ready by the end of October, as you know. But available data suggest already that in many outermost regions, GDP, so the wealth, fell between 15% and 30% in the last year, and that in 2020, in the previous year, tourism in the outermost was at just 30%. So a fall of 70% of its normal level. You will find more details in the report in October.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission welcomes the focus of your report on investing in training and job creation, on generating opportunities for young people and on promoting a sustainable green and digital transition. We endorse completely this vision.</p>
      <p sl="en">We also endorse your position on the need to protect biodiversity and on the need to promote the circular economy and renewable energy while still supporting traditional sectors such as agriculture, fisheries, tourism and culture.</p>
      <p sl="en">We in the European Commission stand ready to support the outermost regions through the new cohesion programmes, through other European Union programmes and whatever instruments we can muster in line with Article 349 of the Treaty.</p>
      <p sl="en">We look forward to working with the Parliament as we shape together the new strategic approach and lay foundations for a sustainable long-term recovery. For this, we want to hear your views and those of your constituents. Please encourage as many of them as possible to reply to our public consultation launched in July and open until November.</p>
      <p sl="en">I believe the future holds many opportunities for the outermost regions, from renewable energy to sustainable tourism, to the blue economy. They can be leaders and pioneers, and we in the European Commission are ready to be their supporters. So thank you very much, et on doit travailler ensemble, trabalhamos juntos para o bem de todos.</p>
      <p sl="en">On doit travailler ensemble.</p>
      <p sl="en">Trabalhamos juntos para o bem de todos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione si svolgerà martedì 14 settembre 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-5000" speaker_id="197641" name="Sara Cerdas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – A aplicação do artigo 349.º do Tratado deverá ter em conta os desafios sociais, demográficos, económicos e climáticos adicionais que as regiões ultraperiféricas enfrentam. As transições verde e digital encontram nas RUP dificuldades acrescidas que importa superar, sendo fundamental elaborar um plano de ação para estas Regiões, envolvendo as autoridades nacionais, regionais e locais, e parceiros. O posicionamento geográfico destas regiões requer a promoção de uma efetiva coesão territorial, apostando em políticas de mobilidade marítima e aérea que aproximem estes territórios e garantam a conetividade, minimizando os custos dos transportes de passageiros e mercadorias e diminuindo os seus impactos ambientais. Exige-se que a concretização do Pacto Ecológico inclua um pacto azul que proteja os recursos oceânicos e desenvolva o potencial marítimo, que a PAC atente às especificidades dos métodos agrícolas, à salvaguarda da biodiversidade e ao desenvolvimento integral e sustentável das zonas rurais. A promoção do turismo sustentável, apoiando projetos-piloto para soluções ecológicas e digitais, é o melhor caminho para o desenvolvimento económico. As novas gerações exigem melhores oportunidades de formação, através da integração da realidade das RUP no Erasmus+, e emprego digno, com políticas que atentem às especificidades económicas locais.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. A new approach to the Atlantic maritime strategy (short presentation)">
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la breve presentazione della relazione dell'on. Younous Omarjee, a nome della commissione per lo sviluppo regionale, su Un nuovo approccio alla strategia marittima atlantica (2020/2276(INI)) (A9-0243/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="30482" name="Younous Omarjee" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, chère Elisa Ferreira, Madame la Commissaire, mes chers collègues, vous le savez, la commission du développement régional a adopté à l’unanimité ce rapport d’initiative sur une nouvelle approche de la Stratégie maritime pour la région Atlantique, qui appelle surtout le Conseil et la Commission à la création d’une macrorégion atlantique comme il en existe, vous le savez, pour la mer Baltique, pour le Danube, pour les Alpes et pour la mer Adriatique et Ionienne. Tout nous y oblige, car l’Arc atlantique, fort de nombreux atouts, est aussi devenu l’épicentre de crises multiples. D’abord, la crise du Brexit, qui a frappé tout l’Arc atlantique et qui continue de le frapper. Et puis, la crise du COVID-19. Enfin, toutes les régions atlantiques sont également très concernées par la crise climatique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tout ceci crée de très fortes inquiétudes à court, moyen et long termes et ne sera pas non plus sans conséquence, Madame la Commissaire, sur la cohésion économique, sociale et territoriale de l’Arc atlantique ni sur les risques d’accélération des tendances au dépeuplement que nous observons déjà. À ces problèmes, nous devons répondre de manière forte et c’est ce que demandent d’ailleurs les acteurs locaux, les autorités publiques, notamment régionales, la Conférence des régions périphériques et maritimes qui, je veux le dire, ont fait un travail tout à fait exemplaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous appelons donc le Conseil européen à répondre à cette attente et à donner mandat à présent pour créer cette macrorégion. Et nous attendons de la Commission d’y travailler dès à présent. Et il n’y a pas lieu, Madame la Commissaire, de différer. Disons-le: quand les régions pensent grand, la Commission européenne pense toujours de manière trop prudente aujourd’hui – comme en témoigne d’ailleurs le plan d’action pour l’Atlantique qui, de notre point de vue, manque d’ambition et est trop éloigné des potentiels, notamment en raison du manque de fléchage budgétaire, du manque de coordination avec les fonds de coopération et les fonds structurels et de la trop grande compétitivité de sa gouvernance. Ce que la Commission propose est d’ailleurs considéré insuffisant par l’ensemble des acteurs de terrain et par notre commission REGI au Parlement européen. Insuffisant pour le développement industriel et l’emploi. Insuffisant pour la pêche durable. Insuffisant pour les ports, pour l’économie bleue et pour les objectifs climatiques.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Arc atlantique est la plus grande façade maritime de l’Europe; et l’Europe, première puissance maritime mondiale, doit penser une stratégie forte pour elle. Vous le savez, la civilisation européenne plonge ses origines multiples dans les profondeurs de l’océan Atlantique. Et d’une certaine manière, la Méditerranée a débouché dans l’Atlantique. De la découverte des Amériques à l’ouverture des nouvelles routes maritimes et commerciales en passant par l’esclavage, la révolution industrielle et la globalisation, aujourd’hui, l’Atlantique est au cœur du continent européen et continue de le façonner.</p>
      <p sl="en">Une Europe qui se pense en puissance mondiale n’a pas d’avenir sans l’Atlantique et devrait donc y accorder une priorité tout à fait stratégique. Et il serait tout à fait paradoxal que la Chine, qui a des visions mondiales, y accorde beaucoup plus d’importance que nous-mêmes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je veux, pour conclure, évidemment, remercier l’ensemble des membres de la commission REGI qui ont contribué à ce rapport, ainsi que les commissions Transports et Pêche pour leur étroite et précieuse collaboration. Puisse ce rapport d’initiative de la commission REGI être fondateur, maintenant, pour cette macrorégion atlantique que tous attendent de leurs vœux.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Elisa Ferreira" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to start by congratulating the rapporteur, Mr Omarjee, for this important report. It is in fact a report that has a strategy, a vision, and I would only like to underline that for this vision to be materialised in something more concrete, as you suggested in your speech, it is not only up to the Commission and Parliament to take that decision. It is very important also to have the engagement and the will of the Council.</p>
      <p sl="en">The report in fact addresses a very important issue – the Atlantic action plan – in response to, and trying to achieve completion of, the ideas and suggestions that were already present in the July 2020 report from the Commission for a sustainable, resilient and competitive blue economy in the European Union’s Atlantic Area covering this Atlantic facet, with the friends Ireland, Portugal and Spain.</p>
      <p sl="en">This action plan is in fact an update to the original plan that dated already from 2013. Even if we don’t move immediately towards this final objective, one of the important novelties of the new action plan is, in fact, the consideration of a governance mechanism that strengthens and gives another capacity for cooperation not just among countries, but among regions. This is an important new element.</p>
      <p sl="en">The new regional dimension is pivotal in the action plan as it includes the outermost regions of the European Union. Moreover, the Commission has been working intensively, as we just said, with the outermost regions, with other thematic platforms to help them set up their own blue economy strategies.</p>
      <p sl="en">I note positively also the suggestion in your report to organise yearly a high—level set of meetings, which the Commission will consider in view of complementing the bottom—up approach of this strategy. We also share similar views on priorities such as transport links, connectivity and boosting innovation in ports. The new action plan fully reflects these.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pillar One focuses on ports as gateways to trade and hubs for the blue economy, including the TEN—T network in the Atlantic, led by Ireland. Pillar Two concerns blue skills of the future and ocean literacy, coordinated by Portugal. Pillar Three deals with marine renewable energy development, coordinated by Spain. Pillar Four focuses on a healthy ocean and resilient coasts, addressing also marine pollution, coordinated by France.</p>
      <p sl="en">This in fact settles and organises the work in a much more rational and acceptable way. These are also the priorities that participating Member States decided jointly to focus on.</p>
      <p sl="en">On fisheries, I would like to point out that this important economic sector is broadly covered by the common fisheries policy. Nevertheless, the Commission is currently exploring with Member States how to integrate fisheries, aquaculture and tourism into the action plan’s implementation.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am pleased that the action plan also has a strong international dimension, with the Atlantic Ocean Research Alliance, including the United States, Canada, Brazil and South Africa. Furthermore, the new Atlantic action plan provides the possibility for third countries to be associated, subject to a joint decision by all participating countries.</p>
      <p sl="en">In our view, existing European funds can provide the necessary financial support for this action plan to be fully implemented. The Commission counts on the regions to mobilise, for instance, indirect funds and to mainstream programmes in that direction. To that end, the Commission is also willing to facilitate the interaction between the Interreg Atlantic Area Monetary Committee and the members of the Atlantic Strategy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Furthermore, the European Maritime Fisheries and Aquaculture Fund co—funds the so—called AspBAN project that has just kick—started in May. This project aims to establish an innovative network of Atlantic port accelerators involving start—ups, small and medium companies, so that ports can be transformed into true blue hubs.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will also fully support further flagship projects in the Atlantic area – for example, on marine renewable energy, in line with the work programme of the European Maritime Fisheries and Aquaculture Fund.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, I would like to stress that the new Atlantic action plan comes at the right time in order to give full effect to the priorities for the blue economy. The action plan provides for the necessary support to put the blue economy not only on the recovery path after the COVID—19 pandemic, but also on the path of green transformation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Thank you very much. Let’s go on working together.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La discussione è chiusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">La votazione si svolgerà martedì 14 settembre 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-5000" speaker_id="199996" name="Isabel Carvalhais" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">por escrito. – Enquanto relatora pelo S&amp;D, e atendendo ao compromisso dos relatores envolvidos no processo, considero que conseguimos um bom texto, na linha da promoção do desenvolvimento económico, social e territorial das regiões atlânticas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gostaria de destacar como pontos importantes da melhoria ao texto inicial a importância de adicionar uma componente social mais forte, que crie mais oportunidades para a criação de emprego justo e sustentável, para a formação e a educação, com foco nos jovens, para a necessidade de mais atenção a diversas áreas relevantes para o desenvolvimento sustentável da Economia Azul, como é o caso das pescas e da aquicultura e do turismo sustentável, e para a necessidade de se dar especial atenção às RUP atlânticas, que diferem muito entre si, sendo fundamental ter-se sempre em consideração as suas especificidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">Destaco igualmente a proposta de criação duma macrorregião atlântica que melhore a coordenação da utilização dos fundos europeus, que impulsione projetos ambiciosos e que reforce a inclusão das autoridades regionais e o papel das RUP atlânticas na governação da Estratégia Atlântica, privilegiando sinergias entre a dimensão marítima e a coesão económica, social e territorial.</p>
      <p sl="en">A aprovação deste relatório significa um passo em frente para garantir o melhor interesse das regiões envolvidas.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Explanations of vote: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem25" title="25. Agenda for next sitting">
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="124812" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">La seduta è tolta e riprenderà domani, martedì 14 settembre 2021, alle ore 9.00 con la comunicazione dei risultati del turno di votazioni di oggi.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno è stato pubblicato ed è disponibile sul sito web del Parlamento europeo.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem26" title="26. Closure of the sitting"/>
</text>
