<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text id="20210308.EN" lang="en" date="2021-03-08" place="Brussels" edition="Revised edition">
  <section id="creitem1" title="1. Resumption of the session">
    <intervention id="1-004-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Dichiaro ripresa la sessione del Parlamento europeo interrotta giovedì 11 febbraio 2021.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem2" title="2. Opening of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem3" title="3. Statements by the President">
    <intervention id="1-008-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Care colleghe e cari colleghi, desidero ringraziare la Prima ministra Ardern, la Vicepresidente Harris, per aver accolto il nostro invito a rivolgersi alla nostra Assemblea oggi per celebrare la Giornata internazionale delle donne e riflettere con noi sulle sfide che ci aspettano. Ringrazio la Signora Presidente Von der Leyen per essere in Aula con noi e la Vicepresidente Jourová.</p>
      <p sl="en">I nostri paesi e le nostre società sono uniti da legami storici, culturali, politici, economici profondi, e anche in questo frangente drammatico per il mondo intero, condividiamo l'impegno per una ripresa economica e sociale dove nessuno sia lasciato indietro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quella di oggi non può essere una celebrazione retorica. Siamo infatti nel pieno di una crisi drammatica che si è aperta esattamente un anno fa e che ha visto le donne e le ragazze non soltanto in prima fila nella risposta sanitaria e nell'emergenza, ma anche subire in pieno le conseguenze economiche, sociali, materiali della pandemia nelle loro vite.</p>
      <p sl="en">Diceva Simone de Beauvoir: "Non dimenticate mai che sarà sufficiente una crisi politica, economica o religiosa perché i diritti delle donne siano rimessi in discussione. Questi diritti non sono mai acquisiti. Dovrete rimanere vigili per tutta la vita". Questa citazione si adatta molto bene alla crisi che stiamo attraversando.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signore e signori, la pandemia di COVID-19 non soltanto ha consolidato ingiustizie e disuguaglianze, ma rischia di cancellare decenni di conquiste delle battaglie delle donne europee sul diritto al lavoro, alla condivisone del lavoro di cura, all'autonomia nelle relazioni, al rispetto e al diritto delle proprie scelte nelle relazioni affettive.</p>
      <p sl="en">In tutti i nostri paesi le donne sono state le prime a perdere il lavoro o a finire in cassa integrazione. I settori più colpiti dall'impatto economico della pandemia sono settori in cui è forte la presenza femminile: il turismo, la cultura, il tempo libero e la ristorazione. La maggior parte della forza lavoro che fornisce servizi essenziali alla cura delle persone è costituita da donne. Le donne rappresentano il 76 % del personale sanitario nell'Unione europea e l'86% dei prestatori di assistenza.</p>
      <p sl="en">A causa della pandemia, molte donne sono state costrette a lavorare a tempo parziale o a rimanere a casa per occuparsi dei loro figli, degli anziani e delle persone con disabilità. L'identikit della povertà in Europa oggi è donna e madre.</p>
      <p sl="en">Inoltre, durante il confinamento, un numero ancora più alto di donne ha subito le violenze di un partner o di un familiare tra le mura domestiche, senza possibilità di fuga, anche perché in molti Stati membri ancora incredibilmente mancano i centri di accoglienza, le linee telefoniche che possano consentire di aiutare le vittime delle violenze.</p>
      <p sl="en">Questa pandemia ha messo in luce un tratto perverso del nostro modello economico e sociale, e cioè la considerazione della povertà come una colpa. La pandemia ha anche messo in evidenza quanto la cura degli altri sia essenziale per la società e tutto questo costituisca un bene pubblico da difendere. E di quanto quel lavoro di cura, oggi affidato in gran parte alle donne, sia in realtà una responsabilità di tutti e debba essere considerato bene pubblico.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signore e signori, possiamo combattere contro questa pandemia e contro l'impatto sociale ed economico che ha e avrà nella nostra vita, nella vita delle persone soltanto se noi metteremo le donne e le ragazze al centro della nostra risposta. Non dobbiamo farlo come tributo a un principio generale, dobbiamo farlo imbracciando i poteri che abbiamo, che ha il Parlamento, che hanno le istituzioni, per cambiare in meglio la condizione materiale di vita delle donne e far compiere un balzo in avanti e non indietro alle donne nella transizione che stiamo costruendo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il continente che ha guidato la lotta per i diritti delle donne oggi è chiamato a promuovere l'uguaglianza reale delle donne come battaglia di tutti. Innanzitutto le donne devono essere presenti in modo paritario nei luoghi dove si assumono le decisioni sulla ripresa. Per questo è essenziale sbloccare la direttiva sulla presenza delle donne nei consigli di amministrazione, da troppi anni ferma in seno al Consiglio, e conto sull'impegno della Presidenza portoghese per questo essenziale obiettivo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ma questo non basta. Occorre partire dall'uguaglianza salariale. Uguale salario per uguale lavoro. Le donne in Europa guadagnano in media il 14,1 % in meno degli uomini. Questo non è più accettabile. Siamo quindi pronti a lavorare alla proposta della Commissione per una trasparenza salariale vincolante presentata ieri e che metteremo al centro del nostro lavoro.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Parlamento si è battuto, come sapete, perché la parità di genere e la dimensione di genere fossero priorità centrali nel bilancio settennale dell'Unione europea e nella valutazione dei piani nazionali di ripresa. Questo non è astratto. Se la ripresa avrà la priorità dell'uguaglianza, questo cambierà la vita delle persone e delle donne molto concretamente in tutti i nostri paesi, nelle città, sui luoghi di un lavoro ritrovato e conquistato, nelle scuole e nelle università, nei centri di ricerca.</p>
      <p sl="en">E ancora, molto concretamente, proprio perché non è il tempo della retorica, abbiamo il dovere di sancire che la violenza sulle donne è un reato grave e che deve essere sanzionato ovunque in tutto il territorio dell'Unione europea. Per questo dobbiamo impegnarci per la ratifica, da parte di tutti gli Stati membri dell'Unione, della Convenzione di Istanbul e per fare della violenza contro le donne un reato a dimensione europea. Non è una questione astratta, dicevo, riguarda ciò che siamo, è parte della nostra carta di identità come grande attore globale e blocco democratico.</p>
      <p sl="en">Signore e signori, questa crisi così drammatica ci consegna la grande opportunità di fare dell'Unione europea un luogo diverso e più eguale. Abbiamo molti strumenti e molte risorse per farlo, li abbiamo varati con grande impegno unitario, in tutto questo anno che abbiamo vissuto così drammaticamente e sono oggi a disposizione anche dell'obiettivo di un'economia più giusta.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le donne, le ragazze, le bambine devono essere le protagoniste della ripresa delle nostre economie e delle nostre società. Questo deve essere un obiettivo, l'obiettivo di tutti, di tutte per questo 2021.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-009-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Ursula von der Leyen" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="President of the European Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, my fellow European women, let’s have a look at what women have endured in 12 months of pandemic. The female doctors and nurses working double shifts for entire weeks and months. The women entrepreneurs who fought back, reinvented their business and pulled out all the stops to save their employees. The mothers of lockdown children who have had to learn the toughest and most amazing job in the world, with no support from the outside world. Look at Vice-President Kamala Harris, look at Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern, and what they’ve done for their countries. Look at their grace, professionalism, compassion and resolve. Look at all these amazing women in our families and communities, and think again: this day is for them.</p>
      <p sl="en">From the women on the front line and the women in the back office, to the businesswomen and the volunteers, to the mothers, to the daughters, to the unsung heroes of this pandemic, this is your day and this is my thank you to all of you.</p>
      <p sl="en">On Women’s Day, I want all European women to know that Europe is at their side. I am on your side. I want Europe to finally become a continent of equal opportunities for men and women. And I know we are not there yet. I know the playing field is not level yet. I know from experience that women have to work twice as hard to get the same salary, the same recognition for the same leadership positions as their male colleagues.</p>
      <p sl="en">I know the obstacles and the prejudices and therefore I am proud that last week the Commission presented two proposals to address two of the great injustices that women still face: the gender pay gap and the gender employment gap. Women in Europe are paid on average 14% less than men. This is simply not right. So we are proposing a European directive for pay transparency. It is built on two simple principles. Equal work deserves equal pay and for equal pay you need transparency. And women must know whether their employers treat them fairly, and when this is not the case, they must have the power to fight back and get what they deserve.</p>
      <p sl="en">And there’s more to do. Too many women in Europe lack a very fundamental opportunity, the opportunity to work and to earn a living. Today, the employment rate for women is 67%, while that of men is 78%. And this is simply not acceptable. So last week we set a new target for Europe. We must cut the gender employment gap in half, and by the end of this decade, 78% of all must have a job. It won’t be easy, but I can promise that we will do all in our power to work towards this goal.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will strengthen childcare, because no woman or man should have to choose between being a mother or father or having a career. We will strengthen elderly care. We will invest in quality education for girls and women. We will push for more women in leadership positions, in public and private bodies across all economic sectors. And we have required that all Member States put women at the centre of their recovery plans. It will only be a true recovery if these plans are for all.</p>
      <p sl="en">Honourable Members, let me quote Vice-President Harris and adapt her words to Europe. We must show every child in Europe that there are no limits to who can lead and hold positions of power in our Union, regardless of colour or gender. Vice-President Harris and Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern, we are indeed in this together. Equality has been enshrined in the European Treaty since 1957. It’s been a long road and we will keep walking. We have to remove the obstacles on the path towards equality. We have to strive for equal opportunities. It is not rocket science. The necessary tools are well known and proven. We just have to implement them and do it. Long live Europe and Happy Women’s Day!</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-010-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ringrazio la Presidente von der Leyen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rimuovere gli ostacoli, è stato detto da tutti in questa giornata che non vuole essere retorica, ma una giornata di impegno, impegno perché effettivamente l'Europa sia capace di dare il segno di una vera parità, e credo che questa sia la conclusione di questa celebrazione. Ringrazio tutti per avervi partecipato.</p>
      <a text="(Applausi)"/>
      <p sl="en">È con profonda tristezza che abbiamo appreso nei giorni scorsi dell'assassinio dell'ambasciatore italiano nella Repubblica Democratica del Congo. Luca Attanasio è stato ucciso insieme al carabiniere Vittorio Iacovacci e all'autista Moustapha Milambo, il 22 febbraio, vicino a Goma, mentre facevano parte di un convoglio del Programma alimentare mondiale degli Stati Uniti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il Parlamento europeo dedicherà un dibattito in questa sessione, giovedì prossimo, a tutto questo ma vorrei iniziare la nostra sessione plenaria inviando le nostre più profonde condoglianze alle famiglie, alle vittime e ai loro cari.</p>
      <p sl="en">I nostri pensieri sono con loro e con tutte le vittime della violenza e vi prego di unirvi a me in un minuto di silenzio.</p>
      <a text="(Il Parlamento, in piedi, osserva un minuto di silenzio)"/>
      <p sl="en">⁂</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-011-0000" speaker_id="197843" name="Andrius Kubilius" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, dear colleagues, our brothers and sisters in Ukraine and Crimea, I am speaking on behalf of all of us. I am speaking to all of you and asking you to commemorate a very sad event in the recent history of the European continent. Seven years ago exactly, at the beginning of March, the Kremlin authorities were finalising the occupation of Crimea. They occupied this beautiful part of Ukraine simply because the people of Ukraine had decided to move closer to the European Union. That was how the most brutal international crime on the European continent after the Second World War was committed.</p>
      <p sl="en">We Europeans, neighbours and friends of Ukraine, were only able to observe this crime with sincere pain. Since then, the European Parliament, on every occasion, has been very clear in its non-recognition of the Crimean occupation policy. The European Parliament is also very clear in its solidarity with the indigenous Tatar and Ukrainian people, who are suffering from the very hard conditions of the occupying regime. Permanent human rights violations and political persecutions are what many of the Crimean people are living through.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me stress that I am absolutely sure, despite our political or regional differences, that the European Parliament will stay strong in its non-recognition policy and its solidarity with the people who are suffering because of the occupation. Our solidarity was very clear when, two years ago, the Sakharov Prize was awarded to one of the victims of the Crimean occupation, the famous filmmaker Oleg Sentsov.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can remind the Kremlin authorities that the Western non-recognition policy is a very powerful instrument. For 50 years, from 1940 until 1990, Lithuania and other Baltic States were occupied by the Soviet Union. For all that time the US and Western Europe did not recognise our occupation and, because of that permanent policy, we regained our freedom in the end. The same will happen with the occupation of Crimea. We shall never recognise this occupation. We shall keep our solidarity with the Crimean people and the people of Ukraine and, in the end, Crimea will become free again. Slava Ukraini!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-012-0000" speaker_id="197469" name="Assita Kanko" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I would like to draw your attention today to the murder of David Polfliet in Belgium. He was 41 years old. He had been trapped by young boys who attacked him and killed him because he was gay. So I’m using this opportunity to say that love is love, and nobody should die for who they are. Please join me in sharing the pain of his family, and wishing for more justice in our Member States.</p>
      <a text="(Applause)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-013-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ringrazio l'onorevole Kanko per averci ricordato questa tragedia.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem4" title="4. Approval of the minutes of the previous sittings">
    <intervention id="1-015-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il processo verbale e i testi approvati delle sedute dell'8, 9, 10 e 11 febbraio sono stati distribuiti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vi sono osservazioni?</p>
      <p sl="en">Se non vi sono osservazioni, il processo verbale è approvato.</p>
      <p sl="en">⁂</p>
      <p sl="en">Ha chiesto di intervenire l'onorevole Ponsatí Obiols per un fatto personale. Onorevole, Le ricordo che il regolamento del Parlamento prevede che l'oratore non possa intervenire sull'argomento della discussione ma deve limitarsi a respingere affermazioni fatte nel corso della discussione con riferimento alla sua persona o a opinioni che gli sono state attribuite, oppure rettificare proprie dichiarazioni precedenti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il regolamento prevede inoltre che il deputato possa chiedere di parlare per fatto personale al momento dell'approvazione del processo verbale della seduta a cui si riferisce la richiesta di intervento. La sua richiesta deve quindi riferirsi ad affermazioni fatte con riferimento alla Sua persona o a opinioni che Le sono state attribuite nella tornata di febbraio.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-016-0000" speaker_id="204443" name="Clara Ponsatí Obiols" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I wasn’t aware that I was going to get this opportunity. There must have been a bit of confusion here, but nevertheless I take the opportunity, thank you.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-017-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ma se evidentemente c'è stato un disguido …</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-018-0000" speaker_id="204443" name="Clara Ponsatí Obiols" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I presume this refers to someone speaking about me not in the previous plenary but the previous one to that. That is why I am confused.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-019-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Evidentemente c'è stato un disguido. La ringrazio e passiamo al prossimo annuncio.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem5" title="5. Request for consent submitted by the Council (Rule 105): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem6" title="6. Council position at first reading: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem7" title="7. Composition of political groups: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem8" title="8. Composition of committees and delegations: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem9" title="9. Extension of the mandate of the special committees: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem10" title="10. Delegated acts (Rule 111(6)): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem11" title="11. Negotiations ahead of the Council’s first reading (Rule 72): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem12" title="12. Signing of acts adopted in accordance with the ordinary legislative procedure (Rule 79): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem13" title="13. Questions for oral answer (submission): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem14" title="14. Action taken on Parliament’s positions and resolutions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem15" title="15. Decision to apply the joint committee procedure (Rule 58): see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem16" title="16. Documents received: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem17" title="17. Order of business: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem18" title="18. A WTO-compatible EU carbon border adjustment mechanism (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-034-0000" speaker_id="96864" name="Presidente" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">L'ordine del giorno reca la relazione di Yannick Jadot, a nome della commissione per l'ambiente, la sanità pubblica e la sicurezza alimentare, "Verso un meccanismo UE di adeguamento del carbonio alla frontiera compatibile con l'OMC" (2020/2043(INI)) (A9-0019/2021).</p>
      <p sl="en">Ricordo agli onorevoli deputati che per tutte le discussioni di questa tornata non è prevista la procedura "catch-the-eye", né saranno accettate domande "cartellino blu".</p>
      <p sl="en">Inoltre, come nelle ultime tornate, sono previsti interventi a distanza dagli Uffici di collegamento del Parlamento europeo negli Stati membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-035-0000" speaker_id="96740" name="Yannick Jadot" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, commissaire Gentiloni, chers collègues, un tel rapport, vous le savez, c’est toujours un travail collectif. C’est toujours un succès collectif ou un échec individuel. Je veux croire que ce sera un succès collectif. Nous avons travaillé, je dois le dire, dans une grande compréhension, dans un esprit pour avancer, dans un esprit de compromis et je voudrais remercier les collègues de la commission de l’environnement, de la santé publique et de la sécurité alimentaire, mais aussi celle du commerce international, celle des affaires économiques et monétaires, celle des budgets ainsi que la commission de l’industrie, de la recherche et de l’énergie qui, évidemment, ont déposé un avis et parfois du fait de leur compétence. Donc, je remercie l’ensemble des collègues pour ce travail.</p>
      <p sl="en">Parce que ce qui se joue, c’est évidemment un enjeu important de crédibilité et de légitimité de l’Union européenne. Nous savons l’urgence climatique, nous la subissons. Les scientifiques ne cessent de nous alerter et nous avons décidé de placer l’agenda climatique au cœur de l’agenda européen, que ce soit avec le pacte vert pour l’Europe, évidemment, et puis avec la négociation en cours sur la loi Climat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mais c’est aussi un enjeu de crédibilité sur la défense de notre économie, la protection de nos entreprises et de notre économie puisqu’avec cette pandémie, nous avons vu aussi que la question de notre souveraineté ou de notre autonomie stratégique, la question des choix d’investissements sectoriels étaient des enjeux essentiels pour anticiper les grands défis de demain. Nous avons ce rapport sur l’ajustement carbone aux frontières qui, évidemment, fait le lien entre le dérèglement climatique, entre le pacte vert européen et l’innovation, la protection et la reconstruction économique et industrielle de l’Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est quoi, ce mécanisme d’ajustement carbone aux frontières? C’est d’abord l’objectif d’élargir le champ de la politique climatique européenne à l’ensemble de l’économie qui nous concerne, puisque jusqu’à maintenant, la politique climatique portait sur la production des gaz à effet de serre sur le sol européen. Avec l’ajustement carbone aux frontières, notre politique climatique couvre également la question des importations et donc c’est essentiel de passer des émissions liées à la production sur le sol européen à notre empreinte carbone. C’est déjà le premier point essentiel de cet instrument.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le deuxième point qui est essentiel également, c’est l’idée que décarboner, c’est important, mais on ne va pas décarboner en délocalisant une partie de notre industrie; on ne va pas décarboner en désindustrialisant l’Europe. On sait à quel point ce sujet est sensible. Aujourd’hui, aucun rapport n’a démontré que dans les années qui se sont écoulées, il y a eu des fuites de carbone, ces délocalisations liées à la politique climatique européenne, mais avec le nouvel objectif – j’espère 60 % d’ici 2030, c’est ce qu’a voté le Parlement européen et je ne doute pas que c’est ce que défend la Commission européenne – nous allons incontestablement resserrer les contraintes sur l’économie, nous allons incontestablement changer les règles sur le marché ETS et donc demander plus d’efforts à nos entreprises. Et il serait inacceptable que ces efforts conduisent à une concurrence déloyale sur les marchés internationaux et aussi sur le marché européen. Donc, l’objectif de l’ajustement carbone aux frontières est de contrer, de combattre cette concurrence déloyale en imposant aux entreprises qui exporteraient sur le marché européen de répondre exactement aux mêmes contraintes que nous imposons à nos entreprises sur le marché européen, sur le sol européen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous avons cet objectif, nous avons cet outil. Nous sommes tombés d’accord et je crois, tous les groupes politiques l’ont défendu, sur le fait que l’ajustement carbone aux frontières allait être le bon mécanisme pour nous protéger de cette concurrence déloyale et pour éviter les fuites de carbone. Mais si nous considérons que c’est le bon mécanisme, alors il doit à un moment se substituer aux mécanismes existants, notamment ceux de la réglementation ETS, dans l’ensemble de nos politiques climatiques, il y avait les quotas gratuits. Vous avez lu comme moi, je l’espère, le rapport de la Cour des comptes sur le système ETS et sur les quotas gratuits qui suivent d’autres rapports de la Cour des comptes, qui nous indique que ces quotas gratuits ne sont pas le mécanisme le plus efficace à la fois pour servir l’objectif climatique qui est l’objet de ce débat, mais qui est le plus efficace aussi pour protéger nos industries.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il y a ce paragraphe 28 dans le rapport. De quoi est-il question dans ce paragraphe 28? Je rappelle que dans les compromis de ce paragraphe 28, ils ont été co-écrits par la plupart des groupes politiques, dont le PPE. Ils ont été co-signés par la plupart des groupes politiques, dont le PPE. Ils ont été votés en commission par la plupart des groupes politiques, dont le PPE. J’aimerais qu’au moment du vote en plénière, notamment le PPE, pas par loyauté, le sujet n’est pas la loyauté, mais dans ce rapport, nous n’anticipons pas la réforme de l’ETS. Notre seul sujet, chers collègues, c’est garantir la crédibilité, la légitimité, la légalité au regard de l’OMC et l’efficacité d’un mécanisme d’ajustement aux frontières pour renforcer notre action climatique et protéger nos industries.</p>
      <p sl="en">En conclusion, je vous demande, chers collègues, de respecter l’ensemble du travail que nous avons fait dans toutes les commissions et je demande particulièrement aux collègues du PPE de soutenir aussi ce qu’a été le travail auquel vous avez participé dans toutes les commissions, dont la commission pour l’environnement. On a une responsabilité historique: lutter contre le dérèglement climatique, c’est une aspiration citoyenne. Protéger nos entreprises et protéger nos emplois, c’est une aspiration citoyenne et c’est l’aspiration des salariés. Alors, faisons-le ensemble, faisons-le comme nous l’avons fait dans les commissions, faisons-le en votant de la même manière que nous l’avons fait dans les commissions.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je remercie l’ensemble des collègues, encore une fois, qui ont participé à ce rapport et l’ensemble des collègues qui voteront dans les jours qui viennent, en tout cas jusqu’à demain et mercredi pour le vote final, en respectant ce qui a été fait dans les commissions.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-037-0000" speaker_id="197401" name="Karin Karlsbro" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">föredragande INTA. – Herr talman! Herr kommissionär! Kollegor och åhörare! Vi står inför en akut, global klimatkris och det finns ingen tid att förlora. Forskarna är överens om att en global prissättning på koldioxid skulle vara den mest effektiva åtgärden för att minska utsläppen. Men så länge det inte är praktiskt möjligt måste vi hitta andra vägar framåt. Hos många av EU:s handelspartner är det billigt eller till och med gratis att släppa ut koldioxid.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det är därför hög tid för EU att införa ett pris på utsläpp från importerade varor. Förorenaren ska betala, inte bara i EU. Vi måste helt enkelt betala för alla utsläpp oavsett var de sker. För att en gränsjusteringmekanism för koldioxidutsläpp ska bli möjlig måste den vara en renodlad klimatåtgärd. Den måste vara i linje med de internationella handelsreglerna under WTO och med våra handels- och investeringsavtal. Samtidigt måste man skapa incitament för producenter både inom och utanför EU att ställa om sin produktion, och för länder att själva prissätta utsläpp. Inga utsläpp ska prissättas två gånger och ingen produktion ska heller skyddas två gånger.</p>
      <p sl="en">Det är inte våra handelspartner vi vill komma åt. Det är utsläppen vi riktar oss mot, vi gör inte det mot någon, vi vill göra det tillsammans med andra länder. Vi vill dessutom att intäkterna ska gå till klimatsatsningar, i framför allt fattiga länder. Tiden där vi fortsätter med ”trade as usual” är förbi. Klimatet måste räddas och handeln måste bli hållbar. Utan att någonsin sluta kämpa för en öppen internationell handel och en fri marknad, så kommer en prissättning av importerade utsläpp vara en nyckel för att sänka utsläppen. EU kan inte vänta. Vi måste låta förorenaren betala oavsett var utsläppen sker.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-038-0000" speaker_id="197554" name="Luis Garicano" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Asuntos Económicos y Monetarios. – Señor presidente, el cambio climático es el reto más complejo a que se enfrenta la humanidad. Para derrotarlo no bastan las buenas intenciones, sino que requerimos soluciones verdaderamente innovadoras.</p>
      <p sl="en">Una de las más importantes es el mecanismo de ajuste en frontera que presentamos hoy, con gran trabajo de nuestros colegas de la Comisión de Medio Ambiente y de las demás comisiones.</p>
      <p sl="en">La lógica del mecanismo es sencilla. Pensemos en un coche: un coche está compuesto por cientos de materiales, que incluyen el aluminio, el acero y el vidrio. Si estos materiales se producen dentro de la Unión Europea, tienen que pagar unos cuarenta euros por cada tonelada de CO2 que generan. Sin embargo, si estos materiales se producen fuera de la Unión Europea, no pagan ningún coste por ese carbono. Por tanto, los coches fabricados en la Unión Europea son menos competitivos. Perdemos competitividad si los materiales vienen de dentro de la Unión Europea.</p>
      <p sl="en">Esto pone a nuestras industrias en una posición muy difícil, pero, sobre todo, le hace un flaco favor a nuestro planeta, ya que solo consigue que las fábricas cierren en Europa y se muevan a otro sitio, con el mismo coste de carbono, con el mismo efecto para el planeta, pero con menos empleos para los europeos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gracias al mecanismo de ajuste en frontera, cualquier material pagará por las emisiones lo que tenga que pagar, da igual si se produce dentro o fuera la Unión Europea. Por ejemplo, los importadores de coches tendrán que pagar por el peso de los componentes básicos el CO2 que produzcan, sea acero, vidrio o aluminio.</p>
      <p sl="en">Commissioner Gentiloni, the great majority of the European Parliament is saying loud and clear that we want the carbon border adjustment mechanism. The Commission should take note of the strong preference in the Parliament for a system based on emissions trading (ETS), our willingness to cover all ETS sectors, as well as final products, and the proposal of the Committee on Economic and Monetary Affairs for fiscal design to assess the carbon content of imports.</p>
      <p sl="en">If the Commission delivers, it will find strong support and a really strong ally in the European Parliament. I think that we have today presented a really feasible proposal to solve one of the biggest problems that we face, and I hope the Commission will really take this forward from here and build a really strong proposal very soon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-040-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Paolo Gentiloni" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, I think it is a welcome initiative by Parliament to highlight the importance of a carbon border adjustment mechanism, or CBAM as we call it now. We know that climate change is the greatest challenge we face. Parliament and the Council are currently debating how to incorporate an increased target for emission reduction by 2030 in the European Climate Law. To make this ambition a reality the Commission will next summer present a revision of all its climate and energy legislation, and the CBAM will be a key element of the Commission’s comprehensive green growth agenda.</p>
      <p sl="en">As highlighted in your report, the overarching objective of CBAM is to help ensure the integrity and effectiveness of our climate policies by addressing the risk of carbon leakage. CBAM is a climate measure. It is not a protectionist measure. It is about enabling the EU to step up to its climate ambitions. It is not to win unfair advantages over our partners. If third-country partners adopted effective decarbonisation policies similar to those of the EU, the need for this adjustment would be less. The CBAM is one of the candidates for possible new own resources, following the own-resources roadmap as part of the interinstitutional agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">The report addresses important aspects of the design of the CBAM. The Commission is currently considering different options. The measure could, for example, take the form of a system which would mirror the ETS system and cover imports from third countries, but other options are also being assessed.</p>
      <p sl="en">The objective of sustainable growth calls urgently for a green transition, but also for a fair transition. The social and employment impacts of the CBAM will be assessed and compared with the likely impacts of increasing the EU climate ambition without introducing such an instrument. The design needs, of course, to respect WTO rules and our trade agreements, as well as other international commitments.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me say a few words about sectors. We have not made our choices yet, but the CBAM will be designed in a way that allows, if need be, for a gradual extension of its scope over time. In selecting the sectors, we will ensure that the measure applies where the risk of carbon leakage is highest. The sectors referred to in your report are among the sectors under consideration.</p>
      <p sl="en">On the timing, the CBAM will not enter into force immediately. Our working assumption is to have it in place by 2023 as set out in the agreement on own resources. We are assessing various scenarios to allow for a smooth and predictable transition from the main measure currently in place to address carbon leakage – the free allowances of ETS – and the CBAM. We need the transition.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is important to engage with trade partners and this concern is also reflected in the report, because climate change is a global issue and the solution also needs to be global, and we have better conditions for this global agreement now. We need to coordinate with our trade partners. If we are ambitious together, we will be more effective, and the mutual benefits of our respective efforts will increase, and the climate COP in Glasgow later this year will be an important moment in this regard. So I am happy to conclude that I share many of the concerns raised in the report, and I look forward to listening to your discussion on this important topic.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-041-0000" speaker_id="197638" name="Margarida Marques" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">relatora de parecer da Comissão dos Orçamentos. – Senhor Presidente, Senhor Comissário Gentiloni, Colegas, nas negociações do período orçamental em curso acordámos a entrada de novos recursos próprios no financiamento da União Europeia. E a Comissão terá de apresentar as propostas legislativas necessárias respeitando um calendário obrigatório.</p>
      <p sl="en">Novos Recursos Próprios, em montante suficiente para cobrir, pelo menos, o capital e os juros do Next Generation EU. O excedente deve ficar no orçamento da União como receita global.</p>
      <p sl="en">Um destes novos Recursos Próprios é exatamente o Mecanismo de Ajustamento das Emissões de Carbono nas Fronteiras, como aliás já referiu o Senhor Comissário Gentiloni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Temos, pois, que assegurar que este Mecanismo faz parte do cabaz de recursos próprios. E que respeita o princípio da universalidade.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mas há um calendário a cumprir. Respeitar os compromissos assumidos obriga a Comissão a apresentar a sua proposta a tempo, para que o Mecanismo contribua para o orçamento da União Europeia o mais tardar a partir de 1 de janeiro de 2023.</p>
      <p sl="en">É isso que esperamos, Senhor Comissário Gentiloni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-042-0000" speaker_id="197718" name="Nicolás González Casares" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Industria, Investigación y Energía. – Señor presidente, en primer lugar, querría destacar el trabajo de Jens Geier, mi compañero, que no puede estar aquí.</p>
      <p sl="en">En buena medida, gracias a las políticas climáticas, la Unión Europea dispone de una industria más eficiente y menos intensiva en carbono, pero a cambio sufrimos una desindustrialización en algunos sectores.</p>
      <p sl="en">Elevar nuestra ambición para el cumplimiento de nuestros compromisos climáticos debe acompañarse de un esfuerzo en las medidas contra la fuga de carbono, como es este ajuste de carbono en frontera: igualdad de condiciones, necesaria tanto para extender nuestras políticas climáticas como para promover esos estándares fuera de la Unión, porque las contribuciones al Acuerdo de París no pueden venir solo de una parte.</p>
      <p sl="en">Las emisiones de CO2 cuentan en nuestro mercado único; también deben hacerlo para las importaciones: que a quien contamine no le salga a cuenta en Europa y no se le otorgue una ventaja competitiva en costes, al contrario. Pero su implementación solo será viable si con ello mejoramos el modelo actual de las medidas contra la fuga de carbono asegurando la protección de nuestra industria y del empleo evitando efectos perversos.</p>
      <p sl="en">Si el ajuste de frontera no puede garantizar esto, no ayudaremos ni a la protección del clima ni a nuestros trabajadores. Pongámoslo en marcha de una manera responsable.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-043-0000" speaker_id="197517" name="Adam Jarubas" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, we need a carbon border adjustment mechanism (CBAM) so that Europe can effectively curb its global carbon footprint from the consumption of goods, not only those made in Europe but also imported ones. This goal is clear: products entering the EU market have to bear the comparable cost of their greenhouse gas emissions, regardless of origin. In the EU we have an emissions trading scheme (ETS), but imported goods have an advantage that is detrimental for reducing global emissions. I think that while working on the report we all agreed on this.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to thank the rapporteur and shadow rapporteurs for their constructive work. But there are some details that we need to clarify. There are voices in favour of us making a transition from one system of anti-carbon leakage measures to another, the current one being free allowances under the EU ETS, the future being the CBAM.</p>
      <p sl="en">And here I think there is a problem. The possible phasing-out of free allowances will have detrimental effects for European exporters. And if we get rid of free allowances, we may foster carbon leakage, not within the sectors directly concerned, but in those dependent on production. Therefore, we have to be very careful when stating that CBAM is an alternative to existing measures. It clearly doesn’t work in the same way.</p>
      <p sl="en">When we are talking about the transition, I would like to make sure, Commissioner, that the design of CBAM will allow for the coexistence of this mechanism with free allocation in a WTO—compatible way. We know that such a design is possible. Otherwise the transition will turn into a direct switch and our economy is not ready for such an experiment.</p>
      <p sl="en">We in the European People’s Party feel that in regard to ETS reform, the report went a little too far, and we would prefer to bring the balance back so that the report is not a report on the future of the ETS system but on the carbon border adjustment mechanism.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-044-0000" speaker_id="197782" name="Mohammed Chahim" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the S&amp;D Group">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, the carbon border adjustment mechanism is an important mechanism within the European Green Deal. In order to decarbonise our industry, we need to have the right instruments in place to incentivise and stimulate our industry to invest in green solutions and, at the same time, make sure we do not have unfair competition from outside the EU. We need a level playing field. Moreover, the carbon border adjustment mechanism sends a clear message to producers outside the EU: if you want your products to enter the EU market, you need to embrace our standards. This will have a significant effect on global CO2 emissions.</p>
      <p sl="en">But let me be clear. The main objective of this mechanism is to decrease global CO2 emissions and the fundamentals of this report are fair. I want to thank the rapporteur for that. He clearly really listened to all parties and tried to make a good compromise. We want to wait for the Commission’s impact assessment to see what the best way is to implement this mechanism. However, at the same time, Parliament has set some clear conditions. With the introduction of the carbon border adjustment mechanism, we have to reassess the free allowances within the emissions trading system. We must avoid double protection.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore we, as Socialists and Democrats, support a gradual, yet rapid, phasing-out of the free allowances when the carbon border adjustment mechanism is installed. It must be done in a transparent and predictable way so that we can give industry, in the EU and outside the EU, time to adjust. We have reached a balanced text on this in the negotiations and we note that the June package, the ‘Fit for 55’ package, is coming with a lot of climate legislation. We have to work together in Parliament to pass this legislation successfully.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is clear that some Groups still have to decide if they want to be on the right side of history when it comes to battling climate change. But, unlike some political groups in this House, most industries have made the decision to decarbonise and are welcoming the European Green Deal. Now they need clear legislation and investments to help achieve our goals.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-045-0000" speaker_id="96711" name="Pascal Canfin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Renew. – Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, mes chers collègues, nous débattons aujourd’hui du mécanisme d’ajustement carbone aux frontières.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est un élément essentiel dans l’arsenal que nous avons pour lutter contre le dérèglement climatique. C’est un élément essentiel parce que nous allons réformer le marché du carbone, c’est prévu pour le mois de juin. Le prix du marché du carbone c’est aujourd’hui 40 € la tonne de CO2, c’est déjà un niveau historique et ce que nous visons, c’est 50 €, peut-être même 60 € la tonne de CO2. Et à ce niveau de prix, c’est impossible pour les industriels européens concernés de rester en concurrence avec des acteurs économiques qui paieraient zéro euro sur le CO2. Moi, je ne peux pas aller dans le nord de la France, à Dunkerque, à l’usine de sidérurgie ArcelorMittal et dire: vous allez perdre des marchés parce que ce sont les Indiens ou les Turcs qui vont exporter sans payer le prix du carbone vers l’Union européenne. Je ne peux pas aller en Pologne et dire aux salariés d’une cimenterie: maintenant, c’est fini votre emploi parce que c’est en Biélorussie ou en Ukraine qu’on va produire le ciment dont on a besoin, qu’ils paient zéro euro pour le carbone. Ce n’est pas possible. C’est pour cela, Monsieur le Commissaire, que nous exigeons que vous ne puissiez pas nous décevoir en juin. Et que veut dire «ne pas nous décevoir»? Cela signifie une méthode très simple, un mécanisme d’ajustement au carbone aux frontières qui est le miroir du marché carbone européen. Pas une taxe, une taxe, c’est l’unanimité, cela veut dire probablement pas de mécanisme à la fin. Pas une taxe qui est payée par les consommateurs, une taxe qui est payée par les industriels qui exportent vers l’Union européenne. Donc, ne vous trompez pas, surtout, d’outil juridique; faites comme le Parlement vous le demande, faites un mécanisme qui est le miroir du marché européen du carbone: le même prix, les mêmes volumes, c’est compatible avec l’OMC. Même Pascal Lamy, l’ancien directeur de l’OMC, le justifie. Et donc, ne vous trompez pas en ayant un mauvais cheval, un mauvais outil juridique, suivez les recommandations qui, je n’en doute pas, seront largement adoptées cette semaine par le Parlement européen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-046-0000" speaker_id="197594" name="Laura Huhtasaari" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ID-ryhmän puolesta. – Arvoisa puhemies, kannatan tulevia hiilitulleja, mikäli niiden avulla saadaan vähennettyä hiilivuotoriskiä ja näin parannettua Euroopan teollisuuden kilpailukykyä saastuttajamaita vastaan. Hiilitullia koskevassa valiokunta-aloitteisessa mietinnössä ajauduttiin kuitenkin monessa kohtaa väärille urille. Mietintö painottaa, että toisin kuin päästökauppajärjestelmässä, mekanismissa ei pitäisi katsoa puun polttamista polttoaineena hiilineutraaliksi, ja että tarkistetussa ja päivitetyssä kehyksessä myös kaadettuun puuhun ja köyhtyneeseen maaperään sisältyvällä hiilellä olisi oltava hinta. Kyllähän puun lahoaminenkin aiheuttaa hiilidioksidipäästöjä. Meidän pitää rajata älykkäästi, meidän ei pidä lähteä vouhottamaan. En halua, että tulevaisuudessa esimerkiksi, kun suomalainen kaataa omasta metsästään puun, hän joutuu maksaa siitä veroa. Tai jos hän lämmittää oman talonsa ja saunansa puulla, hän joutuisi maksamaan siitä veroa. Tehkäämme älykkäästi ja fiksusti tämä hiilitullimietintö.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-047-0000" speaker_id="206158" name="Manuela Ripa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der Verts/ALE-Fraktion. – Herr Präsident! Klimaschutz ist schon lange keine europäische Aufgabe mehr. Klimaschutz kann nur global erreicht werden, das sollte jedem klar sein. Zur Eindämmung der globalen CO2-Emissionen brauchen wir grundlegende Veränderungen, und der CO2-Grenzausgleichmechanismus – kurz CBAM – ist ein ganz wesentlicher Teil davon. Aber auch nur, wenn er richtig angepackt wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der jetzige europäische Emissionshandel – ETS – hat gemessen an den Erwartungen einen unterdurchschnittlichen Beitrag geliefert. Laut dem Pariser Klimaabkommen müssten wir eigentlich auf den Reset-Knopf drücken, doch mit ETS in der jetzigen Form ist es nicht mal der Pause-Knopf! Wir brauchen also einen grundlegenden Ansatz, und CBAM gibt uns die Möglichkeit, genau hier anzusetzen, basierend auf einer Lebenszyklusanalyse, die den ökologischen Fußabdruck genauer beschreibt. Aber freie Zuteilungszertifikate unter ETS und CBAM nebeneinander werden nicht gehen! Da beißt sich die Katze ganz klar in den Schwanz.</p>
      <p sl="en">Da wir globale Maßnahmen brauchen, könnte CBAM genau dort ansetzen, wo ETS zu kurz greift: Durch einen WTO-kompatiblen Ansatz könnten wir eine globale Akzeptanz erreichen und gleichzeitig den Exodus unserer eigenen Industrie verhindern. Diese wird das Instrument aber nur dann anwenden können, wenn unnötige Bürokratie verhindert und der Verwaltungsumfang reduziert wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Einnahmen aus dem neuen Mechanismus sollten innerhalb als auch außerhalb der EU für Klimaschutzmaßnahmen verwendet werden. Aber auch die Verbraucher dürfen nicht den Kürzeren ziehen. Sollte CBAM zu Preiserhöhungen von Verbrauchsgütern führen, müssen Verbraucher mit entsprechenden Maßnahmen entlastet werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-048-0000" speaker_id="197559" name="Grzegorz Tobiszowski" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Panie Przewodniczący! Panie Komisarzu! Rosnące ambicje klimatyczne Unii Europejskiej połączone z nękającym nas kryzysem gospodarczym stawiają przemysł europejski w bardzo trudnej sytuacji. Wobec tego prace nad mechanizmem dostosowywania cen na granicach z uwzględnieniem emisji CO2 należy prowadzić w sposób niezwykle odpowiedzialny i przemyślany. Projektując ten mechanizm, trzeba brać pod uwagę implikacje związane nie tylko z polityką klimatyczną, ale też z konkurencyjnością i rozwojem gospodarczym państw członkowskich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aby nie zaszkodzić europejskiemu przemysłowi pochopnymi decyzjami i działaniami, mechanizm musi zostać wdrożony stopniowo na zasadzie programu pilotażowego obejmującego wybrane sektory. Dopiero gruntowna analiza tej fazy pilotażowej pozwoli zastanowić się nad dalszymi działaniami i wypracowaniem stabilnego mechanizmu, stabilnego aktu prawnego. Z punktu widzenia ciągłości, stabilności i odpowiedzialności kluczowe jest utrzymanie darmowych uprawnień wraz z rekompensatami kosztów pośrednich. Planowany mechanizm należy postrzegać jako uzupełnienie rozwiązań istniejących już w ramach ETS, a zrezygnowanie teraz z tych rozwiązań byłoby decyzją skrajnie nieodpowiedzialną. Nie można też zapomnieć, że wdrożenie … (Przewodniczący odebrał mówcy głos)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-049-0000" speaker_id="197521" name="Manuel Bompard" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe The Left. – Monsieur le Président, mes chers collègues, les politiques climatiques de l’Union européenne ont un angle mort majeur. Nos objectifs climatiques ne prennent en compte que nos émissions territoriales. Nos émissions importées, tout comme celles résultant du commerce international, sont complètement ignorées. Pourtant, nous en sommes bel et bien responsables, puisqu’elles contribuent au fonctionnement de nos sociétés.</p>
      <p sl="en">La création d’un mécanisme d’ajustement carbone aux frontières se justifie donc. Il pourrait être un premier jalon vers la mise en place d’un protectionnisme écologique et solidaire aujourd’hui indispensable. Mais le mécanisme proposé ici repose sur une très mauvaise idée: l’extension du marché carbone de l’Union européenne, dont le caractère inefficace a été démontré à de multiples reprises, notamment par la Cour des comptes européenne. Il faut remplacer le marché carbone par une politique climatique par filière et par des financements à long terme. Il faut planifier par secteur industriel des cibles contraignantes de réduction des gaz à effet de serre, intégrant bien évidemment les émissions importées. Il faut substituer aux logiques de marchés une taxation sociale et écologique aux frontières de l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">De plus, pour être efficace, un tel mécanisme doit inclure les émissions résultant du transport des biens, ce qui n’est pas le cas ici. Contrairement à ce qui a été prévu, il doit couvrir toutes les importations, notamment les importations agricoles, qui sont en grande partie responsables de l’empreinte écologique de l’Union européenne.</p>
      <p sl="en">La proposition sur la table s’attaque donc à une vraie question, mais elle y répond par un mauvais instrument. Car face à l’urgence climatique, les logiques du marché ne font pas partie de la solution, mais bien du problème.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-050-0000" speaker_id="27714" name="Edina Tóth" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Tisztelt Elnök Úr! A klímaváltozás mindannyiunk közös ügye. A közös kibocsátási célok elérésének és az európai ipar versenyképessége megőrzésének egyik eszköze ez a mechanizmus, amelyet úgy kell kialakítani, hogy az kiegészítse és ezáltal meg is erősítse a már meglévő intézkedéseket. Az ETS és az ingyenes kiosztások megtartása mellett egyúttal meg kell védenünk az iparunkat a szénszivárgás további kockázatától is! Úgy vélem azonban, hogy a „CBAM” egyedül nem lehet erre kellőképpen hatékony eszköz. Kérem ezért a Bizottságot, hogy 2021-ben bemutatandó jogalkotási javaslatukat alapos, iparágakra lebontott hatástanulmányokkal támasszák alá és folytassanak intenzív konzultációt az iparágak képviselőivel is, mert egy rosszul kialakított szabályozással az uniós versenyképességet is veszélybe sodorhatják.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-051-0000" speaker_id="193419" name="Christophe Hansen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, Herr Kommissar Gentiloni, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Das Kohlenstoffgrenzausgleichssystem stand 2019 bei den meisten unserer Wahlkampagnen in den Programmen, und das ist auch gut so.</p>
      <p sl="en">Auch die Klimaneutralität bis 2050 wird glücklicherweise von den meisten in diesem Plenum unterstützt. CBAM kann ganz klar zu diesem Ziel beitragen, falls wir es denn richtig anpacken. Wir müssen jetzt jedoch aufpassen, dass wir den richtigen Vogel abschießen und nicht gleich das halbe Biotop unserer europäischen Industrie in Gefahr bringen. Es dient dem Ziel der Klimaneutralität nicht, wenn die Produktion in Drittstaaten verlagert wird. Eine solche „Not in my backyard“-Politik kann und will ich definitiv nicht unterstützen. Über eine solche NIMBY-Politik, Herr Jadot, würden sich nur die chinesischen Staatsbetriebe freuen. Ich hoffe, das ist nicht Ihre Absicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daher ist es für mich eine absolute Priorität, dass CBAM und die bestehenden kostenlosen Zuteilungen unter dem EU ETS der EU auf unserem Weg zur Klimaneutralität vorerst parallel laufen. Ein solches Vorgehen könnte dem carbon leakage effizient und verstärkt entgegenwirken. Ein solches Vorgehen würde unserer Industrie die nötige Planungssicherheit geben und Arbeitsplätze erhalten. Ein solches Vorgehen würde unserer europäischen Klimapolitik eine globale Nase verpassen. Und ein solches Vorgehen würde uns der Klimaneutralität ein gutes Stück näherbringen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-052-0000" speaker_id="124991" name="Jytte Guteland" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, although the EU has taken action to reduce its own climate emissions in the last decades, unfortunately the same cannot be said about the climate emissions that are imported into this Union. In fact, the Union is the world’s largest carbon importer, with a net import of goods and services in the EU representing more than a fifth of the Union’s domestic CO2 emissions. Obviously, this undermines the important work that we are doing to reduce our own emissions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The introduction of the carbon border adjustment mechanism, also known as the CBAM, can be a valuable addition to the efforts to reduce emissions and at the same time ensure that the responsibility to halt climate change is shared by all the actors. This is about Europe showing leadership and doing what’s right, both for the climate as well as for the transition to a climate-neutral and more sustainable future.</p>
      <p sl="en">If we do this right, the CBAM can be a great asset, both for the climate as well as for the economic incentive to develop production methods with lower CO2 emissions and a smaller greenhouse gas footprint. But we must avoid duplication of support mechanisms. For the S&amp;D Group, it’s of central importance that the CBAM does not overlap with the existing provision of free allocation of emission allowances under the Union’s emissions trading system. It would be unjustified from a climate perspective, but also actually detrimental to innovation and technological development in Europe, if we were to create a double support. So let’s not do that.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-053-0000" speaker_id="135511" name="Valérie Hayer (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, aujourd’hui nous ne construisons pas seulement une Europe verte, mais nous construisons aussi une Europe qui se respecte. Il y a quelques années, beaucoup riaient au nez de ceux qui voulaient faire payer l’importation de produits ultra-carbonés. Mais cette idée, les pro-Européens l’ont portée et ils ont refusé d’en faire un nouveau serpent de mer, que seuls les plus idéalistes auraient porté dans leur cœur.</p>
      <p sl="en">Rendons-nous compte. Il aura fallu plus d’une décennie! Plus d’une décennie pour faire accepter une idée simple pourtant: on ne peut pas se targuer d’être les champions de l’écologie et en même temps laisser la Chine, l’usine du monde, abonder notre continent en acier bon marché et pollué.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chers collègues, l’ancienne Europe ouverte aux quatre vents, naïve dans la mondialisation, se meurt. Ce à quoi nous allons assister, ce à quoi nous participons aujourd’hui c’est bien l’émergence de l’Europe leader: l’Europe qui fait respecter la planète chez elle et bientôt chez les autres.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dernier point, ce mécanisme sera vert de la collecte à la dépense parce que cet argent servira à rembourser le plan de relance. Ce plan de relance qui va amorcer la croissance écologique européenne pour de bon.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Commissaire, à travers ce vote, nous exigeons ni plus ni moins que la mise à mort du dumping climatique. Et soyez sûrs d’une chose: nous, députés européens, serons extrêmement vigilants.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-054-0000" speaker_id="94649" name="Catherine Griset" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, l’Union européenne veut être le laboratoire pour tester l’agenda écologiste.</p>
      <p sl="en">Par avant-gardisme, elle cherche toujours à exporter son modèle et ajouter les contraintes aux contraintes. La preuve en est ici, sa volonté d’imposer un prix mondial du carbone alors qu’elle représente moins de 10 % des émissions. L’Union européenne semble aujourd’hui prendre la mesure des dégâts causés à son industrie par ses initiatives contestables comme le pacte vert. Les chiffres parlent: la neutralité climatique visée en 2050 risque d’entraîner en France une hausse de 23 % des fuites de carbone.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il est donc temps de défendre nos intérêts en rétablissant des conditions de concurrence équitables. Reste que ce mécanisme d’ajustement carbone aux frontières doit passer une double épreuve. D’abord, technique à travers la réforme du marché du carbone et le calcul de l’empreinte carbone des produits importés; et ensuite juridique à travers l’accord de l’OMC. Mais quand on décrète l’urgence climatique, on se préoccupe peu de ces règles, d’ailleurs très contournées. Au contraire, on doit les réformer et les aligner sur les critères climatiques tout en soutenant la relocalisation de nos industries.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, pour être soutenable, ce mécanisme ne doit pas servir à financer la transition énergétique dans les pays en développement ni constituer un nouvel instrument fédéraliste. Les recettes générées doivent être redistribuées aux États membres et non devenir un énième fonds vert tiers-mondiste ni se transformer en ressources propres.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem19" title="19. Voting session">
    <intervention id="1-057-0000" speaker_id="197546" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">Before continuing with the debates, I will open today’s voting session. We will vote on the files as indicated on the agenda. The voting session will be open from 18.30 until 19.45.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">The same voting methods will be used as during the last part-sessions. For the vote on the immunities, voting will be by secret ballot. Members will be able to cast their votes in the usual way, but the ballot paper that they receive for signature will not display the way they voted, only the fact that they have voted. All other votes will be held by roll call. Explanations of votes may be submitted in writing. Exceptionally, explanations of votes containing a maximum of 400 words will be accepted.</p>
      <p sl="unknown">I declare the voting session open. You have until 19.45 to vote. The results of the votes will be announced tomorrow at 9.00.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem20" title="20. A WTO-compatible EU carbon border adjustment mechanism (continuation of debate)">
    <intervention id="1-059-0000" speaker_id="197546" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="President">
      <p sl="unknown">We now continue with the debate on the report by Yannick Jadot (A9—0019/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-060-0000" speaker_id="197574" name="Damien Carême" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Monsieur le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, 25 milliards d’euros, ce sont les profits réalisés par les entreprises polluantes en Europe simplement grâce à la revente des quotas carbone qu’elles reçoivent aujourd’hui gratuitement. On marche sur la tête. Polluer n’est plus seulement permis: polluer, c’est devenu rentable. Et le consommateur trinque toujours puisqu’il paye la facture déjà, alors que sa santé et son environnement ne sont pas protégés. 25 milliards d’euros rien qu’entre 2008 et 2015. Et l’addition ne fait que s’alourdir au détriment du climat, de notre santé et de notre environnement. Il est temps que cela cesse. Et bonne nouvelle avec cette proposition, c’est ce que le Parlement européen s’apprête à voter. Cette bataille, nous la menons en tant qu’écologistes depuis des années. Nous demandons la fin des droits à polluer qui sont aujourd’hui distribués gratuitement via le marché carbone européen. Le CO2 émis doit être payé au prix qu’il coûte vraiment, c’est à dire un prix qui intègre l’impact de la pollution sur notre planète, sur l’air qu’on respire. Évidemment, il ne faut surtout pas que nos industries et les emplois qu’elles représentent soient pénalisés, dont ceux chez ArcelorMittal, dans mon ancienne commune près de Dunkerque, cher Pascal. Elles ne doivent pas être non plus les seules à payer le vrai prix du carbone. Ce que nous voulons, c’est la mise en place d’un protectionnisme vert vertueux environnementalement et socialement. C’est simple, nous proposons que les importations soient taxées au même prix carbone que pour nos industries européennes; celles qui viennent de Chine, M. Hansen, comme ailleurs. C’est un mécanisme juste et efficace. C’est imposer à tous les pays qui voudraient importer en Europe des normes environnementales qui protègent l’ensemble du climat; c’est encourager, accélérer la mutation des industries les plus polluantes, partout en Europe comme ailleurs; c’est protéger à la fois nos emplois, notre santé et la planète. C’est ça, l’écologie désirable. C’est ça, une société post-carbone.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-061-0000" speaker_id="197831" name="Hermann Tertsch" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señor presidente, la política de la Comisión Europea cada vez es más esclava de su ideología. El Pacto Verde es un colosal monstruo de ingeniería social al que se desviarán ingentes cantidades de dinero con el pretexto del alarmismo climático.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Unión Europea impone medidas draconianas a las empresas y ahora, conscientes de la competencia exterior y del riesgo de desaparición y deslocalización de sectores enteros, busca su compensación a través de mecanismos muy imprecisos como este que votamos esta semana.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tiene sentido la idea de la Comisión de desarrollar un mecanismo de ajuste en frontera vinculado al carbono que impida que los más graves desequilibrios de competencia se apliquen a las industrias emisoras. Pero no tiene sentido que, tal como recomienda el informe, se liquiden de golpe los diversos instrumentos claves del sistema europeo del comercio de emisiones, como es la asignación gratuita.</p>
      <p sl="en">O se hacen bien las cosas o se acaba fomentando directamente lo que se intenta impedir: cierres y deslocalización; es decir, la liquidación de empleo y la ruina consiguiente por ideología.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-062-0000" speaker_id="197805" name="Silvia Modig (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Arvoisa puhemies, kun nostamme kunnianhimoamme ilmastonmuutoksen ratkaisemisessa vastaamaan Pariisin sopimuksen velvoitteitamme, on meidän samaan aikaan huolehdittava eurooppalaisista työpaikoista ja teollisuudesta. Siksi hiilitulli on tervetullut avaus. Oikein rakennettuna se estää hiilivuodon ja estää myös meitä ulkoistamasta omia päästöjämme EU:n rajojen ulkopuolelle. Sen tulee varmistaa, että ympäristön ja ilmaston kustannuksella tuotetut tuotteet eivät saa epäreilua kilpailuetua EU:n alueella.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tähän mennessä hiilivuotoja on torjuttu päästökaupan sisällä ilmaisjaoilla. Kuten tilintarkastustuomioistuin on todennut, ilmaisjaot ovat hidastaneet siirtymää kohti hiilineutraaliutta ja kannustimen sijaan tuoneet toimijoille ansiotonta voittoa. Hiilitullin käyttöönoton tulee tarkoittaa ilmastolle haitallisista ja innovaatioita hidastavista ilmaisjaoista luopumista. Olennaista on luoda määritelmä tuotteen tai palvelun hiilijalanjäljelle. Sen tulee huomioida jäljitettävyys, jotta koko elinkaaren vaikutukset tulevat huomioiduksi.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU:n kauppapolitiikka kokonaisuudessaan ei ole huomioinut ilmastoa riittävällä tavalla. Tästä vapaakauppasopimukset surullisena esimerkkinä. Hiilitullimekanismi on askel oikeaan suuntaan.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-063-0000" speaker_id="197515" name="Pernille Weiss" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Hr. Formand! Der kan siges rigtig meget godt om ideen med CBAM'en, tolden på CO2 ind i EU – ikke mindst om de bagvedliggende intentioner – men også en masse sludder. Især fordi EU's CO2-kvotesystem, ETS, blandes ind i designet af CBAM'en. CBAM og ETS er altså to forskellige værktøjer, og de skal bruges i respekt for, hvordan de hver især passer deres del af butikken for en grønnere fremtid. CBAM er i sig selv et præmaturt eksperiment, som slet ikke er flyvefærdigt. At CBAM – som det påstås – derfor skulle være et bedre værn mod CO2-lækage og virksomhedsflugt ud af EU end ETS'ets gratiskvoter, det er altså julemandssnak!</p>
      <p sl="en">ETS'et kender vi derimod, og en revision er på vej – den byder vi velkommen i EPP – men når betænkningen om CBAM foreslår udfasning af ETS'ets gratiskvoter frem mod 2030, ja så blander den sig altså i noget, den ikke skal. Og hvis ikke den del stemmes ud, vil det skabe betydelig usikkerhed for de europæiske energiintensive virksomheder, hvilket vil skabe færre investeringer. Virksomheder, som har masser af uvurderlige og uundværlige arbejdspladser, og som leverer solide indtægter via eksport.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jeg håber, at sund fornuft og ansvarlig omgang med EU's økonomiske muskel – vores virksomheder – som jo er den, med hvilken vi skubber verden i den grønnere retning, vinder over politiske drillerier. Dem kan næste generation nemlig alligevel ikke bruge til noget som helst. Kun Kina vil klappe i hænderne, og det var vel ikke meningen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-064-0000" speaker_id="197634" name="Pedro Marques" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Mr President, Commissioner Gentiloni, dear colleagues, we should be proud that Europe is taking the Paris Agreement very seriously. There is no doubt that inaction is not a possibility. Climate action is the only way forward. We are on the verge of a crucial shift towards a sustainable industrial policy towards clean energy and transitioning away from fossil fuels, towards smart and sustainable buildings, infrastructure, transportation and even food. Still, the climate crisis is not a challenge just for Europe, but for the whole world. Europe is doing its part and its ambition cannot be met if we face the consequences of environmental dumping at the same time.</p>
      <p sl="en">The EU carbon border adjustment mechanism is the tool to ensure that there is not a race to the bottom worldwide. I would not expect these kind of divisions from the side of the EPP on such a consensual matter that has been worked on by every committee and other committees for so long.</p>
      <p sl="en">A successful decarbonisation strategy – this is the consensus that we have built. It must fulfil our duty to deliver on the climate transition and to ensure that no one is left behind. The competitiveness of our industry is at stake, as are our workers’ jobs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear colleagues from EPP, these must not be at odds with climate ambition. This is not a matter of protectionism. In fact, we take good notice that the Biden administration is considering a similar path. This is how we can tackle the climate crisis and encourage others to follow the same goal. This is indeed an important step into building a global coalition for climate action.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-065-0000" speaker_id="197770" name="Martin Hojsík (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážený pán predsedajúci, dnes si pripomíname boj žien za spravodlivosť a rovnosť. Aj tento nástroj má byť o spravodlivosti, uhlíkovej spravodlivosti. Potrebujeme zvládnuť klimatickú krízu a postarať sa o vlastné prežitie. Musíme radikálne znížiť emisie skleníkových plynov, no nie všetky krajiny to robia dostatočne. Nástroj uhlíkovej spravodlivosti sme potrebovali už včera. Terajší systém bezplatného prideľovania emisií potrebuje zásadné zmeny, to skonštatoval aj Európsky dvor audítorov. Niektorí veľkí znečisťovatelia by však chceli všetko, aj bezplatné emisie, aj uhlíkový poplatok pri dovozoch. Ale to by nebolo spravodlivé k našim obchodným partnerom, a tento nástroj má byť spravodlivý voči firmám, ľuďom aj planéte. Súčasne musia byť spravodlivý voči rozvojovým krajinám, ktoré sú klimatickou krízou postihnuté najviac. Príjmy z tohoto nástroja si nesmieme nechať iba pre seba. Určite sa nám zídu pri financovaní klimatických opatrení, obnovy ako vlastné zdroje, ale potrebujeme ich použiť aj na riešenie klimatickej krízy v rozvojových krajinách. Pretože rovnako ako ženy aj klíma potrebuje rovnosť a spravodlivosť.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-066-0000" speaker_id="128483" name="Markus Buchheit" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Präsident, sehr geehrte Damen und Herren, liebe Kollegen! Unternehmerische Freiheit war seit jeher die Grundlage unseres Wohlstands.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wie sehr dieses Prinzip jetzt ausgehebelt wird, das zeigt sich nirgends deutlicher als am CBAM-Mechanismus. Erst verzerren die immer gleichen und nicht immer grünen Klimaapokalyptiker den Markt mit Subventionen und Verboten so sehr, dass hunderttausende Arbeiter Sorge um ihre Arbeitsplätze haben müssen, dass unseren Unternehmen ihre Wettbewerbs- und Konkurrenzfähigkeit entzogen wird – noch dazu auf ihrem eigenen Markt –, und dann inszenieren sich genau diese Politiker wiederum als große Retter, indem sie einen Protektionismus betreiben, den sie zuvor bei anderen verurteilt haben. Unsere Unternehmen müssten gar nicht geschützt werden, wenn sie nicht von den eigenen Politikern bedroht würden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Meine Damen und Herren, ebenso wie Sozialismus, so ist es auch jedes einzelne Element des Green Deals, das nicht ein bisschen richtig ist, sondern immer ganz falsch. Zumindest bis wir globale Probleme mit globalen Lösungen angehen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-068-0000" speaker_id="96725" name="Bas Eickhout" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I’d like to say thank you very much for this report, and I’m a bit surprised by the discussion that we are hearing. Every time we are saying the best method is putting a price on pollution, then you can reduce the pollution levels. We have put that in place within the EU through an ETS system. What we are proposing here is to do that also for products that we are importing. It’s fairer and secondly, it’s also providing an incentive for our global partners to reduce their emissions, and that’s how it should be done.</p>
      <p sl="en">But then, of course, there is a link with the free allocation of allowances that we are giving within the EU. You can’t support inside and give free allowances there and then let our global partners pay for it. So it is linked. And the report has been drafted with a very careful balance there, with the agreement of the EPP. And now suddenly they scream that it’s the worst thing to have. Did they not read the report before? You were part of the compromise, so stick to it.</p>
      <p sl="en">And this is to the Commission: you are now looking for your Fit for 55 package. Of course, I think it’s going to be very important to really look at the broad scope of the CBAM and not to be very minimalistic because this can provide you with a lot of the own resources that you are looking for. So please look at this in a broad way so that we can have a fair system where not only European partners are paying for the pollution but also our global partners, for a fair market.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-069-0000" speaker_id="197467" name="Geert Bourgeois" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, een ambitieus klimaatbeleid, waar wij voorstander van zijn, moet altijd rekening houden met de concurrentiekracht van onze bedrijven, met het behoud van onze jobs en met de portemonnee van de burger. Denk aan de gele hesjes. Een koolstofgrensheffing kan bijdragen aan de bescherming van onze bedrijven tegen koolstoflekkage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Maar wij vragen, meneer de commissaris, een zeer grondige impactbeoordeling van de diverse lidstaten, van de diverse sectoren, evenzeer van de koopkracht van de burger en van de bestaande handelsakkoorden. En de koolstofgrensheffing moet ingebed zijn in het beleidskader van de WTO. Zij mag niet protectionistisch zijn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tot slot vragen wij u te spreken met de Verenigde Staten nu het mechanisme voor koolstofgrenscorrectie een prioriteit, of toch minstens een intentie schijnt te zijn van de nieuwe president.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-070-0000" speaker_id="197743" name="Πέτρος Κόκκαλης (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κύριοι συνάδελφοι, κύριε Gentiloni, οι πολιτικές μας δεσμεύσεις στο πλαίσιο της συμφωνίας του Παρισιού και της Ευρωπαϊκής Πράσινης Συμφωνίας για τη μετάβαση στην κλιματική ουδετερότητα απαιτούν αναθεώρηση πλήθους πολιτικών με τα κατάλληλα νομοθετικά εργαλεία. Απαιτούν πολιτική καινοτομία και θάρρος. Οι συμφωνίες μας με τρίτες χώρες θα πρέπει να μην εξάγουν ρύπανση, να μην προκαλούν απώλεια βιοποικιλότητας και να μη στηρίζουν παραβιάσεις ανθρωπίνων δικαιωμάτων. Η απουσία παγκόσμιας τιμής ανθρακικών εκπομπών δημιουργεί στρεβλώσεις στην παγκόσμια αγορά. Χρειάζονται ίσοι όροι ανταγωνισμού στα πλαίσια του Παγκόσμιου Οργανισμού Εμπορίου και με βάση την αρχή «ο ρυπαίνων πληρώνει».</p>
      <p sl="en">Ο μηχανισμός λοιπόν θα πρέπει να συνδυαστεί με τη σταδιακή απόσυρση των δωρεάν δικαιωμάτων στη βιομηχανία με στόχο τον κλιματικό εκμοντερνισμό της και την παγκόσμια πρωτοπορία. Ο μηχανισμός θα πρέπει να επεκταθεί και πέραν των τομέων που καλύπτονται ήδη από το ETS στα εισαγόμενα αγροτικά προϊόντα με σημαντικό αποτύπωμα, αλλά και στις διεθνείς μεταφορές. Επίσης θα πρέπει να έχει αναδιανεμητικό χαρακτήρα και τα έσοδά του να χρηματοδοτήσουν την πράσινη μετάβαση. Το Κοινοβούλιο είναι έτοιμο να στηρίξει μια πολύ φιλόδοξη πρόταση από την Επιτροπή. Ευχαριστώ πολύ τον κύριο Jadot για την έκθεσή του.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-071-0000" speaker_id="197535" name="Agnès Evren" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, pendant de longs mois, lors de la campagne des européennes, nous avons défendu sans relâche, avec mes collègues François-Xavier Bellamy et Nathalie Colin-Oesterlé la création d’un mécanisme d’ajustement carbone aux frontières. Nous l’avons défendu avec conviction parce que nous sommes absolument convaincus que la transition écologique doit être la plus juste possible pour être réalisable.</p>
      <p sl="en">Or, sur qui reposent les normes environnementales toujours plus strictes que nous votons ici au sein de notre institution? Principalement sur nos producteurs, nos industriels et nos agriculteurs … Ce sont eux qui subissent de plein fouet la concurrence de produits, moins chers, qui ont été conçus dans des pays dont les niveaux d’émissions sont bien plus élevés que les nôtres. Avec quelle légitimité pouvons-nous donc ensuite leur demander plus d’efforts, si nous ne sommes pas capables de les protéger?</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce mécanisme d’ajustement est donc indispensable. Il est d’ailleurs au cœur même du pacte vert et sera un outil supplémentaire pour notre diplomatie climatique. Comme toute nouvelle mesure de grande ampleur, il comporte naturellement une part d’inconnu. Et le respect des règles de l’OMC, qui est essentiel, nous laisse peu de marge de manœuvre. Mais le rapport qui nous sera soumis demain est équilibré et constitue une solide base sur laquelle pourra s’appuyer la Commission européenne pour sa proposition législative. C’est pourquoi je vous invite à le soutenir.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-072-0000" speaker_id="124837" name="Joachim Schuster" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Bis 2050 soll Europa ein klimaneutraler Kontinent sein. Insbesondere für sehr energieintensive Industrien, wie etwa die Stahlindustrie, ist das eine große Herausforderung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Politik muss daher die Unternehmen bei der Umstellung auf klimaneutrale Produktion tatkräftig unterstützen. Ein wesentlicher Punkt dabei ist die Verhinderung von carbon leakage. Es darf nicht sein, dass beispielsweise billigere Stahlimporte mit höherem CO2-Gehalt teurere heimische Stahlprodukte mit weniger CO2 verdrängen. Dazu brauchen wir ein Carbon Border Adjustment, das ein level playing field schafft und dafür sorgt, dass umfangreiche Investitionen der Industrie zur Umstellung auf klimaneutrale Produktion kein Nachteil im Wettbewerb werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein weiterer Punkt ist mir wichtig: Bisher erhält die Stahlindustrie kostenlose Zertifikate im Rahmen des Emissionshandels. Erst wenn ein wirkungsvolles Carbon Border Adjustment etabliert ist, können diese Zertifikate schrittweise reduziert werden. Keinesfalls vorher! Allerdings, auch das gehört zur Wahrheit, ist es anschließend unumgänglich, weil es ansonsten nicht WTO-kompatibel wäre.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-073-0000" speaker_id="198176" name="Roman Haider" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsident! Wenn europäische Industriebetriebe ihre Produktion und damit Arbeitsplätze wegen zu strenger Klimaschutz- oder Umweltauflagen ins Ausland, nach Asien, verlagern und dort umweltschädlicher produzieren, dann nennt man das carbon leakage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Genau das hat die EU ja immer versucht, mit einem ganzen Bündel an Maßnahmen zu verhindern, etwa kostenlosen Emissionszertifikaten oder auch dem CO2-Grenzausgleichsmechanismus. Wenn diese Maßnahmen jetzt heruntergeschraubt werden sollen, wenn sie eingeschränkt werden sollen, dann wird das genau zwei Auswirkungen haben: Es werden erstens mitten in der Krise wiederum die Produktion und somit Arbeitsplätze nach Asien verlagert, und dort wird zweitens wieder umweltschädlicher produziert. Daher ist dieser Bericht des Umweltausschusses in doppelter Hinsicht kontraproduktiv.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-074-0000" speaker_id="208722" name="Sara Matthieu" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, de EU heeft als eerste in de wereld een emissiehandelssysteem opgezet en daar mogen we best trots op zijn.</p>
      <p sl="en">Minder trots ben ik op de miljarden euro’s aan gratis uitstootrechten voor de industrie. Die steun is begrijpelijk, maar het komt er wel op neer dat we geld smijten naar bedrijven in de hoop dat ze hier blijven. Die defensieve strategie is niet houdbaar. Het is tijd voor een offensief en assertief klimaatbeleid.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tijd ook om te stoppen met naïef te zijn ten opzichte van China of bijvoorbeeld de VS, die zonder gêne hoge tarieven plaatsen op staal uit onze fabrieken. Dat kan met dit aanpassingsmechanisme voor CO2. We zorgen voor een eerlijk speelveld voor onze bedrijven, we bouwen de gratis miljarden aan uitstootrechten af en we zetten meer geld in voor Europese en internationale klimaatfinanciering. Dat is winst op drie fronten en dat laat Europa toe om echt werk te maken van een ambitieus klimaatbeleid.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-075-0000" speaker_id="197399" name="Jessica Stegrud" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! Förutom att tillskansa sig ännu mer makt på bekostnad av medlemsstaternas självständighet vill EU nu i klimatets namn lagstifta om en importtull på industriprodukter. Med detta vill man minska det globala koldioxidavtrycket. Men blir det verkligen effekten? I praktiken innebär förslaget till exempel att för varje delkomponent i en dator måste det beräknas hur mycket koldioxid som krävs för att producera den. Komponenter tillverkas idag över hela världen och avtrycket är olika överallt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Att beräkna exakt hur mycket, och prissätta därefter, är nästan omöjligt och skulle innebära enorma ansträngningar till stora kostnader och liten nytta. För om EU inför importtullar kommer våra handelspartner att vidta motåtgärder. Vi skulle få ett handelskrig med ökad fattigdom och minskat välstånd som följd. Och vi skulle i slutänden få mindre resurser över till att hantera pandemins efterdyningar, eurokrisen, hälsokrisen, världsfattigdomen och de globala miljöutmaningarna. Det är inte vägen framåt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-076-0000" speaker_id="125064" name="Maria Spyraki" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Commissioner Gentiloni, dear colleagues, as we will be voting for the WTO-compatible EU carbon border adjustment mechanism report, it is important to remember that the establishment of this mechanism is a crucial part of the Green Deal and among the priorities of the von der Leyen Commission.</p>
      <p sl="en">CBAM could be used as a blueprint for a level playing field between EU domestic and foreign producers in specific segments of our industry, which face unfair competition from third countries, especially regarding compliance with environmental criteria and climate objectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to call all colleagues to vote in favour of the amendment of paragraph 28 proposed by the PPE, which managed to strike a balance between pragmatics and ambition in order to address our Green Deal targets. We must ensure that the implementation of the carbon border adjustment mechanism will not undermine European industry capacity, yet that it will also not overlap with existing mechanisms and will be compatible with the WTO.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament should send a clear message that the Commission should come forward with its proposal for the carbon border adjustment mechanism. It should be a message of realism in the spirit of compromise with the widest possible support from all political groups supportive of the European Green Deal. Otherwise, we will not only risk compromising our industry, but also our role as global pioneers in the Green Deal transition and in tackling climate change.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-077-0000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel Schaldemose" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! For at vi når vores mål om klimaneutralitet i 2050 er vi nødt til at se på alle redskaber i værktøjskassen, både nye og gamle. Kommissionens forslag til en CO2-toldmekanisme er et nyt værktøj, men for at det ikke kun er nyt, men også bliver nyttigt, skal det leve op til to ting: Det må ikke blive protektionistisk, og det må ikke føre til et dobbeltkrav eller dobbelte undtagelser. Europæiske virksomheder skal ikke flytte deres forurenende produktion ud af EU for så at sende deres produkter tilbage på vores marked. Den form for kulstoflækage skal vi stoppe. Men vi må heller ikke gå i den modsatte grøft og vælge et protektionistisk redskab, der begrænser handlen uhensigtsmæssig. Derfor skal den nye CO2-told være forenelig med WTO, men vi skal også se på de eksisterende redskaber. Ingen virksomheder skal straffes dobbelt eller belønnes dobbelt, fordi nye og eksisterende regler overlapper hinanden. Lad os se på det sammen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-078-0000" speaker_id="197449" name="Michael Bloss" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Europa lebt von der Industrie, von den guten gewerkschaftsorganisierten Jobs in der Branche, und die Jobs, die wollen wir erhalten. Aber das geht nur, wenn wir uns verändern. Jeder Job in der Industrie muss ein Klimajob werden, also klimaneutral. Und bisher tut sich wenig. Während die Emissionen im Energiebereich sinken, tut sich bei der Industrie nichts. Und dafür gibt es einen Grund: Die freien Zuteilungen von Zertifikaten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir brauchen jetzt die richtigen Rahmenbedingungen, damit die industrielle Revolution der Dekarbonisierung in Europa stattfindet. Und dazu müssen die Freifahrtscheine für die Klimaverschmutzung enden. Das wäre der erste Schritt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein zweiter wäre ein CO2-Preis von über 150 Euro bis zum Jahr 2030, gekoppelt mit dem CO2-Grenzausgleich. Damit stellen wir sicher, dass sich die Dekarbonisierung wirtschaftlich in Europa und in der Welt lohnt. Wer sauber und klimafreundlich wirtschaftet, wird belohnt. Das ist der große Schritt, den wir in der Klimapolitik jetzt brauchen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-079-0000" speaker_id="197572" name="Anna Zalewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Tak dla kierunku zmian, tak dla dodatkowych dochodów Unii Europejskiej w celu wsparcia transformacji energetycznej, tak dla konkurencyjności europejskich firm. Nie dla objęcia wszystkich branż, nie dla wycofania darmowych emisji, nie dla mechanizmu stworzonego do wewnątrz Unii Europejskiej i wreszcie nie dla wyprowadzania pieniędzy do krajów trzecich, bo nawet Frans Timmermans powiedział, że nie ma pieniędzy na transformację energetyczną i że zostały one niewłaściwie policzone.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dlaczego? Dlatego że nie mamy prawa klimatycznego. Komisja Europejska, Rada Europejska i Parlament jeszcze nad nim dyskutują. Nie wiemy, jaki kształt przybierze. 125 razy powiedziano: nie dla prawa klimatycznego. Wreszcie 26 lutego ONZ przedstawiło raport, według którego 40% krajów będących stronami porozumienia paryskiego zadeklarowało, że wspólnie obniży emisje dwutlenku węgla tylko o pół procent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bądźmy mądrzy, bo inaczej skompromitujemy się w oczach Europejczyków i całego świata.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-080-0000" speaker_id="197738" name="Lídia Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, a Europa precisa de continuar a liderar a agenda pelo clima como tem feito. Mas temos de ser, simultaneamente, capazes de garantir um terreno de jogo equilibrado para as nossas empresas face aos concorrentes que vêm de fora do nosso bloco económico. E pergunto-vos: podemos aceitar que as nossas empresas sejam prejudicadas pela nossa ambição climática? Por querermos mais? Enquanto outras vivem impunemente numa situação de dumping climático?</p>
      <p sl="en">As nossas regras e as nossas mensagens têm de ser claras: proteger o planeta e impulsionar um mercado justo para todos. E, para isto, as nossas empresas não podem ser colocadas em posições de desvantagem por respeitarem os nossos elevados standards ambientais.</p>
      <p sl="en">O mercado livre em que acreditamos, a iniciativa privada que valorizamos e o ambiente que respeitamos não se compadecem com concorrências desleais. Precisamos, por isso, também de evitar a batota que representa a deslocalização das empresas apenas para fugirem às nossas ambições e se aproveitarem do facto de não terem de cumprir e respeitar exigentes normas ambientais.</p>
      <p sl="en">Respeitar o planeta, promover a indústria e proteger os empregos são objetivos que não são contraditórios! Pela nossa parte, a Europa cumprirá com todos eles!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-081-0000" speaker_id="125042" name="Javi López" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, Europa no solo tiene la obligación de liderar en el mundo la aplicación del Acuerdo de París y este proceso de descarbonización, también tiene la obligación de arrastrar al resto del mundo en este proceso: hay que recordar que solo en Europa generamos el 8 % de las emisiones y, obviamente, compartimos la capa de ozono.</p>
      <p sl="en">Para ello, utilicemos uno de nuestros instrumentos, nuestro mercado, e introduzcamos un ajuste en frontera de carbono que permita arrastrar al resto del planeta, pero, al mismo tiempo, introduzcamos en el precio de los productos las externalidades medioambientales negativas, haciendo que estos incentivos y desincentivos operen en nuestro favor para combatir el cambio climático.</p>
      <p sl="en">Y no solo eso, también protejamos nuestra industria, que no se encuentre atrapada por una competencia desleal en términos medioambientales con las importaciones exteriores.</p>
      <p sl="en">En favor de nuestra industria, en favor de nuestro planeta, este informe va a dar un paso para poner en pie el ajuste en frontera de carbono que Europa necesita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-082-0000" speaker_id="197802" name="Ville Niinistö" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, we need a global price for carbon. That is elementary for us to achieve our global climate objectives and to make sure that the whole world moves towards low carbon production. And we, as Europe, also have a responsibility to play as well, because our consumption partly creates emissions outside Europe. So we have a right and a responsibility to regulate these emissions. We must push forward climate action both within the Union and by our trading partners.</p>
      <p sl="en">While we make sure that EU industry is competitive in this change, it is also obvious that industry has to play its role. For us, it is better to support green investments in European industries and readjust that way, rather than support the continuation of emissions. So it is clear that, with the introduction of the carbon border adjustment mechanism, the free allowances have to be history. I hope that the Commission takes Parliament’s position on this seriously and makes sure that we create a clearer, more global price for carbon.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-083-0000" speaker_id="4289" name="Angelika Niebler" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Verehrter Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen, liebe Kollegen! Unsere Wirtschaft steht nach wie vor vor großen Herausforderungen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Auswirkungen der Corona-Pandemie sind belastend für unsere Unternehmen, und gleichzeitig erhöhen natürlich unsere ambitionierten Klimaschutzziele den Druck auf die heimische Industrie. Carbon leakage ist eine ganz konkrete Gefahr, solange andere Wirtschaftsregionen in Sachen Klimaschutz nicht ein vergleichbares Niveau wie wir in der Europäischen Union erreichen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Mit dieser Gefahr dürfen wir unsere Unternehmen nicht alleine lassen. Zu glauben, dass der Ausgleichsgrenzmechanismus ein Allheilmittel wäre, ist zu einfach gedacht. Eine Exportwirtschaft braucht Zugang zu globalen Märkten, und wir brauchen auch globale Kooperationen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Andere Wirtschaftsregionen werden reagieren, wenn wir carbon-border-adjustment- Mechanismen einführen. Wir haben bewährte Mechanismen, um unsere Wirtschaft zu unterstützen, die wir jetzt auch auf keinen Fall in Frage stellen dürfen. Eine Kürzung der freien Zuteilungen im Rahmen des ETS bei Einführung des Ausgleichsmechanismus würde unsere Industrie, unsere Unternehmen, doppelt bestrafen. Wir müssen global uns international für ein Emissionshandelssystem einsetzen und so zu einer gerechten Bepreisung kommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich fasse nochmals zusammen: Ich glaube, wir dürfen unsere bewährten Mechanismen wirklich nicht in Frage stellen; wir müssen auf andere Wirtschaftsregionen in der Welt einwirken und Klimadiplomatie betreiben; und wir brauchen ein ordentliches impact assessment, das auch die handelspolitischen Konsequenzen nicht außer Acht lässt.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-084-0000" speaker_id="197584" name="Sándor Rónai" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Csaknem másfél év telt el azóta, hogy itt az Európai Parlamentben kihirdettük az éghajlati vészhelyzetet. Elfogadtuk a klímatörvényt, célul tűzve ki hogy 2050-re Európa az első karbonsemleges kontinens lehet. Szép eredmény és nagyon fontos mérföldkő volt ez mindannyiunk számára. Csakhogy mit érnek ezek az erőfeszítések, ha a szén-dioxid-kibocsátással járó iparágak átkerülnek Európa országain kívülre. Az európai zöld átmenet sikeréhez elengedhetetlenül szükséges és fontos az is, hogy Európa ne csupán zöldebbé tegye a munkahelyeket, hanem ezeket a zöldebbé tett munkahelyeket meg is tudja őrizni. Nem dőlhetünk hát hátra, hanem ezekre a kihívásokra is megfelelő válaszokat kell találjunk, amikor kereskedelmi és védővámpolitikánkat találjuk ki.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-085-0000" speaker_id="183338" name="Jakop G. Dalunde" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman! På vissa sätt är Europa en ledare i den gröna omställningen, men på andra sätt är vi sämst. Ett exempel är att vi i Europa importerar mest koldioxid i hela världen. Oavsett hur bra vi är på att lyckas med att minska våra utsläpp på hemmaplan, så kvarstår fortfarande utsläppen i resten av världen, som vi orsakar genom vår konsumtion.</p>
      <p sl="en">Därefter är det oerhört positivt att vi nu tar ett steg mot en klimatavgift på importerade varor. Det är pusselbiten som har saknats hittills i vårt klimatarbete. Det är ett verktyg som kan ge konkurrensfördelar för de europeiska företag som har en ambitiös inställning till sitt klimatarbete, men som också innebär ett utökat incitament till andra delar av världen – USA, Kina, Brasilien. Ett incitament för att de ska utöka sin klimatpolitik så att de slipper betala klimatavgifterna. Det här är någonting som vi gröna gått till val på, och jag är stolt över att vi nu har kommit framåt i den här frågan.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-086-0000" speaker_id="197652" name="Angelika Winzig" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, geschätzte Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Hinter dem CO2-Ausgleichsmechanismus stehen drei hehre Ziele: Das erste: Der Schutz unserer europäischen Unternehmen vor unfairem Wettbewerb durch ausländische Betriebe mit geringeren Umweltstandards. Zweitens ist der CO2-Ausgleichsmechanismus eine wichtige Säule des Green Deals, und drittens werden die Steuereinnahmen für die grüne Transformation bzw. für die Refinanzierung des Wiederaufbaufonds verwendet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber gut gemeint ist nicht immer gut getroffen, und ich habe jetzt in der Diskussion mitbekommen, dass einige Abgeordnete wirklich überhaupt kein unternehmerisches Verständnis bzw. überhaupt keine betriebliche Praxis haben. Denn das Wichtigste in dieser Wirtschaftskrise ist jetzt, die Produktion in Europa zu halten und Jobs zu sichern und Jobs zu schaffen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Verlagerung von Produktionen in einer globalisierten Welt ist für Unternehmen nicht besonders schwierig, es ist aber auch nicht verwerflich, denn sie brauchen nur ihren ausländischen Kunden zu folgen, ihren Märkten zu folgen. Sie sparen Transportkosten, sie sparen Zollkosten. Und auch Investitionen und Produktionskosten sind zirka um ein Drittel geringer als in Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Solange wir keine international einheitliche CO2-Bepreisung haben, muss die bestehende carbon-leakage-Regelung bleiben, vor allem auch mit der Gratiszuteilung der Zertifikate. Unsere Unternehmen brauchen Planungssicherheit. Planungshorizonte sind oft mehr als zehn Jahre. Österreich ist ein Exportland ohne Atomkraftwerke und Kohlekraftwerke, und ich will nicht, dass unsere Betriebe dann durch Gegensanktionen bestraft werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-087-0000" speaker_id="96668" name="Seán Kelly" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, the EU, and particularly this House, have been very active and ambitious in terms of climate change action, and we have already substantially reduced our domestic greenhouse gas emissions. However, emissions from imports have been rising, which affects any effort we make to reduce our global GHG footprint.</p>
      <p sl="en">Most countries claim to have a serious plan to cut greenhouse gas emissions, but the EU actually has one: a one trillion euro European Green Deal that aims to make us carbon neutral by 2050.</p>
      <p sl="en">This brings us to the introduction of the carbon border adjustment mechanism at our external borders. European leadership in climate action – leadership that benefits citizens across the globe – should not be to the detriment of our competitiveness. The CBAM seeks to protect European companies from unfair competition from non-European climate polluters who operate in countries with less stringent standards. However, the transition must not destabilise our economy by reducing our competitiveness, leading to carbon leakage.</p>
      <p sl="en">Finally, I believe that we must remain very cautious when phasing out current measures of the ETS that prevent CO2-intensive industries from relocating their production to outside the EU. The EU system of free allowances and CBAM must work simultaneously. That’s what we have to do.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-088-0000" speaker_id="125670" name="Massimiliano Salini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Commissario Gentiloni, la decisione di introdurre il meccanismo alla frontiera è una decisione che correttamente affonda le sue radici dentro l'esigenza di tutelare le imprese europee in un mercato che non sempre si manifesta come corretto.</p>
      <p sl="en">Abbiamo partner commerciali che si rifiutano di rispettare quelle regole di tutela ambientale che noi abbiamo continuato a rispettare, nonostante la grave crisi indotta dalla pandemia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Oggi il più grande produttore di acciaio al mondo, cioè la Cina, nel corso dell'anno 2020 ha aumentato di un altro 6 % la propria quota di mercato dell'acciaio. L'Europa ha perso il 17 % della propria quota e, nel frattempo, le quote di carbonio costano dai 22 euro alla tonnellata di un anno e mezzo fa a 40 euro oggi e nel giro di un anno, un anno e mezzo, andranno a 60 euro. È corretto definire questa come una misura di tutela ambientale, ma è corretto considerare che stiamo perdendo centinaia di migliaia di posti di lavoro.</p>
      <p sl="en">E quindi è vero, parlare da questo podio, come facciamo da quando c'è il Covid che non parliamo più da là ma parliamo da qua, ha aumentato un po' il tasso di retorica degli interventi, signor Commissario.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tuttavia il ruolo che abbiamo è la responsabilità nei confronti dei più deboli e nei confronti dei più deboli noi dobbiamo ribadire che l'Europa è il continente che produce meglio e con le migliori performance ambientali. Non denigriamo questo modello di sviluppo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-089-0000" speaker_id="197778" name="Tom Berendsen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, de doorrekeningen van de verkiezingsprogramma’s in Nederland laten zien dat bij de twee partijen die zich het groenst en duurzaamst noemen, de concurrentiepositie van de industrie verslechtert en de productie verplaatst zal worden naar het buitenland. Dat is niet goed voor het klimaat.</p>
      <p sl="en">De Europese industrie levert 30 miljoen banen en produceert tegelijkertijd ook de materialen die wij nodig hebben voor onze economie van de toekomst. Daarvoor willen wij niet afhankelijk worden van andere delen van de wereld.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ja, wij willen in Europa de schoonste en duurzaamste industrie. Maar tegelijkertijd moeten onze bedrijven wel overleven op wereldniveau, in concurrentie met partijen die zich niet aan dezelfde strenge regels hoeven te houden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daarom is deze CO2-heffing aan de grens, mits we die goed uitvoeren, een prima idee in combinatie met slim industriebeleid. Alleen dan houden we de banen van de toekomst in Europa, zorgen we ervoor dat we niet afhankelijk worden van anderen en doen we daadwerkelijk iets voor het klimaat.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-090-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Paolo Gentiloni" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I think this debate is encouraging because of the large convergence on the need for the instrument we are discussing: the CBAM is absolutely needed to promote the climate transition to avoid carbon leakage and to support, of course, competitiveness and jobs.</p>
      <p sl="en">I am quite confident that the impact assessment that is ongoing will help us on the fine-tuning of the design of the mechanism – which is, of course, a new mechanism, on the sectors that will be involved gradually since the beginning and then enlarging in the next years, and also on the timing of the introduction of the new rules and on the phasing-out of aspects of existing rules. We know that we have a target which is 2023 in the interinstitutional agreement.</p>
      <p sl="en">So I think that we have a good basis on the fact that this issue is now on the global agenda. It was not the case one year ago. It was completely unthinkable to have some of the main trade powers discussing a carbon border mechanism or carbon tax or other things, and in this global debate the European Union has the advantage of the early movers, which is the advantage of trying to give a contribution to set new standards. I think that we will give this contribution and this will help us on this historic challenge of the climate transition.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Il-President" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Id-dibattitu ngħalaq.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il-votazzjoni tal-emendi se ssir għada u l-votazzjoni finali l-Erbgħa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stqarrijiet bil-miktub (Artikolu 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-5000" speaker_id="23816" name="András Gyürk" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Az európai klímapolitika hatékonyabbá tétele, a zöld átállás előmozdítása, valamint a szénszivárgás kockázatának elkerülése mindannyiunk közös érdeke. A széndioxid-kibocsátás határokon történő kiigazítását célzó mechanizmus hasznos lehet e törekvések megvalósításához. Ahhoz, hogy az új eszköz hatékonyan járuljon hozzá a célok teljesítéséhez, három kitételnek kell megfelelnie. Az új mechanizmus elsődleges feladata az európai vállalkozások és ipar védelme kell, hogy legyen. Olyan szabályozásra van szükség, ami a káros tevékenységek következményeit a szennyezőkkel és nem az emberekkel fizetteti meg.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ez a méltányos átállás alappillére. Szintén elengedhetetlen, hogy az új mechanizmus az EU kibocsátás-kereskedelmi rendszerével párhuzamosan működő struktúra formájában, a meglévő eszközök kiegészítésével, erősítésével kerüljön kialakításra. A mechanizmus nem befolyásolhatja az ingyenes kibocsátási egységek rendszerét. A kereskedelmi konfliktusok elkerülése érdekében az új eszköznek összhangban kell lennie a Kereskedelmi Világszervezet szabályaival, valamint az Európai Unió nemzetközi kötelezettségvállalásaival is. Végül a mechanizmus kidolgozása során kellő óvatosságra és körültekintésre van szükség. Az Európai Bizottságnak ezért alapos, iparágakra lebontott hatástanulmányokat kell készítenie, valamint konzultálnia kell az iparági szereplőkkel. Egy, az európai baloldal nyomására, elsietett szabályozás vállalkozások százait és munkahelyek ezreit tenné kockára, ami a katasztrofális gazdasági hatásokon túl a zöld átállás társadalmi elfogadottságát is aláásná.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-7500" speaker_id="197537" name="Alexandr Vondra" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">písemně. – Pokud chceme celosvětově snížit emise skleníkových plynů, je jasné, že bez nástroje, který přiměje k akci i země mimo EU, se neobejdeme. Musíme ale zajistit, aby takový mechanismus byl skutečně kompatibilní s pravidly WTO a doplňoval (nikoliv nahrazoval) fungující systém obchodování s emisními povolenkami. Ten nedávno vstoupil do své čtvrté fáze a i nadále správně počítá se zachováním bezplatných povolenek pro energeticky nejnáročnější provozy. Zpráva Yannicka Jadota to v zásadě reflektuje, ale klíčové bude, jak nyní zareaguje Komise, která má přijít s konkrétním legislativním návrhem. Ten nesmí poškodit evropské exportéry v energeticky náročném průmyslu, jako je třeba keramika, porcelán a sklo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-091-8750" speaker_id="124877" name="Jadwiga Wiśniewska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">na piśmie. – UE narzuciła sobie rygorystyczne cele osiągniecia neutralności klimatycznej do 2050 r. Ucieczka emisji, czyli przenoszenie produkcji, a tym samym emisji CO2, za unijne granice do krajów, które mają mniej rygorystyczne przepisy, zniweczyłaby te cele, a tym samym nie ograniczyłoby globalnych emisji CO2. Takie działania importerów szkodzą unijnej gospodarce, osłabiając jej konkurencyjność. Importerzy powinni zostać objęci analogicznymi kosztami emisji CO2 uzależnionymi od wartości uprawnień do emisji, które przeciętny europejski producent musi kupić w ramach systemu EU ETS. Dodatkowo wdrożenie CBAM wywarłoby istotną presję na naszych partnerów spoza UE w zakresie wdrażania ambitniejszych polityk na rzecz ochrony klimatu. Popieram zapisy utrzymujące bezpłatne uprawnienia w unijnym systemie handlu emisjami m.in. dla sektorów, które zostaną objęte CBAM (tj. stalowego, cementowego), oraz włączające sektor nawozowy na listę CBAM.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem21" title="21. Administrative cooperation in the field of taxation (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-093-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Il-President" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il-punt li jmiss fuq l-aġenda huwa d-dibattitu dwar ir-rapport ta’ Sven Giegold, f’isem il-Kumitat għall-Affarijiet Ekonomiċi u Monetarji, dwar il-proposta għal direttiva tal-Kunsill li temenda d-Direttiva 2011/16/UE dwar il-kooperazzjoni amministrattiva fil-qasam tat-tassazzjoni (COM(2020)0314 – C9-0213/2020 – 2020/0148(CNS)) (A9-0015/2021)</p>
      <p sl="en">Nixtieq ninforma lill-onorevoli Membri li, għad-dibattiti kollha ta' din is-sessjoni parzjali, mhux se jkun hemm proċedura "catch-the-eye" u mhux se jiġu aċċettati karti blu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Barra minn hekk, bħal fis-sessjonijiet parzjali preċedenti, huma previsti interventi mill-bogħod mill-Uffiċċji ta' Kollegament tal-Parlament fl-Istati Membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-094-0000" speaker_id="96730" name="Sven Giegold" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Europa ist ja voll von lustig klingenden, komplizierten Begriffen. Die siebte Richtlinie über die Verwaltungszusammenarbeit im Steuerbereich ist ein klassisches Beispiel dafür.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Steuersysteme sind national, während unser Markt längst europäisch und oft weltweit ist. Diese Differenz machen sich Steuerhinterzieher, Steuervermeider und Steuerflüchtlinge seit Langem zunutze. Europa geht hier mit der Richtlinie über die Zusammenarbeit im Verwaltungsbereich bei Steuerfragen voran, um dafür zu sorgen, dass diese Möglichkeiten für milliardenschwere Steuerhinterziehungen und Steuervermeidungen geringer werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es ist deshalb gut, dass jetzt auch die digitalen Plattformen in den Bereich der europäischen Steuerzusammenarbeit aufgenommen werden. Immer mehr Umsätze werden über Amazon, Ebay, Airbnb getätigt. Es ist einfach ein Gebot des fairen Wettbewerbs, dass auch dort getätigte Umsätze effektiv an die Steuerbehörden der Steuerpflichtigen gemeldet werden. Die europäische Steuerzusammenarbeit kommt mit dieser Richtlinie im digitalen Zeitalter an.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Europäische Kommission hat darüber hinaus einige weitere Verbesserungen der bestehenden sechs Richtlinien vorgeschlagen. Es ist ein guter Kommissionsvorschlag, der uns hier vorliegt, und ich bin dankbar, dass er hier im Parlament auch so aufgenommen wurde, und ich bedanke mich ausdrücklich bei allen Schattenberichterstatterinnen und Schattenberichterstattern, die geholfen haben, hier Vorschläge zu machen, um diesen Vorschlag der Kommission noch besser zu machen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Denn das Problem mit dem Vorschlag der Kommission ist weniger, was drinsteht, sondern mehr, was nicht drinsteht. Denn nach wie vor gibt es große Lücken der europäischen Steuerzusammenarbeit, und hier machen wir fraktionsübergreifend stärkere Vorschläge, als sie bisher Realität sind. Mit Ausnahme der ID-Fraktion haben sich alle Fraktionen konstruktiv und in die gleiche Zielrichtung an dieser Arbeit beteiligt, und darüber bin ich sehr froh.</p>
      <p sl="en">Da geht es z. B. darum, dass wir wollen, dass in Zukunft Informationen zu allen Einkommenskategorien ausgetauscht werden und nicht nur zu denjenigen, zu denen die Mitgliedstaaten einfachen Zugang haben. Wir wollen auch, dass es mehr Transparenz dahingehend gibt, in welchen Bereichen die Steuerzusammenarbeit eigentlich funktioniert. Und wir wollen auch, dass die Daten, die ausgetauscht werden, nicht nur für Steuerzwecke genutzt werden können, sondern auch im Bereich der Geldwäschebekämpfung und auch in anderen Formen der Kriminalitätsbekämpfung effektiver genutzt werden können. Es sollte doch selbstverständlich sein, dass wir im Bereich der Finanzkriminalität umfassend zusammenarbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jüngst hat auch der Europäische Rechnungshof über die gleiche Richtlinie einen Bericht abgefasst und festgestellt, dass es große Probleme gibt, die bisher nicht adressiert sind. Insbesondere ist die Qualität der Daten nicht ausreichend, und es gibt keine Sanktionen für diejenigen, die die Daten im Bereich des automatischen Informationsaustausches bereitstellen müssen, um sie anzureizen, konkret die Richtlinie perfekt und zureichend umzusetzen. Zudem ist unklar, wie gut die Daten eigentlich genutzt werden. Daher gibt es weiteren Verbesserungsbedarf im Bereich dieser Richtlinie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es wäre auch einfacher gewesen, wenn man auch im Bereich der digitalen Plattformen die kleineren Plattformen außen vor gelassen hätte, so wie es die OECD ursprünglich vorgeschlagen hätte – so hätten wir mit weniger Bürokratie die gleichen steuerlichen Mehrerträge erreicht. Es ist deshalb gut, dass schon demnächst die achte Reform dieser Richtlinie vor der Tür steht, diesmal mit dem Hauptfokus auf die crypto-assets. Das ist dringend notwendig, und daran wird auch auf internationaler Ebene gearbeitet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber ich möchte es ganz deutlich sagen: Die vielen Begrenztheiten, auch dieser guten Richtlinie, zeigen, dass wir hier weiter gehen müssen. Gerade durch die Coronakrise sind die öffentlichen Kassen leer. Gleichzeitig brauchen wir in großem Maße Zukunftsinvestitionen. Wir können uns die grenzüberschreitenden Steuerhinterzieher, Steuerflüchtlinge und aggressiv Steuervermeidende nicht mehr leisten. Auch können sich die Unternehmen, die in der Coronakrise stark gelitten haben, den unfairen Wettbewerb durch Unternehmen nicht mehr leisten, die ihren Beitrag nicht zahlen wollen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Daher fordere ich die Kommission auf: Nutzen Sie die Revision dieser Richtlinie in der achten Version, um ein umfassendes Paket vorzulegen, damit die Steuerzusammenarbeit tatsächlich grenzüberschreitend klappt. Beschränken Sie sich hier nicht nur auf die crypto assets, sondern sorgen Sie dafür, dass das ganze Universum der Steuerzusammenarbeit in Europa verbessert wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zu guter Letzt will ich noch sagen: Der Rat hat ja seine Position schon gefunden. Er hat sich leider entschlossen, die Positionen des Parlaments nicht einzubeziehen. Daher ist es umso wichtiger, dass nun die Kommission unsere Vorschläge ernst nimmt, die wir ja hoffentlich mit großer Mehrheit beschließen werden, und wir dann bei der achten Revision der Richtlinie wirklich gemeinsam an einem starken Regime arbeiten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Im Übrigen zeigt der ganze Vorgang, wie dringend es notwendig ist, dass wir auch im Steuerbereich letztlich zu Mehrheitsentscheidungen kommen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-095-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Paolo Gentiloni" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, this DAC7 is a very good step forward in terms of information exchange. It goes even further than the OECD rules. Of course, the number DAC7 shows that we are proceeding step by step with the support of Parliament. And I appreciate the diligent and strong work done by Parliament in reviewing the proposal and your commitment on the file.</p>
      <p sl="en">The amendments you propose touch upon important issues for the Commission. We share their principles and their objectives. And you know that we will address them in the coming steps, or will try to. I think with your support we can do this.</p>
      <p sl="en">Allow me to say a few words on this proposal at the beginning of the debate. We agree on the importance of automatic exchange of information in as many categories as possible. At the same time, we know that Member States may not all collect information on all categories of income at the moment. They should thus be given sufficient time to adjust to the expanded categories of income.</p>
      <p sl="en">The proposal to add an obligation for a financial institution to report information on the ultimate beneficial owner of the account would increase the usefulness of the information reported and help to identify the beneficial ownership. It is a very significant amendment. I think it could be addressed in a future amendment of the directive.</p>
      <p sl="en">We agree with you on the need for an adequate level of investment in IT, digital infrastructure and professional training. Member States should ensure that they provide the necessary IT, financial and human resources, and the Commission stands ready to support Member States with their needs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me underline that many of the amendments proposed by Parliament could also be taken into account in a possible future legislative proposal amending the DAC.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will especially look into further improvements in the exchange of information with respect to financial accounts, cross-border ruling and advanced pricing arrangements, and penalties and compliance measures. With respect to the penalties and compliance measures, my services are preparing a comprehensive framework that will ensure the effective application of DAC7 that will be proposed as part of the next amendment, DAC8, which is scheduled to be proposed towards the end of this year. We are also counting on the support of the European Parliament in view of this future revision of the directive.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-096-0000" speaker_id="197738" name="Lídia Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo PPE. – Senhora Presidente, a cooperação administrativa na área dos impostos é uma dimensão da integração europeia que pode e deve ser mais ambiciosa. Cada Estado-Membro determina que impostos cobra, quanto cobra e como os cobra. Esta soberania fiscal faz sentido, mas só se cumpre integralmente se tivermos os instrumentos necessários para uma tributação justa, equilibrada e eficaz. Num mundo progressivamente mais globalizado pela digitalização, e numa Europa com um mercado único cada vez mais aberto, precisamos de uma fiscalidade adaptada aos dias de hoje. Desafios que não são de um ou outro país, mas comuns, sobretudo quando partilhamos um espaço como a União Europeia.</p>
      <p sl="en">O pacote legislativo da Comissão para uma tributação mais justa e simples, de que resulta esta Diretiva, é um passo importante, mas precisa de ser consequente. É ao Conselho da União, presidido este semestre por Portugal, que cabe decidir e, aparentemente, prepara-se para ignorar o contributo deste Parlamento. Se a posição era expectável, não deixa de ser reprovável. Ainda está a tempo de reconsiderar e esse é o primeiro apelo que aqui deixo.</p>
      <p sl="en">À Comissão, que a semana passada questionei sobre esta matéria, deixo um segundo apelo: que trabalhe numa revisão mais profunda da Diretiva. Decidimos esta semana sobre a DAC 7 e já está anunciada uma DAC 8. Está na hora de fazer um trabalho mais detalhado e estável. Sucessivas alterações legislativas perturbam o trabalho das administrações fiscais e geram incerteza nas empresas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Temos muito para fazer: melhorar o sistema de troca de informações entre autoridades tributárias, aumentar os recursos para as administrações fiscais, proteger os direitos dos contribuintes, evitar os custos burocráticos para as empresas e garantir a proteção dos dados para todos. As propostas que aprovamos esta semana vão nesse sentido, mas não decidimos sozinhos nem sobre tudo. Esperamos ter essa oportunidade num futuro próximo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-097-0000" speaker_id="197697" name="Aurore Lalucq" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Madame la Présidente. Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, 1 à 2 %, c’est ce que payent en moyenne comme impôts des entreprises du type Airbnb, que ce soit en Italie, en Espagne ou dans un pays comme le mien, la France, là où la restauration et l’hôtellerie, au niveau national, seront taxés entre 15 et 25 %. À chaque fois, le processus est le même: Airbnb facture ses clients, son activité locative dans d’autres pays, au Royaume-Uni et en Irlande par exemple, et fait en sorte de déclarer en France uniquement ses activités de type marketing, ce qui lui permet de déclarer des revenus extrêmement bas et donc d’être taxé de manière extrêmement basse, là aussi. En fait, toutes les plateformes fonctionnent de la même façon, que ce soit Uber, Airbnb, etc. D’où la nécessité du travail qu’on fait en ce moment, et d’où l’importance d’avoir intégré les plateformes numériques dans cette directive d’échange d’informations parce que si ces plateformes font partie du quotidien des Européens, elles doivent aussi se plier aux règles des Européens et cela commence par un truc tout bête qui s’appelle la transparence fiscale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, certes, le chemin est encore long, mais on peut saluer le travail qui est fait au niveau européen en ce moment et qui va continuer à se faire sur la question de la transparence fiscale, de la coopération fiscale et à terme, nous l’espérons, de la justice fiscale. Les Européens nous attendent et ils le méritent.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-098-0000" speaker_id="197418" name="Monica Semedo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Renew Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, when discussing new fiscal measures we must also consider the effects on our economies. We have to continue to attract investment in the EU and ensure that our financial centres remain competitive. Money is already flowing to third countries such as Hong Kong and Singapore.</p>
      <p sl="en">Of course, maintaining our attractiveness must be done in conjunction with a robust, compliance and transparency rule. This will also help to prevent dirty money being washed through our banking systems by criminals.</p>
      <p sl="en">This proposal enhances cooperation between EU tax authorities. It is another important step forward in our fight against tax fraud, tax evasion and tax avoidance. Renew Europe is striving for a fair tax system. Online platforms have been making huge profits, especially during the current pandemic. However, they are not necessarily paying their fair tax share. These new tax transparency rules will help to change this imbalance. Accordingly, Renew Europe supports this proposal.</p>
      <p sl="en">But I have a comment on the process that was followed for this file. A particularly disappointing aspect was that the Council apparently did not wish to consider the views of the European Parliament. They reached an agreement at the technical level last November, before we, the European Parliament, adopted our position. Furthermore, they decided on a position that weakens the proposal in certain areas. The principle of sincere cooperation between institutions, and the European Parliament’s role in a consultative process, has seemingly been lost. These attempts to bypass procedures entrenched in our Treaties must stop.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-099-0000" speaker_id="132191" name="Gunnar Beck" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der ID-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Der EU-Rechnungshof klagt, Steuerberichtspflichten kosten Behörden und Unternehmen jährlich hunderte Millionen Euro, doch die Informationen würden kaum verwendet. Ergo: Dank sechs EU-Richtlinien kostet Zusammenarbeit viel, und die Erfolge sind begrenzt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Was fordert der grüne Berichterstatter im Parlament? Mit Recht, dass Amazon und andere Corona-Profiteure nicht beliebig Steuern vermeiden. Doch wahrhaben, dass das auch eine Folge des EU-Binnenmarktes ist, das will er nicht. Und dann fordert er noch „weitestgehenden Informationsaustausch“ statt nur in begründeten Fällen und ein level playing field, sprich einheitliche EU-Steuern.</p>
      <p sl="en">Seien wir ehrlich: Es geht gar nicht um bessere Zusammenarbeit, sondern um immer höhere Steuern und perfekte Bürgervollüberwachung zur Finanzierung von Euro, Klimarettung und Migration – keine Investitionen, sondern Linksstaatlichkeit, die jährlich hunderte Milliarden verschlingt.</p>
      <p sl="en">EU-Bürger zahlen jetzt schon die höchsten Steuern, wir haben weltweit das niedrigste Wachstum, verlieren rasant an Wettbewerbsfähigkeit, und Weltmeister sind wir bei der Verschuldung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Auch wir sind gegen Steuerflucht und Trockenlegung von Steueroasen. Aber bitte auf Basis von Rechtsstaatlichkeit und Realitätssinn, nicht linksstaatlicher Missachtung von Privatsphäre und Datenschutz.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-100-0000" speaker_id="197545" name="Bogdan Rzońca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">w imieniu grupy ECR. – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Wspólnie musimy działać przeciw zjawisku unikania podatków. Doceniamy pracę Komisji Europejskiej w tym zakresie, jak i współpracę z OECD. To bardzo dla nas ważne. Oczywiście poszczególne państwa także mogą dobrze ściągać podatki. Polska jest takim przykładem uszczelnienia systemu podatkowego. Mamy tu ogromne sukcesy i dużo większe bogactwo. Możemy wydawać środki na politykę społeczną czy politykę gospodarczą. W dobie niezwykłej roli platform internetowych nie marnujmy więc energii i traktujmy poważnie podatnika europejskiego, zwracając uwagę na to, że cyfrowi giganci po prostu łamią przepisy podatkowe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bardzo jednak się dziwię, że przy analizie dyrektywy o współpracy administracji w zakresie podatków wprowadza się kwestię praworządności, doszukując się jakichś problemów w tej materii. Moim zdaniem nie jest to trafne. Nasi wyborcy oczekują realnej dyskusji i skutecznych, technicznych rozwiązań, a nie politycznej agendy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-101-0000" speaker_id="28586" name="Δημήτριος Παπαδημούλης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">εξ ονόματος της ομάδας The Left. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κάθε χρόνο χάνονται από το δημόσιο ταμείο εκατοντάδες δισεκατομμύρια ευρώ, εξαιτίας του ξεπλύματος μαύρου χρήματος, της φοροδιαφυγής, της φορολογικής απάτης, της φοροαποφυγής. Αιτία αυτής της τεράστιας απώλειας είναι η αναποτελεσματική ευρωπαϊκή συνεργασία για την αντιμετώπιση του οικονομικού εγκλήματος. Το Ευρωπαϊκό Κοινοβούλιο ζητά ταχύτερα βήματα για την αποτελεσματική αυτή συνεργασία. Και τα ζητούν και οι πολίτες. Το 63% των πολιτών θέλει ισχυρότερη ευρωπαϊκή συνεργασία και ισχυρότερο ρόλο του Ευρωπαϊκού Κοινοβουλίου. Η Επιτροπή οφείλει να συνεργασθεί με το Κοινοβούλιο, για να γίνει πράξη αυτή η συνεργασία, γιατί στο Συμβούλιο υπάρχουν κυβερνήσεις που υποστηρίζουν τη μη συνεργασία, για να ευνοούν τα συμφέροντα φορολογικών παραδείσων εντός της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης· και αυτό είναι απαράδεκτο.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-102-0000" speaker_id="125020" name="Paul Tang" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, more and more people generate their income online via Uber, Airbnb and other online platforms. With the latest DAC revisions, the EU rules have caught up, finally, and have closed a tax gap worth billions of euros each year. But how long has Uber benefited, and how long Airbnb, and what damage did that do to those taxi companies and hotels that do pay taxes?</p>
      <p sl="en">We should not allow unfair competition, clear inequalities and missing revenue but we do, because when fighting tax avoidance, the Council takes baby steps. Every Member State can block or delay proposals. Moreover, decisions are made behind closed doors and the Council is uncooperative since it refuses even to take into account Parliament’s position, and it refuses to share data that is needed to monitor the status quo, so Parliament is frustrated in doing its job.</p>
      <p sl="en">It’s time that the Council realised that fighting tax avoidance requires public transparency. It’s about transparency towards taxpayers, sharing data with tax administrations and in public records, but also about the transparency of tax policies, showing who proposes what and who opposes what, so that national and European parliaments can fulfil their democratic duty.</p>
      <p sl="en">With public transparency and accountability, it will become very clear that baby steps are just not enough, and it’s time to grow up and leap forward to a fairer economy.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-103-0000" speaker_id="197767" name="Eugen Jurzyca" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca, nech sa páči mojich 5 signálov k tejto téme. Po prvé, nezamieňajme si spoluprácu v daňovej oblasti s harmonizáciou daní. Po druhé, daňová konkurencia je dobrá, je pozitívna pre konkurencieschopnosť Európskej únie a rast ekonomiky. Po tretie, daňové úniky treba obmedzovať. keďže narúšajú férovú súťaž firiem na jednotnom trhu. Po štvrté, členské štáty by mali zvýšiť kvalitu a presnosť daňových informácií, ktoré si vymieňajú, aby boli praktickejšie na využitie ostatnými členskými štátmi. Bez dostatočnej kvality dát nebude efektívna ani ich využiteľnosť pre znižovanie daňových únikov. A po piate, tu presne je priestor pre Komisiu, ktorá by mala proaktívnejšie vstupovať do koordinačného procesu výmeny informácií.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-104-0000" speaker_id="88715" name="José Gusmão (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Senhora Presidente, o mercado interno da União Europeia foi construído com livre circulação de capitais, mas sem os mecanismos necessários para que essa livre circulação de capitais fosse utilizada para iludir a tributação das grandes empresas multinacionais, no setor digital e não só no setor digital, gerando uma corrida para o fundo que é má para os cidadãos, mas não é má para todos, como é moda dizer-se nestes debates. É boa para essas empresas multinacionais e é boa para todos os territórios, incluindo Estados-Membros que assentam os seus modelos de economia e de contas públicas na predação de receitas fiscais alheias.</p>
      <p sl="en">Os cidadãos estão fartos desta realidade, que enfraquece os serviços públicos e aumenta a tributação dos rendimentos do trabalho. A cooperação administrativa fiscal e a transparência fiscal têm que ser um passo para criar regras de tributação mínima dos rendimentos de capital dentro da União Europeia, tornando transparente a corrida para o fundo a que temos assistido na União Europeia e no mundo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-105-0000" speaker_id="96998" name="Evelyn Regner" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! FinCEN-Files, OpenLux – all diese Steuerskandale – zeigen uns auf, wie dringend wir ein zeitgemäßes, ein transparentes Steuersystem brauchen. Denn in einer Welt, in der Unternehmen global wirtschaften, können nationale Steuersysteme allein nicht die Antwort sein. Besonders jetzt benötigen Staaten enorm viel öffentliches Geld, um ein krisensicheres Gesundheitssystem zu finanzieren, um die Wirtschaft für Frauen wie für Männer, also gendergerecht, wiederaufzubauen. Und dieses Geld können wir uns holen – natürlich von großen Unternehmen, die den Staaten Steuern in Milliardenhöhe schuldig bleiben. Ich bin fest davon überzeugt, ein solches Steuersystem ist möglich, wenn Staaten besser zusammenarbeiten. Und deshalb ist es so wichtig, beim Austausch von Steuerinformationen eben auch die digitalen Plattformen wie Uber, Google und Netflix mit zu inkludieren. Aber – darauf möchte ich hinweisen – es braucht geeignete Daten, es braucht geschultes Personal, also große und keine Babyschritte. Gestalten wir aktiv diese zeitgemäße, transparente, effiziente und faire europäische Steuerpolitik.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-106-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Paolo Gentiloni" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, honourable Members. Yes, with this DAC7 we are mainly imposing new reporting rules on platform operators in order to have clarity on the income of the sellers that use these platforms. I think this is a new step forward. If we compare this to, for example, the OECD level, this confirms a more advanced EU transparency.</p>
      <p sl="en">But we know very well that, at the same time, tax avoidance is ever more sophisticated at global level and also in Europe. And so while declaring my personal satisfaction with this debate and with the support for the directive, I am absolutely sure that we need further steps, and I think that with your support these further steps will be possible.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Il-President" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Id-dibattitu ngħalaq.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il-votazzjoni tal-emendi se ssir għada u l-votazzjoni finali l-Erbgħa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Stqarrijiet bil-miktub (Artikolu 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-107-5000" speaker_id="28615" name="Roberts Zīle" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">rakstiski. – Es pilnībā atbalstu priekšlikumu par administratīvo sadarbību nodokļu jomā. Attīstoties digitālajām platformām un to lietojumam dažādu darījumu veikšanai, attiecīgi jāattīsta arī ES tiesību akti. Šis ziņojums attiecināms uz tādiem ar nodokli apliekamiem darījumiem, kuri iepriekš normatīvo aktu regulējumā nebija ietverti. Ieteiktās izmaiņas dalībvalstīm un to kompetentajām iestādēm nodrošinās mehānismus ar nodokli apliekamo darījumu kontrolei, kā arī atvieglos pārrobežu jautājumu risināšanu. Direktīva veicinās tiešsaistes darījumu efektīvāku pārskatāmību un kontroli. Es aicinu savus kolēģus atbalstīt šo priekšlikumu un paplašināt ES nodokļu pārskatāmības noteikumus.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem22" title="22. Corporate due diligence and corporate accountability (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-109-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Il-President" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Il-punt li jmiss fuq l-aġenda huwa d-dibattitu dwar ir-rapport ta’ Lara Wolters, f’isem il-Kumitat għall-Affarijiet Legali, dwar diliġenza dovuta korporattiva u obbligu ta' rendikont korporattiv. (2020/2129(INL)) (A9-0018/2021)</p>
      <p sl="en">Nixtieq ninforma lill-onorevoli Membri li, għad-dibattiti kollha ta' din is-sessjoni parzjali, mhux se jkun hemm proċedura "catch-the-eye" u mhux se jiġu aċċettati karti blu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Barra minn hekk, bħal fis-sessjonijiet parzjali preċedenti, huma previsti interventi mill-bogħod mill-Uffiċċji ta' Kollegament tal-Parlament fl-Istati Membri.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-110-0000" speaker_id="5392" name="Lara Wolters" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, I want to share with you a few recent headlines: ‘Widespread Uyghur forced labour in China region that supplies a fifth of the world’s cotton’; ‘Massive damage done to Curaçao coral reef: construction company blamed’; ‘Report reveals: more than 6 500 migrant workers have died in Qatar’s World Cup prep’.</p>
      <p sl="en">The stories behind these headlines are seemingly unrelated, but they share one thing: in all these cases, European companies were involved and contributed to harm through their activities.</p>
      <p sl="en">I want us, this week, to take a first step towards righting those wrongs. I want us to ensure better access to justice for victims in third countries. And I also want to make sure that European legislation can be applied even if the harm was done in China, Qatar or Curaçao, if it transpires that a European mother company has failed to act responsibly.</p>
      <p sl="en">At the moment, that is far too difficult, and if you think about it, this is entirely non—intuitive. If a regular citizen breaks someone’s window, even accidentally, I can assure you they have no smokescreens to hide behind. But in international law there are plenty. While a large company has the resources and the brightest legal minds at its disposal, those affected often lack the money and means to seek remedy.</p>
      <p sl="en">We live in a world in which businesses so inclined can still shift their adverse social and environmental impacts to the most vulnerable people and places on the planet. And on International Women’s Day I cannot help but notice that these impacts are not gender neutral: women face a higher likelihood of poverty, sexual abuse and violence within the supply chains that we are now talking about.</p>
      <p sl="en">One of the problems is that in a global economy doing the right thing does not give a business a competitive advantage. And I refuse to believe that that is something we simply have to accept – that deforestation or forced labour are part and parcel of global supply chains. What we’re dealing with here is a lack of commonly enforced rules for responsible business conduct and the absence of a framework for supply-chain liability.</p>
      <p sl="en">It is no surprise that the debate on this has become more prominent through the years. The UN and the OECD have courageously led the hard-fought development of guidance for businesses and pushed the envelope. But the time for voluntary standards is now over. According to a recent survey by the Commission only a third of respondents said that some form of due diligence was carried out. That same study showed that a majority of businesses recognise the value of new EU rules. Indeed, let’s not forget the thousands of businesses that are already doing the right thing but that do not feel supported by current rules.</p>
      <p sl="en">Those businesses understand that mandatory standards are the only path to a level playing field and to business certainty. They also understand that modern consumers have high standards, and that doing business in the 21st century means doing business responsibly. All of this is why, over the past few months, we have been working on an ambitious law that would apply to anyone wanting to sell their goods or services on the internal market, including non-EU companies.</p>
      <p sl="en">That law requires of companies their best efforts to identify and address adverse impacts on human rights, the environment and governance, and this in their entire value chain, inside and outside the Union. The agreement we reached ensures the involvement of NGOs and local communities, and stresses the role of trade unions.</p>
      <p sl="en">For us to transform supply chains in a meaningful way, due diligence should be exercised by all companies with risks in their supply chain. But we have paid special attention to SMEs and included only those that do face risks or are listed on the stock exchange. Obligations should be proportional and reasonable, meaning smaller companies should do what can reasonably be expected of them, in accordance with their means.</p>
      <p sl="en">But exempting SMEs altogether flies in the face of our joint goals. A small company can cause harm too. And so it is risks rather than size we should focus on. Yes, the rules should be workable, SMEs have indeed come to tell me that, and I agree with them. But they have not come to ask me for an exemption, since they know that that could have a chilling effect on their business. They are often part of the supply chains of larger companies and they would risk being cut out. An exemption would also make it harder once SMEs grow or want to secure financing for growth and I therefore urge Members to vote against the amendment seeking to exempt SMEs.</p>
      <p sl="en">The European Parliament has the chance this week to become a leader in responsible business conduct. For businesses, we are creating a level playing field and legal clarity. For consumers, we are ensuring fair products. For workers, we are enhancing protection. For victims we are improving access to justice. And for the environment, we are taking a step that is very long overdue.</p>
      <p sl="en">I would like to warmly thank my colleagues from my Group, but also from across all Groups, for their cooperation and Commissioner Reynders for his availability throughout the process. I am convinced that this report, if adopted, can be a first joint step towards a European gold standard for sustainable, responsible business.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-111-0000" speaker_id="197694" name="Raphaël Glucksmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur pour avis de la commission des affaires étrangères">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, les citoyennes et les citoyens qui nous ont élus n’en peuvent plus. Ils en ont assez. Assez de ce système qui permet aux plus riches et aux plus puissants une totale impunité. Assez de cette exploitation des plus faibles et du saccage de notre planète. Assez de voir leurs politiques, leurs représentants s’aplatir devant des intérêts financiers. Assez de voir Nike, Zara et tant d’autres multinationales faire de l’argent sur le dos d’esclaves ouïgours. Assez de 30 années de délocalisation et de course effrénée au coût de production le plus bas. Ils en ont assez et ils ont raison.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chers collègues, le texte que nous allons voter ici répond à leur colère. Il initie une véritable révolution juridique. Une législation européenne sur le devoir de vigilance des entreprises répond à une idée simple, basique: les multinationales doivent être juridiquement responsables de l’ensemble de leurs chaînes de production. Jusqu’ici, ce n’est pas le cas. Aujourd’hui, Zara ou Nike ne sont responsables de rien car elles ne produisent rien elles-mêmes. Leurs fournisseurs peuvent allègrement violer les droits humains ou détruire l’environnement sans qu’elles n’aient de comptes à rendre à personne. Cela doit cesser et cela cessera le jour où ces mastodontes devront faire face à la justice en Europe pour des crimes commis sur leurs chaînes de production en Afrique ou en Asie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chers collègues, nous devons nous demander ce que nous faisons là. Pourquoi sommes-nous là? Sommes-nous là pour servir les intérêts de Volkswagen ou de Sanofi, ou sommes-nous là pour servir l’intérêt général et les droits humains? L’Europe est le premier marché du monde, la première puissance commerciale du monde, nous avons ici les moyens de changer la donne à l’échelle du globe. Si nous le décidons, nous le pouvons. Alors ensemble, c’est le moment de le décider.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-112-0000" speaker_id="1909" name="Bernd Lange" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Verfasser der Stellungnahme des mitberatenden Ausschusses für internationalen Handel. – Frau Präsidentin! Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Handel eröffnet Perspektiven und Handel sichert Beschäftigung; und dann meinen einige, Handelspolitik sei quasi das Schmierfett für normale Entwicklung. Nein, das ist sie nicht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Handelspolitik ist ein Instrument, um Globalisierung fair und nachhaltig zu gestalten. Deswegen ist es wichtig, genau zu schauen, wo sich Handel zurzeit hauptsächlich realisiert, und das ist in globalen Lieferketten: Über 70 % des globalen Handels werden in Lieferketten realisiert. Da müssen wir ran und sicherstellen, dass die fundamentalen Arbeitnehmerrechte, dass die Frage der Umweltstandards, die Frage des Pariser Klimaschutzabkommens wirklich zum Maßstab unternehmerischen Handelns in der gesamten Lieferkette wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das, was jetzt auf dem Tisch liegt, gemeinsam von mehreren Ausschüssen und von vielen Fraktionen erarbeitet, respektiert genau das. Ich gehe davon aus, dass wir das auch mit einer großen Mehrheit so verabschieden können, weil das die Verantwortung ist – ich möchte nämlich nicht mehr, dass die Schokolade für die Kinder mit Kinderarbeit hergestellt wird oder dass der Christbaumschmuck von Zwangsarbeit trieft.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bei Zwangsarbeit, Herr Kommissar, müssen wir noch mal darüber nachdenken, ob wir jenseits der Sorgfaltspflicht – in Bereichen, in denen Sorgfaltspflicht nicht garantiert werden kann – auch über ein Verbot des Zugangs von Produkten mit Zwangsarbeit zum europäischen Markt nachdenken müssen; denn es kann nicht sein, dass es hier unterschiedliche Standards für Unternehmen mit Sorgfaltspflicht und Unternehmen ohne Sorgfaltspflicht gibt. Insofern glaube ich, dass hier eine entsprechende Ergänzung notwendig ist.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bin der festen Überzeugung, dass wir in der Tat jetzt darangehen müssen, Globalisierung gerecht zu gestalten, und das machen wir mit einem Lieferkettengesetz.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-113-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Didier Reynders" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, je suis particulièrement heureux d’avoir aujourd’hui un débat avec vous au sujet du devoir de vigilance des entreprises à travers leurs chaînes de valeur.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Commission se félicite du travail et du rapport de la commission des affaires juridiques ainsi que de l’intérêt du Parlement européen sur ces questions. Je souhaite en particulier féliciter et remercier la rapporteure Lara Wolters ainsi que les rapporteurs fictifs sur ce dossier avec lesquels j’ai eu l’occasion d’échanger à plusieurs reprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous partageons l’ambition d’une action législative horizontale au niveau européen afin de concrètement mettre en œuvre les engagements de l’Union en faveur d’une transition vers une économie plus juste et plus durable.</p>
      <p sl="en">We see a clear momentum across Europe towards a legislative proposal, a sustainable corporate governance, and the Commission will deliver on this. The objective of the Commission is to foster a sustainable, fair and competitive EU economy as we recover from the current crisis. This initiative will be an important contribution to achieving those goals. The private and public sector should both contribute to achieve this common goal.</p>
      <p sl="en">In addition, it is important that we respect our values, both within and outside the Union. We want to incentivise, outside of Europe, good practices that protect the environment in line with our international commitments and our efforts on climate change and environmental protection.</p>
      <p sl="en">Similarly, EU companies should make all reasonable efforts to make sure that practices against human rights, labour and social rights that are not tolerated within the Union do not take place in their supply chain.</p>
      <p sl="en">We want effective action: an enforcement mechanism to ensure that forced labour does not find a place in the value chain of EU companies. Many EU companies are seriously committed to preventing adverse sustainability risks and impacts throughout their value chains, thereby contributing to addressing key societal challenges. Let me insist on this. Many companies are already showing us the way, and this is a field where we want to work with companies and to support them, notably by putting in place a strong level playing field at EU level.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ample economic evidence shows that sustainable companies, those properly integrating the interests of their stakeholders – including workers – into their decision-making and paying attention to their environmental and social impact, often perform better, are more productive and more resilient. This should be Europe’s competitive edge. Sustainable corporate governance is part of the overall transformation towards a more sustainable and inclusive economy, and it can contribute to companies’ resilience and performance in the long term.</p>
      <p sl="en">Companies should carry out sustainability due diligence proportionate to their capabilities, to mitigate social, human rights and environmental harm in their business operations and supply chains. This means that those facing bigger risks would need to do more, as due diligence is a proportionate tool.</p>
      <p sl="en">Harmonised EU legislation would avoid risk of fragmentation of the internal market. As you know, such fragmentation increases the cost for businesses and investors. Due diligence rules under EU law would also bring legal certainty and as I said, a level playing field in the whole European Union. It is something many businesses and citizens are calling for throughout the EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will present its legislative proposal on sustainable corporate governance later this year. We envisage a holistic approach where a corporate due diligence obligation is underpinned by directors’ duty. We will also consider the complementarity work carried out by this Parliament on the report prepared last year by Mr Pascal Durand.</p>
      <p sl="en">Specific attention will be given to the costs and burdens for companies, including indirect costs and, in particular, for SMEs. I can assure you that I will be very attentive to this issue. A possible range of solutions is being considered as part of the impact assessment the Commission is currently conducting. This could go from limitations of the scope of application according to the size and riskiness of the sector or companies, to adapting certain requirements to the size of the company, in line with the proportionality principle.</p>
      <p sl="en">We are also looking into possible targeted support, such as guidance, tools, funding or technological solutions for traceability. As supported by Parliament in your draft report, we are looking to base the future of the due diligence obligation on existing international guidelines and commitments stemming from international agreements.</p>
      <p sl="en">As regards liability, we are assessing this issue as part of the preparatory work for our initiative, having in mind international standards and the need to ensure an effective enforcement mechanism in line with our objectives.</p>
      <p sl="en">Let me also assure you that the Commission will ensure alignment between this proposal and a review of the Non-Financial Reporting Directive, in order to avoid duplication of reporting obligations for companies. We will also ensure coordination and coherence with other complementary initiatives, such as the one on deforestation, in particular when it comes to the definition of ‘deforestation-free’.</p>
      <p sl="en">To conclude, the Commission is currently in the process of finalising the results of the public consultation we conducted on this initiative, which closed on 8 February. We received not less than 470 000 contributions. An impact assessment is currently being prepared, and I thank you very much for your support for this initiative, for your attention today, and I am, of course, now looking forward to our debate.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-115-0000" speaker_id="29579" name="Marc Tarabella" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur pour avis de la commission du développement">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, je remercie tout d’abord Lara Wolters, la rapporteure, ainsi que les rapporteurs fictifs, les rapporteurs pour avis de la commission du développement dont je vais essayer de tracer le résumé de ce qui a été souhaité.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’introduction d’un instrument de devoir de diligence obligatoire est primordial afin de faire respecter les droits humains, les droits du travail, les normes environnementales, tant au sein de l’Union européenne qu’au-delà de ses frontières.</p>
      <p sl="en">En tant que rapporteur, je souhaiterais aujourd’hui mettre l’accent sur certains points clés de l’avis de la commission du développement. J’en ai relevé sept.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le premier, c’est qu’il est absolument nécessaire de disposer d’un cadre obligatoire et harmonisé au niveau européen pour garantir des conditions de concurrence équitables pour les entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le deuxième, c’est que l’obligation de respecter et de protéger les droits de l’homme, l’environnement et d’éviter les risques de corruption doit être intégrée à l’ensemble des chaînes de valeur mondiales, des produits, des services et des relations commerciales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le troisième, la nouvelle législation devrait s’appliquer à tous les secteurs, à tous les types d’entreprises à travers l’Union européenne, l’accent étant mis sur les risques.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le quatrième, ces procédés de diligence raisonnable obligatoires doivent couvrir les activités des entreprises et leurs relations commerciales, y compris leurs chaînes d'approvisionnement et de sous-traitance.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le cinquième, un système complet de responsabilité comprenant une responsabilité administrative, civile et pénale devrait être mis en place afin de faire respecter la nouvelle législation et assurer son application, y compris au moyen de sanctions de toute nature.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le sixième, il est essentiel que la future législation soit pleinement alignée sur les obligations juridiques et les normes existantes aux niveaux international et européen, et elle doit s'attaquer à tous les types de violations des droits de l’homme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Enfin, les chapitres sur le développement durable et des accords de libre-échange doivent devenir contraignants et exécutoires.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pour conclure, j’espère que cette proposition de résolution soit à la base d’une législation ambitieuse. Je remercie, une fois de plus, toutes les personnes impliquées dans ce dossier crucial et vous souhaite un excellent travail législatif, Monsieur le Commissaire.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-116-0000" speaker_id="96761" name="Axel Voss" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der PPE-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Es ist mir eine besondere Freude, heute unter Ihrem Vorsitz hier auch sprechen zu können, und lieber Herr Kommissar, recht herzlichen Dank auch für Ihre Rede.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das Ganze war in der Tat eine große Zusammenarbeit, Teamwork. Was wir hier erreicht haben, das war nicht einfach, das müssen wir auch sagen. Aber es lohnt sich für das Ziel, das wir hier erreichen wollen – nämlich verbindliche Sorgfaltspflichten sind eben der wichtige Schritt hier, für mehr Verantwortung in einer Europäischen Union auch entsprechend Lieferketten für Menschenrechte und Umwelt herzustellen.</p>
      <p sl="en">An die Kommission – auch da möchte ich noch einmal darauf hinweisen: Der Ball liegt jetzt in Ihrem Feld. Das Ganze ist – auch das sei noch einmal gesagt – kein Selbstläufer. Es ist insbesondere für Sie jetzt auch entsprechend an der Zeit, zu sagen oder uns vorzuschlagen, was wir, wo wir keine Lösungen gefunden haben – nämlich auch hinsichtlich einer bestimmten Größenbeziehung von Unternehmen, wie wir das am Ende machen. Und deshalb ist immer zu überlegen, starre Größen, wie sie in manchen Mitgliedstaaten diskutiert werden, sind höchstwahrscheinlich für das Ziel hier nicht besonders hilfreich.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber was eben insgesamt notwendig ist für einen europäischen Rahmen, ist eine Vollharmonisierung, obwohl ich weiß, dass die rechtlichen Möglichkeiten hier eingeschränkt sind. Aber wir sollten es halbwegs doch versuchen anzustreben. Deshalb ist für uns eben wichtig, dass wir Rechtssicherheit für Unternehmen haben, dass wir Entlastungen auch für die KMU haben, ob das Programme sind, Digitalisierung oder die Verpflichtung von Mitgliedstaaten, hier auch zu helfen. Wir brauchen meines Erachtens auch den sogenannten risikobasierten Ansatz, weil in einer ersten Lieferkette manche große Unternehmen 200 000 bis 300 000 Erstlieferanten haben. Und das ist nicht etwas, was leicht zu schaffen ist. Deshalb: risikoorientiert, nach Sektor, nach Standort. Und die Unternehmen sollen hier auch selber priorisieren können, und die zivile Haftung hier in dem Fall auch nur für den Fall, dass auch dort nur die Haftung existiert, wo wir hier einen direkten Schaden sozusagen auch verantwortlich machen können.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb noch mal: Es ist wichtig, hier für Unternehmen diese Balance hinzubekommen. Darauf achten wir sehr. Deshalb auch noch mal der Dank an die Berichterstatterin, an alle Schattenberichterstatter, dass es uns gelungen ist, diese Balance herzustellen. Herzlichen Dank für die Kooperation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-117-0000" speaker_id="124936" name="Maria Arena" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe S&amp;D. – Madame la Présidente, vivre dans la globalisation, cela signifie que nous avons la chance de partager des savoirs, des cultures, de consommer des produits que nous n’aurions jamais consommés sans la globalisation. Mais cela signifie aussi que nous sommes interdépendants et que nos comportements ici ont des répercussions ailleurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’hyperglobalisation dans laquelle nous nous sommes inscrits ces dernières décennies signifie aussi l’apparition de dérèglements économiques, sociaux et environnementaux dommageables pour tous. Elle a permis, par exemple, à des entreprises de se délocaliser vers des pays moins exigeants en matière sociale, fiscale ou environnementale, laissant sur le carreau des milliers de travailleurs protégés et exploitant des travailleurs ne bénéficiant d’aucune protection. Disposer d’un smartphone, d’un ordinateur ou encore d’une voiture électrique signifie aussi la surexploitation minière en Afrique au détriment des populations, car souvent ces métaux rares ne sont pas payés à leur juste prix.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ces exemples nous montrent que la globalisation que nous vantons, dont nous bénéficions, a besoin aussi d’être encadrée. Tout comme nous l’avons fait pour le règlement sur l’exploitation des minerais des conflits, en ayant un dispositif contraignant exigeant la responsabilité des entreprises, nous voulons la même chose pour tous les secteurs d’activité. Nous voulons que les produits qui sont consommés en Europe soient libres du travail des enfants, libres du travail forcé et libres de la déforestation.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-118-0000" speaker_id="124693" name="Pascal Durand" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Renew. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, Monsieur Reynders, le message que le Parlement vous envoie avec ce texte porté avec conviction et courage par ma collègue Lara Wolters, que je veux saluer évidemment ici, comme cela a été fait précédemment, est un formidable message d’espérance et d’humanité, mais également de pragmatisme et de souveraineté.</p>
      <p sl="en">D’Humanité, d’abord, parce qu’il signifie que pour nous, Européens, sur cette planète, nous voulons que tous les êtres humains soient égaux en dignité et en droits. Nous voulons évidemment, nous savons et nous ne sommes pas naïfs que tous les obstacles et les oppositions que nous rencontrerons dans des pays souvent totalitaires où la vie humaine ne compte que pour bien peu, où le travail forcé, l’esclavagisme et le travail des enfants est une réalité quotidienne et les discriminations, la règle. Mais nous affichons clairement notre volonté de changer cette réalité et de faire avec le levier le plus efficace que possède l’Union européenne, celui du commerce, de l’échange, de la production et de l’importation et nous avons l’intelligence de le faire ensemble: les politiques, les entreprises et toutes les parties prenantes syndicats, ONG et organisations de consommateurs. Et ce message d’humanité alors, Monsieur le Commissaire, devient un message d’espérance, d’espérance pour des centaines de millions de personnes qui, à travers le monde, n’ont pas accès aux droits les plus élémentaires, mais qui fournissent pour nous leur force de travail ou les matières premières dont nous avons tant besoin, mais également qui crient leur désespoir d’être respectés et de pouvoir enfin trouver justice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce message d’espérance concerne bien sûr aussi notre planète, qu’elle ne soit plus détruite et surexploitée au mépris des règles internationales et de sa capacité à se régénérer et à se renouveler juste pour maximiser des profits de quelques entreprises internationales qui, avec cynisme, méprisent tous ces droits, là où d’autres essayent et mettent un point d’honneur à les respecter.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, je vous l’ai dit et je terminerai là-dessus. C’est un message de pragmatisme aussi et de souveraineté européenne car dans un monde qui change, rien ne serait pire pour l’Union que de rester inactive et d’attendre que tous ces bouleversements nous soient imposés de l’extérieur. Nous devons rester maîtres de notre destinée, vous l’avez dit, Monsieur le Commissaire, et les garants de nos valeurs au sein et hors de l’Europe. Voilà votre mission, Monsieur le Commissaire, et transformez ces beaux messages en un texte …</p>
      <a text="(La Présidente retire la parole à l’orateur)"/>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-119-0000" speaker_id="124738" name="Gilles Lebreton" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, la recherche du profit est un but légitime pour les entreprises, mais il ne faut pas qu’elle s’effectue au prix de la violation délibérée des droits de l’homme ou du saccage de l’environnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est pourquoi, il paraît normal de soumettre les entreprises et notamment les multinationales à un devoir de vigilance raisonnable pour éviter de telles dérives. Il s’agit en somme de moraliser le capitalisme. Ce devoir de vigilance raisonnable a déjà été posé en France par une loi du 27 mars 2017 et je me réjouis que cet exemple français soit suivi aujourd’hui par le Parlement européen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il faut toutefois veiller à ce que la future règle européenne reste raisonnable et ne fasse pas peser sur nos entreprises des contraintes démesurées. C’est pourquoi il n’est possible de soutenir un tel texte que si trois conditions sont respectées.</p>
      <p sl="en">Premièrement, le devoir de vigilance ne doit porter que vis à vis des sous-traitants et des partenaires avec lesquels l’entreprise a un contact direct et non sur la totalité de la chaîne d’approvisionnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deuxièmement, il doit clairement s’analyser en une obligation de moyens et en aucun cas en une obligation de résultat.</p>
      <p sl="en">Troisièmement, il ne doit peser que sur les grandes entreprises car les PME n’ont pas les moyens de l’exercer. Je rappelle que c’est la position adoptée par la loi française de 2017 qui exclut de son champ d’application les entreprises de moins de 5 000 salariés.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-120-0000" speaker_id="2054" name="Heidi Hautala" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Mars, Nestlé, Barry Callebaut, Mondelēz and other multinational chocolate companies are facing in the United States a lawsuit in which eight children, now young adults, claim that they were used as slave labour on cocoa plantations in the Cote d'Ivoire.</p>
      <p sl="en">They call for justice, but, the same companies are in the forefront, calling for mandatory human rights and environmental due diligence legislation in the EU. Is this a paradox? No. These companies know that years of using voluntary certificates and labels do not allow them to tell that there is no child labour or no deforestation in the chocolate we in Europe consume.</p>
      <p sl="en">Due diligence legislation does not shift the responsibility from states to companies. States have an obligation to protect human rights and fundamental freedoms – business enterprises are required to respect human rights. The companies must acquire the necessary capacity to do their due diligence in the manner which is reasonable to expect from them. By consulting key stakeholders in their business environment, companies become aware of the most important human rights and environment risks in their entire value chain. Due diligence legislation is needed so that there can be a level playing field between companies. As long as we turn a blind eye on human rights violations in corporate value chains, we actually reward those who escape their responsibilities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-121-0000" speaker_id="197467" name="Geert Bourgeois" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de ECR-Fractie. – Voorzitter, het is onze ethische plicht op te komen tegen de schending van mensenrechten en vóór milieuregels en goed bestuur. Onze bedrijven moeten transparant en zorgvuldig omgaan met de hele toeleveringsketen. Jammer genoeg hebben de vele vrijwillige initiatieven waaraan ik hulde wil brengen niet gezorgd voor afdoende resultaat. Dus moeten er dwingende regels komen. Maar mijnheer de commissaris, maak van onze bedrijven niet wereldwijd een schietschijf door omkering van de bewijslast. Wentel de verantwoordelijkheden van de lokale besturen niet af op onze bedrijven. Leg onze kmo’s geen dure, zware, niet na te komen verplichtingen op. Ik vraag u dan ook om een grondige effectbeoordeling voor onze grote bedrijven. Eenduidige inspanningsverbintenissen zonder omkering van de bewijslast en steun van onze kmo’s met een steunpunt, eerder dan met maatregelen die hun internationalisering belemmeren.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-122-0000" speaker_id="197533" name="Manon Aubry" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe The Left. – Madame la Présidente, 6 500 morts sur les chantiers de la Coupe du monde où opère Vinci. 790 000 enfants esclaves pour produire le cacao de Nestlé. Au moins un million de femmes et d’hommes ouïgours pour récolter le coton de Nike et assembler les téléphones d’Apple dans les camps d’internement chinois. McDonald, qui profite de la déforestation de milliers d’hectares en Amazonie. Pourquoi l’Union européenne, si ferme pour couper dans nos dépenses publiques de santé, est-elle incapable de condamner les crimes systématiques des multinationales?</p>
      <p sl="en">Avec le devoir de vigilance que nous votons aujourd’hui, nous voulons mettre un terme à cette criminalité organisée qui exploite les gens et l’environnement. Nous empêcherons les multinationales de déléguer impunément le sale boulot à leurs filiales opaques et à leurs fournisseurs véreux. Avec le devoir de vigilance, les portes des tribunaux s’ouvriront aux victimes qui demandent réparation.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ce n’est qu’une première étape pour reprendre le contrôle face à ces géants de l’argent qui se croient au-dessus des lois. Mais c’est déjà une belle victoire sur le terrain des droits humains et de l’environnement. Une victoire que nous arrachons aux patrons et à leurs lobbies qui se sont agités pour nous la voler. Nous l’arrachons à BusinessEurope et au Medef venus faire les basses œuvres du CAC 40 à Bruxelles et nous l’arrachons surtout grâce à une mobilisation inlassable des associations, des citoyens et de quelques élus déterminés à faire primer l’intérêt des gens sur celui de l’argent. Cette victoire, c’est un rappel cinglant aux multinationales: vous ne dicterez pas la loi aux États et aux citoyens, parce que, comme l’a rappelé une mobilisation citoyenne sur les réseaux sociaux en France en faveur du devoir de vigilance: qui commande ? C’est nous et certainement pas les lobbies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-123-0000" speaker_id="118859" name="Il-President" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Infakkar lilek u lill-kollegi li skont l-Artikolu 10, paragrafu 3, m’għandhomx jintwerew strixxuni f’dan il-Parlament.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-124-0000" speaker_id="197438" name="Mislav Kolakušić" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, poštovani kolege, dragi građani, farmaceutska industrija stavlja na tržište skupinu jednih od najopasnijih proizvoda koji se stavljaju u kompletnom gospodarstvu na tržištu.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lijekovi i cjepiva mogu biti iznimno učinkoviti i poticati zdravlje, ali isto tako mogu biti iznimno štetni, mogu oštetiti tuđe zdravlje doživotno, a mogu izazvati i smrtne posljedice.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dužna pažnja prilikom odobravanja lijekova je nešto što je štitilo građane Europe i svijeta cijelo ovo vrijeme. Trideset godina je prosječno vrijeme koliko je bilo potrebno da se pronađe učinkovito cjepivo protiv pojedinih virusa. Sada smo u situaciji da je ne jedna osoba otkrila cjepivo protiv ovog virusa i dobila Nobelovu nagradu nego je u manje od deset mjeseci deset ili petnaest kompanija pronašlo cjepivo protiv koronavirusa.</p>
      <p sl="en">To je malo vjerojatno i ja u to ne vjerujem.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-125-0000" speaker_id="197515" name="Pernille Weiss" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Den mest effektive måde at udbrede og beskytte menneskerettigheder og fremme overholdelse af miljømæssige og sociale standarder er ved at virksomheder og borgere hver især opfører sig ordentligt, kritisk og ansvarligt. For os europæere er det nogenlunde let. Vi har en relativt høj moral og systemer, der hjælper os med at omsætte værdier til realiteter. Sådan er det bare ikke i hele verden. Derfor må nogen gå foran, og EU har stadigvæk den økonomiske og kulturelle muskel til at kunne gøre det. Men den muskel, den skal vi også bruge rigtigt, så den ikke brænder sammen undervejs, for så er intet opnået. Tværtimod.</p>
      <p sl="en">Der er en masse godt i betænkningen om corporate due dilligence, men der er også lidt skidt. Skidt som vi må få pillet ud af betænkningen, før vi sender den videre til Kommissionen. Der er nemlig lagt op til alt for mange uklare forpligtelser og administrative byrder for mange virksomheder, og især de mindre og de mange. Det vil ramme millioner af SMV'er og den underskov af grønne og socialt ansvarlige iværksættere, som vi har så hårdt brug for. Jeg kan godt forestille mig, at venstrefløjen er ligeglad. Men jeg håber, at vi er flest i det her hus, som vil være med til at passe godt på Europas økonomiske muskel, så vi med den kan skubbe verden i en bedre retning. Især i de her år, hvor Kina buldrer frem, så kommer vi ingen vegne med gode intentioner.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-126-0000" speaker_id="5729" name="Kathleen Van Brempt" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, we weten uit onderzoek, maar eigenlijk ook uit ervaring, dat het respecteren van mensenrechten en minimale milieucondities nog heel vaak met de voeten worden getreden in onze productieprocessen en in onze waardeketens. We weten ook dat bedrijfsleiders en bedrijven heel vaak niet weten of negeren wat er in hun productie en in hun waardeketens gebeurt. Dus er moet snel verandering in komen. En alle hulde aan Lara Wolters, die met een sterk verslag een horizontale verplichtende wetgeving vooropstelt. En het moet duidelijk zijn dat het nakomen van die wetgeving een voorwaarde moet zijn opdat producten op onze markt kunnen komen. En daar ligt de link met internationale handel: ervoor zorgen dat daar het level playing field is. En laat me het voorbeeld geven van China – onze groep wil daarin duidelijk zijn – : het hebben van een horizontale verplichtende zorgplichtwetgeving zal een voorwaarde zijn voordat we kunnen bespreken of we een goed investeringsakkoord hebben met China.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-127-0000" speaker_id="197401" name="Karin Karlsbro (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru talman, herr kommissionär, kära kollegor! Mänskliga fri- och rättigheter är en ledstjärna för det europeiska samarbetet. Hållbarhet med respekt för människor och miljö är grunden för ansvarsfullt företagande. Vår handelspolitik ska bygga på öppenhet så att alla länder kan delta i den globala ekonomin. Men värdekedjorna blir ofta långa och komplexa. Många företag har ett fantastiskt hållbarhetsarbete och de jobbar förebyggande för att förhindra att det någonstans i kedjan har förekommit tvångsarbete eller att verksamhet skett i strid mot grundläggande respekt för miljö och regler, men alla tar verkligen inte sitt ansvar. Att kränka mänskliga rättigheter eller att förstöra miljön får aldrig bli en konkurrensfördel. Därför måste vi ha regler som gäller alla oavsett var företagets huvudkontor ligger. En lagstiftning om due diligence för människor och miljö som riktar sig till stora företag och där kraven är proportionella, kan bli effektiv och göra stor skillnad.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-129-0000" speaker_id="97236" name="Marie Toussaint" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, établir un devoir de vigilance est urgent.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le devoir de vigilance, c’est défendre les droits sociaux, c’est protéger l’avenir de la planète, c’est garantir les libertés démocratiques. À l’heure où nous parlons, plusieurs centaines d’enfants travaillent encore pour le marché européen, 80 000 hommes et femmes ouïgours sont présumés victimes de travail forcé, 10 % de la déforestation dans le monde est causée par la consommation européenne. Certaines entreprises européennes, quant à elles, continuent à investir dans les énergies fossiles ou les pesticides dangereux, au détriment du climat, de la biodiversité, de notre santé et de la sûreté de la planète. Mettre en place le devoir de vigilance, c’est rappeler une vérité simple: on ne peut pas produire n’importe quoi, n’importe comment, quel qu’en soit le prix humain, social et environnemental. Le travail forcé, la prédation, l’accaparement des ressources doivent cesser. En ce 8 mars, souvenons-nous aussi que l’on ne défendra pas les droits des femmes sans défendre le droit des ouvrières et des paysannes écrasées partout par la loi du profit. Ne laissons plus la finance nous dicter nos lois: adoptons ce devoir de vigilance ambitieux européen, nous le pouvons, nous le devons, alors nous le ferons.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-130-0000" speaker_id="197829" name="Jorge Buxadé Villalba" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidente, comisario, este proyecto sobre la diligencia debida en las empresas nos lleva al abismo del sentido común.</p>
      <p sl="en">En España, en un año, cuatro millones de parados, 900 000 trabajadores con contratos suspendidos, 200 000 negocios cerrados, 600 000 autónomos sin actividad … y en toda Europa es lo mismo: 15 millones de parados. Y ahora este Parlamento Europeo les dice a las empresas que tienen que ser agentes activos de la Agenda 2030 y ellas son las que tienen que garantizar los derechos humanos, la lucha contra el cambio climático y la buena gobernanza en terceros países y en toda la cadena de valor.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bien saben ustedes que esto no sirve para nada, porque las violaciones de derechos humanos se persiguen con policía, con jueces y con cárcel, pero no imponiendo más cargas, más obligaciones, más gastos, más responsabilidades y, por supuesto, sanciones incluso a las empresas. De seguir adelante la única consecuencia es que las empresas y los trabajadores europeos van a ser menos competitivos y más pobres, y donde ahora hay empresas europeas habrá empresas chinas o americanas.</p>
      <p sl="en">¿Queremos combatir a las multinacionales globalistas? Bien, hagámoslo, pero dejemos fuera a nuestras pequeñas y medianas empresas. Díganles de verdad que subcontratar en terceros países que no tienen cuotas de género o de sexo en las empresas es un atentado al Derecho de la Unión Europea, pero, sin embargo, nosotros seguimos firmando acuerdos con teocracias islamistas. ¿Por qué les exigimos a las empresas aquello que no nos exigimos a nosotros?</p>
      <p sl="en">No es el momento de sobrecargar a las empresas. Ni ustedes ni yo nos jugamos ni nuestro dinero ni nuestra vida, pero los que están ahí fuera, los trabajadores y los empresarios europeos, se están jugando su dinero y su vida. Estamos a tiempo de pararlo si excluimos a las pequeñas y medianas empresas. Esta crisis ha demostrado que Europa es un juguete roto en manos de la industria china, y tenemos que proteger a nuestros empresarios y trabajadores.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-131-0000" speaker_id="96646" name="Helmut Scholz (The Left" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir können fraktionsübergreifend stolz sein, dass wir als Parlament mit diesem Bericht endlich eine sehr umfängliche legislative Initiative ergreifen. Das Europäische Liefergesetz wird kommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alle in der EU operierenden Unternehmen mit mehr als 250 Beschäftigten oder die börsennotiert sind, werden verpflichtet, die Einhaltung von Menschenrechten, Umweltschutz, würdigen Arbeitsbedingungen entlang ihrer Lieferketten zu gewährleisten. Das kann und muss nach den Konfliktmineralien-Richtlinien ein weiterer wichtiger Baustein für fairen, nachhaltigen internationalen Handel werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Kommission ist gefordert, mutig ein Gesetz vorzulegen, das die Einfuhr von Produkten auf den europäischen Markt verhindert, die mit Einsatz von Kinderarbeit, Zwangsarbeit, modernen Formen der Sklaverei oder mit die Gesundheit oder die Umwelt ruinierenden Methoden hergestellt wurden. Schaffen Sie auch für die KMU die Möglichkeit des Nachweises, dass sie über saubere Lieferketten verfügen. Sorgen Sie dafür, dass es schmerzt, wenn schwarze Schafe unter den Unternehmen bei Missachtung ihrer Sorgfaltspflicht erwischt werden. Eröffnen Sie den Opfern einen Zugang zu Entschädigungen. Die haben das nämlich nötiger als Investoren.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-132-0000" speaker_id="96830" name="Enikő Győri" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Elnök Asszony! Jót akarni nagyon fontos, de közben nem kellene lábon lőni magunkat. Nézzük, miként működne ez a tervezet a gyakorlatban! Minden szavam a JURI tervezetén alapul. Joe egy kávézó tulajdonosa egy uniós tagállamban. A kávét Zulutól, egy afrikai termelőtől veszi, több beszállítón keresztül. Az irányelv értelmében Joe felelős az egész értékláncért, így Zulu viselt dolgaiért is. Mivel Joe szabálykövető, megtesz mindent, amit az irányelv előír: stratégiát ír, nyomoz, ellenőriz. Kávét főzni már nincs ideje. Egy szép napon megjelenik Vilmos, a civil és azt állítja: Joe hibát követett el, mert vele nem konzultált, pedig ő megmondta volna, hogy Zulu a talajra veszélyes permetet használ. Emiatt azt követeli, Joe fizessen kártérítést és nyilvánosan kérjen bocsánatot.</p>
      <p sl="en">A nemzeti hatóságok bírságot rónak ki, eltiltják Joe-t az állami támogatásuktól. Jön egy újabb Covid-hullám, Joe lehúzhatja a rolót. A javaslat tehát kkv-ellenes, szabadpiac-ellenes és beavatkozik a szerződéses jogba. Kérem, ne szavazzák meg! A Bizottság pedig, várja be a hatástanulmányt! Nézzük meg, miként érinti a versenyképességet, a beszállítói láncokat és csak utána mutassa be a javaslatot!</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-133-0000" speaker_id="129164" name="Tom Vandenkendelaere" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, slechts een op de drie bedrijven in Europa kan inschatten wat de impact is van hun activiteit op het vlak van mensenrechten en milieu. Het merendeel van de Europese bedrijven heeft er dus geen flauw benul van of er bijvoorbeeld in zijn waardeketen sprake is van kinderarbeid of het systematisch dumpen van afvalstoffen in rivieren. De wetgeving in Europa hierover is te versnipperd. Bedrijven laten bijdragen aan een duurzame keten is nochtans noodzakelijk. Vele bedrijven focussen sterk op die kortetermijnwinsten, terwijl het verduurzamen van een waardeketen op lange termijn even belangrijk is. Toch mogen we niet blind zijn voor de vele vrijwillige initiatieven die al bestaan bij onze Europese bedrijven vandaag. Vandaar dat ik deze oproep voor een Europese aanpak onderschreef. Het zou een gelijk speelveld creëren en een competitief voordeel uitbreiden naar alle bedrijven en onze interne markt, maar onder de juiste voorwaarden en mits met een proportionele aanpak. Het kan niet zo zijn dat onze kmo’s de dupe worden van deze wetgeving omdat ze zich aan het einde van de schakel bevinden, omdat ze niet over voldoende capaciteit of informatie beschikken. Vandaar dat ik de Europese Commissie met aandrang oproep om voldoende garanties in te bouwen en de administratieve last te beperken. Enkel op die manier zullen we komen tot een gedragen wetgeving die voldoende incentives geeft om een waardeketen te verduurzamen. Proportionaliteit is het sleutelwoord.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-134-0000" speaker_id="197678" name="Bettina Vollath" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar! Viel zu lange haben wir in Europa den Unternehmen die Verantwortung überlassen, dafür zu sorgen, dass ihr Handeln Mensch und Umwelt nicht schadet.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Erfahrung hat gezeigt: Das reicht einfach nicht. Trotz positiver Ausnahmen halten sich bisher viel zu wenige an Standards zum Schutz von Mensch und Natur. Darum brauchen wir in der EU dringend ein für alle verbindliches Lieferkettengesetz, denn ein solches hilft Mensch und Wirtschaft.</p>
      <p sl="en">Klare Regeln erleichtern das Arbeiten für Unternehmen, schützen Verbraucherinnen und Arbeitnehmerinnen und ermöglichen Geschädigten den Zugang zu Rechtsmitteln. Daher hoffe ich darauf, dass die Kommission auf Basis dieses Berichtes einen starken Vorschlag vorlegen wird. Nur wenn Sie jetzt mutig vorangehen, wird die wirtschaftliche Zukunft der EU eine umwelt- und menschenrechtsfreundliche Zukunft sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nur so können wir auch die Probleme unserer Zeit lösen: Egal ob Klimakrise, Ausbeutung oder Menschenrechtsverletzungen – all das wird sich nur so lösen lassen. Wenn Unternehmen endlich zu dieser Verantwortung stehen, dann kann unsere Welt zu einem besseren Ort werden.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-135-0000" speaker_id="204332" name="Barry Andrews (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, a number of other speakers have mentioned the legal case where Nestlé are a defendant in respect of child slaves that escaped from Côte d’Ivoire and Nestlé have made the case of impunity, or immunity, because of remoteness, being so far away, and a lack of control. There is another case in the UK where last month the UK Supreme Court accepted the proposition that the parent company could owe a duty of care in respect of damage caused by a subsidiary in a third country, thus accepting that the most vulnerable communities, at the furthest end of the supply chain, deserve the protection of the British court. In the US, there is a case involving Dell, Tesla, Microsoft, Google and Apple as defendants in a case involving children who are injured and children who have been killed in a mine collapse associated with cobalt mining in the Democratic Republic of Congo.</p>
      <p sl="en">Now these cases can be avoided with proper due diligence properly implemented. These cases can in fact improve the position of companies, but the least we can do, I would say to the Commissioner, is make sure that we don’t weaken the hand of vulnerable communities as plaintiffs, and that we make sure that they have access to remedies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-136-0000" speaker_id="86793" name="Anna Cavazzini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, lieber Herr Kommissar! Mit sehr hoher Wahrscheinlichkeit wurden die Kakaobohnen für diese Schokolade von Kinderhänden gefertigt und ein Hungerlohn dafür gezahlt. Wahrscheinlich findet das niemand von Ihnen hier im Saal gut, so wie auch die meisten Verbraucherinnen und Verbraucher Produkte haben wollen, die nicht mit Menschenrechtsverletzungen zu tun haben. Sie wissen jedoch nicht oft, wo genau die Jeans herkommt, was sich hinter dem Schokoriegel verbirgt oder wo die Ledertasche genau herkommt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Jahrelang wurde bei den Unternehmen auf Freiwilligkeit gesetzt – mit wenig Wirkung. Das Europaparlament hat jetzt die Möglichkeit, Geschichte zu schreiben. Eine Geschichte, die von menschenwürdigen Arbeitsbedingungen handelt, von Unternehmen, die ihre Verantwortung entlang der gesamten Lieferkette wahrnehmen, und von einem Ende der Straflosigkeit bei Fabrikbränden oder Chemieunfällen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wollen wir die Globalisierung wirklich fair und gerecht gestalten – und das sagen wir Politikerinnen und Politiker immer alle in unseren Sonntagsreden –, dann brauchen wir weitreichende gesetzliche Regeln für die menschenrechtliche Sorgfalt in der Wirtschaft. Und genau das schlägt der Parlamentsbericht vor. Ich freue mich besonders, dass meine Forderung nach einem zusätzlichen Importverbot für Produkte aus Zwangsarbeit Einzug gehalten hat in den Bericht. Und jetzt ist die Kommission am Zug.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-137-0000" speaker_id="204733" name="Dorien Rookmaker" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, het voortbestaan van de EU hangt af van ondernemingen, het voortbestaan van een onderneming hangt af van het kunnen balanceren tussen de belangen van alle betrokkenen. Dit heet met een chique woord stakeholder management. Het bestaat al vele jaren en het werkt. Dus wat is het nut van extra regelgeving? Het is aan de ondernemer om verbetering goed te timen, afhankelijk van onder meer de robuustheid van de organisatie en de stand van de economie. Om nu in tijden van COVID met een gigantisch pak aan voorschriften, nieuwe regels voor het bedrijfsleven aan te komen, getuigt van een volstrekt gebrek aan inlevingsvermogen van de rapporteur. De rapporteur geeft aan dat het bedrijfsleven zich niet bewust is van de eigen impact op de omgeving, maar begrijpt ze zélf wel wat voor impact ze heeft op het bedrijfsleven? Het wantrouwen naar ondernemingen druipt uit dit verslag. Met dit initiatief worden problemen niet opgelost, maar gecreëerd. Het is van het allergrootste belang dat alle EU-instellingen nu zelfbeheersing opbrengen en hun regelzucht tot nader order opschorten. Zo kan het bedrijfsleven weer even op adem komen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-138-0000" speaker_id="204333" name="Salvatore De Meo" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, negli ultimi anni consumatori e investitori hanno posto sempre più attenzione alla sostenibilità dei modelli produttivi e alla responsabilità sociale delle imprese.</p>
      <p sl="en">È significativo che proprio oggi, che si celebra la Giornata internazionale della donna, si discuta di una normativa europea chiara in materia di dovuta diligenza e responsabilità, affinché le scelte imprenditoriali e commerciali tengano nell'adeguata considerazione i diritti umani, soprattutto di bambini e donne ancora oggi spesso violati, e tengano in considerazione gli impatti sociali e ambientali, soprattutto in prospettiva delle ambiziose sfide della transizione verde e digitale. Anche in questo l'Europa può essere di stimolo agli altri continenti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Tutto bene, però bisogna tener conto delle peculiarità del tessuto imprenditoriale dove vi sono paesi, come l'Italia, in cui il sistema è composto in gran parte da piccole e medie imprese che costituiscono la spina dorsale di importanti filiere produttive europee. Nei rapporti commerciali bisogna evitare il rischio che le imprese economicamente più forti scarichino i propri obblighi di dovuta diligenza e responsabilità sulle piccole e medie imprese della loro filiera o addirittura li possano evitare con la delocalizzazione della produzione.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bisogna evitare che le piccole imprese vengano gravate di ulteriori oneri, specialmente in un momento in cui invece bisogna dar loro ripresa e rilancio. Per queste ragioni auspico che per le piccole e medie imprese ci possano essere modelli volontari e ove non sia possibile fornire loro un adeguato sostegno per favorire una loro dovuta diligenza.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-139-0000" speaker_id="197717" name="Ibán García Del Blanco" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, en primer lugar, quería darle las gracias, sobre todo, a la ponente. Voy a centrar en ella todo el esfuerzo que han realizado tantos diputados y tantos compañeros, en este caso en Lara Wolters, porque sé que el trabajo no ha sido nada fácil. Solo en mi comisión se han presentado cientos de enmiendas y se ha llegado a compromisos muy avanzados, progresistas y apoyados además en una mayoría parlamentaria, en principio, que va a ser amplia.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo estoy un poco sorprendido por algunas intervenciones que he escuchado aquí en las que se apela a la incapacidad que tendríamos, en el caso de adoptar este tipo de medidas, para competir con otros países. Y parece que lo que quieren algunos es que nos comportemos como esos países.</p>
      <p sl="en">Señorías, la Unión Europea es un proyecto político y un proyecto civilizatorio que se basa en ideales elevados. Hemos decidido que aquí no vale cualquier cosa y que nosotros no vamos a tolerar cualquier cosa: con todas nuestras contradicciones, con todos nuestros problemas, con todos nuestros pasos hacia atrás y hacia delante. Pero es una decisión que hemos tomado y que han tomado, sobre todo, nuestros ciudadanos y nuestras ciudadanas.</p>
      <p sl="en">Vamos a ayudar, a quienes quieren cumplir, a cumplir; vamos a intentar que sea, además, un marco equilibrado; vamos, además, a dar posibilidades equilibradas también a aquellos que evidentemente tienen menos medios para poder afrontar algunas obligaciones; pero no seamos pacatos, no seamos tímidos, demos pasos hacia delante.</p>
      <p sl="en">Yo quiero pedirle a la Comisión que sea tan valiente como lo está siendo este Parlamento y lo va a ser este Parlamento aprobando esta norma y, por cierto, a los Estados miembros, que adopten también de manera individual cada uno de ellos un esquema regulatorio de acuerdo a esta norma que vamos a aprobar.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-140-0000" speaker_id="197444" name="Svenja Hahn (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Unternehmertum ist Verantwortung. Keinem Unternehmer, keiner Unternehmerin kann es egal sein, ob es Zwangsarbeit oder Kinderarbeit in den eigenen Lieferketten gibt. Und dennoch gibt es sie.</p>
      <p sl="en">Globalisierung bedeutet auch Globalisierung von Verantwortung. Ein Lieferkettengesetz muss es Unternehmen einfacher machen, ihrer menschenrechtlichen Sorgfalt nachzukommen. Ein Bürokratiemonster schützt keine Menschenrechte. Deshalb ist ein deutscher Alleingang auch ein Fehler. Er gefährdet den gemeinsamen Markt und schafft Unsicherheit durch Hin und Her, wenn die EU-Regeln kommen. Ein Lieferkettengesetz muss da ansetzen, wo es gebraucht wird. Deswegen ist es gut, dass das Parlament dem sektor-, risiko- und größenbasierten Ansatz folgt. Mit Unternehmensgröße und sensibler Branche wächst Verantwortung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber Herr Reynders, die Kommission würde es sich zu leicht machen, wenn sie Schutz von Menschenrechten nur an Unternehmen delegiert. Ich erwarte klare Ansagen und politische Maßnahmen gegen systematische Menschenrechtsverletzer wie China. Ein europäisches Lieferkettengesetz kann und darf nur ein Baustein sein.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-141-0000" speaker_id="197889" name="Grace O’Sullivan" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">(Verts/ALE). – A Uachtaráin, tá fhios agam go bhfuil mé ag labhairt ar son a lán daoine san Aontas Eorpach. Nuair a théimid ag siopadóireacht, ba mhaith linn fios a bheith againn nach ndearna na hearraí a cheannaímid aon dochar d’aon duine.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ba mhaith linn go mbeadh an bia ar ár bplátaí agus na héadaí ar ár ndroim déanta ar bhealach nach sáraíonn cearta daonna. Ní theastaíonn uainn earraí a dhéantar trí dhúshaothrú oibrithe agus leanaí a cheannach. Más gnólacht thú agus má theastaíonn ár ngnó uait, caithfear ár n-éilimh a chinntiú.</p>
      <p sl="en">Fáiltím roimh chinnteacht dhleathach sa réimse seo agus ceapaim go bhfuil sé thar a bheith tábhachtach, ní hamháin dúinne agus ár gcearta mar thomhaltóirí eolacha, ach go háirithe do chearta na ndaoine is leochailí ar domhain.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-142-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Didier Reynders" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames, Messieurs les députés, permettez-moi tout d’abord de vous remercier pour toutes les contributions que vous avez apportées au débat ce soir à nouveau.</p>
      <p sl="en">L’Union européenne, vous le savez, s’est dotée d’un agenda ambitieux en matière de durabilité. C’est le cas de la Commission menée par la présidente Ursula von der Leyen, à travers le pacte vert européen green que nous avons adopté au début de notre mandat mais c’est aussi le cas, je l’ai constaté à de nombreuses reprises, de votre Parlement. Et pour réaliser les avancées concrètes dans la mise en œuvre de nos engagements sociaux, environnementaux ou en matière de droits humains, il est essentiel d’utiliser toutes les politiques à notre disposition, du commerce au développement, mais il est également essentiel de promouvoir un renforcement de la gouvernance des entreprises. La gouvernance durable des entreprises est un élément majeur, c’est une opportunité pour tous, en ce compris le monde économique. Et le devoir de vigilance est un élément essentiel à cet égard.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, le nouveau cadre que nous souhaitons mettre en place apportera des bénéfices à l’ensemble de l’économie, et ce, même au-delà de nos frontières, comme plusieurs l’ont rappelé ce soir.</p>
      <p sl="en">La Commission inscrira dans sa proposition horizontale un certain nombre de choix.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le choix du champ d’application, beaucoup ont rappelé leur attention particulière aux petites et moyennes entreprises, mais aussi en tenant compte de la notion de risque.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le choix de transparence pour organiser une publication des engagements pris par les entreprises.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le choix aussi de la responsabilité civile ou à travers la supervision administrative, comme le droit des victimes, qu’il faudra également prendre en considération dans notre proposition.</p>
      <p sl="en">Et puis, bien entendu, le choix d’un devoir de vigilance, probablement sur l’ensemble de la chaîne d’approvisionnement si, comme je l’ai entendu de la part de beaucoup d’intervenants, nous voulons pouvoir lutter contre le travail des enfants ou le travail forcé qui souvent se trouvent assez loin dans la chaîne d’approvisionnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors voilà, nous allons travailler à cette proposition concernant bien entendu l’ensemble des entreprises non seulement présentes directement dans l’Union européenne, mais venant travailler aussi dans cette Union européenne, même si elles viennent de pays tiers. Et je me réjouis bien entendu de poursuivre nos échanges sur ce sujet dans les mois à venir, j’espère, pas dans les années à venir parce que je souhaiterais vraiment que la proposition ambitieuse que nous voulons présenter soit adoptée dans un délai raisonnable. En tout cas, je peux à nouveau vous garantir de l’engagement de la Commission et de mon engagement personnel dans ce dossier.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung über die Änderungsanträge findet am Dienstag, 9. März 2021, statt. Die Schlussabstimmung folgt dann am Mittwoch, 10. März 2021.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-2500" speaker_id="124696" name="Andrus Ansip (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjalikult. – Ma nõustun raporti peamise ideega, et äritegevusstandardid Euroopas peaksid olema vastutustundlikud ning ettevõtted peavad oma tegevuses vältima inimestele ja planeedile kahju tegemist. Siiski on kavandatav administratiivne koormus väikeettevõtete jaoks ebaproportsionaalselt suur ning on kaheldav, kas sisuliselt riigi kohustusi on ikka õige delegeerida eraettevõtetele. Igasugused uued siduvad reeglid ei tohiks puudutada VKEsid või vähemalt peaksid need olema kohandatud nende vajadustele. Ühtne uus reeglistik peab olema proportsionaalne ja realistlik selles osas, mida ettevõtted saavad ja suudavad teha, ilma et need uued reeglid ohustaks Euroopa ettevõtete konkurentsivõimet maailmas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-3750" speaker_id="197446" name="Milan Brglez" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">pisno. – Primerna skrbnost in odgovornost podjetij bi kot načelo morala postati integralni del poslovnega modela in operacij podjetij tako znotraj Unije kot v odnosu do tretjih držav, v skladu z določili iz ustanovnih pogodb EU.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kljub številnim aktom mehkega prava (priporočil, smernic, deklaracij) na mednarodni, regionalni in EU ravni obstajajo podjetja, ki se uresničevanja omenjenega načela lotevajo stihijsko, pomanjkljivo ali celo na način psevdo-družbene odgovornosti, medtem ko njihovo delovanje vpliva na (ireverzibilno) okoljsko degradacijo in (tudi posledično) spoštovanje človekovih pravic.</p>
      <p sl="en">Zato pozdravljam napore in prizadevanja Evropskega parlamenta za sprejetje zakonodajnega okvira na tem področju, saj je očitno, da zgolj prostovoljne zaveze ne delujejo. Istočasno je v tem okviru potrebno okrepiti tudi dostop do učinkovitega pravnega varstva prizadetim posameznikom ali skupnostim, ki so žrtve neodgovornega ravnanja podjetij.</p>
      <p sl="en">Za učinkovitost teh mehanizmov (na ravni EU) se zavzemam tudi neposredno pri oblikovanju predloga revizije Aarhuške uredbe, katere namen je izboljšati dostop do pravnega varstva v okoljskih zadevah in s tem omogočiti pravočasno preprečevanje okoljske škode, še preden bi ta imela resne posledice za ljudi. Menim namreč, da je od razpoložljivosti in učinkovitega delovanja takih mehanizmov, s katerimi stremimo k najvišjim možnim okoljevarstvenim standardom, ne nazadnje odvisna uresničitev ambicioznega zelenega prehoda ter gospodarske transformacije, ki smo jo začrtali v okviru evropskega zelenega dogovora.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-4375" speaker_id="40599" name="Sirpa Pietikäinen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – On itsestään selvää, että jokaisella yrityksellä on lain mukaan huolellisuusvelvoite talousasioissa. Tällä hetkellä yritysten vaikutukset ilmastonmuutokseen ovat kuitenkin vielä suuremmat ja vakavammat kuin niiden taloudelliset vaikutukset. Sen vuoksi on tärkeää, että huolellisuusvelvoite laajennetaan koskemaan myös yritysten suoria ja epäsuoria vaikutuksia ympäristöön, biodiversiteettiin ja ilmastonmuutokseen ja että arvioidaan sekä niiden sosiaalisia velvollisuuksia että hallintotapaa. Yritysmaailmassa vastuullisuudesta ja kestävyydestä puhuttaessa käytetään usein termilyhennettä ESG (environment, social, governance), ja jo nyt useimmat yritykset käyttävätkin ESG-kriteeristöä arvioidessaan toimintaansa. Onkin perusteltua ulottaa ESG-kriteerit koskemaan huolellisuusvelvoitetta, sillä ilmastonmuutoksen edetessä yrityksille on vielä tässä vaiheessa suhteellisen edullista ennakoida ja välttää riskit, joita se toiminnallaan aiheuttaa. Lisäksi tulevaisuudessa sijoittajia kiinnostavat yritykset, joissa ESG-riskit on minimoitu. ESG:n mittaaminen on siis vähintään yhtä tärkeää kuin taloudellinen huolellisuus, ja siksi sen raportoinnin ja valvonnan on oltava yhteismitallista taloudellisen huolellisuuden kanssa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-5000" speaker_id="213330" name="Ernő Schaller-Baross" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">írásban. – Az emberi jogok védelme, környezetvédelem és a tisztességes vállalatirányítás fontos uniós prioritások, melyeknek a gazdasági életben is érvényesülniük kell. Azok az intézkedések azonban, amelyeket ennek érdekében alkalmazunk, arányosnak és célhoz kötöttnek kell lenniük, megőrizve az uniós vállalatok versenyképességét. Az EU-ban működő 24 millió kkv az uniós gazdaság gerincét képezi. A Covid-járvány kitörése előtt az EU GDP-jének több mint felét állították elő és mintegy 100 millió munkavállalót foglalkoztattak. A jelenlegi járványhelyzetben felelőtlenség újabb előírásokkal terhelni az európai vállalatokat és elvárni azt, hogy egymást ellenőrizzék az emberi jogok, környezetvédelmi előírások és a tisztességes vállalatirányítás érvényesülése terén.</p>
      <p sl="en">Álláspontom szerint ez nem a vállalkozások, hanem a hatóságok feladata. A versenyképesség rovására megy, hogy a javaslat szerint a cégeknek saját üzletpolitikájukat civil szervezetek és aktivisták bevonásával, az ő beleszólásuk alapján kell kialakítaniuk, nem pedig tulajdonosaik, részvényeseik, munkavállalóik és általában a piaci igények alapján hozzák meg gazdasági, üzletviteli döntéseiket. A Parlament javaslatát nem előzte meg semmilyen hatásvizsgálat, emiatt az számos, jogi értelemben is kivitelezhetetlen rendelkezést tartalmaz. Kiemelten fontos, hogy a Bizottság jogalkotási javaslatát részletes és alapos hatástanulmány előzze meg, különösen az európai vállalkozások helyzetére és versenyképességére nézve. Ki kell állnunk az európai kis-és középvállalatok mellett, ez az Unió fenntartható és hosszú távú gazdasági növekedésének kulcsa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-143-7500" speaker_id="124726" name="Henna Virkkunen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">kirjallinen. – Parlamentissa on laaja yksimielisyys pakollisen, EU:n tason yritysvastuulainsäädännön tarpeesta. Tuen myös itse tällaisen lainsäädännön säätämistä, kunhan tietyt reunaehdot täyttyvät. Parlamentti on vahvistanut aiemmissa äänestyksissä myös tavoitteensa hallinnollisen taakan vähentämisestä. Samaan on sitoutunut myös EU:n komissio. Kun uusi lainsäädäntö tehdään oikein, näiden tavoitteiden välillä on löydettävissä oikea tasapaino. JURI-valiokunnan pohjaesityksessä tämä tasapaino ei valitettavasti toteudu, sillä sääntely kohdistuu sekä suorasti että epäsuorasti pk-yrityksiin, joilla on sääntelyn taustalla oleviin ongelmiin käytännössä olematon yhteys. Teimme siksi useiden, neljää eri poliittista ryhmää edustavien kollegoiden kanssa joukon muutosesityksiä, joilla haluamme selkeyttää ehdotetun lainsäädännön soveltamisalaa. Pk-yritykset tulisi rajata kokonaan soveltamisalan ulkopuolelle, ja korkean riskin alojen ja suurten yritysten määritelmää on selkeytettävä. Lisäksi ehdotetussa lainsäädännössä tulisi selkeästi todeta, että vastuuvelvoitteiden siirtäminen sopimusteitse alihankkijoille on kielletty. Viesti on suunnattu myös komissiolle: kun lainsäädäntöesitystä nyt valmistellaan, hallinnolliseen taakkaan ja pk-yritysten asemaan on kiinnitettävä enemmän huomiota.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem23" title="23. Implementation of the Construction Products Regulation (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-145-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Christian Doleschal im Namen des Ausschusses für Binnenmarkt und Verbraucherschutz über die Umsetzung der Verordnung (EU) Nr. 305/2011 zur Festlegung harmonisierter Bedingungen für die Vermarktung von Bauprodukten (Bauprodukteverordnung) (2020/2028(INI)) (A9-0012/20219).</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich darf noch einmal kurz daran erinnern, dass keine spontanen Wortmeldungen und auch keine blauen Karten akzeptiert werden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Außerdem sind wie jetzt schon auch in der vorangegangenen Debatte wieder Zuschaltungen aus den Verbindungsbüros des Parlaments vorgesehen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-146-0000" speaker_id="197473" name="Christian Doleschal" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatter. – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Vertreter der Kommission, sehr verehrte Abgeordnete! Der Binnenmarkt ist unumstritten eine der wichtigsten Errungenschaften unserer europäischen Integration. Er ist tragende Säule der Europäischen Union. Eine Branche, die im Besonderen davon profitiert, ist sicherlich der Bausektor. Über 18 Millionen Menschen sind europaweit darin beschäftigt, größtenteils grenzüberschreitend.</p>
      <p sl="en">Umso wichtiger sind dabei einheitliche Regeln und Anforderungen für einen reibungslosen Warenverkehr. Seit Juli 2013 gelten die Spielregeln der Bauprodukteverordnung. Harmonisierte Normen für die CE-Kennzeichnungen von Bauprodukten und die Vorgehensweise bei der Erstellung einer Leistungserklärung in Bezug auf ihre wesentlichen Merkmale werden dort festgelegt. Dieses System der technischen Regulierung und Normung hat sich als großer Katalysator für die Wettbewerbsfähigkeit und Innovation bewiesen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Doch seit einigen Jahren kommt dieses System ins Stocken. Von 444 Normen sind gerade einmal zwölf in den letzten vier Jahren im Europäischen Amtsblatt veröffentlicht worden. Seit Dezember 2018 wurde keine einzige harmonisierte Norm mehr veröffentlicht. Dieser Stillstand ist unter anderem auf die formalen Anforderungen zurückzuführen, im Besonderen durch die Interpretation des EuGH-Urteils in der Rechtssache „James Elliot“. Die Folgen der fehlenden Veröffentlichungen von Normen sind fatal. Die fehlende Veröffentlichung von Normen hält nicht mit den Entwicklungen im Bausektor Schritt. Technologien entwickeln sich weiter. Der Regelungsbedarf steigt. Die Rechtsunsicherheit für Unternehmen, Bauherren, Planer und Architekten wächst stetig. Gerade vor diesem Hintergrund müssen wir den Unternehmen Planungs- und Rechtssicherheit zurückgeben.</p>
      <p sl="en">In unserem Bericht schlagen wir deshalb vor: Neben kurzfristigen Lösungen sollte man auch auf langfristige Lösungen zur Überarbeitung der Bauprodukteverordnung setzen. Wir schlagen eine Kombination aus Maßnahmen zur Beseitigung des Rückstaus der nicht veröffentlichten Normen und langfristigen Lösungen vor. Gerade für die Überarbeitungszeit benötigen wir sofortige Lösungen, um die dringenden rechtlichen und technischen Herausforderungen in den Griff zu bekommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir wollen eine stärkere Einbindung der Interessensvertreter in alle Schritte der Ausarbeitung der Normen. Wir brauchen praktikable Lösungen und müssen sicherstellen, dass die von der Kommission erteilten Normungsaufträge klaren und pragmatischen Leitlinien folgen. Auch müssen wir sicherstellen, dass es zumindest für den Moment der Übergangsphase alternative Normungsmethoden, wie z. B. die der EOTA, gibt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir brauchen eine klare Definition des CE-Zeichens. Leider wird das CE-Zeichen für Bauprodukte weiterhin oftmals als Qualitätssiegel verstanden, obwohl es nicht angibt, ob ein Bauprodukt sicher ist oder bei jedem Bauwerk verwendet werden kann. Wir sollten hier Klarheit für den Endnutzer schaffen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Eine Überarbeitung der Bauprodukteverordnung birgt aber auch eine große Chance: Gerade digitale Technologien wie Smart Declaration of Performance haben ein immenses Potenzial, schnell transparente und zuverlässige Informationen bereitzustellen. Der Bausektor ist einer der am wenigsten digitalisierten Bereiche – und das trotz seines großen Potenzials. So könnten wir zum Beispiel durch digitale Tools Überschneidungen oder doppelte Informationen auf Bauprodukten vermeiden. Die überarbeitete Bauprodukteverordnung könnte genau dafür den geeigneten Rechtsrahmen bieten.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir wollen eine stärkere Überwachung von Bauprodukten. Eine möglichst einheitliche Durchsetzung der Harmonisierungsvorschriften durch die nationalen Marktüberwachungsbehörden ist erforderlich. Wir fordern die Kommission daher auf, zügig Durchführungsrechtsakte gemäß der Verordnung zur Marktüberwachung zu erlassen. Wir müssen sicherstellen, dass im gesamten Bausektor die gleichen Wettbewerbsbedingungen gelten, und das auch für Bauprodukte, die online angeboten werden oder aus Drittstaaten zu uns kommen. Wir dürfen keine Kompromisse eingehen: Es geht nicht nur um Produktsicherheit, sondern auch um einen fairen Wettbewerb!</p>
      <p sl="en">Zuletzt müssen wir sicherstellen, dass die Bauprodukteverordnung fit für die Zukunft gemacht wird. Gebäude und Infrastruktur sind ein bedeutendes menschengemachtes Rohstofflager. Wir begrüßen es daher, dass die Kommission bereits in verschiedenen Initiativen und Aktionsplänen angekündigt hat, das Bauwesen insgesamt nachhaltiger zu machen. Bei der Beschaffung und Herstellung von Bauprodukten und ihrer Verwendung bei Bauwerken muss insgesamt ein nachhaltiger Übergang vollzogen werden. Das sollte unter Berücksichtigung der jeweiligen Produktkategorie individuell bewertet werden. Wir sollten einen Anstieg der Preise bei Bauprodukten vermeiden.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sehr geehrte Damen und Herren, ich könnte noch viel länger über die Bauprodukteverordnung sprechen. Vielleicht kann das in der Diskussion noch erfolgen. Ich bitte um Unterstützung dieses sehr wichtigen Berichts.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-147-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Didier Reynders" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, permettez-moi tout d’abord de saluer la démarche de ce rapport d’initiative. Je prends la parole ce soir en remplacement de mon collègue Thierry Breton, qui n’est pas en mesure d’être présent au moment où nous intervenons. Je tiens à remercier M. Doleschal et ses collègues de la commission du marché intérieur et de la protection des consommateurs pour la qualité de leur analyse au sujet de la mise en œuvre du règlement des produits de la construction.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comme vous, la Commission juge qu’il est temps d’assurer le bon fonctionnement du marché intérieur des produits de la construction et d’en maximiser enfin le potentiel. Le contexte actuel de crise sanitaire démontre plus que jamais l’importance d’un marché unique, plus intégré et plus compétitif. Le marché unique conditionne la résilience et la reprise de notre économie. Le marché unique est également l’atout indispensable qui nous permettra de réussir la double transition vers une économie plus verte et plus numérique.</p>
      <p sl="en">Comme le souligne votre rapport, en Europe, 18 millions de personnes sont employées dans le secteur de la construction, lequel contribue à 9 % du produit intérieur brut. Ainsi qu’il ressort du rapport de mise en œuvre de 2015 et de l’évaluation de 2019, le règlement sur les produits de construction traverse une crise profonde. Nous nous trouvons dans une impasse en matière de normalisation technique pour les produits de construction, car les normes qui nous sont proposées par le Comité européen de normalisation (le CEN) pour citation au Journal officiel ne peuvent l’être pour des raisons majoritairement juridiques. En outre, les normes existantes ne répondent, pour la plupart, plus aux attentes des États membres, de l’industrie et des professionnels de la construction. Quant à la surveillance du marché, elle est inégale et insuffisante. Les interprétations par les États membres du règlement varient considérablement, ce qui fausse les règles du jeu. Le principal problème est certes l’impasse de la normalisation. Comme notre partenaire, le CEN, nous avons fait de notre côté tout ce que nous pouvions pour résoudre les problèmes liés au règlement «produits de la construction» dans sa forme actuelle. L’initiative conjointe sur la normalisation consistant en un dialogue de trois ans avec le CEN, qui s’est achevé en décembre 2019, n’a pas produit de résultats tangibles et la Commission européenne n’a aucun pouvoir juridique pour corriger les lacunes des normes techniques dans le cadre réglementaire actuel. Nous le savons, toutes les parties prenantes attendent désespérément une lueur d’espoir. Nous en sommes parfaitement conscients, ainsi que de l’impact de la situation actuelle sur le secteur. Une solution doit dès lors être trouvée. Or, au vu des échecs à répétition de ces dernières années, rien ne garantit malheureusement qu’avec le CEN, nous finissions par dégager enfin une solution dans le cadre réglementaire actuel. Rien ne garantit non plus que si nous parvenions à une telle solution, elle puisse empêcher à l’avenir que nous nous retrouvions de nouveau dans le type de situation que nous connaissons à l’heure actuelle. Bien qu’il serait sans doute plus simple de conserver le processus de normalisation tel que nous le connaissons aujourd’hui, nous devons également envisager d’autres pistes, notamment des voies de secours qui donnent à la Commission la possibilité d’intervenir en cas de normes techniques défaillantes. De telles voies devraient bien sûr aussi intégrer le savoir de l’industrie et des autres parties prenantes concernées dans l’élaboration de futures spécifications techniques. Réparer c’est une chose et le règlement sur les produits de construction mérite certes d’être réparé à de multiples égards. Rendre le règlement apte à répondre aux enjeux du futur est une autre chose et c’est un défi de taille: les produits de construction représentent plus de 40 % des matières premières consommées par l’industrie. Si nous prenons au sérieux l’objectif du pacte vert pour l’Europe, le green deal, il est donc impératif de nous atteler à la tâche de rendre le secteur plus écologique et plus circulaire. La position du Parlement européen sur la question de l’adaptation du règlement des produits de construction aux besoins futurs sera évidemment précieuse pour le travail de la Commission et je vous remercie pour vos contributions au débat de ce soir. Je me réjouis bien entendu de les entendre, comme vos questions et vos observations.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-148-0000" speaker_id="4560" name="Antonius Manders" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">namens de PPE-Fractie. – Voorzitter, mijn collega Christian Doleschal heeft precies de puntjes op de i gezet waar die ontbraken en ik wil niet zo ver ingaan op de details zoals hij dat deed, want hij is de expert en ik niet. Maar ik wil wel een aantal zaken noemen. Ik ben altijd een pleitbezorger geweest van verordeningen, dus direct werkende wetgeving voor de hele interne markt om een level playing field te creëren voor het midden- en kleinbedrijf en grote bedrijven, maar ook voor de burgers geeft dat helderheid. Nu blijkt uit deze verordening dat er behalve de bouwproductenverordening ook nog standaarden zijn die kennelijk niet op elkaar zijn afgestemd, waardoor er toch nog per lidstaat drempels worden ingevoerd waardoor de interne markt niet functioneert.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wellicht, en de commissaris noemde dat al, zou er een versnelde procedure moeten komen zodat niet alleen overheden via de rechterlijke macht naar het Europese Hof van Justitie kunnen stappen, maar dat het midden- en kleinbedrijf in het kader van een bindende arbitrageprocedure binnen vier maanden een uitspraak kan verwachten van het Europese Hof. Stel wat mij betreft speciale juridische kamers daarvoor in. Collega Lebreton was het daar al mee eens overigens. Dus het zou heel goed zijn, want daarmee geef je met name kleinere bedrijven heel snel duidelijkheid, rechtszekerheid en zorgt dat ervoor dat zij over de grens kunnen ondernemen. We hebben zojuist gesproken over de due diligence. Ik denk dat het heel belangrijk is om aan te geven dat het niet kan dat bedrijven van buiten de Europese Unie met staatssteun onze bedrijven beconcurreren. En ik denk dat het goed is dat we due diligence ook op deze verordening toepassen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-149-0000" speaker_id="124785" name="Maria Grapini" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">în numele grupului S&amp;D. – Stimați colegi, raportul pe care îl dezbatem în această seară, referitor la libera circulație a materialelor de construcție, din punctul meu de vedere este extrem de important și, așa cum l-am discutat și în grupul politic din care fac parte, și cu raportorul, cred că a plecat de la o situație reală. În primul rând, IMM-urile s-au plâns de faptul că metodele actuale de supraveghere a pieței privind materialele de construcție sunt insuficiente, dar mai ales ineficiente și este nevoie într-adevăr de stabilirea unor condiții armonizate pentru comercializarea produselor de construcții în piața internă. Sigur că avem nevoie de armonizarea normelor pentru evaluarea performanțelor produselor, în funcție de principalele caracteristici.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este nevoie și de asigurarea unor condiții echitabile pentru operatorii economici și, dacă vom face aceste evaluări, evident vom avea această condiție. În evaluarea regulamentului pentru produsele de construcții trebuie să se țină seama de costurile pe care le vor avea întreprinderile, mai ales IMM-urile. Marcajele naționale fragmentează foarte mult piața internă și creează și incertitudini juridice pentru întreprinderi, constructori. De aceea, cred că este bine să insistăm pe un limbaj comun tehnic în piața internă și autoritățile naționale de supraveghere a pieței materialelor de construcție să colaboreze strâns cu autoritățile naționale de control al construcțiilor. Vă mulțumesc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-150-0000" speaker_id="204419" name="Sandro Gozi" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Renew. – Madame la Présidente, pour construire une Europe plus résiliente et tournée vers la transition écologique et numérique, nous avons un atout fondamental: un marché intérieur équilibré, performant et consolidé, en phase avec les objectifs du pacte vert pour l’Europe et de l’économie circulaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Repenser le marché intérieur doit nous permettre d’évoluer avec les avancées technologiques, mieux utiliser les innovations actuelles et mettre en place une nouvelle protection des consommateurs. Ceci vaut aussi pour un secteur essentiel comme celui de la construction.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est pourquoi, nous demandons à la Commission une révision ambitieuse du règlement sur les produits de construction et la mise en place de règles efficaces, facilement applicables et harmonisées. Certains pays pensent pouvoir s’affranchir de certaines règles communes. Établir un cadre précis pour toute l’Europe, c’est donc nous assurer de maintenir la libre circulation des produits de construction. Ce que nous demandons est donc simple. Tout d’abord, trouver des solutions efficaces pour améliorer la gouvernance de ces acteurs. Et ensuite, des solutions rapides pour améliorer les processus de normalisation. Pour ce faire, nous avons besoin d’un calendrier précis ainsi qu’une participation accrue de l’industrie des États membres et de toutes les parties prenantes.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le secteur de la construction souffre aussi du manque de numérisation. L’augmentation des ventes en ligne doit donc également nous pousser à réguler aussi les plateformes. Nous devons assurer une meilleure information des consommateurs sur la durabilité des produits et travailler davantage sur la réutilisation et le recyclage des produits de construction. Ce domaine est une partie essentielle de la mosaïque d’un marché intérieur durable et doit faire partie de la future révision législative.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cher Commissaire, cher Didier, notre mandat à la Commission est donc clair: travaillons ensemble à des solutions pour la durabilité, la résilience et l’efficacité industrielle.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-151-0000" speaker_id="197627" name="Virginie Joron" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, chaque année, on construit en France 100 000 logements sociaux. Chaque année, la France subit 100 000 demandes d’asile et 200 000 migrants légaux, sans compter les 40 000 mineurs isolés qui ne sont pour la plupart ni mineurs ni isolés, soit l’équivalent d’une ville comme Strasbourg qui arrive chaque année. Alors, on construit toujours plus et surtout n’importe comment. On ne peut pas s’en réjouir. L’Europe des cathédrales et des belles pierres est devenue l’Europe du béton et des mosquées. Nos villes sont défigurées et nos églises détruites pour laisser place à des parkings ou des supermarchés low-cost. Il faut avoir le courage de dire que certaines banlieues en France sont surpeuplées et que l’on n’a pas besoin de l’arrivée de populations supplémentaires extra-européennes. Aujourd’hui, ces déplacements de population transforment l’environnement, à l’instar du déplacement des campagnes vers les villes, par exemple.</p>
      <p sl="en">Cependant, ce rapport sur les produits de construction, puisqu’il faut en parler, je le voterai parce que je suis pour la fiabilité des produits et la sécurité surtout. Il y a beaucoup trop de produits faussement marqués CE sur le marché européen. Nous sommes pour des normes claires contre le bruit, pour la protection de l’environnement et surtout pour la sécurité des 18 millions de travailleurs de la construction de l’Europe.</p>
      <p sl="en">Quant au premier producteur mondial de matériaux de construction, le français Lafarge, il a été vendu aux Suisses. Un mauvais point de plus au passif d’Emmanuel Macron.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-152-0000" speaker_id="204420" name="Claude Gruffat" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur Reynders, chers collègues, en France, on dit «quand le bâtiment va, tout va». Et c’est vrai, le secteur de la construction est souvent la locomotive de nos économies. C’est pourquoi il est plus que temps de faire de ce levier un atout pour le social, le climat et l’environnement.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le texte proposé comporte de nombreuses avancées pour un secteur de la construction à la hauteur des urgences du moment. Une information claire, plus transparente, des nouvelles exigences de performance des produits liées à la santé, à la sécurité et aux aspects environnementaux. Ces exigences de performance sont la clé pour un secteur propre et plus respectueux.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le soutien à la circularité des produits de construction, et Dieu sait si dans ce domaine, il y a beaucoup à faire, de vraies garanties pour la sécurité des travailleurs qui manipulent les produits et bien sûr, pour celle des consommateurs.</p>
      <p sl="en">Monsieur Reynders, la Commission doit mettre le secteur de la construction au service de la transition. Inspirez-vous de ce rapport qui répond au manque de cadre actuel. Ne manquons pas à nos obligations envers les générations futures.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-153-0000" speaker_id="96810" name="Carlo Fidanza" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">a nome del gruppo ECR. – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, Signor Commissario, il settore edilizio rappresenta anch'esso uno dei comparti produttivi duramente colpiti dalla pandemia, a causa della carenza di approvvigionamento dei materiali e del calo degli investimenti e del blocco temporaneo dei lavoratori. A ciò si aggiungono anche migliaia di attività che sono state costrette a chiudere i battenti con gravi ripercussioni a livello occupazionale.</p>
      <p sl="en">Consapevoli della necessità di misure immediate ed efficaci, capaci di coinvolgere l'intero indotto, abbiamo ritenuto, insieme al collega Doleschal che ringrazio e ai colleghi relatori ombra, necessario sfruttare questo momento di grande difficoltà per focalizzarsi su una pronta ripresa, con obiettivi quali lo snellimento della burocrazia, la digitalizzazione e la parità di condizioni tra operatori economici e la vigilanza del mercato, soprattutto nei confronti di tutti quei prodotti venduti online da paesi terzi, che al momento non garantiscono né il rispetto dei nostri standard né la concorrenza leale nel mercato interno.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ci auguriamo che la Commissione possa colmare in tempi brevi una serie di lacune che nel frattempo hanno comportato la nascita di ulteriori requisiti nazionali e di ostacoli ingiustificati, oltre che una frammentazione e un indebolimento del mercato interno.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-154-0000" speaker_id="197417" name="Tomislav Sokol" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Poštovana predsjedavajuća, gospodine povjereniče, kolegice i kolege, Uredbom o građevnim proizvodima osigurava se slobodno kretanje građevnih proizvoda na unutarnjem tržištu. Njezina je ispravna provedba od iznimne važnosti imajući na umu da građevinski sektor stvara 18 milijuna radnih mjesta u Europi i generira 9 posto njezina BDP-a, a pri tome je upravo standardizacija jedan od temelja zajedničkog tržišta i ovom Uredbom se ona želi postići.</p>
      <p sl="en">Izravnom provedbom ove Uredbe osigurava se da građevni proizvodi postižu svoju deklariranu učinkovitost uzimajući u obzir zdravstvene, sigurnosne i ekološke aspekte povezane s njihovom uporabom, a ja zbog toga naglasak stavljam upravo na sigurnost građevnih proizvoda.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nedavna serija potresa koja je pogodila Europsku uniju nažalost nije zaobišla niti moju domovinu Hrvatsku. Razorni potres je ostavio za sobom razrušene domove, kulturne, obrazovne i zdravstvene ustanove, vjerske objekte i javnu infrastrukturu, a nažalost izgubljeni su ljudski životi. Saniranje posljedica potresa trajat će godinama i zahtijevat će ogromna financijska ulaganja. Međutim, građevine ćemo obnoviti, ali izgubljene ljudske živote nažalost ne možemo vratiti.</p>
      <p sl="en">Kolegice i kolege, ovim želim ukazati na važnost ove Uredbe i čitavog sektorskog zakonodavstva u području građevine, osiguravanje manje temeljnih zahtjeva za građevine iz aneksa 1 Uredbe među kojima i mehaničke otpornosti i stabilnosti znači i očuvanje ljudskih života. Stoga pozdravljam donošenje ovog izvješća i pozivam na još odlučnije korake s ciljem ispravne provedbe europskog zakonodavstva koje jamče lakše poslovanje na zajedničkom tržištu, ali i sigurnost naših građana.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-155-0000" speaker_id="37312" name="Christel Schaldemose" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Byggeriet i Europa skal være grønt, det skal være sikkert, og det skal være fornuftigt. Det er en af de beskeder, vi i dag sender til EU-Kommissionen om byggevareforordningen. New Green Deal, og cirkulær økonomi skal være en del af det europæiske byggeri. Det bæredygtige valg skal være førstevalg, når man vælger byggematerialer. Dermed gør vi byggeriet grønnere. De nye regler skal håndhæves med større styrke af de nationale myndigheder. Man skal kunne stole på, at byggematerialer lever op til EU's regler, uanset om der bygges i Billund eller i Bukarest, sådan gør vi byggeriet mere sikkert. Og specifikke minimumskrav skal bruges klogt og forsigtigt. Vejret er forskelligt i Europa, og det skal reglerne afspejle. Minimumskravet til, hvor meget sne et tag skal kunne bære, skal ikke være det samme i Nordsverige som i Nice. Det er sund fornuft. Så hvis Kommissionen tager vores opfordringer om byggevareforordningen med sig, så kan vi tage et stort skridt frem imod at få et mere bæredygtigt byggeri i Europa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-156-0000" speaker_id="197668" name="Vlad-Marius Botoş (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Doamna președintă, domnule comisar, suntem într-un moment în care toate domeniile economice trebuie să se adapteze, pentru a putea respecta angajamentele ecologice și digitale pe care Uniunea Europeană și le-a asumat. Aceasta implică însă inovație, mai ales în domeniul materialelor de construcție, unde accentul trebuie să cadă pe materiale ecologice, reciclabile, cu grad mare de izolare termică. Avem nevoie ca aceste materiale inovative să poată ajunge rapid în toată piața comună europeană, în toate cele 27 de state membre. Tocmai de aceea este important ca procesul de standardizare să fie grăbit, iar inovația să fie la îndemâna tuturor actorilor implicați pe piața materialelor, de la giganții domeniului, la întreprinderile mici și mijlocii.</p>
      <p sl="en">Barierele financiare între marii și micii producători nu fac decât să prelungească perioada de tranziție în domeniul materialelor de construcție. Pentru ca acest domeniu care reprezintă 9 % din produsul intern brut al Uniunii Europene – cum bine ați spus – să țină pasul cu dezvoltarea necesară pentru a respecta Green Deal, trebuie accelerat procesul de armonizare a materialelor. Este nevoie, așadar, de o cooperare sporită între Comisia Europeană și statele membre, pentru a grăbi implementarea regulamentelor existente, dar și pentru îmbunătățirea lor și pentru supravegherea pieței. Doar așa ne putem asigura că toți consumatorii Uniunii au acces la materiale de bună calitate în domeniul construcțiilor. Mulțumesc.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-157-0000" speaker_id="197610" name="Alessandra Basso" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, Commissario, onorevoli colleghe e colleghi, il buon testo è frutto di un dibattito che si è concentrato su molti temi da noi sollevati. Sono soddisfatta e ringrazio il relatore per questo importante risultato raggiunto.</p>
      <p sl="en">La nostra priorità è sempre stata quella di raggiungere una reale parità di condizioni nel mercato interno, eliminando gli ostacoli che in passato hanno impedito la libera circolazione di merci nell'Unione creando barriere ingiustificate ed arbitrarie. Questi ostacoli derivanti da modifiche unilaterali hanno causato danni alle aziende italiane.</p>
      <p sl="en">L'eliminazione delle barriere che si sono create nel tempo alla libera circolazione è la direzione nella quale volevamo andare per avere davvero un'Unione che sia al servizio delle imprese.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-158-0000" speaker_id="197538" name="Beata Mazurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Przepisy dotyczące prawa budowlanego powinny być formułowane i egzekwowane w taki sposób, by zapewniały najwyższy poziom bezpieczeństwa dla pracowników i konsumentów. Powinny być przyjazne dla środowiska naturalnego i, gdzie to możliwe, zbieżne z celami gospodarki o obiegu zamkniętym. W dobie pandemii i spowolnienia gospodarczego, biorąc pod uwagę rosnące ceny nieruchomości, priorytetem powinno zostać upewnienie się, by zmiany te nie wpłynęły negatywnie na cenę produktów i usług, co w ostateczności odbije się na portfelach konsumentów.</p>
      <p sl="en">Bariery techniczne w handlu wyrobami budowlanymi, które w dalszym ciągu występują na wspólnym rynku, muszą być ograniczone, by zapewnić swobodny przepływ tych wyrobów. Jednocześnie należy się zastanowić, czy nadmierne znakowanie produktów budowlanych to dobry kierunek i czy nie będzie on kolejnym wymogiem utrudniającym sprawne funkcjonowanie przedsiębiorstw budowlanych. Należy wziąć pod uwagę aspekt cyfrowy tej branży, mianowicie jego znikomą obecność, przynajmniej z punktu widzenia nabywcy, na etapie sprzedaży. Wprowadzenie nowych rozwiązań cyfrowych przyczyni się do ulepszenia branży, pozwoli na sprawniejsze przekazywanie informacji o produkcie oraz zwiększy przejrzystość rynku wyrobów budowlanych.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-159-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Didier Reynders" is_mep="False" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">membre de la Commission. – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, les débats se suivent et nous restons dans le même cadre de gouvernance et d’économie durable. Une fois de plus, je voudrais saluer votre rapport d’initiative. Il souligne l’importance majeure du marché unique des produits de la construction. Mais il reste, vous le savez, encore beaucoup à faire pour rendre ce marché pleinement opérationnel. Et la Commission compte sur le soutien du Parlement européen à cet égard et se réjouit de la poursuite de notre coopération en vue de cet objectif commun.</p>
      <p sl="en">Je vous remercie à nouveau pour l’ensemble des contributions que vous avez apportées dans l’élaboration de ce rapport et à l’occasion du débat ce soir. J’espère que nous pourrons effectivement progresser dans la voie décrite par le rapport d’initiative.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-160-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung findet am Mittwoch, 10. März 2021 statt.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem24" title="24. Equal treatment in employment and occupation in light of the UNCRPD (debate)">
    <intervention id="1-162-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Katrin Langensiepen im Namen des Ausschusses für Beschäftigung und soziale Angelegenheiten über die Umsetzung der Richtlinie 2000/78/EG des Rates zur Festlegung eines allgemeinen Rahmens für die Verwirklichung der Gleichbehandlung in Beschäftigung und Beruf unter Berücksichtigung der VN-BRK (2020/2086(INI)) (A9-0014/2021).</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-163-0000" speaker_id="197461" name="Katrin Langensiepen" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Berichterstatterin. – Sehr geehrte Damen und Herren, liebe Kolleginnen! Heute stimmen wir über meinen Bericht „Festlegung eines allgemeinen Rahmens für die Verwirklichung der Gleichbehandlung in Beschäftigung und Beruf unter Berücksichtigung der UN-Behindertenrechtskonvention“ ab, der im Sozialausschuss mit 47 Ja-Stimmen, also einer überwältigenden Mehrheit, hier angenommen wurde.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich möchte mich an dieser Stelle bei meinen Abgeordnetenkolleginnen und bei den entsprechenden Adviserinnen ganz herzlich für die äußerst gute Zusammenarbeit – hier fraktionsübergreifend – bedanken. Die Verfassung des Berichts gab mir hier auch einen tieferen Einblick, wofür der europapolitische Gedanke auch stehen kann: Für eine gemeinsame Sache – im besten Fall zur Verbesserung der Lebensbedingungen in unserem gemeinsamen Europa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Aber der Bericht wurde nicht nur ausschließlich von uns geschrieben. Ohne die breite Unterstützung der Verbände und Organisationen, die sich seit Jahrzehnten für die Rechte von Menschen mit Behinderung einsetzen, wäre der Bericht in diesem Umfang nicht zustande gekommen. Namentlich möchte ich sie hier nennen: Autism-Europe, Bundesarbeitsgemeinschaft Inklusionsfirmen, Europäische Blindenunion, Europäisches Behindertenforum, Europäisches Netzwerk für selbstbestimmtes Leben, Europäische Union der Gehörlosen, Inclusion Europe, International Federation for Spina Bifida and Hydrocephalus, Mental Health Europe, Equinet, Professoren der Akademie und Fundamental Rights Agency. Herzlichen Dank!</p>
      <p sl="en">Zudem freut es mich auch besonders, Ihnen berichten zu können, dass unser Bericht – mein Bericht – Ihnen auch in leichter Sprache vorliegt. Das ist neu und sollte für alle Berichte Standard werden, um politische Teilhabe zu garantieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Um was geht es in meinem Bericht? Es geht um uns, um die Situation von uns Menschen mit Behinderungen auf dem Arbeitsmarkt, dass dieser endlich inklusiv und besser und auch auf Augenhöhe gestaltet wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Derzeit kann man die Situation für uns Menschen mit Behinderungen leider nur als schlecht bezeichnen. Nun, bevor wir in die Statistiken einsteigen, eine kleine Anekdote vorab. Als Kind wollte ich Nachrichtensprecherin werden. Ich wollte vor der Kamera stehen, die Nachrichten präsentieren, und da sagte man mir dann: „Naja, also du musst schon realistisch sein. Jemanden wie dich – mit einer offensichtlichen Behinderung – wird man niemals vor die Kamera lassen. Vergiss den Traum, ist sowas wie auf den Mond zu fliegen.“</p>
      <p sl="en">Man hat mir dann einen Ausbildungsplatz in einer Einrichtung angeboten. Das waren ungefähr 50 Euro Lohn im Monat, kein Ausgang mehr nach 22 Uhr und ich hätte einmal im Monat nach Hause gedurft. Ich hatte keinen Rechtsbeistand. Ich war ein freier Mensch, 18 Jahre alt, warum diese Freiheitseinschränkungen? Und ich lehnte ab. Die Leitung dieser Einrichtung war erbost, denn ihnen gingen Fördergelder flöten und man orakelte und prophezeite mir: Ich werde niemals auf dem freien Markt einen Arbeitsplatz finden. Und so wie mir damals geht es heute auch vielen jungen Menschen mit Behinderungen, denen man klar sagt, wo der Weg hingeht, nämlich in die Werkstatt und in die Einrichtung.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gerade in Deutschland sind die Strukturen von Werkstätten weder inklusiv noch bereiten sie auf den regulären Arbeitsmarkt vor, was eigentlich ihr Job ist, das zu tun. Werkstätten dürfen keine Dauerlösung sein, sondern sollten tatsächlich den Übergang zum ersten Arbeitsmarkt schaffen. Deshalb müssen wir die richtigen Voraussetzungen für einen inklusiven Arbeitsmarkt schaffen. Mit Aufklärung, staatlicher Unterstützung für angemessene Vorkehrungen und Sichtbarkeit von uns Menschen mit Behinderung ist Arbeit in Vielfalt möglich. Hier liegt es am politischen Willen, darin zu investieren.</p>
      <p sl="en">Im vorigen Jahrhundert hatten Werkstätten, Einrichtungen, geschlossene, geschützte Räume vielleicht eine Berechtigung. Wir befinden uns aber im Jahr 2021 und wir brauchen einen angemessenen, inklusiven, barrierefreien Arbeitsmarkt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ein paar Zahlen zur Veranschaulichung: Nur 50,6 % der Menschen mit Behinderungen sind erwerbstätig – 48,3 %, das sind wir Frauen mit Behinderungen, und 53,3 % der Männer im Vergleich zu 74,8 % bei Menschen ohne Behinderung. Nur 20,7 % von uns Frauen mit Behinderung, sind in Vollzeit erwerbstätig im Vergleich zu 28,6 % der Männer mit Behinderung. Diese Daten geben allerdings keine Auskunft darüber, wie viele Menschen im offenen Arbeitsmarkt beschäftigt sind, und wie viele davon Menschen mit Behinderungen sind, die in Heimpflege leben, bei denen es weit unwahrscheinlicher ist, dass sie einer Arbeit nachgehen. Was ebenfalls die wenigsten von euch Menschen ohne Behinderung – viele – nicht wissen, ist: Häufig haben wir Menschen mit Behinderungen in den Werkstätten gar keinen Arbeitnehmerinnenstatus. Wir bekommen auch keinen regulären Lohn, wir bekommen ein Taschengeld.</p>
      <p sl="en">Deshalb fordere ich in meinem Bericht ein klares Auslaufenlassen der Einrichtungen und Werkstätten, die Artikel 27 der UN-Behindertenrechtskonvention entgegenstehen. Hierfür brauchen wir klare Ziele und zeitliche Vorgaben für den Übergang. Das ist keine Meinung einzelner, keine Katrin-Meinung, das steht so in der UN-Menschenrechtskonvention.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lassen Sie mich kurz zurückkommen zu meiner Anekdote. Als es mit dem Journalismus nicht so wirklich geklappt hat – weil es wird ja eh nichts –, habe ich noch etwas viel Verrückteres getan: Ich bin Europaabgeordnete geworden – und das ist ein viel besserer Job.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bin hier leider auch die einzige Frau mit sichtbarer und – ich glaube bisher hat sich niemand anders hier gemeldet – sogar die einzige Frau mit Behinderung – sichtbar oder nicht – unter 705 Abgeordneten in diesem Hohen Haus. Das kann nicht sein.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also, liebe Mitgliedstaaten, bewegt euch hier. Liebe Parteien, werdet vielfältiger. Politische Teilhabe, so wie es in den UN-Behindertenrechtskonventionen, aber auch in der neuen Disability Strategy steht, ist ein Menschenrecht.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir haben heute den 8. März. Wir kämpfen auch für die Frauenrechte. Also lasst uns kämpfen für die Frauenrechte, für die Menschenrechte, für Menschen mit Behinderungen. Lasst uns die fünfte Antidiskriminierungsrichtlinie aufheben. Wir brauchen die EU-Leitlinien für angemessene Vorkehrungen, Diversitätsquoten und und und. Lasst uns kämpfen dafür.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-164-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, on behalf of the European Commission I welcome your report on the implementation of the Employment Equality Directive. We fully agree that an inclusive and accessible workplace is vital for persons with disabilities to be able to participate in the labour market, and we welcome the ideas and the recommendations which you put forward on this topic.</p>
      <p sl="en">As you rightly pointed out in your report, having the right skills and qualifications is a prerequisite for accessing and succeeding in the labour market, and participation in employment is the best way to ensure economic independence and social inclusion. We also support your call for a non-discriminatory workplace. Discrimination has no place in the EU, and therefore we pay significant attention to the implementation of the EU equality directives, including the Employment Equality Directive.</p>
      <p sl="en">This debate is very timely. Just a few days ago, the Commission launched a new strategy for the rights of persons with disabilities. It builds on our previous exchanges on your report, on the evaluation of the previous strategy, and on a broad consultation with key partners which took place last year. The strategy confirms the great attention that the Commission attaches to equality and non-discrimination and its commitment to implement the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities within the field of EU competences.</p>
      <p sl="en">We know that this House provides the same level of attention to this area of policy as we do, and I thank rapporteur Langensiepen and the whole Committee on Employment and Social Affairs (EMPL) for their continuous work on this topic. Your contribution is very important for us.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission is continuously monitoring the implementation of the Employment Equality Directive. It is currently preparing its third report on the Directive’s application, together with the application of the Racial Equality Directive. In preparing the new report we took due account of the report by MEP Langensiepen, as well as of the related European Parliament study.</p>
      <p sl="en">I fully agree that awareness of the rights and obligations deriving from the EU Equality Directive is essential for employers and for workers. Reasonable accommodation of persons with disabilities has also to be better understood and applied in practice by employers. I also agree that poor and uneven enforcement and low sanctions of violations may diminish the effectiveness of EU law. I am also well aware that the Directive does not legally require Member States to designate an equality body, while equality bodies play a central role in the implementation of the equal treatment directives. The upcoming Commission report will touch upon all these issues. On this basis, the Commission may propose, as appropriate, a legislative initiative aiming at strengthening the role of equality bodies. Our new disability strategy promotes the social and economic inclusion and participation of people with disabilities in society, free from discrimination and in full respect of their rights on equal basis with others.</p>
      <p sl="en">First, the strategy emphasises that the job environment needs to be accessible. Accessibility and reasonable accommodation must go together to create appropriate conditions for inclusive labour markets. We will pay close attention to the correct implementation and evaluation of all EU rules regulating accessibility and identify gaps and needs for further legislative actions.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Action Plan on the European Pillar of Social Rights announced the target of an employment rate of 78 percent for the adult population with the 2030 horizon. Yet the employment gap between persons with and without disabilities remains high, and further actions are needed to reduce it. The strategy aims at fostering access to quality and sustainable employment.</p>
      <p sl="en">In 2022, the Commission will present a package to improve labour market outcomes of persons with disabilities, seeking further cooperation with the European Network of Public Employment Services, social partners and organisations of persons with disabilities. We also call on the Member States to establish targets for increasing the employment rate of persons with disabilities and to facilitate self-employment and entrepreneurship. We encourage the use of EU funds.</p>
      <p sl="en">The Commission will also continue to promote inclusive education, which lays the foundations for an inclusive labour market. Free movement is a basic right and a fundamental EU freedom. Persons with disabilities still face obstacles in their enjoyment of this right, among others, because their disability status is not recognised among Member States. To improve this, we propose to build on the pilot project of the European Disability Card, implemented so far in eight Member States, with a view to extending it by the end of 2023 to all Member States. And yes, we at the Commission want to lead by example. We will adopt a renewed HR strategy that will include actions to promote diversity and inclusion of persons with disabilities. Furthermore, we intend to act in the areas of accessibility of our buildings and communication. We know that a strong commitment is needed to implement this strategy successfully and to support persons with disabilities to fully enjoy their rights.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will work closely with Member States, stakeholders, persons with disabilities, and we want to work closely with all the stakeholders, especially with persons with disabilities. Nothing about persons with disabilities without persons with disabilities.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-165-0000" speaker_id="96812" name="Juan Fernando López Aguilar" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">ponente de opinión de la Comisión de Libertades Civiles, Justicia y Asuntos de Interior. – Señora presidenta, señora comisaria de Igualdad Helena Dalli, intervengo en este debate para presentar la opinión de la Comisión de Libertades Civiles, Justicia e Interior con tres coordenadas en mente.</p>
      <p sl="en">La primera, el informe de iniciativa sobre el nivel de aplicación de la Directiva en vigor del año 2000. La segunda, la Estrategia sobre los Derechos de las Personas con Discapacidad 2021—2030 de la Comisión. Está también la Convención de las Naciones Unidas, vinculante para la Unión Europea en su calidad de Derecho internacional y fuente del Derecho de la Unión; pero la tercera es la Carta de los Derechos Fundamentales de la Unión Europea, cuyos artículos 21, 26 y 34 son terminantes en sus mandatos de inclusión, integración y promoción de la autonomía personal de las personas con discapacidad.</p>
      <p sl="en">El mensaje que quiero emitir en nombre de la Comisión LIBE es que es hora de que el Consejo desbloquee la Directiva de igualdad de trato y esta se sume, naturalmente, a la Directiva en vigor, que garantiza los derechos de acceso al empleo de las personas con discapacidad, porque la Directiva de igualdad de trato lleva bloqueada por el Consejo más de diez años, tanto que fue negociada antes de la entrada en vigor del Tratado de Lisboa. Es hora de que además se someta al procedimiento legislativo ordinario.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-166-0000" speaker_id="197720" name="Frances Fitzgerald" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, in an ideal world work and employment would mean empowerment, independence and full inclusion in society for people with a disability. But unfortunately, that is frequently not a reality. On this International Women’s Day let us remember that women with disabilities make up 16% of the total population of women and 60% of the overall population of persons with a disability in the EU, ensuring that our continent allows all people with a disability to fully participate and that economic and social life is not catering to a small population, but rather benefits all of us, economically and socially.</p>
      <p sl="en">In Ireland and across Europe, we have many vibrant disability organisations that need to be supported further in their work for greater inclusion. They work to raise awareness of rights, to share research and best practice, and to combat youth and senior unemployment. The EU should make full use of the abilities of all its citizens. Rights is not a favour we should ask for from others, but it is a bare minimum.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-167-0000" speaker_id="124692" name="Δημήτρης Παπαδάκης" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Εισηγητής της γνωμοδότησης της Επιτροπής Αναφορών. – Κυρία Πρόεδρε, το γεγονός ότι τα άτομα με αναπηρία εξακολουθούν να αντιμετωπίζουν πολλές προκλήσεις και διακρίσεις που σχετίζονται με την προσβασιμότητα, τη συμμετοχή στην απασχόληση, την εκπαίδευση και την κινητικότητα είναι απαράδεκτο. Απαράδεκτο είναι επίσης ότι πολλοί εργοδότες εξακολουθούν να μη λαμβάνουν κατάλληλα μέτρα για την αντιμετώπιση αυτών των ζητημάτων, τα οποία είναι ζωτικής σημασίας.</p>
      <p sl="en">Καλώ λοιπόν την Ευρωπαϊκή Επιτροπή να λάβει αποτελεσματικά μέτρα σε συνεργασία με τις οργανώσεις των ατόμων με αναπηρία και τους κοινωνικούς εταίρους για την επίτευξη της κοινωνικής και οικονομικής ένταξης των ατόμων με αναπηρία. Τα κράτη μέλη θα πρέπει να διασφαλίσουν ότι η απασχόληση των ατόμων με αναπηρία περιλαμβάνεται στα εθνικά μεταρρυθμιστικά προγράμματα τους. Ούτε η πανδημία μπορεί να αποτελέσει δικαιολογία για τον αποκλεισμό των συμπολιτών μας με αναπηρία. Σήμερα, Παγκόσμια Ημέρα της Γυναίκας, τονίζουμε τον ρόλο των γυναικών, οι οποίες έχουν την πρωταρχική ευθύνη για τη φροντίδα των παιδιών και των εξαρτώμενων ατόμων με αναπηρία, και το ότι οι γυναίκες με αναπηρία αντιμετωπίζουν διπλή διάκριση.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-168-0000" speaker_id="197692" name="Stelios Kympouropoulos" is_mep="True" mode="spoken" role="on behalf of the PPE Group">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, a few days after the release of the new European Disability Strategy, I am very pleased that we have this chance to share such valuable thoughts on this very important right for disabled persons.</p>
      <p sl="en">What concerns me the most is that the protection of the equal right to employment is often misinterpreted by policymakers as the right to supported, sheltered occupation through social enterprises. Unfortunately, this leads to further segregation of disabled people. What we should focus on instead is providing the means to link disabled persons to the open labour market, no matter what one’s impairment.</p>
      <p sl="en">I can understand that this goal is more challenging because it demands our inclusion in every aspect of life. People cannot be employed in the open labour market when they are excluded from the mainstream educational system, when they cannot use public transport or do not have the support they need in their daily life in order to be independent. But after all, inclusion in real life is, and should be, our objective. Let us stop creating fake segregational schemes for disabled persons in order to keep us out of your way.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-169-0000" speaker_id="202073" name="Marc Angel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">im Namen der S&amp;D-Fraktion. – Frau Präsidentin! Es wäre gut, wenn wir hier ein Rednerpult hätten, das verstellbar wäre und was auch barrierefrei wäre, dann hätte unser Vorredner auch hier unten reden können. Ich hoffe, dass das in Zukunft hier geändert wird.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dear Commissioner, dear colleagues, the right for fair paid work, to an inclusive and well accessible workplace for persons with disabilities is far from being a reality in Europe. The European Union counts 100 million persons with disabilities, and they suffer from too much discrimination on the labour market. In the EU only 50.6% of persons with disabilities are employed compared to 74.8% of persons without disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Today on International Women’s Day it is important to underline that women with disabilities continue to face multiple and intersectional discrimination in all areas of life. This must change and we must step up our efforts. All EU policies must be aligned with the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">Therefore, this excellent report of Ms Katrin Langensiepen, where I had the honour to be the shadow S&amp;D rapporteur comes very timely. Timely are also the new EU disability strategy, the proposed directive on pay transparency and the action plan for the European pillar on social rights presented by Commissioners Dali and Schmit a few days ago. We Socialists and Democrats fully support the Commission’s proposals and also this excellent report because it contains many of our priorities. Allow me to enumerate a few of them:</p>
      <p sl="en">We need a revision of the equal treatment in employment and occupation directive, a revision that has to be a participatory process, including organisations of people with disabilities, just like the rapporteur did while drafting this report.</p>
      <p sl="en">We must introduce compulsory quotas for diversity in the workplace with effective and proportionate sanctions. We need a harmonised definition of disability in order to ensure mutual recognition of the disability status and allow free movement in the EU. We must further develop social economy, make sure all sheltered workshops comply with the UNCRPD. Sheltered workshops must provide people with disabilities skills to gain employment in the open labour market. In sheltered workshops, persons with disabilities must be covered by social security, good working conditions and minimum wages. Member States must use tax incentives and support financial measures for companies that employ persons with disabilities.</p>
      <p sl="en">In 2021 we can no longer tolerate that so many persons with disabilities suffer multiple and intersectional discrimination. Therefore we urge for a rapid ratification of the Istanbul Convention, the unblocking in the Council of the horizontal anti-discrimination directive and the inclusion of the gender dimension in all EU policies.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-171-0000" speaker_id="197522" name="Radka Maxová" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">za skupinu Renew. – Paní předsedající, milé kolegyně, milí kolegové, je mi ctí, že jsem mohla být zpravodajkou Renew Europe této zprávy. Problematika osob se zdravotním postižením je pro mě srdeční záležitostí. Úmluva OSN o právech pro osoby se zdravotním postižením je založena na rovnosti, zaručuje osobám se zdravotním postižením všechna lidská práva a podporuje jejich aktivní zapojení do života, a to platí i o zařazení na pracovní trh. Vzdělání a zaměstnanost jsou zásadní pro nezávislý život, a to znamená být plnohodnotným členem společnosti, nikoli jen příjemcem dávek. Příliš mnoho osob se zdravotním postižením nemá v Evropské unii práci. Z osob se zdravotním postižením je zaměstnaných pouze 50,6 % oproti 74,8 % osob bez zdravotního postižení. To znamená, že velká část našich občanů nemůže být součástí komunity. To znamená, že jsou chudší. To znamená, že nemohou ukázat, jak jsou chytří a talentovaní.</p>
      <p sl="en">Evropské instituce a členské státy ve veřejné správě by v této oblasti měly jít příkladem a zavést příslušná opatření pro naplnění úmluvy OSN. A to i stanovením závazných pravidel rozmanitosti pro nábor lidí se zdravotním postižením a zaměstnáváním osob se všemi typy zdravotního postižení na všech úrovních. Jako Evropská unie nemůžeme nadále být světovými lídry, co se týče ochrany lidských práv, pokud selháváme jako instituce a nezajistíme rovné pracovní podmínky.</p>
      <p sl="en">Lidé se zdravotním postižením nejsou jednotná skupina. Každý má jinou identitu a někdy to může vést k průřezové nebo vícenásobné diskriminaci, například jako u LGBTI lidí s postižením či u žen s postižením, kterých pouze necelých 21 % pracuje na plný úvazek. Vidím důležité využít digitalizaci jako skvělou příležitost pro vytvoření spravedlivější společnosti a příležitost ke zvýšení začlenění osob se zdravotním postižením na trhu práce.</p>
      <p sl="en">Chci poděkovat všem kolegům a kolegyním, kteří tomuto tisku věnovali čas.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-172-0000" speaker_id="189065" name="France Jamet" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe ID. – Madame la Présidente, mes chers collègues, oui, les personnes handicapées sont doublement touchées par le chômage et il y a urgence à corriger ce déséquilibre avec bon sens et pragmatisme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Nous regrettons cependant que le rapporteur de ce texte ait jugé bon de polluer ce débat essentiel avec une idéologie intersectionnelle fumeuse, car elle instrumentalise des critères et des particularismes qui tendent au communautarisme pour fracturer et dissoudre l’unité de la nation.</p>
      <p sl="en">C’est pour éviter cette dérive et rester à l’écart de ces lubies d’extrême gauche que notre groupe Identité et Démocratie a déposé une proposition de résolution alternative. Nous ne devons pas perdre de vue le vrai combat des travailleurs handicapés: l’accessibilité des lieux de travail, l’adaptation de leur poste et les offres de formation professionnelle. Voilà les premiers freins à une embauche et à une réalisation professionnelle au cœur des entreprises. C’est ce défi que nous devons nous attacher à relever.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-173-0000" speaker_id="193292" name="Tilly Metz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">au nom du groupe Verts/ALE. – Madame la Présidente, je félicite ma collègue Katrin Langensiepen pour cet excellent rapport.</p>
      <p sl="en">En ce qui concerne l’égalité de traitement en matière d’emploi et de travail, le constat est assez clair: 20 ans après l’adoption de la directive, le monde du travail reste très ségrégé, voire fermé à la plupart des personnes handicapées. Tout commence par l’enseignement. Sans système scolaire inclusif, sans accès égalitaire à des formations et à des études, difficile de concevoir un marché du travail inclusif et égalitaire. Les ateliers protégés s’inscrivent malheureusement souvent dans la continuité de l’enseignement spécial. Un monde en parallèle, sans vraiment de perspective, avec un risque accru de pauvreté et de dépendance financière. Une véritable insertion professionnelle qui reconnaisse et valorise les compétences de l’employé, c’est surtout une question de dignité. Comment y arriver? Des quotas? Oui, mais l’accent doit aussi être mis sur l’accompagnement des entreprises et ici, le secteur public devrait être exemplaire.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le changement doit surtout s’opérer au niveau de la mentalité et de l’attitude, car la diversité, c’est un atout, c’est une chance aussi dans le monde professionnel.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-174-0000" speaker_id="204414" name="Margarita de la Pisa Carrión" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">en nombre del Grupo ECR. – Señora presidenta, merecen la pena todos los esfuerzos para conseguir la presencia plena de las personas con discapacidad en nuestra sociedad.</p>
      <p sl="en">Este informe debería ser una herramienta para promover su vida profesional, pero se ha quedado en una declaración ideológica que pone más acento en una supuesta discriminación que en hacer viables nuevas ideas. Es un enfoque truncado de futuro, ya que, con resentimiento, quiere destruir lo avanzado hasta ahora para imponer una alternativa uniforme que ignora la singularidad de cada persona.</p>
      <p sl="en">Es imprescindible garantizar la oferta de opciones laborales variadas que puedan adaptarse a la situación de cada persona con discapacidad; no solo para que puedan integrarse en nuestra sociedad, también para que nosotros nos enriquezcamos con su maravillosa presencia.</p>
      <p sl="en">La discapacidad necesita ser entendida en su verdadera diversidad, que nada tiene que ver con la de género. Se ha de abandonar el discurso victimista que instrumentaliza y manipula y que utiliza esta realidad social para intereses totalmente ajenos a sus verdaderas necesidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">Todos, como personas, tenemos el mismo valor y dignidad, que no depende únicamente de nuestras capacidades o utilidad social, como afirma este documento. Es en las relaciones, en los afectos cercanos y desinteresados donde encontramos la plenitud personal. Este texto no lo tiene en cuenta. ¿Por qué lo ha omitido? ¿Por qué no habla de la familia? ¿No será que se pretende un Estado sobreprotector que las sustituya? La verdadera necesidad de este mundo es el amor, que busca la unión y no el enfrentamiento.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-175-0000" speaker_id="197754" name="Sandra Pereira" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">em nome do Grupo The Left. – Senhora Presidente, Senhora Comissária, a realidade da esmagadora maioria das pessoas com deficiência continua a ser marcada pela limitação e pela negação de direitos que, apesar de já estarem previstos em diferentes instrumentos jurídicos, tardam em concretizar-se nas suas vidas.</p>
      <p sl="en">As pessoas com deficiência são um dos grupos sociais que mais sofre as consequências do desemprego, da precariedade, sendo dos grupos mais atingidos pela pobreza e pela exclusão social. É urgente assegurar o acesso das pessoas com deficiência ao emprego com direitos. Essa inclusão laboral exige, inevitavelmente, um quadro geral da regulação do trabalho, da valorização dos salários e da promoção da contratação coletiva, garantindo que a contratação destes trabalhadores parte do referencial laboral aplicado aos outros trabalhadores em termos de remuneração ou tempo de trabalho adaptando-os às suas necessidades.</p>
      <p sl="en">A igualdade de tratamento no emprego e na atividade profissional passará igualmente pela garantia de que os sistemas de apoio à contratação não constituem uma diluição dos encargos salariais com o trabalhador com deficiência, nomeadamente através de comparticipação pública. Estas são reivindicações justas e antigas das pessoas com deficiência e das suas organizações.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gostaria de terminar a minha intervenção com uma saudação à luta das pessoas com deficiências e das organizações de defesa dos seus direitos e com uma saudação especial neste 8 de março, Dia Internacional da Mulher, às mulheres com deficiência assim como a todas as mulheres que diária e incansavelmente contribuem para a elevação da qualidade de vida de todas as pessoas com deficiência.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-176-0000" speaker_id="197734" name="Λευτέρης Νικολάου-Αλαβάνος" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, την εμπορευματοποίηση της υγείας-πρόνοιας, που εφαρμόζουν η Ευρωπαϊκή Ένωση και οι αστικές κυβερνήσεις, βιώνουν οι άνθρωποι με αναπηρίες των εργατικών λαϊκών οικογενειών. Όλη την έκθεση διαπερνάει η απόσυρση της κρατικής ευθύνης από τη στήριξη των αναγκών τους. Στο όνομα της ανεξάρτητης διαβίωσης η υποβάθμιση και η εμπορευματοποίηση των υπαρχουσών κρατικών δομών μεταφέρεται με βαρύ κόστος στους ίδιους και τις οικογένειές τους. Τα νοσοκομεία μίας νόσου, κλειστά για χρόνια πάσχοντες, τα αφημένα στην τύχη τους κέντρα αποκατάστασης και ειδικής αγωγής, τα ιδιωτικά ιδρύματα με τα χιλιάδες κρούσματα και θύματα Covid-19 επιβεβαιώνουν τον εγκληματικό χαρακτήρα αυτής της στρατηγικής. Η έκθεση υπερθεματίζει στην ευρωενωσιακή γραμμή περί πρόσβασης, που γενικεύει την εμπορευματοποίηση κάθε παρεχόμενης υπηρεσίας, παραπέμπει την απασχόληση στην ελεύθερη αγορά των τσακισμένων μισθών και δικαιωμάτων, προτείνει επιδοτήσεις και φοροαπαλλαγές για τους καπιταλιστές.</p>
      <p sl="en">Απαιτούμε αποκλειστικό δημόσιο δωρεάν σύστημα υγείας-πρόνοιας, δωρεάν ειδική αγωγή υψηλής ποιότητας για όλα τα παιδιά με αναπηρίες, εξασφάλιση του δικαιώματος για δουλειά, με πλήρη δικαιώματα στους ικανούς προς εργασία, λειτουργία, με ευθύνη του κράτους, προστατευόμενων παραγωγικών εργαστηρίων.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-177-0000" speaker_id="204336" name="Miriam Lexmann" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Vážená pani predsedajúca, v januári to bolo desať rokov , odkedy je Dohovor o právach osôb so zdravotným postihnutím pre Európsku úniu záväzný, no napriek tomu vidíme, že iba zlomok osôb so zdravotným postihnutím je zamestnaných na plný pracovný úväzok. Nezamestnanosť osôb so zdravotným postihnutím je takmer dvojnásobná a najhoršie sú na tom mladí ľudia. Prebiehajúca pandémia nám ukázala dôsledky nedostatkov pri umožňovaní práce z domova pre tieto osoby. Desať rokov po vstupe dohovoru do platnosti tak môžeme skonštatovať, že cieľ prístupnosti trhu práce sme zatiaľ ani zďaleka nedosiahli, či už za to môže pretrvávajúca diskriminácia, nedostatok povedomia u zamestnávateľov, alebo bariéry prostredia, je načase s tým niečo urobiť. V prvom rade si musíme uvedomiť, že pokiaľ nebudeme pracovať na odstraňovaní fyzických bariér prostredia, nič sa nezmení. Častokrát sa totiž zamestnanec nedokáže do práce ani dostať a pracovať kvôli tomu, že pracovisko nemá potrebné úpravy. Mnoho ľudí stále žije v inštitúciách, kde o zamestnávaní nemôže byť ani reči, a mnoho členských štátov sa uspokojí so zamestnávaním v chránených dielňach. V nich však pracujúci často nemajú postavenie a ochranu riadnych zamestnancov a pracujú tam dlhodobo napriek pôvodnému účelu takýchto dielní. Apelujem preto na dokončenie deinštitualizácie a debarializácie. Pandémia nám ukázala, že mnoho vecí dokáže fungovať vďaka digitálnym nástrojom. Investujme preto do výskumu a technológií a nových asistenčných riešení, zapojme umelú inteligenciu, ktorá má obrovský potenciál pokiaľ dizajnovaná na eticky na základe kvalitných dát, a pomôžeme osobám so zdravotným postihnutím, aby konečne mohli naplno využiť svoj potenciál.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-178-0000" speaker_id="122978" name="Alicia Homs Ginel" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Señora presidenta, señora comisaria, el desempeño de un empleo de calidad es un medio clave al hablar de inclusión social, es un aspecto esencial para afrontar la vida adulta con autonomía e independencia y es imprescindible para el disfrute efectivo de los derechos humanos y las libertades fundamentales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sin embargo, para los casi 100 millones de personas con discapacidad en la Unión Europea conseguir un empleo de calidad supone un gran reto, y, como ocurre siempre cuando hablamos de empleo, lo es todavía más para las personas jóvenes y para las mujeres con discapacidad, doblemente discriminadas y de las que no me quiero olvidar, especialmente en un día como hoy.</p>
      <p sl="en">Por ello, debemos aprovechar el contexto de la recuperación y el marco que nos brinda la nueva Estrategia Europea sobre Discapacidad para apostar por modelos de empleo verdaderamente inclusivos que salvaguarden la igualdad de los derechos y oportunidades, que garanticen la accesibilidad y la adaptación de los puestos de trabajo y que pongan fin a la brecha salarial a la que se enfrentan los grupos sociales más desfavorecidos.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-179-0000" speaker_id="197663" name="Dragoș Pîslaru (Renew" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, Commissioner Dalli. Congratulations to the rapporteur, Katrin Langensiepen and the Parliament team for the shape of this own—initiative report. Renew Europe firmly believes in creating access and opportunity for all to have a decent job, to be a productive member of society, to have an independent life. This includes people with various forms of disabilities as a primary target for our renewed efforts.</p>
      <p sl="en">What we need beyond educating ourselves and making all the steps outlined in this report is to change our perspective on the high unemployment rates we find throughout Europe, among all categories of persons with disabilities. Our ignorance, our intolerance, our outdated practices or our slowness to adapt, deprive even our societies of the talent and potential of so many of our fellow citizens. And that is a tragedy for all of us as a whole. We have to rethink the way we see this issue. This is not about expenditure to artificially pretend to create jobs for some people, this is about investment for creating access and opportunities that persons with disabilities need. We have over 30 million visually impaired persons in Europe. The vast majority are underemployed or unemployed. Yet smart reading digital tools, including the use of AI, make it now possible more than ever for them to perform complicated tasks which before were thought to be completely out of their reach.</p>
      <p sl="en">We need to support this resolution, but we also need to support the longer-term battle for labour and employment of person with disabilities, including with courageous and visionary investments. We will all be better off, we will all prosper if we manage to make this mental shift.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-180-0000" speaker_id="197586" name="Stefania Zambelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, con una semplice tessera, le persone con disabilità potrebbero avere accesso agli stessi servizi in tutti i 27 Stati membri e non dovrebbero subire così ulteriori discriminazioni.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ad oggi nessuna persona con disabilità è in possesso di un riconoscimento europeo. In Italia, solo il contrassegno della macchina dà loro il riconoscimento, con enormi difficoltà ad accedere a tutti gli altri servizi. Da troppo tempo si discute su questo argomento ed è per questo che ho anche presentato un'interrogazione per accelerare la creazione di una tessera europea sulla disabilità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Non complichiamo la vita a chi ha già enormi problemi. Questa tessera potrebbe avere dei benefici nel mondo del lavoro, dove i dati sull'occupazione sono allarmanti: il 50 % dei disabili è disoccupato. Una semplice tessera potrebbe dar loro un vantaggio enorme.</p>
      <p sl="en">Da qui il mio impegno per lavorare insieme per raggiungere questo obiettivo.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-181-0000" speaker_id="197550" name="Sylwia Spurek" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! W Unii Europejskiej są państwa, w których kobieta z niepełnosprawnością ruchową jest wnoszona na fotel ginekologiczny przez recepcjonistę i lekarkę, bo gabinet nie jest dostosowany do jej potrzeb. W Unii są państwa, w których kobieta z niepełnosprawnością intelektualną, dorosła kobieta, jest całkowicie pozbawiona możliwości decydowania o swoim leczeniu. O tym, czy może skonsultować z lekarzem swój stan zdrowia, decyduje jej opiekun prawny. Są państwa, w których głucha kobieta musi iść do lekarza ze swoim małoletnim słyszącym dzieckiem, które służy za tłumacza. Inaczej nie porozumie się z lekarzem.</p>
      <p sl="en">Możemy dyskutować o racjonalnym dostosowaniu miejsc pracy, o równych zarobkach i o kwotach w zatrudnianiu osób z niepełnosprawnościami. Ale osoby z niepełnosprawnościami nie będą w stanie funkcjonować na konkurencyjnym rynku pracy, jeżeli nie zapewnimy im podstawowego prawa – prawa do godności.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-182-0000" speaker_id="197544" name="Elżbieta Rafalska" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Wśród problemów dotyczących kwestii niepełnosprawności ciągle obecność osób niepełnosprawnych na rynku pracy jest poważnym wyzwaniem. W wielu krajach Unii Europejskiej wskaźnik bezrobocia jest dwukrotnie większy niż w normalnej populacji i współczynniki aktywności zawodowej zarówno kobiet, jak i mężczyzn niepełnosprawnych są znacząco niższe, a osoby niepełnosprawne zarabiają również mniej.</p>
      <p sl="en">Pytanie jest takie: jak to zmienić, skoro o tym mówimy od lat? Co zrobić, żeby ta sytuacja się poprawiła? Rozwiązaniem mogą być alternatywne systemy, a więc zatrudnienie osób niepełnosprawnych na otwartym rynku pracy, a także konieczność zmodyfikowania dotychczasowych systemów. Ale z całą pewnością nie przekreślałabym lekką ręką, o czym mówiło dziś wielu przedmówców, żeby zrezygnować z zakładów pracy chronionej. No i na pewno najlepszą receptą jest dobra edukacja, w tym edukacja cyfrowa.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-183-0000" speaker_id="96829" name="Ádám Kósa" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Nagyszerű eredmény ennek a jelentésnek a megszületése. Számomra jelképes az is, hogy pont akkor kerül erre sor, amikor az Európai Bizottság is benyújtja a 2021–2030 közötti fogyatékosságügyi stratégiát. 12 éve vagyok EP-képviselő. Amióta bizalmat kaptam, folyamatosan egyeztetek fogyatékossággal élők érdekképviseleti szervezeteivel Magyarországon és nemzetközi szinten is, mert meggyőződésem, hogy ők tudják a legjobban, hogy mire van szükségük. Ezt az elvet követtem már 2010-ben is, amikor elkészítettem a 2010–2020 közötti európai fogyatékosságügyi stratégiáról szóló jelentést. Eltelt egy évtized azóta. Az új stratégia itt van és az újabb európai parlamenti jelentés is, amelynek én voltam az egyik árnyék-jelentéstevője.</p>
      <p sl="en">Langensiepen asszonnyal kiválóan lehetett együttműködni. Közös munkánk eredménye sok helyen kész tényként mutatkozik meg. Szépen köszönnek ezek vissza a szövegben. Hármat szeretnék kiemelni: az egyik az újfajta emberi jogi alapú megközelítés szorgalmazása az oktatás területén; a horizontális adatgyűjtés fogyatékossággal élő emberekről, akikről eddig nem gyűjtöttek adatokat; és a kommunikációs akadálymentesítés, mert eddig európai uniós szinten elsősorban a fizikai akadálymentesítéssel vagy ezzel foglalkoztak. Elégedett vagyok, de nem pihenek, hanem folytatom a munkát ugyanolyan lelkesedéssel.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-184-0000" speaker_id="197863" name="Maria Walsh" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, dear Commissioner, delighted to be here and start by saying inclusion is a right, not a privilege. It is not a matter of political correctness; it is how we progress in policymaking. On this day, International Women’s Day, I want to remind the Commission and, importantly, all my colleagues in this Chamber who use their voice and vote every month, of the importance of systematically including the interests and rights of women and girls with disabilities in every policy.</p>
      <p sl="en">I equally want to remind my colleagues at home in Ireland to work with us and implement those interests and rights of women and girls with disabilities into national policies. This is particularly important in regards to education, employment and social policy, where persons with disabilities are too often excluded from education and from employment opportunities, thus making access to full-time employment even more difficult and thereby increasing inequalities and social exclusion even further.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-185-0000" speaker_id="199941" name="Marianne Vind" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Fru formand! Vi skriver år 2021, men desværre har vi stadig rigtig store udfordringer med beskæftigelsen for Europas over 80 millioner mennesker med handicap. Det er kun omkring halvdelen af alle personer med handicap, der er i job, og det er altså kun medregnet dem, som man vurderer kan varetage et job. Personer med handicap har lige så meget ret til et arbejdsliv, hvor man tjener sine egne penge og har et fællesskab med kollegaerne, og det er uanset om man sidder i kørestol eller er på autismespektret. Der er faktisk noget, vi kan gøre. I EU stiller vi nemlig krav til, hvordan arbejdspladsen skal se ud, og vi har i dag alt for få krav til tilpasning af arbejdspladsen eller brugen af nye teknologier. Også selv for de mest almindelige handicap. Når arbejdspladsen ikke er rummelig, så fratages millioner af mennesker muligheden for et arbejdsliv. Så lad os for alvor få gjort noget ved de rummelige arbejdspladser. Det kan lade sig gøre.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-186-0000" speaker_id="124973" name="Gerolf Annemans" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Voorzitter, ook inzake de gelijke behandeling op de arbeidsmarkt van personen met een handicap geldt het subsidiariteitsprincipe: de noodzaak om op elk niveau passende ondersteuning te bieden, te beginnen bij de lokale gemeenschap. Wanneer wij lidstaten hier vragen werkgevers aan te moedigen om personen met een handicap in dienst te nemen, dan moeten wij in onze lidstaten zelf ook het goede voorbeeld geven. De werkzaamheidsgraad van gehandicapten in België bijvoorbeeld ligt een pak onder het Europese gemiddelde. De Belgische en ook de Vlaamse overheid halen bij lange na het quotum van 3 procent niet en bungelen achteraan in Europa. Ook de toegang tot en de verbetering van mobiliteit en toegankelijkheid van gebouwen zijn een taak voor de lokale overheden. In het uitwerken van maatregelen moet de boutade niet over ons, zonder ons de leidraad zijn. En dus moet er nauw samengewerkt worden met gehandicaptenorganisaties om relevante initiatieven te nemen. Ik wil hier tot slot de sleutelrol van mantelzorgers beklemtonen en ook dat het de gepaste ondersteuning, morele en financiële steun is die ze verdienen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-187-0000" speaker_id="197792" name="Daniela Rondinelli" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, in un mondo ideale il lavoro è sinonimo di emancipazione e inclusione, ma nell'Europa dell'austerità prima e della pandemia poi, per tante persone con disabilità il lavoro è un miraggio.</p>
      <p sl="en">È inaccettabile che a dieci anni dalla Convenzione ONU sulle persone con disabilità, in tanti Stati Membri non sia ancora cambiato nulla. Questa risoluzione è un grido d'allarme, nel momento in cui la Commissione lancia la nuova strategia sulla disabilità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ritengo che l'Europa non potrà accontentarsi di enunciazioni di principio, ma dovrà prevedere politiche concrete, come la portabilità dei diritti, il diritto all'indipendenza, il pieno accesso al lavoro e allo studio e servizi essenziali.</p>
      <p sl="en">Per questo chiediamo che nel semestre europeo si fissino anche obiettivi sociali, affrontando il tema delle discriminazioni multiple e prevedendo quote obbligatorie in materia di assunzioni nelle istituzioni pubbliche, come nel settore privato, con adeguate sanzioni in caso di inosservanza.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le persone con disabilità chiedono di lavorare per realizzare se stesse e di ricevere finalmente quanto è stato loro negato sinora in termini di opportunità e qualità della vita.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-188-0000" speaker_id="197414" name="Λουκάς Φουρλάς" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Κυρία Πρόεδρε, κυρία Επίτροπε, χαίρομαι που χαιρετίζω δύο κυρίες σήμερα, Ημέρα της Γυναίκας. Η εισηγήτρια μπορεί να μην κατάφερε να γίνει παρουσιάστρια ειδήσεων, έγινε όμως παρουσιάστρια αλήθειας και ζωής και την ευχαριστούμε. Ένας στους έξι πολίτες της Ευρωπαϊκής Ένωσης αντιμετωπίζει κάποιας μορφής αναπηρία. Οφείλουμε να καταπολεμήσουμε τον εγκλεισμό που βιώνουν πολλοί άνθρωποι με αναπηρία. Η ένταξή τους στην εργασία αποτελεί θεμελιώδες δικαίωμα, αλλά και υποχρέωσή μας. Από τα στατιστικά στοιχεία που έχουμε στη διάθεσή μας μόνο το 50% των ανθρώπων με αναπηρίες βρίσκονται στην απασχόληση αυτή τη στιγμή. Οφείλουμε να διασφαλίσουμε ένα προσβάσιμο και φιλικό εργασιακό περιβάλλον, όχι ως χάρη, αλλά ως υποχρέωση εφαρμογής των προνοιών της Σύμβασης των Ηνωμένων Εθνών για τα Δικαιώματα των Ατόμων με Αναπηρία. Αυτά τα δικαιώματα πρέπει να είναι εγγυημένα, ειδικά σε αυτές τις περιόδους κρίσης, όπως αυτή που βιώνουμε σήμερα. Θα πρέπει να διασφαλίσουμε ότι όλα τα προγράμματα είναι κατανοητά και προσβάσιμα σε όλους. Να σιγουρευτούμε δηλαδή ότι θα φτάσουν κοντά τους. Οι άνθρωποι αυτοί δεν επαιτούν· απαιτούν τα δικαιώματά τους και μαζί τους και εμείς.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-189-0000" speaker_id="197403" name="Alex Agius Saliba" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Sinjura President, ix-xogħol jagħtik dinjità, u iva, ix-xogħol jista’ jagħti lura wkoll id-dinjità lill-persuni b’diżabilità. Ix-xogħol huwa element kruċjali għall-ħajja indipendenti kif ukoll fattur elementari għall-parteċipazzjoni effettiva – il-parteċipazzjoni kompleta tal-persuni b’diżabilità fis-soċjetà tagħna.</p>
      <p sl="en">Għalhekk, għalkemm l-Unjoni hija firmatarja tal-Konvenzjoni tal-Ġnus Magħquda, il-persuni b’diżabilitajiet varji qed ikomplu jesperjenzaw diskrimazzjoni kontinwa – mill-edukazzjoni sad-dritt li jgħixu ħajja indipendenti, mil-leżjonijiet tad-dritt li jkollhom kwalità tal-ħajja adegwata u protezzjoni soċjali sad-dritt tax-xogħol.</p>
      <p sl="en">Il-ġimgħa li għaddiet, il-Kummissjoni ppubblikat l-Istrateġija Ewropea għall-persuni b’diżabilità għall-għaxar snin li ġejjin, u ta’ dan nixtieq nirringrazzja lill-Kummissarju Helena Dalli għax-xogħol li wettqet. Issa però huwa importanti li naraw li din l-Istrateġija tħalli impatt fuq ħajjet dawn ħutna. Huwa d-dmir tagħna li niżguraw li l-persuni b’diżabilità jgħixu f’Unjoni inklużiva u d-dritt ta’ trattament ugwali fejn jidħol ix-xogħol huwa wieħed mill-aqwa espressjonijiet tal-ugwaljanza u l-integrazzjoni.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-190-0000" speaker_id="197488" name="Guido Reil" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir reden heute über die Gleichstellung von Menschen mit Behinderungen im Arbeitsmarkt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das ist ein sehr wichtiges Thema, das mir auch persönlich sehr am Herzen liegt. Denn behinderte Menschen sind häufiger arbeitslos, häufiger langzeitarbeitslos, häufiger in prekären Beschäftigungsverhältnissen, häufiger arm und häufiger obdachlos. Aber was will dieser grüne Bericht jetzt? Wie will er diesen Menschen helfen?</p>
      <p sl="en">Erst einmal stellt dieser grüne Bericht fest: Es gibt da behinderte Menschen, die anscheinend mehr unsere Unterstützung brauchen als andere – z. B. behinderte Menschen, die LGBTI sind, oder behinderte Menschen, die Roma oder Flüchtlinge sind. All diese Menschen brauchen anscheinend mehr unsere Unterstützung als andere.</p>
      <p sl="en">Wir reden darüber, dass es eine verpflichtende Quote von Diversitätsarbeitsplätzen gibt. Wir reden darüber, dass es Diversitätsberatungsstellen gibt. Da werden unseren grünen Freunden wieder Jobs besorgt – wie schon so häufig.</p>
      <p sl="en">Also für mich ist dieser linksgrüne Bericht ein Schlag in die Fresse für jeden behinderten Menschen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-191-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Einen kleinen Moment.</p>
      <p sl="en">Das kann ich nicht stehenlassen. Das ist kein parlamentarischer Ausdruck: „Ein Schlag in die Fresse“.</p>
      <p sl="en">Ich bitte Sie, solche Ausdrücke zukünftig zu unterlassen.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-192-0000" speaker_id="124895" name="Krzysztof Hetman" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Pani Przewodnicząca! Pani Komisarz! W instytucjach unijnych często słyszę taki slogan: „Aby nikt nie został z tyłu” (So no one is left behind). Musimy mieć świadomość, że osoby z niepełnosprawnościami zostają z tyłu i niestety slogan wciąż jest tylko sloganem . W całej Unii Europejskiej tylko niewiele ponad 50% osób z niepełnosprawnościami pracuje. Jest to grupa zagrożona szczególnym ubóstwem i wykluczeniem społecznym. Nierówny dostęp do rynku pracy jest więc faktem i musimy kontynuować wysiłki, żeby osoby z niepełnosprawnościami były aktywne zawodowo i samodzielne. Aby tak się stało, potrzeba jednak działań wielowymiarowych skierowanych zarówno do przyszłych i obecnych pracowników z niepełnosprawnościami, jak i pracodawców i ogółu społeczeństwa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Osoby z niepełnosprawnościami są zdolnymi i rzetelnym pracownikami. Jeśli chcemy jednak zapewnić im równy dostęp do miejsca pracy czy systemu kształcenia i szkolenia, musimy mieć na uwadze, że często wymaga to szczególnych rozwiązań. Jestem więc zwolennikiem tworzenia różnego rodzaju zachęt, także podatkowych, dla przedsiębiorców, którzy zatrudniają te osoby. Nie bez znaczenia jest także kwestia usuwania fizycznych barier w miejscu pracy i tworzenia klimatu dostępności, a także promowania elastycznych rozwiązań i pełnego korzystania z potencjału nowych technologii.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-193-0000" speaker_id="124867" name="Brando Benifei" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, in questo ultimo anno a fare le spese della pandemia sono state purtroppo ancora di più le categorie svantaggiate già da prima, come le persone con disabilità.</p>
      <p sl="en">Gli ultimi dati ci mostrano chiaramente discriminazioni lavorative intollerabili all'interno degli Stati membri. Per questo dobbiamo impegnarci per una piena attuazione della Convenzione sui diritti delle persone con disabilità. È un tema che mi sta molto a cuore e ho avuto l'onore di rappresentare proprio questo Parlamento alla Conferenza delle parti contraenti alle Nazioni Unite a New York qualche anno fa.</p>
      <p sl="en">Dobbiamo aumentare le tutele sociali, introducendo quote di assunzioni per le persone con disabilità, garantendo eguale retribuzione, aumentando investimenti in formazione e nella mobilità accessibile – penso al grande lavoro fatto su quest'ultimo tema da attivisti come Iacopo Melio, oggi consigliere regionale e cittadino europeo dell'anno, e al mio concittadino Nicola Torre – perché serve la partecipazione delle persone con disabilità alla realizzazione delle politiche che li riguardano.</p>
      <p sl="en">C'è molto da fare: riformare l'atto europeo sull'accessibilità e sostenere la strategia della Commissione europea. Siamo pronti a lavorare, i diritti non possono rimanere solo sulla carta.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-194-0000" speaker_id="197686" name="Julie Lechanteux" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Madame la Présidente, chers collègues, les chiffres exposés aujourd’hui sur la situation professionnelle des personnes en situation de handicap font froid dans le dos. Ils sont la preuve de votre désintérêt envers les plus fragiles d’entre nous: ceux qui ont eu la malchance de naître avec des pathologies invalidantes ou ceux qui, au fil des années, ont perdu une partie importante de leurs capacités physiques ou mentales.</p>
      <p sl="en">Le taux de chômage des personnes en situation de handicap est astronomique: il s’élève à 17 %. En Europe, il y a trente millions de personnes aveugles et malvoyantes, un million de personnes sourdes et malentendantes utilisant la langue des signes et sept millions de personnes en situation de handicap mental.</p>
      <p sl="en">Alors, je vous le demande: pourquoi continuer d’accueillir des migrants économiques qui profitent de toutes les aides sociales octroyées, qui violent nos frontières, font peser les salaires à la baisse et pour un certain nombre, deviennent des terroristes?</p>
      <p sl="en">Je souligne là le deux poids, deux mesures, car vous ne faites rien en faveur de nos compatriotes en situation de handicap. Cette cause mérite pourtant que notre action soit pour les nôtres avant les autres.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-195-0000" speaker_id="197480" name="Nicolaus Fest" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Frau Präsidentin! Frau Langensiepen, ich schätze Sie ja persönlich, aber Ihr Bericht ist mal wieder Schrott. Eine Ansammlung von Gemeinplätzen, Trivialitäten und Dummheiten.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-196-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Herr Kollege Fest, können wir vielleicht den gegenseitigen Respekt wahren in dieser Debatte?</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-197-0000" speaker_id="197480" name="Nicolaus Fest" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich habe doch gesagt: Ich schätze sie persönlich, aber ihr Bericht ist Schrott.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-198-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">„Schrott“ ist aber, glaube ich, keine Parlamentssprache.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-199-0000" speaker_id="197480" name="Nicolaus Fest" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich weiß, dass Sie heute auf Krawall gebürstet sind.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-200-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Nein, Herr Kollege, ich achte nur auf eine würdige Debatte. Ich darf Sie bitten, das auch zu tun.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-201-0000" speaker_id="197480" name="Nicolaus Fest" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich habe ihr meinen Respekt verkündet, aber inhaltlich redet sie Unfug. Sie räumen ja selber ein, dass Sie keine ausreichende Datenbasis haben, aber – natürlich – behaupten kann man immer mal alles. Sie behaupten z. B. einen ethnic pay gap – im Sportbereich, lassen Sie sich da informieren, ist das oftmals umgekehrt. Aber Sie müssen natürlich den Europäern strukturellen Rassismus unterjubeln, sonst würden Sie wohl Schwierigkeiten in Ihrer Partei bekommen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Sie behaupten ebenso ein diskriminatorisches pay gap zu Lasten der Roma. Dass viele Roma zumindest in Deutschland bei den schulischen Leistungen selbst hinter den schwachen Deutschen zurückliegen, wird hier ausgeblendet. Aber ohne gute Ausbildung kriegt man eben keinen Job, es sei denn, man heißt Erik Marquardt oder Bütikofer und gehört zur Grünen Partei im Europaparlament.</p>
      <p sl="en">Und auch die anderen Diskriminierungen, die Sie aufzählen, sind Voodoo und linker Sozialismus. Das ist alles Quatsch. Die Grünen sind seit Jahren führend in den Landesparlamenten. Wenn es so viele Diskriminierungen gibt, dann sollten Sie die Partei wechseln, denn Ihre Partei ist politisch dafür verantwortlich, vor allem für die von Ihnen beklagte Diskriminierung im LGBTI-Bereich. Also, Frau Langensiepen, verlassen Sie die Partei, denn Ihre Partei ist politisch verantwortlich für diese Diskriminierung.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-202-0000" speaker_id="photo_generic" name="Helena Dalli" is_mep="False" mode="spoken" role="Member of the Commission">
      <p sl="en">Madam President, on behalf of the Commission, I welcome your report on the implementation of this report, and I really thank you for this wide-ranging debate and very important discussion, and I am grateful for your valuable opinions and recommendations.</p>
      <p sl="en">We agree on many of them, and I believe that we are able to take a lot of them into account in the preparation of the new disability strategy. So the implementation is ahead of us. We intend to work closely with Member States, civil society and representative organisations of persons with disabilities whose opinions and assistance are key for successful implementation.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will create the disability platform, which will replace the current high—level group on disability. It should support the implementation of this strategy and the national disability strategies.</p>
      <p sl="en">We will encourage Member States to adopt ambitious national strategies to foster the implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities and of the EU strategy at national, regional and local level. We will also promote the use of EU funding by Member States to support the implementation of their national strategies and the UN Convention.</p>
      <p sl="en">Only with your support and dedication can the objectives of this strategy be fully achieved. I thank you for your support, and good night.</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p>
      <p sl="en">Die Abstimmung über die Änderungsanträge findet am Dienstag, 9. März 2021, statt. Die Schlussabstimmung am Mittwoch, 10. März 2021, statt.</p>
      <p sl="en">Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 171)</p>
    </intervention>
    <intervention id="1-203-5000" speaker_id="204368" name="Christian Sagartz" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">schriftlich. – Die aktuelle COVID-Krise hat immense Auswirkungen auf den europäischen Arbeitsmarkt. Besonders hart trifft es aber Menschen mit Behinderung. Die Arbeitslosenquote ist doppelt so hoch im Vergleich zur Gesamtbevölkerung. Fast ein Drittel ist von Armut und sozialer Ausgrenzung bedroht. Das sind schockierende Fakten und hier gibt es Handlungsbedarf. Wir müssen sicherstellen, dass Menschen mit Behinderung gute Chancen am Arbeitsmarkt gewährt werden. Nur so ist eine umfassende Teilhabe an der Gesellschaft möglich. Hürden müssen abgeschafft, und Diskriminierungen entschieden entgegengewirkt werden. Dazu müssen wir als Europäisches Parlament ein starkes Zeichen setzen. Es liegt aber nun an uns, hier den Worten auch Taten folgen zu lassen und viele der angesprochenen Aufgaben in dem Bericht so rasch als möglich umzusetzen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
  <section id="creitem25" title="25. Explanations of vote: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem26" title="26. Corrections to votes and voting intentions: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem27" title="27. Agenda for next sitting: see Minutes"/>
  <section id="creitem28" title="28. Closure of the sitting"/>
  <section id="creitem29" title="29. Closing of the session">
    <intervention id="1-210-0000" speaker_id="197437" name="Die Präsidentin" is_mep="True" mode="spoken">
      <p sl="en">Ich erkläre die Sitzungsperiode 2020-2021 des Europäischen Parlaments für geschlossen.</p>
    </intervention>
  </section>
</text>
